<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Esthetics of Power in Modern Erotic Art</title>
				<author>Carol Duncan</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Heresies: Issue 1</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="46"/>
			<head><title>The Esthetics of Power in Modern Erotic Art</title></head>
			<note>*An excerpt from the forthcoming book, The New Eros, ed., Joan Semmel, to be
				published by Hacker Art Books, New York.</note>
			<byline><persName>Carol Duncon</persName></byline>

			<p> In this essay, I am using the term erotic not as a self-evident, universal category,
				but as a culturally defined concept that is ideological in nature. More
				specifically, I am arguing that the modern art that we have learned to recognize and
				respond to as erotic is frequently about the power and supremacy of men over women.
				Indeed, once one begins to subject erotic art to critical analysis, to examine the
				male-female relationships it implies, one is struck with the repetitiousness with
				which the issue of power is treated. The erotic imaginations of modern male
				artists—the famous and the forgotten, the formal innovators and the
				followers—re-enact in hundreds of particular variations a remarkably limited set of
				fantasies. Time and again, the male confronts the female nude as an adversary whose
				independent existence as a physical or spiritual being must be assimilated to male
				needs, converted to abstractions, enfeebled or destroyed. So often do such works
				invite fantasies of male conquest (or fantasies that justify male domination) that
				the subjuga- tion of the female will appear to be one of the primary motives of
				modern erotic art.</p>
			<p>In Delacroix's Woman in White Stockings (1832), for example, an artist's model (i.e.,
				a sexually available woman) reclines invitingly on a silken mattress. The deep red
				drapery behind her forms a shadowy and suggestive opening. The image evokes a basic
				male fantasy of sexual confrontation, but the model does not appear to anticipate
				pleasure. On the contrary, she appears to be in pain, and the signs of her distress
				are depicted as carefully as her alluring flesh. Her face, partly averted, appears
				disturbed, her torso is uncomfortably twisted, and the position of her arms suggests
				surrender and powerlessness. But this distress does not contradict the promise of
				male gratification. Rather, it is offered as an explicit condition of male
				pleasure—the artist's and the viewer's.</p>
			<p>The equation of female sexual experience with surrender and victimization is so
				familiar in what our culture designates as erotic art and so sanctioned by both
				popular and high cultural traditions, that one hardly stops to think it odd. The
				Victorian myth that women experience sex as a violation of body or spirit or both,
				and that those who actively seek gratification are perverse (and hence deserving of
				degradation), is but one of many ideological justifications of the sexual
				victimization of women devised by the modern era. In the 20th century, the theory
				and practice of psychology has given new rationalizations to the same underlying
				thesis.</p>
			<p>The visual arts are crowded with images of suffering, exposed heroines—slaves, murder
				victims, women in terror under attack, betrayed, in chains, abandoned or abducted.
				Delacroix's Death of Sardanapalus (1827), inspired by a poem by Byron, is a tour de
				force of erotic cruelty. Ingres' Roger and Angelica (1867) also depicts woman as
				victim. Here, an endangered and helpless heroine—naked, hairless and swooning—is
				chained to a large, phallic-shaped rock, immediately below which appear the
				snake-like forms of a dragon. This fantastic but deadly serious statement documents
				a common case of male castration anxiety. But the artist-hero (he is Ingres-Roger)
				masters the situation: he conquers the dangerous female genitals. First he
				desexualizes Angelica—reduces her to an unconscious mass of closed and boneless
				flesh; then he thrusts his lance into the toothy opening of the serpent—Angelica's
				vagina transposed. Given the fears such an image reveals, it is no wonder that
				Ingres idealized helpless, passive women. The point here, however, is that neither
				Ingres' fears nor his ideal woman were unique to him.</p>
			<p>Americans, too, thrilled to images of female victims. Hiram Power's The Greek Slave
				(1843) was probably the most famous and celebrated American sculpture in the
				mid-19th century. Overtly, the viewer could admire the virtuous modesty with which
				Powers endowed the young slave girl, as did critics in the 19th century; but
				covertly, Powers invites the viewer to imagine himself as the potential oriental
				buyer of a beautiful, naked, humiliated girl who is literally for sale (he specified
				that she is on the auction block). The narrative content of this sculpture supports
				the same underlying thesis we saw in the Delacroix: for women, the sexual encounter
				must entail pain and subjugation, and that subjugation is a condition of male
				gratification. But even in paintings where nudes are not literally victims, female
				allure is treated in terms related to victimization. For Ingres, Courbet, Renoir,
				Matisse and scores of other modern artists, weakness, mindlessness and indolence are
				attributes of female 'sexiness. Germaine Greer's description of the female ideal
				that informs modern advertising could as well have been drawn from modern nudes: </p>
			<pb n="47"/>
			<quote>Her essential quality is castratedness. She absolutely must be young, her body
				hairless, her flesh buoyant, and she must not have a sexual organ.</quote>
			<note>The Female Eunuch (New York, 1972), p. 57.</note>
			<p>That is, in the modern era, woman's desirability increases as her humanity and health
				(relative to male norms) are diminished.</p>
			<p>The need to see women as weak, vapid, unhealthy objects-—while not unique to the
				modern era—is evidently felt with unusual intensity and frequency in bourgeois
				civilization, whose technical advances so favor the idea of sexual equality. Indeed,
				as women's claims to full humanity grew the more relentlessly would art rationalize
				their inferior status. For while literature and the theatre could give expression to
				feminist voices, the art world acknowledged only male views of human sexual
				experience. In that arena, men alone were free to grapple with their sexual
				aspirations, fantasies and fears. Increasingly in the modern era, artists and their
				audiences agreed that serious and profound art is likely to be about what men think
				of women. In fact, the defense of male supremacy must be recognized as a central
				theme in modern art. Gauguin, Munch, Rodin, Matisse, Picasso and scores of other
				artists, consciously or unconsciously, identified some aspect of the sexist cause
				with all or part of their own artistic missions. Art celebrating sexist experience
				was accorded the greatest prestige, given the most pretentious esthetic rationales
				and identified with the highest and deepest of human aspirations.</p>
			<p>Nudes and whores—women with no identity beyond their existence as sex objects—were
				made to embody transcendent, "universally significant statements. In literature as
				in art, the image of the whore even came to stand for woman in her purest, most
				concentrated form, just as the brothel became the ultimate classroom, the temple in
				which men only might glimpse life's deepest mysteries: "A Henry Miller, going to bed
				with a prostitute [in Tropic of Cancer], feels that he sounds the very depths of
				life, death and the cosmos." <note>Simone de Beauvoir, The Second Sex (New York,
					1961), p. 187.</note> Picasso's famous brothel scene, the Demoiselles d’Avignon
				(1907), where the viewer is cast as the male customer makes similar claims—claims
				that art historians advocate as "humanistic“ and universal.<note>3. Leo Steinberg,
					"The Philosophical Brothel, Part I," Art News (Sept., 1972), pp. 20-29; and Gert
					Schiff, "Picasso's Suite 347, or Painting as an Act of Love," in Woman as Sex
					Object, ed. Thomas B. Hess and Linda Nochlin (New Vork, 1972), pp.
					238-253.</note> Art-making itself is analogous to the sexual domination of
				whores. The metaphor of the penis-as-paintbrush is a revered truth for many
				20th-century artists and art historians. It also insists that to create is to
				possess, to dominate, and to be quintessentially male.</p>
			<quote>I try to paint with my heart and my loins, not bothering with style
				(Vlaminck).</quote>
			<note>4. In Herschel B. Chipp, Theories of Modern Art (Berkeley, 1970), p. 144.</note>
			<quote>Thus I learned to battle the canvas, to come to know it as a being resisting my
				wish (dream), and to bend it forcibly to this wish. At first it stands there like a
				pure chaste virgin and then comes the willful brush which first here, then there,
				gradually conquers it with all the energy peculiar to it, like a European colonist
				...(Kandinsky).</quote>
			<note>5. Quoted in Max Kozloff, "The Authoritarian Personality in Modern Art," Artforum
				(May, 1974), p. 46. Schiff, op. cit., actually advocates the penis-as-paintbrush
				metaphor.</note>
			<p>The kind of nudes that prevail in the modern era do not merely reflect a collective
				male psyche. They actively promote the relationships they portray, not only
				expressing but also shaping sexual consciousness. For the nude, in her passivity and
				impotence, is addressed to women as much as to men. Far from being merely an
				entertainment for males, the nude, as a genre, is one of many cultural phenomena
				that teaches women to see themselves through male eyes and in terms of dominating
				male interests. While it sanctions and reinforces in men the identification of
				virility with domination, it holds up to women self-images in which even sexual
				self-expression is prohibited. As ideology, the nude shapes our awareness of our
				deepest human instincts in terms of domination and submission so that the supremacy
				of the male "I" prevails on that most fundamental level of experience.</p>
			<p>Twentieth-century art has equally urged the victimization and spiritual diminution of
				women, shedding, however the narrative trappings and much of the illusionism of the
				19th century. The abandoned Ariadnes, endangered captives and cloistered harem women
				of 19thcentury art become simply naked models and mistresses in the studio or whores
				in the brothel. In nudes by Matisse, Vlaminck, Kirchner Van Dongen and others, the
				demonstration of male control and the suppression of female sub¬ jectivity is more
				emphatic and more frequently asserted than in 19th-century ones. Their faces are
				more frequently concealed, blank or mask-like (that is when they are not put to
				sleep), and the artist manipulates their passive bodies with more liberty and
				"artistic" bravado than <pb n="48"/>ever. <figure>
					<caption>Left to right: Edvard Munch. Madonna. 1849-95. Nasjonal Gallieret,
						Oslo; Willem de Kooning. Untitled Drawing. 1969; Joan Miro. Woman's Head.
						1938. Private Collection; Pablo Picasso. Seated Bather. 1929. Museum of
						Modern Art, New York; Maurice Vlaminck. Bathers. 1907 Private Collection.
						Kees van Dongen. Reclining Nude. 1904. Private Collection.</caption>
				</figure></p>

			<p> The image of the femme fatale, especially popular at the turn of the century, would
				seem to contradict the image of woman as victim. Typically, she looms over the male
				viewer, fixing him with a mysterious gaze and rendering him will-less. Yet she is
				born of the same set of underlying fears as her powerless, victimized sisters, as
				the depictions often reveal. Munch's Madonna (1893-94), a femme fatale par excel¬
				lence, visually hints at the imagery of victimization. The familiar gestures of
				surrender (the arm behind the head) and captivity (the arm behind the back, as if
				bound) are clearly if softly stated. These gestures have a long history in Western
				art. The dying Daughter of Niobe, a well-known Greek sculpture of the 5th century
				B.C. exhibits exactly this pose. The raised arm is also seen in numerous 5th-century
				statues of dying Amazons and sleeping Ariadnes, where it conveys death, sleep or an
				overwhelming of the will. It may also convey the idea of lost struggle, as in the
				Amazon statues or in Michaelangelo's Dying Captive (The Louvre), themselves
				masterpieces of victim imagery with strong sexual overtones. But in the modern era,
				the raised arm (or arms) is emptied of its classical connotation of defeat with
				dignity and becomes almost exclusively a female gesture—a signal of sexual surrender
				and physical availability. Munch used it in his Madopna to mitigate his assertion of
				female power; the gesture of defeat subtly checks the dark, overpowering force of
				Woman. The same ambivalence can also be seen in the spatial relationship between the
				figure and the viewer: the woman can be read as rising upright before him or as
				lying beneath him.</p>
			<p>However lethal to the male, the late 19th-century femme fatale of Munch, Klimt and
				Moreau ensnares by her physical beauty and sexual allure. In the 20th century, she
				becomes bestial, carnivorous and visibly grotesque. In images of monstrous females
				by Picasso Rouault, the Surrealists and de Kooning, the dread of woman and male
				feelings of inferiority are projected, objectified and universalized. Yet here too
				the devouring woman implies her opposite, combining features of both the powerless
				and the threatening. The women in Picasso's Demoiselles d'Avignon, although
				physically mutilated and naked (vulnerable), aggressively stare down the viewer are
				impenetrably masked, and display sharp-edged, dangerous-looking bodies. Picasso
				ambivalently presents them with sham and real reverence in the form of a desecrated,
				burlesque icon, already slashed to bits. De Kooning, in his contin¬ uing Woman
				series, ritually invokes, objectifies and obliterates the same species of
				goddess-whore. Here too a similar ambivalence finds its voice in shifting, unstable
				forms whose emergence and destruction are accepted in the critical literature as the
				conscious "esthetic" pretext for his work. The pose his figures usually take— a
				frontal crouch with thighs open to expose the vulva—also appears in the Demoiselles
				d'Avignon (in the lower right figure), which, in turn, derives from primitive art.
				Like Picasso's figures, de Kooning's women are simultaneously inviting and
				repelling, above and below the viewer obscene modern whores and terrifying primitive
				deities.</p>
			<p>The pronounced teeth in de Kooning's Woman and Bicycle (1950)—the figure actually has
				a second set around her throat—also speak of primitive and modern neurotic fears of
				the female genitals. The vagina dentata, an ancient fantasy into which males project
				their terror of castration—of being swallowed up or devoured in their partner's
				sexual organs—is commonly represented as a toothed mouth. The image, which appears
				frequently in modern art, is a striking feature of Mirö's Woman's Head (1938). The
				savage creature in this painting has open alligator jaws protruding from a large,
				black head. The red eye, bristling hairs and exaggerated palpable nipples, in
				combination with the thin weak arms, help give it that same mixture of comic
				improbability and terribleness that characterize Picasso's Demoiselles and de
				Kooning's Women. But in addition—and true to Mirö's love of metamorphosing forms—the
				image can be read literally as the lower part of a woman’s body, seen partly as if
				through an X ray. Inverted, the arms become open legs, the dark, massive head a
				uterus, and the long, dangerous jaws a toothed vaginal canal. The predatory creature
				in Picasso's Seated Bather (1929) not only has saw-toothed jaws, but several
				features of the praying mantis.</p>
			<p>The praying mantis, who supposedly devours her mate, was a favorite theme in
				Surrealist art and literature. In paintings by Masson, Labisse, Ernst and others,
				the cannibalistic sexual rites of this insect become a metaphor for the human sexual
				relationship, and the female of the species becomes the Surrealistic version of the
				femme fatale. More subhuman and brutal than her 19th-century predecessors, she
				testifies to the higher level of sexual anxiety and hostility experienced by the
				20th-century male. For as women increasingly demanded a share of the world, the
				defense of male authority became more desperate:</p>
			<quote>Now become a fellow being, woman seems as formidable as when she faced man as a
				part of alien Nature. In place of the myth of the laborious honeybee or the mother
				hen is substituted the myth of the devouring female insect: the praying mantis, the
				spider. No longer is the female she who nurses the little ones, but rather she who
				eats the male.</quote>
			<note>De Beauvoir, op. cit., p. 179.</note>
			<p>Pictures of nudes in nature also affirm the supremacy of the male consciousness even
				while they ostensibly venerate or pay tribute to women as freer or more in harmony
				with nature than men. From the Bathers of Delacroix to those of Renoir and Picasso
				nude-in-nature pictures almost always ascribe to women a mode of existence that is
				categorically different from man's. Woman is seen as more of nature than man, less
				in opposition to it both physically and mentally. Implicitly, the male is seen as
				more closely identified with culture, "the means by which humanity transcends the
				givens of natural existence, bends them to its purposes, controls them in its
					interests."<note>Sherry Ortner, "Is Female to Male as Nature is to Culture?"
					Feminist Studies, 1, No. 2 (Fall, 1972), p. 10</note></p>
			<p>This woman/nature-man/culture dichotomy is one of the most ancient and universal
				ideas ever devised by man and is hardly new to modern Western culture. However, in
				Western bourgeois culture, the real and important role of women in domestic,
				economic and social life becomes ever more recognized: increasingly, the bourgeoisie
				educates its daughters, depends upon their social and economic cooperation and
				values their human companionship. Above all, the idea that women belong to the same
				order of being as men is more articulated than ever before. In this context, to
				cling to ancient notions of women as a race apart from men—as creatures of nature
				rather than of culture—is to defend blatantly an ideology that is everywhere
				contested and contradicted by experience. Nevertheless, the majority of nude-in¬
				nature pictures state just this thesis.</p>
			<p>In countless 19th- and 20th-century paintings—Romantic, Symbolist or
				Expressionist—female nudes in outdoor settings are treated as natural inhabitants of
				the landscape. Although modern artists have characterized it differently, they agree
				that this woman-nature realm is an inviting but alien mode of experience. It both
				attracts and repels the male. It beckons him to step out of rationalized, bourgeois
				society and to enter a world where men might live through their senses instincts or
				imaginations. But the condition of entry—shedding the social identity of the
				bourgeois male—also entails loss of autonomy and of the power to shape and control
				one's world. The male artist longs to join those naked beings in that other imagined
				realm, but he cannot because he fails to imagine their full humanity—or his own.
				While he values his own instincts, or that part of himself that responds to nature,
				he regards this portion of his nature as feminine," antagonistic to his socialized
				masculine ego and belonging to that other "natural" order. Nor can he acknowledge in
				women a "masculine principle"—an autonomous self that knows itself as separate from
				and opposed to the natural, biological world. Like Munch before his Madonna, he
				hovers before his dream in ambivalent desire.</p>
			<p>Rarely do modern artists imagine naked men in that other realm. When they do, as in
				works by Cézanne or Kirchner, the male figures tend to look uncomfortable or
				self-conscious. More often, the male in nature is clothed—both in the literal sense
				or metaphorically—with a social identity and a social or cultural project. He is a
				shepherd, a hunter an artist. Matisse's Boy With Butterfly Net (1907) is a
				magnificent image of a male in nature (or rather a male acting against nature),
				highly individualized and properly equipped for a specific purpose. In beach scenes
				by the Fauves and the Kirchner circle, males—when they are present—are not "bathers"
				i.e., placid creatures of the water, but modern men going swimming in bathing suits
				or in the raw. They are active, engaged in a culturally defined recreation, located
				in historical time and space. The female bather who has no counterpart in modern
				art, is a naked existence, outside of culture. Michelet, the 19th-century historian,
				poetically expressed the ideas implicit in the genre: man, he wrote, creates
				history, while woman: </p>
			<pb n="50"/>
			<quote>follows the noble and serene epic that Nature chants in her harmonious cycles,
				repeating herself with a touching grace of constancy and fidelity. .. . Nature is a
				woman. History, which we very foolishly put in the feminine gender, is a rude,
				savage male, a sun-burnt, dusty traveller... </quote>
			<note>Jules Michelet, Woman (La Femme), trans. J. W. Palmer (New York, 1860), pp.
				104-105.</note>
			<p>Even in Matisse’s Joy of Living (1906), where men and women share an Arcadian life,
				cultural activities (music-making, animal husbandry) are male endeavors while women
				exist merely as sensual beings or abandon themselves to emotionally expressive but
				artless and spontaneous dance.</p>
			<p>How we relate to these works becomes a compelling issue once their sexual-political
				content is apparent. The issue, however, is difficult to grasp without first coming
				to terms with the ideological character of our received notions of art. For in our
				society, art—along with all high culture—has replaced religion (that is, among the
				educated) as the repository of what we are taught to regard as our highest, most
				enduring values. As sanctified a category as any our society offers, art silently
				but ritually validates and invests with mystifying authority the ideals that sustain
				existing social relations. In art, those ideals are given to us as general,
				universal values, collective cultural experience, "our" heritage, or as some other
				abstraction removed from concrete experience. Physically and ideologically, art is
				isolated from the rest of life, surrounded with solemnity, protected from moral
				judgement. Our very encounters with it in museums, galleries and art books are
				structured to create the illusion that the significance of art has little or nothing
				to do with the conflicts and problems that touch common experience. Established art
				ideologies reinforce this illusion. According to both popular and scholarly
				literature, true artistic imaginations transcend the ordinary fantasies, the class
				and sex prejudices and the bad faith that beset other human minds. Indeed, most of
				us believe that art, by definition, is always good—because it is of purely esthetic
				significance (and the purely esthetic is thought to be good), or because it confirms
				the existence of the imagination and of individualism, or because it reveals other
				"timeless" values or truths. Most of us have been schooled to believe that art, qua
				art, if it is "good" art, is never bad for anyone, never has anything to do with the
				oppression of the powerless, and never imposes on us values that are not universally
				beneficial.</p>
			<p>The modern masterpieces of erotic art that! have been discussing enjoy this
				ideological protection even while they affirm the ideals of male domination and
				female subjugation. Once admitted to that high category of Art, they acquire an
				invisible authority that silently acts upon the consciousness, confirming from on
				high what social customs and law enforce from below. In their invisible and hence
				unquestioned authority, they proclaim—without acknowledging it—what men and women
				can be to themselves and to each other. But once that authority is made visible, we
				can see what is before us: art and artists are made on earth, in history, in
				organized society. And in the modern era as in the past, what has been sanctified as
				high art and called True, Good and Beautiful is born of the aspirations of those who
				are empowered to shape culture. </p>

			<epigraph>
				<p>My gratitude to Flavia Alaya and Joan Kelly-Gadol, whose own work and
					conversation have enriched and clarified my thinking.</p>
			</epigraph>

		</body>
		<back>
			<p>Carol Duncan is an art historian who teaches at Ramapo College. She has published in
				Artforum and The Art Bulletin and her essay "Teaching the Rich" appears in the an¬
				thology New Ideas in Art Education (edited by Gregory Battcock). She is also on the
				"anti-catalogue" committee of Artists Meeting for Cultural Change.</p>
		</back>


	</text>
</TEI>
