<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>"Female Experience in Art": The Impact of Women's Art in a Work
					Environment</title>
				<author>Ruth E. Iskin</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Heresies</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="71"/>
			<head><title>Female Experience in Art“: The Impact of Women's Art in a Work
					Environment</title></head>
			<byline><persName>Ruth E. Iskin</persName></byline>

			<p> In early summer of 1975 1 was asked by the Women's Committee and the Office of Equal
				Opportunity of Aerospace Corporation to curate an exhibition of women's art on the
				subject of female experience. This seemed to me to offer the potential of reaching a
				broad audience and avoiding the defensive reactions often attached to "feminist
				art“ or "female sensibility“ in the art world.<note>The exhibition also provided a
					good starting point for sorting out my own views on the more complex issues of
					feminist content and female sensibility in art, though 1prefer the term "female
					form language“ to "female sensibility" or "female imagery" because the latter
					have come to be identified with one specific, biologically oriented
					theory.</note> This art has been at the heart of an ongoing, often heated
				controversy which has clouded the issues and obstructed direct perception of the
				work. </p>
			<p>Female experience has been the starting point for the new art created by feminists
				since 1969. Consciousness raising and other forms of women's communication,
				sharing and group action, initiated as a result of the women's movement, made female
				experience a rich source of subject matter and sparked the fresh energy with which
				women are making art. For the show I selected the work of 15 L.A.
					artists<note>Funding limitations did not permit the inclusion of works by
					artists who reside outside of the L.A. area.</note> to represent both a broad
				scope of women's experiences and a diversity of media, ranging from large environ¬
				mental pieces to paintings, drawings, photography, prints, collage, assemblage,
				and artists" books. In an attempt to build a bridge between the art and the
				creators' intentions, I requested written statements from the artists, which,
				along with biographical information, were available in a folder in the exhibition
				area.</p>
			<p>The exhibition was on view from August 18th through September 5th in the Cafeteria
				Conference Dining Rooms of the Aerospace Corporation. It was the first
				exhibition of professional art on the company's grounds, preceded only by shows of
				art by employees. Although sponsored and funded by the corporation, the show was
				initiated by feminist employees who conceived it to offer "insight into the
				emotional aspects of contemporary women.“<note>Orbiter Vol. 15, No. 20 (1975), p. 2,
					from a letter to the editor by the Women's Week Planning Committee.</note> They
				scheduled it to coincide with Women's Week, a program featuring prominent speakers
				and entertainers.</p>
			<p>The management of Aerospace Corporation ("a non-profit research and development
				corporation which provides technical direction of general systems of engineering,
				primarily for the Air Force“<note>Glenda Madrid (of the Aerospace Office of Equal
					Opportunity and Women's Planning Committee) in conversation with the
					author.</note>) had been forced to develop new policies for hiring women in
				order to meet affirmative-action requirements for receiving government funds. Women
				are in the minority, constituting only 25% of the roughly 3,200 Aerospace employees.
				Most of them (80%- 85%) are in lower-echelon clerical and secretarial positions;
				only a few rank among the engineers, scientists, or chief administrators. The
				company was, no doubt, hoping that the art exhibition and the activities of
				Women's Week would go on record as testimony to their newfound good will toward
				women. Much to my surprise, and to the dismay of the sponsors, the exhibition became
				the focal point of hot debate. Violent emotional reactions, protest and. support
				quickly assumed the dimensions of a local scandal and echoed for months in letters
				to the editor in <title>The Orbiter</title>, the company's newspaper.</p>
			<p>The art in the exhibition offered a feminist point of view on subject matter usually
				treated from a male perspective. Though one might assume that the controversial
				responses arose out of an alienation from contemporary art forms, it seems that the
				conflict stemmed primarily from feminist content.<note>Though some of the
					non-feminist viewers more familiar with contemporary art forms did not share the
					protesters' offense, it is very unlikely that a "neutral“ exhibit of
					contemporary art would have caused similar negative reactions. In addition, none
					of the protesters mentioned any criticism of art forms; all their comments
					tended to focus on content, and most of them made reference to a general
					distaste for feminism.</note> None of the works included were blatantly
				political protest art, yet they all reflected, to varying degrees, a new feminist
				consciousness. It was this consciousness —judging from the reactions of many of
				the female viewers—that was unfamiliar and threatening.</p>
			<p>We are accustomed to think of political art as crude, illustrative, or plainly
				propagandistic, in contrast to "good/serious/modernist" art. It has of course been
				pointed out that no art is entirely disconnected from its historical, political,
				cultural, and geographical environment, and that therefore any art reflects these
				conditions. However, feminist art is often labeled political art because the
				consciousness it reflects is held by a minority, and it is at odds with the tacit
				beliefs of those in power. The label "political art“ is used to demean the work
				rather than to evaluate its artistic significance.</p>
			<p>In a recent interview with Judy Chicago, the artist articulated her thoughts and
				feelings about these issues:</p>
			<quote>The issue of politics for me arises at the point where my work interfaces with
				culture; it does not arise at the point of origin in my studio. never think about
				politics when ! make my art; rather 1 think about being true to my own impulses,
				and for a woman to be true to her own impulses is, at this point in history, a
				political act.... What ! challenge is the idea that masculinity is inherently
				better than femininity; that hardness is better than softness, that defensiveness
				is better than vulnerability, and <pb n="72"/>
				<pb n="73"/> that violence is better than sharing. The assertion of womanhood is a
				challenge to all these values that allow war dehumanization, rape, and art that
				lacks relationship with reality to continue.<note>All the quotations from artists
					are from recent interviews conducted for this article</note></quote>

			<p> Faith Wilding elaborated on the relation between personal and political
				change:</p>
			<quote>It has always been a tenet of the feminist movement that the personal is
				political. It is political because when a person becomes transformed, enters into
				public experience, and infuses her own experience into the public, the world becomes
				transformed for her but in addition she then has the possibility of transforming
				the world. We have witnessed too many people who are in politics who have never
				experienced any kind of personal change or real vision.</quote>

			<p> What specifically triggered the controversy? The art in the exhibition included a
				wide range of feminist work: parodies on public images of women (Helen Alm Roth and
				Carole Caroompas); private images of women and interior spaces (Margaret Neilson);
				women's self-images integrated with their historical and mythological references
				(Judy Chicago and Faith Wilding); references to women's vulnerability, powerless¬
				ness, and powerfulness (Astrid Preston); relics of admired female figures as magic
				talismans (Hazel Slawson); communal efforts (Maria Karras); and the quilt/grid
				pattern and color pink seen as tributes to women's collaborative forms (Sheila de
				Bretteville).</p>
			<p>In her tableau environment Remnants in Homage to Lily Bart from Edith Wharton's House
				of Mirth, Nancy Youdelman "reconstructed" a scene from the book with theatrical
				grandeur and presence. The tableau represents the climax of Wharton's novel, when
				Lily Bart, having lost her wealth and status kills herself. Hauntingly life-like,
				her full-size figure, bearing the artist's own features reclines in bed. Her skin
				tone is grayish and the sleeping drops that caused her death are by the side of her
				bed. The tloor is cluttered with remnants of her life: letters photographs delicate
				laces dresses, corsets, and veils. Youdelman creates metaphors (sleep, passivity,
				death) for what have been essential aspects of female experience: economic
				dependence on others, lack of ultimate control over one’s own life, victimization by
				circumstances. In the guise of a 19th-century tragedy, Lily Bart's story is
				emblematic for women who have remained powerless in society.</p>
			<p>In Youdelman's photographic series Leaves: A Self Portrait, the artist is lying on
				the ground, gradually being covered with leaves (from photograph to photograph)
				until she is entirely buried:</p>
			<quote>It represented ways I felt; 1 felt numb all over, or like a sleepwalker,
				something that could just disappear and 1 think that is that powerlessness in
				female experience, sleep. There is also something esthetic about it; 1 love the
				color of the leaves; it is about death and one could suppose that it might also mean
				renewal.</quote>
			<p> Youdelman treads on precarious ground in presenting the passive female figure,
				lying unconscious as horizontal female figures have so often been used in the
				history of (male) art to entice the spectator by reminding him of his vertical
				superiority. However Youdelman's tableau successfully evokes the solemn empathy of
				the viewer who is confronted with the victims feelings about her powerlessness.</p>
			<p>In Jan Lester's tableau environment—Cats Enamoured Kits: Helpless Tom and Merciless
				Sex Kitten (1974)—two cats are anthropomorphized to enact a sexual-encounter
				scene. The human environment, dress and behavior patterns throw into relief the
				stereotyped patterns of men and women, only the roles are reversed. The female cat
				plays the determined "attacker the seducer while the male cat withdraws with some
				apprehension. At the same time, Lester sees her work as a manifestation of how women
				are perceived when they take an active role in a situation:</p>
			<quote>The tableau had to do with sexual politics and with the female taking power. It
				goes farther than just one sexual encounter, it goes out into the world in
				general. It is one situation like a snapshot that makes it clear that this goes on n
				al situations in society.</quote>
			<pb n="74"/>
			<p>Sherie Scheer's series—Heavenly Visions— depicts Fragonard-inspired images of her own
				baby as a cherub floating in an infinite blue California sky. "Wherever they go,
				they have no choice in it. ... The heavenly vision in which they appear is both
				ideal and it is limbo." This reflects Scheer's own experience as a first-time
				mother:</p>
			<quote>I found the child very sensual. It was unexpected to me what a strong female
				biological experience it was to have a child, and then to be absolutely in love with
				the child. In the course of using her as model, however, 1 made her cry, sometimes
				neglected her, and in a way used her, both as a model and as inspiration. was aware
				that the art that makes it in L.A. or made it at the time (two years ago) was
				non-image-oriented and I am very image-oriented. 1 was also entirely aware that
				showing babies in one's art was really outrageous and it gave me a devilish
				pleasure, because think that a lot of art that makes it is empty formula and doesn’t
				have any blood in it; it is not daring and it is not a turn-on either. So it was
				like breaking a taboo, and especially for a woman artist.</quote>
			<p>Like Scheer Gilah Hirsch deals with female power within its traditional domain. She
				uses the imagery of food as "a secret biography, a metaphorical code.</p>


			<quote>The shape and color of food itself was so completely right and ripe for my own
				feelings that it became a symbol for me; especially the tomato strawberry, and egg
				became symbols for myself. These are expressed in scale and potency; it is a strange
				word to use in relationship to an egg, a potent egg. The strawberry is one of the
				few fruits that carries its seed on the outside, it is a vulnerable fruit; it is
				juicy and has strength and vulnerability at the same time. Rather than feminist,
				these paintings are, 1 think, more expressive of femaleness. It was a personal
				statement for me....l can't separate my experience from a female experience; 1
				feel powers in me, very specifically in certain centers in me.</quote>
			<p>Suzanne Lacy's book <title>Rape Is</title> (1972) has a white cover which becomes
				bloody red on the inside. To open the book one must tear apart a red sticker labeled
					"rape.“<note>The precedent for this feminist use of the sticker is Susana
					Torre's exhibition catalogue for "Twenty-Six Contemporary Women Artists“
					(Aldrich Museum, Ridgefield, Conn. April, 1971), in which tearing the seal
					implied not only physical violation in order to "enter" the long-hidden works of
					women artists, but also the destruction of a square cold black seal on a white
					cover, which represented the prevalent Minimal Art, to reach the warm inside
					covers, colored red.</note> Lacy's book names 21 instances of rape—not only as a
				sexual violation but also as a series of psychological assaults:</p>
			<quote>Rape is when you are skipping home from school, and are surrounded suddenly by a
				gang of large boys. Rape is when the man next door exposes himself and you feel
				guilty for having looked. Rape is when you're walking alone, thinking your own
				thoughts and a man driving by shouts "HI SWEETIE!"</quote>

			<pb n="75"/>
			<p> The traditional representation of rape in art (with the exception of
					Kollwitz<note>Kollwitz's etching Raped is unique in its complete focus on the
					experience of the raped woman: she is lying on the ground, dead or unconscious.
					Neither the rapist nor his act are in the picture.</note>) represents the
				experience of the rapist by focusing on his strength, activity and beauty, and
				further removes rape from a realistic experience through mythological disguise.
				Lacy first forces the viewer to enact a metaphorical rape ("deflowering" the book
				by tearing the sticker) and then confronts the viewer with what rape means to its
				victim.</p>
			<p>In Karen Carson's drawings of beds (1971-75) woman is the bed. The drawings are
				expressionistic in style and imagery, powerful as well as satirical statements
				about the myth of happiness in sexual relationships. In this case, too, the
				"disturbing“ feminist content of Carson's drawings arises from the art-historical
				tradition of reclining female figures on beds and sofas. Many of these women become
				an integral part of the inanimate, passive, yet sexually inviting surface on which
				they are reclining. Unlike males Carson identifies with the oppressed— the
				woman/bed—and at the same time, as artist, she takes active charge of that
				surface, penetrates it with a giant screw (<title>Screw</title>), converts it into
				a carton of eggs (<title>Fasy Lay</title>), severs it with a saw blade (<title>Edge
					of Night</title>), or crowns it with a giant camera (Easy Shot).</p>
			<p>These surreal visualizations are take-offs on popular puns, which function as titles
				and were often the starting points for the drawings. The series began as a macabre
				though humorous comment on popular sexist consumerism. What emerges is a violent
				denunciation of sexual roles, until finally the bed—former haven of consumer
				pleasure—disintegrates from within (<title>Cracking Up</title> and <title>Shattered
					Dreams</title>), smashing any illusions we might still have about bed and woman.
				In these most recent drawings the formerly inanimate object erupts uncontrollably,
				and its fragments fly into space. What is commonly labeled Women’s Liberation is
				in fact, as Carson expresses it, an excruciatingly painful process beginning with
				the recognition of exterior oppression, leading to the experience of oppression
				from within and finally building toward a complex re-integration—represented by the
				artist's new work—collages in which the torn and mutilated fragments are reunited on
				a cohesive surface.</p>
			<quote>would say that these drawings were intentionally propagandistic.... It had to
				do with consumer and sexual politics. The frame of mind that ! was in when I did
				these drawings was severe frustration over treatment by men. The drawings were also
				politically charged for me because ! talked about them to all kinds of groups from
				Valley housewives to a continuation high school culture-hour class; thought people
				would be bored by these draw<pb n="76"/>ings and they weren’t. They seemed to have a
				good time, and related to the drawings immediately. Now, it is not necessary to
				have a good time when viewing art, but there was blanket recognition of the issues.
				When 1 looked in the newspaper I noticed that you could apply sexual politics,
				directly or indirectly, to almost every image in the advertisement world; every
				image implies sexual oromises. My original fantasy was that ! would have enough
				money to take out a full page ad in the L.A. Times, and just change the images a
				little bit. Obviously the most political thing about that was my fantasy about how
				many people 1 could reach that way. It is the nature of good political art to be
				recognizable and understandable by a lot of people and maybe at a visceral level
				too. Political art is often satirical, and probably most effective at that
				level.</quote>
			<p>The exhibition provided an opportunity to witness the heightened impact of
				contemporary feminist art when viewed by a "non-art“ audience—a cross-section of
				middle America that normally would not encounter art, and specifically by a female
				audience alienated from feminism. (The negative response came primarily from
					women<note>The men seemed to react neutrally to the show, probably because the
					art did not expose their experience, and possibly, as was suggested to me by
					Glenda Madrid, because they are more prone to intellectualize and thus more
					removed from the level of emotional response the show raised for women.</note>)
				It can also be seen as a test case for implementing a long-desired goal —bringing
				art into a public daily work environment.</p>
			<p>Had the show at Aerospace been exhibited in any number of established or alternative
				gallery spaces, it probably would not have caused unusual debate, and certainly it
				would not have prompted any doubt about the artistic merit of the work.<note>When I
					curated the Aerospace exhibition ! did censor myself at one point: l did not
					include Chicago's Red Flag lithograph even though, dealing with menstrua tion,
					it would have fit well into an exhibit on female experience in art. Its literal
					character prevented me from exhibiting it in that context, as l anticipated that
					it would be shocking to the audience.</note> In the Cafeteria Conference Rooms
				of Aerospace, however, the exhibit infiltrated a male environment that ordinarily
				would not display women's work made from a feminist perspective and certainly
				would not give it public acclaim. The work was predominantly considered
				scandalous: it engendered passionate objections and firm negative judgments. The
				show was labeled pornography rather than art by people who were unlikely ever to
				have considered what is or isn’t art.</p>
			<p>This disclaimer was the protesters' attempt to dismiss such threatening and upsetting
				material. Casting it as pornography implied that the art lacked any real esthetic
				value and therefore need not be taken seriously. The level of naiveté of the
				critical responses—when opposed to the more sophisticated criticism to which we are
				accustomed from much of the art world— was refreshing in its directness. One letter
				of protest stated:</p>
			<quote>I object to the Art Exhibition. 1 find it degrading. As a woman, and hopefully
				a lady, find it extremely offensive. 1am unable to lower my sights to the gutter
				level of this exhibit. In my opinion, it is lewd, vulgar, obscene and immoral.
				Since when did good taste and modesty go out-of-style?<note>Orbiter, Vol. 15, No. 17
					(1975), p. 2.</note></quote>

			<p> In another letter signed by 36 people-almost a petition—the art was called:</p>
			<quote>...in poor taste, bad character, and a definite infringement on the rights of all
				women anc men who give sex the dignity, respect and honor that was intended for the
				human race. The Aerospace Corporation has drastically changed its practices since
				the 1960s to allow this type of "smut“ to be exhibited, and the employees were
				encouraged through desk-to-desk distribution and advertising to view the
				exhibition.<lb/> We are sure that with much less expense to the Company, the
				representatives... could have arranged for a display of pornography, pictures and
				books from one of the adult bookstores in the Los Angeles Area, and at a lower
				insurance premium. The Aerospace Women's Committee does not speak for all of the
				female employees, as there are those of us who still adhere to the old principle
				that we were liberated immediately when we were born in America, we enjoy being
				treated as a woman and we are definitely Miss or Mrs. and not Ms.<note>12.
					Ibid.</note></quote>
			<p>Clearly these female viewers at Aerospace "saw" in the art their own worst fears of
				feminism. Their objections though focused on the exhibition, were rooted in their
				alienation from the organized women's movement. Confronted by art that dealt with an
				oppression familiar in most of their lives, real images that did not correspond to
				the illusion of the American dream presented a powerful threat.</p>
			<p>The art was perceived as offensive precisely because it was not placed in a
				neutralizing environment like a gallery, where viewers can easily hide behind
				anonymity. The art invaded their own daily working sphere where it threatened how
				they were viewed in their professional positions. Brought into the work context, the
				art reflected more directly upon them. The heightened emotional reactions caused a
				strong need to disassociate themselves verbally from the picture of womanhood
				presented in the show.</p>
			<p>While identification with female experiences and values is threatening in any
				situation in a patriarchal society, such identification may be virtually impossible
				when introduced into a work environment dominated by male values and power. Such an
				environment, by implication, and as a condition for the possibility of working
				there, demands a woman's identification with patriarchy over a recognition of her
				own oppression. To admit that what was expressed in the art is real—women's
				powerlessness and powerfulness their sexual feelings and experiences, and the fact
				that women are rape victims—is to shatter the very myth that has sustained
				traditional womanhood all along. It is admitting publicly to an embarrassing,
				private part of woman's experience which she has attempted to conceal even from
				herself in an effort to preserve the "human dignity" of which <pb n="77"/> she is
				robbed daily. This response is one we all felt during initial stages of our
				feminism, when we first became conscious of the shame and self-dislike we had buried
				for so long, before we were ready to reshape our own feelings by taking pride in
				ourselves other women, and art that dealt with these subjects.</p>
			<p>The reactions of the women at Aerospace are not, I suspect, uncommon. I doubt very
				much that a minority of Black workers in a predominantly white work environment
				would find it any easier to respond to an exhibition of art exposing painful aspects
				of the experience of being Black in American society; or that Detroit factory
				workers for example, readily identify with the realistic presentation in Rivera’s
				mural of the hardships of factory work.<note>Joanne Parent (one of the authors of
					"The Fourth World Manifesto“) told me the following incident. While she was
					working in a factory, experiencing first-hand the hardships involved, she
					understood how well Rivera's mural portrayed those; but when she commented on
					that to her fellow workers they negated or at least minimized their own
					experience of oppression compared to its heightened portrayal in the mural. The
					similarity to women's situation is that workers who (consciously or
					unconsciously) feel powerless in their jobs deny the pain of their experiences
					if its expression would jeopardize the only wage-earning option available to
					them. It is no accident that women all over the country first explored their
					oppression in the private, safe, and supportive context of consciousness-raising
					groups, removed from the institutions in which they experienced that
					oppression in their daily lives.</note> There is, however an important
				difference between the situation of women and other workers. Regardless of their
				status, women are subject to their oppression as women which crosses class
				boundaries. In âddition to their job or profession—whether factory worker teacher
				nurse, doctor engineer or scientist—women still do the unpaid, endless, menial labor
				of housework, bear children and carry the sole responsibility of raising them. All
				women are potential rape victims, and all women live in a male-dominated society
				which is based on various cultural versions of enslavement and denies women's
					culture.<note>It is for this reason that feminism and feminist art have validity
					for all women. For the same reason, the Marxist model of workers' oppression
					does not ultimately address itself to women's oppression, beyond that of
					working-class women. For an extensive analysis of these issues see "The Fourth
					World Manifesto," reprinted in: Radical Feminism, Anne Koedt. Ellen Levine,
					Anita Rapone, eds. (New York, 1973), pp. 322-357.</note></p>
			<p>Those women who had not attempted to step out of female role-conditioning in their
				jobs at Aerospace were more oppressed than other workers because they received lower
				wages and had lower professional status. They were the most offended by the show The
				middle-class women who rebelled against female role-conditioning in their jobs at
				Aerospace (the engineers programmers scientists) were the only ones who had
				developed a feminist consciousness and reacted favorably to the exhibition. For
				example, in a letter of support, one woman expressed her response to the exhibition
				and the protesters' views:</p>
			<quote>That women have suffered personally and professionally from conditions ranging
				from lack of opportunity to manipulation and even exploitation on the basis that
				they are women is uncomfortable to face.<lb/> The Art Exhibition, a high quality
				collection of some very honest and courageous works, was unusually rich in content
				for those of us who in some way or another have "been there." Although there was a
				deliberate intent to shock, it was as a means to focus emotionally on the art; it
				was not propagandistic. These are personal and esthetic interpretations of some of
				the hard truths encountered by women, and the obscenity lies in the fact that
				these wrongs arise because of wide-range departure from good human values.<lb/>
				Those who want to oppose smut should look for it in our politics, in our mores, in
				the management of our corporations, in our personal relationships.<note>Orbiter,
					Vol. 15, No. 20 (1975), p. 2.</note></quote>
			<p>In her review of the exhibition Melinda Worz concluded:</p>
			<quote>The Female Experience in Art offers a wide panorama of contemporary women's
				attitudes. It is gratifying to see such a high quality showoutside the established
				sacred halls of art, as part of a working environment.<note>Art Week, Vol. 6, No. 29
					(Sept. 6, 1975)</note></quote>
			<p>In thinking now about this exhibition, 1 realize that it was unrealistic to expect an
				enthusiastic reception, or even acceptance, for art like this among female viewers
				who were not already feminists or somewhat sympathetic to feminism. It might have
				seemed that the work was not perceived for what it was—but on the contrary it was
				in fact accurately perceived, and found objectionable. Such response is typical when
				feminism is introduced into a male-dominated culture.</p>
			<p>For those women at Aerospace who were sympathetic to feminism, the exhibition was a
				positive experience providing a new awareness of the existence of women's culture
				created by contemporary feminists. In that sense the exhibition did broaden the
				audience for contemporary feminist art. For some of these women who previously had
				no particular interest in art, the exhibition was a beginning of what has since
				become an ongoing interest and commitment to women's art.</p>
			<quote>I am still thinking about one piece in the show which 1 would like to own if 1
				had money. decided that if 1 bought art, it would be women's art because of my
				commitment to feminist artists.<note>17. Glenda Madrid, in a recent conversation
					with the author. Madrid was also a major source of information for the
					responses to the exhibition and the statistics and position of women employees
					at Aerospace.</note></quote>
			<p>Earlier that same summer, my colleagues and in the Feminist Studio Workshop<note>The
					Feminist Studio Workshop is the first alternative institution for women in the
					arts and humanities; it is housed in the unique context of the Woman's Building
					in Los Angeles. Since it was founded in 1973, over 100 women have received their
					education at the Feminist Studio Workshop, and several thousand students have
					participated in the Extension Program at the Woman's Building.</note> had come
				to a collective definition of feminist art based on our goals, experiences and
				observation of our students' work. We defined the function of feminist art as
				raising consciousness inviting dialogue, and transforming culture. It became clear
				to me that both the individual art exhibited at Aerospace and the exhibition as a
				whole in fact realized these goals to the extent that was possible in that time and
				space. </p>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p> Ruth Iskin is a feminist art historian living in Los Angeles, formerly co-director
				of Womanspace and the editor of Womanspace journal. Now she is director of the
				Woman's Building Galleries, on the faculty of the Feminist Studio Workshop, and an
				editor of Chrysalis: A New Magazine of Womens Culture. </p>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
