<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Issue 1 Introduction</title>
				<author/>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Heresies: Issue 1</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<head>From the First-Issue Collective</head>
				<pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue01/images/01_004.jpg"/>
							
				<p> Feminism—Art—Politics. What is their connection? In theory? In reality?</p>
				<p>Once there was a women's art center that was very excited about an “Art as Work“
					seminar 1 proposed. They wanted a short personal resumé to follow the course
					description in the catalogue — to let students know who 1 was, where I was
					coming from: Harmony Hammond is a lesbian feminist artist who has exhibited at
					Callery X and Gallery Z and taught at R. University and C. University. They
					wanted my labels and then did not like them. No seminar. Really, was coming on
					too strong. Couldn’t 1 use a different word? Or just not say it at all? Would 1
					be teaching art or politics? They were an “Art center. They were afraid, they
					said, afraid would jeopardize.</p>
				<p>Jeopardize what? Their art? Their teaching? Their students? Their bodies? Their
					minds? Their sexuality? Their politics? Their power? Their authority? Their
					thinking? They did not know, they were just afraid. 1did not fit their concept
					of a feminist and therefore ! was dangerous.</p>
				<p>Labels. The meaninglessness of labels. The power of labels. The confining. What
					does it mean to be a lesbian, radical feminist, activist, mother, artist? 1 am
					all of these individually and combined. It means 1 am political. It means I want
					to change existing power relationships. A list of experiences. The power of
					labels is the power of ideas and action combined.</p>
				<p>The political mother, the political artist, the political feminist, and the
					political lesbian refuse to be second- class. They take action by “doing.“ They
					refuse to be isolated into separatist stances, and they become a total whole.
					They add up to what Charlotte Bunch has called a “non-aligned feminism"—not
					automatically attached to one line ot feminism (socialist/left vs. reformist vs.
					cultural/ spiritual) but rather evaluating each individual issue and situation
					from an independent feminist perspective. Lesbian. Radical feminist. Activist.
					Mother. Artist.</p>
				<p>The common denominator is woman. Women are oppressed as a class. This oppression
					underlies the patriarchal institutions of capitalism, imperialism, racism, and
					heterosexism. To end all forms of oppression we must first end the oppression of
					all women regardless ot sexuality or economic class, racial or cultural
					background.</p>
				<p>Lesbian. Radical feminist. Activist. Mother. Artist. Together they form my
					teminism. Feminism is my politics. My art both is formed by and is a statement
					of my feminism.</p>
				<signed>H.H.</signed>
			</div>
			<div>
				<p> While l’d always worked in social programs, 1 never considered myselt a
					political person. Political groups so often revealed confused priorities that 1
					inevitably ended up by questioning my own. But feminism was different—so much
					was personally at stake. If I questioned my commitment (how can 1 be amused by
					this or not outraged by that), I soon found l was not amused and l was outraged
					by things ! might once have considered innocuous or simply unalterable. Feminism
					had become a persistent way of living and thinking and the most important
					awareness of my life.</p>
				<p>Today ! trust the impulses calling out for radical change because theyre rooted
					in a lifetime of self-analysis continuously and consistently validated by other
					women. Frustration, it seems, is being resolved in conviction and action and the
					awareness of this power has been startling to me. Needless to say, art which
					strengthens that awareness is exhilarating.</p>
				<p>l am a medievalist, I was attracted to the field by the escapist fantasies of
					folklore and romance. But ! now feel that all art—whether ancient or modern—can
					be seen and judged within a feminist context.</p>
				<signed>A.L.</signed>
			</div>
			<div>
				<p> When pressed by the people who ask “What do you do?" at times ! call myself an
					artist and then no one knows what to expect. The term is so vague and useless
					that it does not begin to identify a point of view. The fact that art work keeps
					the bourgeoisie in style, and the bourgeoisie keeps all the art, suggests that
					most artists don't bother with politics and ideology, instead they are united by
					a lifestyle: generally you must privatize your work, hang your head to the left
					late at night in the bars, and think deeply about how your work will be
					understood in the melancholic future; be concerned about your isolation from the
					community.</p>
				<p>It is difficult not to become a cynic. Opportunism knocks. Even the women's
					movement is another stepping stone towards critical recognition. Most people are
					more concerned with the objects we are producing than the world into which we
					place our work. 1 make abstract paint- ings and super-8 films—but not for a
					living. I work as an editor for a left news magazine called Seven Days. This is
					where ! learned the business of developing an audience and disseminating
					information. Heresies is an attempt to politicize the art world; a chance to
					attack the history ot our work as opposed to “documenting" it.</p>
				<p>have been a feminist it seems ever since Inoticed I was living with great
					difficulty, it came out during the 1960s - but that's a long story. In the
					1970s, feminism has tendencies which serve merely to push liberal institutions
					to their farthest extremes. This has left many women caught in a dubious
					struggle; a recognition of strength and an inability to act. The feminist
					movement should not work towards gaining economic power, but towards developing
					a coherent ideology if we are to participate in change and work towards
					socialism. (You knew l’d say that.) The point is that an understanding of
					feminism without an analysis of class is like a long-tailed cat in a room full
					of rocking chairs. Capitalism is so efficient that it can sustain its own
					alternatives, likewise the art world—one more radical magazine.</p>
				<signed>E.H.</signed>
			</div>

			<pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue01/images/01_005.jpg"/>
			<div>
				<p> I am a feminist first and a socialist second, rather than a Socialist-Feminist.
					Not because I don't care about what happens to the oppressed men in the world.
					Not because lm against an ideally democratic socialism. But because women's
					oppression crosses economic-class lines. Its a matter of focus. Clearly the
					needs of welfare-class women are most urgent and those of upper-class women are
					least urgent. Some socialists say that getting rid of patriarchy won’t change
					the world. I wonder. Even in revolutionary socialist movements women must
					maintain an autonomous base. Revolution for Everyman isn’t the same as real
					social change; it has taken place in the past without solving the "woman
					question."</p>
				<p>In the meantime, living in a capitalist country without a strong Socialist Party
					provokes an irresistible urge to kill time as a liberal feminist. Even though
					l’m aware of the dangers of opportunism, reformism, co-optation, and all the
					slimy horde, 1 often find myself working for reform rather than revolution
					because I can't bear to see nothing done.</p>
				<p>Within the art world, this means l work to get women artists into a system I
					oppose. Outside, in the real world, this means I want the ERA passed because its
					going to make a difference in women's lives. I want to see a politically aware
					feminist culture and I hope that Heresies will help create it and help destroy
					some of the boundaries that separate women from the power to make a better
					society that will fit our needs as well as men's.</p>
				<p>(P.S. Because l’m a critic, l’ve been called a “class enemy" of artists, which is
					bullshit. l’m exploited by publishers, and perhaps editors, just as artists are
					exploited by galleries, and perhaps critics. lidentify with artists whether or
					not they identify with me because long experience has shown me that our lives
					are more or less the same.)</p>
				<signed>L.R.L.</signed>
			</div>
			<div>
				<p> When we decided that each of us in the first issue collective should write an
					individual statement to put our political differences “out front,“ I thought it
					was a fine idea. But trying to write one page about my notion of how feminism
					relates to Marxism relates to making theory and making films was easier said
					than done: too much to argue in too little space. So what 1 wanted to do was
					write, please see my article on page x” where l’ve tried to work out some of
					these problems in more analytical depth. But my sister-editors said, “write
					something personal." They chided me for my rhetorical style and my obsessive?
					academic? commitment to making “complete” arguments. "Who are you in all that,"
					they asked. O.K. 1m a woman, l'm white, l'm 28. 1m a film teacher, l'm a
					student, l'm a writer, theorist, critic, filmmaker, I do political work—in the
					feminist community and with a new Coalition (July 4th) thats building toward a
					mass, progressive peoples' movement in this country. I guess l’m whats come to
					be called a cultural worker.</p>
				<p>Often it seems there’s just not enough time in each day to do all the things that
					have to be done. And to earn a living, and write a dissertation, and see the art
					l care about, and do the laundry, and talk with students, and be with the
					friends I love, and see the ocean sometimes. Putting it all together, l'doften
					like a few clones of myself to help out. juggle whats possible with whats
					not.</p>
				<p>Where does the fight for women fit with fighting imperialism? Does working in
					collectives really help change our deeply entrenched American individualism? How
					can “cultural workers” best advance these struggles? I often argue esthetics
					with my political comrades. Films, 1 say, don’t have to be simplistic to
					communicate with mass audiences. We’re all subject to subtle propaganda from
					Hollywood and Madison Avenue. We’re all jugglers of contradictions and need to
					see and hear and read about alternatives to what is. We have to make films that
					not only say something different but say it in a different way. They have to be
					made in a practical political context, in a coherent theoretical context, and
					they have to be able to recapture the imaginations of masses of people being
					lulled to sleep by the crap thats sold as “mass art." We have to find strategies
					for making our alternate points of view visible, making peoples' voices heard,
					our ideas and films seen; find ways of tighting the commercial monopolies that
					own the air waves, the movie screens, the mass media, that own
					<emph>us</emph></p>
				<p>I argue politics with my feminist sisters. No more separatism, I say. I work on
					HERESIES to say that and also because—another contradiction—l need community in
					a country that is in fragments. In short, and as labor people like my
					grandparents always said: women, artists, men, people, we’ve got to get
					organized.</p>
				<signed>J.B.</signed>
			</div>
			<div>
				<p> What kind of socialist-feminist-artist am I?</p>
				<p>What kind of socialist artist loves Corot as well as Courbet and forgives oil
					painting its bourgeois origins and abstract expressionism its heraldry of U.S.
					imperialism?</p>
				<p>What kind of feminist artist sees pink as a private color to be sparingly
					used?</p>
				<p>To the women’s movement 1 would like to bring, as to art, the subtlest
					perceptions. To political action, I would like to bring, as to art, a precise
					and delicate imagination. The personal is the political only if you make it so.
					The connections have to be drawn. Feminism without socialism can create only
					utopian pockets. And the lifespan of a collective is approximately two
					years.</p>
				<p>Socialism without feminism is still patriarchy. But more smug. Try to imagine a
					classless society run by men. Trying to be part of a collective is a little like
					being a chameleon set on plaid. I may split apart before I get the pattern
					right. But somehow it seems worth the pain because l believe community is the
					highest goal.</p>
				<p>I believe every woman's life is a little better because of what we are doing.</p>
				<signed>M.S.</signed>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
