<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Moratorium: Front Lawn: 1970</title>
				<author>Kate Jennings</author>

				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Heresies: Issue 1</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="97"/>
			<head><title>Moratorium: Front Lawn: 1970</title></head>
			<byline><persName>Kate Jennings</persName></byline>

			<lg>
				<l>watch out! you may meet a real</l>
				<l>castrating female</l>
				<l>or</l>
				<l>you'Il say I'm a manhating braburning</l>
				<l>lesbian member of the castration</l>
				<l>penisenvy brigade, which I am</l>
			</lg>
			<p>I would like to speak.</p>
			<p>I would like to give a tubthumpingtablebanging emotional rap AND be listened to, not
				laughed at. You don’t laugh at what your comrade brothers say, you wouldn’t laugh at
				the negroes, the black panthers. Many women are beginning to feel the necessity to
				speak for themselves, for their sisters. I feel the necessity now.</p>
			<p>It's the moratorium. l would say, oh yes, the war is bad a pig bosses war may the nlf
				win, I also say VICTORY TO THE VIETNAMESE WOMEN. Now our brothers on the left in the
				peace movement will think that what I am about to say is not justified, this is a
				moratorium. It's justified anywhere. We've heard you loud and clear before, brother¬
				shits, we know we have to work towards the Revolution and then join the ladies
				liberation auxiliary if we have any time left over. l've worked my priorities out, I
				will work towards what I know about, what I feel, and I feel because l'm told ad
				infinitum that l'm a woman, l'm a second-class citizen, and l should shutup right
				now because my mind's between my legs. I say you think with your pricks. We should
				all get our priorities straight and organise around our own injustices, our own con¬
				dition. There are a lot of people here who feel strongly about the Vietnam war. But
				how many of you, who can see so clearly the suffering and misery in Vietnam, how
				many of you can see at the end of your piggy noses the women who can't get
				abortions, how many of you would get off your fat piggy asses and protest against
				the killing and victimisation of women in your own country. Go check the figures,
				how many Australian men have died in Vietnam, and how many women have died from
				backyard abortions. Yes, that's cool, they're only women, and you'Il perhaps worry
				if your own chickie gets pregnant. Can you think about all the unwanted children, or
				the discrimination against unmarried mothers. Illegal dangerous abortions are going
				to be performed regardless. So make them legal. And to these women who think an
				abortion campaign, or women's lib for that matter, is reformist, I quote "in
				fighting for our liberation we will not ask what is revolutionary or reformist, only
				what is good for women" some of us are revolutionaries, some of us are manhunting
				crazies, but we are all working toward one thing, the liberation of women, and
				most of us will recognise that this will only happen in a socialist society.</p>
			<p>We all feel very strongly about conscription and freedom of the individual, some go
				to great lengths to martyr themselves on the issue of the draft. I don’t feel very
				strongly anymore about the ego scenes of the mike jones's around me. I do feel
				strongly about my freedom and my sisters' freedom. Women are conscripted every day
				into their personalised slave kitchens, can you, with your mind filled with the
				moratorium, spare a thought for their freedom, identity, minds and emotions, they're
				women, and your stomach is full. It suits you to keep women in the kitchens, and
				underpaid menial jobs, and with the children. You, by your silence, apathy and
				laughter sanction the legislators, the pig parliamentarians, the same men who
				sanction the war in Vietnam. You won’t make an issue of abortion, equal pay, and
				child minding centres, because they're women's matters, and under your veneer you
				are brothers to the pig politicians. And I say to all you highminded intellectual
				women who say you're liberated with such force and conviction, I say you make me
				sick. So women's lib doesn’t concern you. Ask your companion what he would prefer—to
				talk to you or fuck you? (and if you say you'd prefer to be fucked, you've absorbed
				your conditioning well). And the women in the suburbs are no concern of yours? Your
				mother is no concern of yours? so long as you think you're liberated, all's well.
				You and your sisters and the silent suburban women are all part of a capitalist
				PATRIARCHAL society which you cannot ignore.</p>
			<p>And don’t start to trust the sympathetic men who want a socialist society. Where will
				the women be after the revolution? Go, ask them, the men on the left stink—they
				stink from their motherfucking socks to their long hair, from their jock straps to
				their mao and moratorium badges. The ones who pretend to espouse our aims are far
				worse than those who at least wear their true colors on their sleeves. And to my
				brothers on the drug scene. Grass is good. Oh yes, but instead of becoming happy and
				peaceful and oh so motherfucking loving all I can see is you sitting there,
				asserting, even grooving on your maleness, dominating every joint every puff.
				Chickies aren’t very good at rapping, aren’t clever or subtle enough. I mean, it's a
				male scene, isn’t it, you fat arrogant farts.</p>
			<p>Okay, I've stopped trying to love and understand my oppressors.</p>
			<p>I know who my enemy is.</p>
			<p>I will tell you what I feel, as an individual, as a woman.</p>
			<p>I feel that there can be no love between men and women.</p>
			<p>Maybe after the revolution people will be able to love each other regardless of skin
				color, ethnic origin, occupation or type of genitals. But if that happens it will
				only happen if we make it happen. Starting right now.</p>
			<p>I feel hatred.</p>
			<p>I feel anger.</p>
			<p>Without indulging in an equality or marxist argument I say all power to women
				because that's what I feel.</p>
			<p>ALL POWER.</p>
			<p>And I say to every woman that every time you're put down or fucked over, every time
				they kick you cunningly in the teeth, go stand on the street corner and tell every
				man that walks by, every one of them a male chauvinist by virtue of HIS birth¬
				right, tell them all to go suck their own cocks. And when they laugh, tell them that
				they're getting bloody defensive, and that you know what size weapon to buy to kill
				the bodies that you've unfortunately laid under often enough.</p>
			<p>ALL POWER TO WOMEN.</p>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p>"Kate Jennings is a feminist. She believes in what Jane Austen recommended at
				fifteen: Run mad as often as you chuse; but do not faint.'" This "biography" appears
				on the jacket of Jennings' book of poems (from which "Moratorium" is
				reprinted)—Come to Me My Melancholy Baby. published in 1975 by Outback Press,
				Fitzroy (Victoria), in her native Australia.</p>
		</back>

	</text>
</TEI>
