<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On Woman's Refusal to Celebrate Male Creativity</title>
				<author>Rivolta Femminile</author>
				
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic><title>Heresies: Issue 1</title></analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      	<front><p>Rivolta Femminile is an Italian group of radical
      		feminists founded in Rome in July 1970, now
      		associated with other feminist groups in Milan,
      		Turin, Genoa and Florence. They have con
      		sistently resisted hierarchal structures and male
      		dominated institutions and their development
      		of feminist theory has been detailed in publica
      		tions such as Carla Lonzi's Sputiamo su Hegel
      		(7970) and La Donna clitoridea e la donna vagi
      		nale (1977), the collective's Sessualita femmi
      		nile e aborto (1977) and Carla Accardi's Su
      		periore e inferiore (1972). The latter records the
      		author's dismissal from her job after discussing
      		the Rivolta Femminile manifesto with her fe
      		male high school students. All publications are
      		available from Rivolta Femminile, Via del
      		Babuino 16, Rome, Italy.</p></front>
         <pb n="100"/>
   	<body>
         <head><title>On Woman's Refusal to Celebrate Male Creativity<note>Text written by Rivolta Femminile, March 1971; free translation by Arlene Ladden from Carla Lonzi, <title>Sputiamo su Hegel: La Donna clitoridea e la donna vaginale e altri scritti</title>, Scritti di Rivolta Femminile, 1, 2, 3, Milan, 1974.</note></title></head>
				<byline>Rivolta Femminile</byline>
         
				<p>We in Rivolta Femminile refuse to pay tribute
				to male creativity because we are aware that in
				the patriarchal world—that is, in a world made
				by men and for men—even the liberating force of creativity is the prerogative of men. Woman—in so many ways a subsidiary being—is
				denied every role which could effect à recognition of these inequities. For her, there is no
				prospect of liberation.</p>
				<p>The creativity of men speaks to the creativity
				of other men while woman, as client and spectator of that dialogue, is assigned a status which
				excludes competition. Woman is locked into a
				role which, a priori, assures the male artist an
				audience. While creating art is seen to have a
				liberating function, art as an institution insists
				that woman be the neutral witness to the work
				of others. Man’s energy, even in art, is spent by
				competing with other men. Only the contemplation of art invites woman's involvement.</p>
				<p>This is the nature of patriarchal creativity: to
				depend upon aggressive competition with male
				rivals and on the passive appreciation of women. Man, the artist, feels abandoned by woman
				as soon as she abandons her archetypal spectator's role; their mutual solidarity rests solely on
         <pb n="101"/> the conviction that, as a spectator gratified by
				creativity, woman reaches the highest possible
				point in the evolution of her species.</p>
				<p>But, on the contrary, woman is discovering
				that the patriarchal world needs her—that
				man's self-liberating efforts absolutely depend
				on her—and that woman's liberation can only
				be realized independent of patriarchal previsions and the dynamics by which men liberate
				themselves. The artist depends upon woman to
				glorify his work and she, until she begins her
				own liberation, is happy to oblige. The work of
				art cannot afford to lose the security inherent in
				her exclusively receptive role.</p>
				<p>Once aware of her position in relation to
				male creativity, woman is left with two possibilities: the first—until now, the only available
				option—of distinguishing herself within the creative hierarchy historically defined by men
				(which alienates her from other women while
				men recognize her only indulgently); or—the
				feminist alternative—of autonomously recover
				ing her own creativity, nourished by her awareness of past oppression.</p>
				<p>To celebrate male creativity is ultimately to
				submit to the historic sovereignty of men, to
				that patriarchal strategy which deliberately subjugates us. But let woman remove herself, and
				the struggle for male supremacy becomes not
				man lording it over woman, but merely a struggle between individual men.</p>
				<p>By refusing to celebrate male creativity, we
				are not judging creativity, nor are we contesting
				it. Rather, with our absence, we are refusing to
				accept it as defined; we are challenging the
				concept of art as something which men graciously hand down to us. By ceasing to believe
				in a refracted liberation, we are unleashing
				creative energy from patriarchal bonds.</p>
				<p>With her absence, woman performs a dramatic act of awareness, creative because it is liberating.
         </p>
   	</body>

   </text>
</TEI>
