<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Heresies Project</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p>A Bucknell Production</p>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Information about the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="101"/>
			<head><title>WHAT IS LEFT?</title></head>
			<byline><persName>Assata Shakur</persName></byline>

			<lg>
				<l>AFTER THE BARS AND THE GATES AND THE DEGRADATION</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>AFTER THE LOCK INS AND THE LOCK OUTS AND THE LOCK UPS</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>I MEAN, AFTER THE CHAINS THAT GET ENTANGLED INTHE GREY OF ONE'S MATTER</l>
				<l>AFTER THE BARS THAT GET STUCK IN THE HEARTS OF MEN AND WOMEN</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>AFTER THE TEARS AND DISAPPOINTMENTS</l>
				<l>AFTER THE LONELY ISOLATION</l>
				<l>AFTER THE CUT WRIST AND THE HEAVY NOOSE</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>I MEAN, LIKE, AFTER THE COMMISSARY KISSES</l>
				<l>AND THE GET-YOUR-SHIT-OFF-BLUES</l>
				<l>AFTER THE HUSTLER HAS BEEN HUSTLED</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>AFTER THE SAD FUTILE MANEUVERS</l>
				<l>AFTER THE SHRILL AND BARREN LAUCHTER</l>
				<l>AFTER THE CONTRABAND EMOTIONS</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>AFTER THE MURDERBURGERS AND THE COON SQUADS AND THE TEAR CAS</l>
				<l>AFTER THE BULLS AND THE BULLPENS AND THE BULLSHIT</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>I MEAN LIKE, AFTER YOU KNOW THAT GOD CANT BE TRUSTED</l>
				<l>AFTER YOU KNOW THAT THE SHRINK IS A PUSHER</l>
				<l>THAT THE WORD IS A WHIP, AND THE BADGE IS A BULLET</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>AFTER YOU KNOW THAT THE DEAD ARE STILL WALKING</l>
				<l>AFTER YOU REALIZE THAT SILENCE IS TALKING</l>
				<l>THAT OUTSIDE AND INSIDE ARE JUST AN ILLUSION</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>I MEAN, LIKE, WHERE IS THE SUN?</l>
				<l>WHERE ARE HER ARMS AND WHERE ARE HER KISSES?</l>
				<l>THERE ARE LIP PRINTS ON MY PILLOW</l>
				<l>I AM SEARCHING</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>I MEAN, LIKE, NOTHING IS STANDSTILL AND NOTHING IS ABSTRACT</l>
				<l>THE WING OF A BUTTERFLY CANT TAKE FLICHT</l>
				<l>THE FOOT ON MY NECK IS APART OF A BODY</l>
				<l>THE SONG THAT I SING IS APART OF AN ECHO</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>I MEAN, LIKE, LOVE IS SPECIFIC</l>
				<l>IS MY MIND A MACHINE GUN?</l>
				<l>IS MY HEART A HACKSAW?</l>
				<l>CAN I MAKE FREEDOM REAL? YEAH,</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
				<l>I AM AT THE TOP AND BOTTOM OF A LOWER-ARCHY</l>
				<l>I AM IN LOVE WITH LOSERS AND LAUCHTER</l>
				<l>I AM IN LOVE WITH FREEDOM AND CHILDREN</l>
				<l>LOVE IS MY SWORD AND TRUTH IS MY COMPASS</l>
				<l>WHAT IS LEFT?</l>
			</lg>

		</body>
		<back>
			<p>Assata Shakur/Joanne Chesimard; courtesy of Assata Shakur Defense Committee.</p>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
