<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Wages For Housework: The Strategy for Women's Liberation</title>
				<author>Pat Sweeney</author>

				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Heresies: Issue 1</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="104"/>
			<head><title>Wages For Housework: The Strategy for Women's Liberation </title></head>
			<byline><persName>Pat Sweeney</persName></byline>
			<p>Many "feminist" writers have contributed to the ideology of housework.
				Radical-feminists, while recognizing the identification of housework with our female
				nature, have proposed sharing this work with a man and leaving the home for outside
				work. Socialist-feminists, describing housework as precapitalist, have pro claimed
				that our goal should be toward "industrialization," which would liberate our time
				for more work—but in a factory, if not a collective kitchen. Liberal feminists have
				defined our problem as "lack of consciousness," describing women as dupes of Madison
				Avenue ad-men. Finally, there are those feminists who, much to capitalists'
				rejoicing, have glorified our forced labor in the home as the embodiment of the best
				human potentials: our capacity to nurture and care, our very capacity to love. One
				thing they all agree on is that women should not be paid for this work, because this
				presumably would institutionalize us in the home, and extend the control of the
				state to "the one area of freedom we have in our lives."</p>
			<p>Contrary to these criticisms, the Wages for Housework Committee's perspective is
				based on the fact that housework is already controlled and institutionalized
				(Mother's Day is nothing less than the celebration of this institutionalization!)
				precisely because this work is unwaged. Society is organized to force us into this
				job, and the fact that we don’t receive a wage for the work continuously undermines
				our power to refuse it.</p>
			<p>That housework is unwaged means first of all that it appears not as work, but as part
				of our female nature. Thus, when we refuse part of this work—as, for example,
				lesbian women do in refusing to provide sexual services to men—we are branded as
				perverts, as if we were breaking some law of nature. We are divided into "good“ and
				"bad" women depending on whether or not we do the housework and whether or not we do
				it for free. In this society to be a good woman — or just to be a woman—is to be a
				good servant at everyone's disposal 24 hours a day; it means accepting that this
				work should not be paid because it supposedly fulfills our nature, and thus contains
				its own reward.</p>
			<p>Housework is not just washing dishes, scrubbing floors, or raising babies. What we do
				at home is produce and reproduce workers: every day we create and restore the
				capacity of others (and ourselves) to work, and to be exploited. It is ironic that
				as houseworkers we are not in cluded in the nation’s labor force, for without this
				work the workforce would not exist. The lack of a wage obscures the indispensability
				of our work to the functioning of this society. Housework makes every other work
				possible. No car could be produced, no coal could be dug, no office could be run, if
				there were not women at home servicing and reproducing those who make the cars,
				those who dig the coal, those who run the offices. This is the sexual division of
				labor: workers make cars, and women make the workers who make the cars. And to make
				a worker is a much more time- and energy-consuming job than to make a car! Not only
				do we "reproduce“ them physically— cooking their dinners, doing the shopping
				(shopping is work, not consumption as some "feminists" would have us believe). We
				also service workers emotionally—taking the brunt of their tiredness and frustration
				day after day. And we service workers sexually—the Saturday night screw keeps them
				going for yet another week at the assembly line or desk.</p>
			<p>It appears that we freely donate all this work to our husbands and children out of
				our love for them. In reality we are working for the same bosses, who are getting
				two workers for the price of one. Our lives are governed by the same work schedule
				as those we serve. When we cook dinner or when we "make love" is determined by the
				factory time-clock. Not only the quantity, but also the quality of workers we
				reproduce is controlled. If they don’t need many workers, we are sterilized; if they
				need more workers we are denied access to contraceptives and are forced to resort to
				backstreet butchers (the right to life is never claimed for women). Likewise, if we
				are on welfare or we tend to produce "troublemakers," we are again sterilized.</p>
			<p>In every case, our sexuality is continuously under control to make sure that we use
				it productively. Lesbianism and teenage sex are il legal, and rape in the family (or
				the battered wife) is not a crime since readily available<pb n="105"/> money of our
				own that creates the battered wife or the closet lesbian and forces so many of us to
				remain in unwanted family situations. With money in our hands, we would have the
				power to walk out whenever we wanted. Men would certainly think twice before raising
				their hands to us if they knew that we could leave any minute, without the prospect
				of starving.</p>
			<p>Our wageless condition in the home is the material basis of our dependence on men.
				This weakness in the community, as wageless houseworkers, is ultimately the weakness
				of the entire class. Capitalism takes away from us in the community (through
				inflation—price hikes rent increases, fare increases, etc.) what we have gained
				through our power in the factory. Women pay a double price for this defeat. Higher
				prices mean an intensification of our work, since we are expected to absorb the cost
				of inflation with extra work.</p>
			<p>The struggle for wages for housework is a struggle for social power—for women first,
				but ultimately for the entire working class. In fact, by demanding wages for the
				work we already do, instead of demanding more work, we are posing the question of
				the immediate reappropriation of the wealth we have produced. Exploitation is the
				enforcement of unpaid labor the only source of capitalist profits. Thus to attack
				our wagelessness is to attack capitalism at its roots for capital is precisely the
				accumulated labor that has been robbed from workers generation after generation.</p>
			<p>In contrast, the strategy that has been offered to us by "feminists" and the left—the
				strategy to obtain more work-would only mean further enslavement to the present
				system. It is capital that poses work as the only natural destiny in our lives, not
				the working class, whose struggles are always directed toward gaining more money and
				less work. To pose the "right to work" as our road to liberation ignores that we are
				already working, and that housework does not wither away when we go out for a paid
				job. Our work at home simply intensifies: we do it at night when everybody is
				already asleep, or in the morning before everyone awakes or on weekends. Our wages
				remain low—and they quickly disappear in paying for day-care centers lunches,
				carfare, etc. Furthermore, with two jobs we have even less time to organize with
				other women. Unions have long accused women of being backward. But when did unions
				consider that we are not free to attend meetings after our second job is over
				because we must hurry to report back to our first one—picking up the kids at the
				day-care center or babysitter's getting to the supermarket before it closes, fixing
				dinner for the men who expect it to be ready when they come home from work?</p>
			<p>Another illusion is that to go "out to work" is to break our isolation and gain the
				possibility of a social life. Very often the isolation of a typing pool or a
				secretarial office matches our isolation in the home. We certainly aspire to a
				social life better than the one provided by an assembly line. But going out of the
				home is not much of a relief if we don’t have any money in our hands, or if we go
				out just for more work.</p>
			<p>We also reject the idea that sharing our exploitation in the home with a man can be a
				strategy for liberation. "Sharing the housework" is not an invention of the Women's
				Movement. Women have continuously tried to get men to share this work. Despite some
				victories, we have discovered that this battle also has many limitations. First, the
				man is not home most of the time. If he brings in the money, and we are economically
				dependent on him, we don’t have the power to force him to do housework. In fact it
				is often more work for us to get the man to share the work than do it ourselves.
				Most importantly, this strategy confines us to an individual struggle which does not
				give us the power (or the protection) of a mass struggle. And it assumes that every
				woman has (or wants) a man with whom to share the work.</p>
			<p>As for a possible rationalization of house work, we must immediately say that we are
				not interested in making our work more efficient or more productive for capital. We
				are interested in reducing our work, and ultimately refusing it altogether. But as
				long as we work in the home for nothing, no one really cares how long or how hard we
				work. For capital only introduces advanced technology to cut its costs of production
				after wage gains by the working class. Only if we make our work cost (i.e. only if
				we make it uneconomical) will capital "discover“ the technology to reduce it. At
				present, we often have to go out for a second shift of work to afford the dishwasher
				that should cut down our housework!</p>
			<p>Who will pay for this work?</p>
			<p>We demand wages for housework from the government for two major reasons. First, every
				sector of the economy benefits from our work we don’t work for one boss, we work for
				all the bosses. Consequently we demand the money from the state. Second, the
				government already is our boss. In every country the government is responsible for
				guaranteeing an adequate labor force to industry. This means that the govern ment
				directly regulates and controls our work through the family, world population
				control, immigration laws, and finally by entering the community whenever we refuse
				to perform our work.</p>
			<p>The question "who will pay?" is usually posed so as to subvert the cause. It is
				assumed that the government is broke, and that our demand will only divide the
				working class by forcing the government to tax other workers to pay us a wage. In
				reality, by getting more power for our selves, we will be giving more power not only
				to men (power not over us but with respect to their bosses) but to every sector (the
				young, the elderly, and the wageless in general). We will <pb n="106"/> begin to
				break the power relations which so far have kept us divided. Through a united
				working class we can force the government to tax the corporations, not other
				workers.</p>
			<p>A posture of defeat also ignores the struggles women have made against housework and
				what we have been able to win in rélation to this work. It is no accident that after
				the massive struggles welfare mothers waged in the 1960s for more money from the
				government—the first money we have won for housework—the number of female-headed
				families has dramatically increased (doubling every decade) along with the number of
				divorces, particularly among women with children, and the number of young women who
				have been able to set up independent households. This is not to glorify welfare.
				Welfare does not even begin to pay for all our work—we need much more and we need it
				for all of us. But it is to recognize how even a little money has begun to break
				down some of the most powerful mechanisms of discipline which traditionally have
				kept us in line.</p>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p>Pat Sweeney is an active member of the Wages For House work Committee (288-8 8th
				Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11215) and one of the founders of the Nassau County Womens
				Liberation Center.</p>
		</back>


	</text>
</TEI>
