<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>ABCS</title>
				<author>Susan Yankowitz</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Heresies: Issue 1</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="54"/>

			<head><title>ABCS</title></head>
			<byline><persName>Suson Yankowitz</persName></byline>

			<div type="letter" n="a">
				<head>AN APPLE</head>
				<p>Manuelo Manchik admires the apple before devouring it. He cups the thing in the
					palm of his hand, turning it this way and that; the light bounces off the curves
					of its golden skin. O golden delicious, you make a mouth water! The fruit is
					round and firm and fully packed; unlike the mealy banana, it will resist his
					teeth just a little. Again his mouth waters as he delays the coming pleasure. He
					cups the thing in the palm of one hand, stroking it with the other; it is smooth
					and cool beneath his fingers. O golden delicious, you do tempt a man! Yes there
					is no doubt, you were made to be eaten. He opens his mouth wide and chomps
					through to the core in a single bite. Two black seeds slither in a rill of juice
					down his chin.</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="b">
				<head>BREASTS</head>
				<p>At a gathering of talents, artistic and profane, MM had spotted across the
					crowded room his own dreamed-of Olympia, half-reclining on a fat settee. The
					exquisite naturalness of her Manet pose enchanted him no less than her near
					nudity. Under her see-through blouse her breasts were classic. O wonder. O no
					wonder that they pushed out the silk (or was it cheap nylon?) of her blouse
					exactly like breasts; that to exploring hands (at other hours of course for now
					she was half-reclining naturally alone) they were as round and firm and full as
					round firm full breasts; and that the nipples which tipped these breasts
					resembled nothing so much as the nipples which tip such breasts. In short and in
					sum, her breasts were truly like breasts. But MM had no interest in the obvious.
					He was a man of imagination, of poetry even. The excesses of similitude
					multiplied by their exact number his pleasures. He saw what he saw: Olympia with
					breasts which were breasts and at the same time various other roundnesses not
					breasts. And roundness was all, preferable even to that commonplace of
					literature, ripeness. Only one fact was crucial and he had ascertained it,
					subtly brushing his fingers against her shoulders: she was not made of wax. So
					when MM opened his mouth wide one night days later and bit with gusto into the
					breast on the left, that same breast bled. Damn, he had erred in his
					distinctions! But Manuelo Manchik was not a man to hang fire. With a gesture of
					magnificent unconcern, he wiped his chin and continued eating.</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="c">
				<head>CHYME</head>
				<p>Olympia had accepted that name, accepted too the play of tongue and teeth,
					accepted even the discomfort of her body crushed beneath him when poing! she was
					punctured. Too late to cry foul! she fell, undone by mastication. Softened by
					saliva she travelled in mouthfuls through his gullet and into the fat sac of his
					stomach. There she lodges, divided against herself. Fool, she chides herself, to
					have come to chyme!</p>
				<p>Her head is separated from her body. Her legs, each in one long piece, are
					severed from her crotch and from each other, Her two loose breasts bounce from
					wall to wall, free-floating, as his stomach contracts and dilates in diges-
					tion. Pressed against the locked pyloric door sheisgrateful at least that she
					will not be further fractured by the cleaving peristaltic actions of his
					intestine. There is no disguising the situation: she is split, sundered, she is
					not in one piece. If she does not want to sour in his belly (and why would she
					desire such a fate?) she must somehow (but how?) reverse the process herself.
					But herself is not. From deep inside Manuelo's stomach, she surveys the chaos of
					her members and thinks: I must pull myself together! </p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="d">
				<head>DREAM?</head>
				<p>Maybe it's all a dream, she reasons reasonably enough, and when I wake up I'll
					find myself me again, just me, no one's Olympia, in toto. And so she falls to
					sleep so she can fall awake. This is the dream she finds: she is standing in
					water being fucked in the ass by the shameless beak of a crane. His long legs
					pinion her hips. He wades and fishes, taking his time. It hurts. What can she do
					but submit? Her name is not Leda; the power is all his.</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="e">
				<head>ESCAPE</head>
				<p>She wakes up gagging with her left foot in her mouth. No use sucking on the toes,
					they're not sour balls, they won't dissolve or sweeten her palate. Her mouth is
					dry with sleep and anxiety; she could have suffocated during that nighttime
					shift. There is no escaping the fact now: she must escape! But how? She wags her
					head a few times to float the foot free as she ponders the ins and outs. The
					nearest exit is the rear. Can she deliver herself through there? MM is <pb
						n="55"/> notoriously tight-assed. She experiments, jamming her foot in the
					door; MM jumps. Assured of the flexibility of that aperture, she glances upward
					to the other hole, further away but far less foul. Keeping her foot wedged in
					the crack she sticks a finger up his throat; MM gags. Both routes are open to
					her. Which out should she take?</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="f">
				<head>FLATULENCE</head>
				<p>MM ejects a fart and holds his nose in indignation. The cream of the art world
					thins around him. Many noses are held. How could she, the bitch, upset him so?
					He excuses himself gracefully from the room, leaving his smell behind. Is he
					stuck with her forever? Must he pay with his immaculate reputation for one
					night's overindulgence? O she is lodged there in his gut, forcing him to take
					strong measures.</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="g">
				<head>GLUTTONY</head>
				<p>"I'd like to eat you up," he had said. She had been enthusiastic. Whose sin was
					it then? Definitely food for thought, his and hers.</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="h">
				<head>HIS AND HERS</head>
				<p>HIS: She tempted me. <lb/> HERS: He ate.</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="i">
				<head>INDIGESTION</head>
				<p>"I'm carrying her around. She weighs me down. Really, I'm not a free man
					anymore," Manuelo confided to his friend the doctor, picking his teeth with an
					indigestible sliver of fingernail. "You must get her out of your system,"
					replied the learned doc. "May I prescribe a laxative?" </p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="j">
				<head>JUSTICE MORE OR LESS POETIC</head>
				<p>She hadn't cared who drove into her. He had had a full set. It was good sport
					yes. And what a ball! He had swung hard, lifted high and, rimming the cup first
					with a brilliant display of control, had dropped right in: hole in one, Mandelo
					Manchik was not the sort to putter around. Well, neither was she.</p>
				<p>"You're a real swinger," he complimented her.</p>
				<p>"Just par for the course, she replied, refering of course to her life.</p>
				<p>Now she was teed-off, finding herself in the trap. O she had been green in those
					green days, but she would lie in the roughage no longer. With a method to her
					madness she slices into his intestine with her teeth. MM howls then doubles
					over, squeezing her (according to plan) more closely together; his cramp adheres
					her. When he straightens up she delights to see the connections: her legs
					secured to her groin and her groin to her torso, o classic venus though still
					not Olympia for her breasts and arms are still somewhere adrift. And her head,
					that obstinate be-bumped ball, is lying slightly offcourse, planning the next
					shot. </p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="k">
				<head>KIDDING</head>
				<p>When she reached twenty-five, her psychiatrist had said (though gently): "All
					kidding aside, my dear, you are no longer a child prodigy." She had run home
					crying to her mother, blurting the tragic news. "So? What are you going to do
					with yourself?" mother had asked, heart-to-heart.</p>
				<p>"I gotta grow up sometime, ma. He's right. So here's what: I'm gonna have a
					baby!" "What? What?" disbelieving ma had hollered, flinging her daughter from
					her sacked-out breast. "I'm going to have a bastard?" "No, ma, no," she calmed
					her mother. "<emph>I'm</emph> gonna have the bastard."</p>
				<p>The child was born crying and one gulp of air later, died. The bereaved not yet a
					mother invited her psychiatrist to the funeral and told him then and there that
					they were quits. That was how he would remember her: standing gravely at the
					grave, dressed all in black, a grown-up color.</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="l">
				<head>LIKE</head>
				<p>"I like you," MM had said (as had others), thinking to flatter.</p>
				<p>"No you're not," she retorted almost at once, angry almost. "You're not like me
					at all."</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="m">
				<head>MILK OF MAGNESIA</head>
				<p>He takes the prescribed dosage and waits.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="letter" n="n">
				<head>NO ANSWERS</head>
				<p>In the park, Abigale is lying on her belly, waiting as pre-arranged for her best
					friend, the putative Olympia. She pokes with a spring twig at the underside of a
					caterpillar, trying to hurry it out of its skin.</p>
				<p>"Where are your wings, caterpillar?" she asks.</p>
				<p>"And where was I before I was born?"</p>
				<p>"And where, sky, do you get off, looking down on me?"</p>
				<p>Everything is mute. The silence is its own question.</p>
			</div>

			<pb n="56"/>

			<div type="letter" n="o">
				<head>OSCILLATIONS</head>
				<p>Suddenly everything starts churning. Using all anchored organs for ballast, she
					holds herself together; he will not shake her up, will not fragment her. His
					belly bloats with gases, goes into a rumble. So! He is trying to purge himself
					by purging her. The rejection infuriates her. She will come out when she is good
					and ready, and she will use the exit of her choice. Tough shit, Manuelo! She
					braces hersef against his spasms.</p>
			</div>


			<div type="letter" n="p">
				<head>P'S &amp; Q'S</head>
				<p>"Mind them!" her mother had warned. But what were they? She had learned the
					alphabet thoroughly but the deeper meanings of p's and q's had eluded her. If
					she had gone further in her study of letters, would she have led a simpler
					life?</p>
			</div>


			<div type="letter" n="r">
				<head>REFLECTION</head>
				<p>MM strains.</p>
				<p>O resists.</p>
				<p>The battle is in earnest. Some old words rise to the occasion. "The man who hates
					you and the woman who is hated are probably one and the same," her psychiatrist
					had suggested, maddening her (at the time) into silence.</p>
				<p>Was he speaking of suicide?</p>
				<p>Hers?</p>
				<p>The thought sobers her and sheds light. After all, it is almost spring out there.
					The crocuses are already beginning their day-open night-close ritual. She could
					if she chose walk outside without a coat, breathing sunlight. Someone, also
					without a coat, might be coming round the corner fated to bump chests with her.
					Her mind too, she realizes, can turn corners. And certainly Abigale, her old
					friend, must be waiting for her in the park this very moment.</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="s">
				<head>SURE IS</head>
				<p>His stomach is storming around her with a vengeance. She holds on for dear life.
					O yes, it is so so dear, good old life. It is indeed of the essence, hers in
					particular. Her imagination has never yet failed her. She will live! Out of the
					darkness the closet, the belly of this male whale. The way is lighted by divine
					coincidence as MM opens his mouth widely to expel a belch. The light rays down
					his throat, a sign. Her route has been decided. Really, there are possibilities
					in everything, even a belch, she concludes.</p>
			</div>


			<div type="letter" n="t">
				<head>TRANSLATION (AFTER RILKE)</head>
				<p>Manuelo has thrown caution to the winds. "Do something," he pleads. "I need
					help."</p>
				<p>"Yes," agrees the doctor, "you must change your life."</p>
				<p>O but it hurts! His eyes are blind with tears.</p>
				<p>Manuelo weeps with the effort to restrain them.</p>
			</div>

			<div type="letter" n="u">
				<head>UNITED SHE CAN</head>
				<p>He falls back into his chair, trying to relax, inadvertently giving her the room
					she needs to maneuver. She holds herself snugly in her own arms; they mate with
					their respective sockets, home at last. Now able to manipulate with her hands,
					the rest is easy. She catches her drifting breasts and fixes them onto her
					chest. She knows which is which, having observed in moments of self-criticism
					that the left is slightly larger than the right. It occurs to her at this
					juncture that nature is purposive in all plans. Nothing is very much like
					anything else, each thing is essentially itself and under no compulsion to be
					other. Goodbye then, Manuelo's Olympia! Goodbye velvet settee and languid pose!
					MM's ass presses down into the seat, squeezing her upward. Her body rises toward
					her head and miraculously naturally unites with it. He cannot keep her down. He
					does not want to. She is on her way.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="letter" n="v">
				<head>VOYAGING</head>
				<p>Still afraid that she will fall apart — these connections are so tenuous, so
					untested — she kicks her feet, gingerly at first, then with increasing vigor as
					she finds to her elation that they will move her. She paddles upward toward his
					heart. O the current there is strong; she struggles bravely; she falters, sucked
					into its vortex; she kicks, she flails and manages, through stratagems newly
					known to science, to bypass the whole throbbing mass. The worst is over. She
					catches her breath at his lungs and then, with a great final spurt, dives
					through his esophagus.</p>

			</div>
			<div type="letter" n="w">
				<head>WHOOPS!</head>
				<p>She spills out of his mouth.</p>
				<p>"Hi, Manuelo."</p>
				<p>"Olympia!"</p>
				<p>They stand gaping at each other, both of them messy with blood and other slime.
					She sets him straight at once. "My real name's Claire. Can I take a shower?"</p>
			</div>

			<pb n="57"/>
			<div type="letter" n="x">
				<head>x =</head>
				<p>Claire, not Olympia then. He looks at her in this new light as he scrubs her
					back. How could he not have noticed those pimples on her shoulders? Perhaps that
					is why he was unable to stomach her. But no, no, the mystery is more than skin
					deep.</p>
				<p>"Scrub harder, Manuelo."</p>
				<p>He does, marveling at the dead skin which peels off, flake by flake. How many
					layers are there? He stares into the skin, lost in ponderings beneath the
					surface and then, with a wild cry of exultation, realizes that he has found his
					calling. Dermatology will teach him the topography of the flesh. Through that
					mundane profession he will explore the twin mysteries of desire and disgust.</p>
				<p>"You're breaking the skin again!" shouts Claire.</p>
				<p>"Enough!"</p>
			</div>
			<div type="letter" n="y">
				<head>YOU</head>
				<p>"You have helped me to find myself," they admit simultaneously and, with a tender
					embrace, part forever.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="letter" n="z">
				<head>ZOON</head>
				<p>Shining in the sunlight which is shining too, she runs to the park. Abigale is
					asleep; a caterpillar is making a moustache on her upper lip. Claire picks it
					off and tosses it carelessly into the grass. It slithers away as Abigale
					wakes.</p>
				<p>"Where have you been?" drowsy A asks. Claire hesitates. What words could convey
					the absurdity, the enormity of her adventure? An attempt is necessary. She
					begins to stammer a reply but her stomach, miraculously to the rescue, speaks
					first: loudly it rumbles, fiercely it growls. Both women laugh. The noise
					suffices for response.</p>
				<p>Claire stretches out her hands to Abigale and, with a little tug, pulles her to
					her feet.</p>
				<p>"It's time for another beginning," Claire says.</p>
				<p>"It always was," Abigale grins.</p>
				<p>And off they go, old friends hand in hand, in search of apples.</p>
			</div>
		</body>

		<back>
			<p>Susan Yankowitz's first novel, <title>Silent Witness</title>, was published by Knopf
				in May. Her play, <title>Still Life</title>, will be produced in January at the
				Women's Interarts Theatre, and her published plays incude <title>Slaughterhouse
					Play</title>,<title>Terminal</title>, <title>Boxes</title>, and <title>The
					Prison Game</title>, among others.</p>
		</back>

	</text>
</TEI>
