<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Allegra_issue15_33</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: hmb010@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>In some circuits, Black women have become
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>valuable commodities on the social scale. As fem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>inism has become respectable and Black women
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>criticize white women on their racism, a lot of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>whites want to prove it&apos;s just not so. They invite
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>us to submit articles, perform, read, or speak on
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>panels. This has brought about a relatively new
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>situation in my life—whites coming to me, asking
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>for input.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>Once I welcomed being in this position; often I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>went for it. I consciously figured on getting across
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>as a token. That position would be my point of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>entry to places where white racism would ordi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>narily have left me out of the program. Now with
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>a Black women&apos;s community to live and work in,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>white structures are not so appealing. I look back
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>with bitterness at whites whose dealings with me
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>were not based on who I am, but on what I look
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>like: a Black woman to fit into their program.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>It was a real disservice when white women
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>looked at me, saw the Black, and greeted me with
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>eagerness because of a hidden agenda. It took a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>while before I realized it wasn&apos;t my charm and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>personal magnetism that was operating—I&apos;ve got
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>a big ego and I&apos;m a slow learner. How bitterly I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>remember the white women who took me in as a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>token and how bitterly I remember myself going
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>for the bait—hook, line, and sinker. I want to be
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>treated as an individual, not seen with awe and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>fear as someone&apos;s dream nightmare. I want to be
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>seen as a person who wants to do a job for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>reasons not unlike their own: a person subject to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>pride, fear, greed, anger, ambition, high ideals,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>willingness, trust, and love, like themselves. In¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>stead, many see me as a Third World&quot; woman
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>to be used to make a project look good if I act
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>right.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l38' n='N038'/>I feel a personal shame for having been will¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l39' n='N039'/>ing to be that statistic or chocolate chip in the ses
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l40' n='N040'/>of white cookie. From that token&apos;s position, I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l41' n='N041'/>tried to take myself somewhere, but doubted
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l42' n='N042'/>underneath that I could have gotten in on my owr
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l43' n='N043'/>merit, not being sure of my place in the structure.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l44' n='N044'/>That&apos;s the legacy I inherited from the perverted
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l45' n='N045'/>relationship where some whites looked good
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l46' n='N046'/>practicing tokenism and I was willing to let them
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l47' n='N047'/>get over through me. I was left not knowing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l48' n='N048'/>where I really stood with them, trying to figure
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l49' n='N049'/>out what they thought I was, and then trying to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l50' n='N050'/>be that so I could do what I wanted to do in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l51' n='N051'/>service of who I really was.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l52' n='N052'/>Once I looked with trust to the feminist option.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l53' n='N053'/>It was the minority viewpoint I would read and
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>hunger after and identify with. I appreciate that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>there is a women&apos;s community with networks and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>publications, and that we do share a general
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>point of view. With feminism established as a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>part of the current order, some things are easier
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>for me, but elements of the old ways do continue
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>to take on new forms. Now that a feminist angle
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>is being targeted into cigarette commercials,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>feel ripped off all over again. In a like manner,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>Black is &quot;hip&quot;—well, not so hip anymore. More
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>accurately, now white women are supremely
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l12' n='N012'/>sensitive to being accused of racism and try to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l13' n='N013'/>avoid the word like the plague; it makes their shit
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l14' n='N014'/>turn to water if anyone even thinks the word in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l15' n='N015'/>their direction. Now that they are conscious of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l16' n='N016'/>Black women who come out with such very hip
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l17' n='N017'/>analysis and delivery, many of them want to hold
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l18' n='N018'/>onto us.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l19' n='N019'/>I resent feeling that they want us around for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l20' n='N020'/>the power of our image: picture a handsome,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l21' n='N021'/>angry Black woman on the cover of many a mag¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l22' n='N022'/>azine that ever so rarely deals with a Black view¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l23' n='N023'/>point. So many women who are talking about
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l24' n='N024'/>racism are more concerned about public rela¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l25' n='N025'/>tions than they are with gut-level sisterhood.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l26' n='N026'/>They want us so that they don&apos;t have to feel un¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l27' n='N027'/>comfortable should any Blacks call them on the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l28' n='N028'/>question, or should any other whites get into the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l29' n='N029'/>game of reminding their sisters that there are no
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l30' n='N030'/>women of color in evidence. Real reconstruction is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l31' n='N031'/>bypassed. It&apos;s easier to opt for the cosmetic treat¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l32' n='N032'/>ment. This is like being a nice girl. You smile
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l33' n='N033'/>at anyone who smiles at you and you don&apos;t dislike
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l34' n='N034'/>anyone because that&apos;s the way you&apos;ve been
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l35' n='N035'/>brought up. But the truth of it all is that only by
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l36' n='N036'/>trading honest viewpoints can people negotiate
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l37' n='N037'/>and work out frank differences.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l38' n='N038'/>White women deny that they seek out women
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l39' n='N039'/>of color because pressure has been put on them
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l40' n='N040'/>These white women are almost trained to re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l41' n='N041'/>spond with a politically correct manner when
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l42' n='N042'/>they&apos;re questioned. If some of them would ac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l43' n='N043'/>knowledge resentment or that they are bewil¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l44' n='N044'/>dered that they can&apos;t seem to do anything right
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l45' n='N045'/>by Black women anymore, some truth could
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l46' n='N046'/>emerge that&apos;d free us on all sides. But so many
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l47' n='N047'/>are afraid to come from anything other than
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l48' n='N048'/>masks of good behavior.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l49' n='N049'/>Yet I know now when whites are running
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l50' n='N050'/>from me, trying to deflect any confrontations they
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l51' n='N051'/>fear I will want to bring into play. I can tell by
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l52' n='N052'/>their aggression on the subjects of race and rac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l53' n='N053'/>ism—as though it were outside of them somehow
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l54' n='N054'/>or as if by giving an appropriate nod to guilt
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l55' n='N055'/>blame, and responsibility in a politically correc¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l56' n='N056'/>stance, they&apos;ll be safe from the anger they seem
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l57' n='N057'/>to expect from me. They are ill at ease and run
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l58' n='N058'/>from a feeling of discomfort that they project onto
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l59' n='N059'/>me. When whites beat their breasts and tall
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l1' n='N001'/>about what&apos;s being done to the poor darkies, they
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l2' n='N002'/>are still taking the missionary position and fuck¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l3' n='N003'/>ing Black people.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l4' n='N004'/>I have yet to hear white women talk about
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l5' n='N005'/>Black women as people, as individuals they like
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l6' n='N006'/>or dislike. In the conversations I have heard, we
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l7' n='N007'/>are either heroic,&quot; surviving,&quot; or &apos;triply op-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l8' n='N008'/>pressed.&quot; They&apos;ll urge sympathy on us for Black
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l9' n='N009'/>men&apos;s purported sexism or condemn white men
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l10' n='N010'/>as a class group, but never voice a criticism of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l11' n='N011'/>Black women. It makes me wonder. When a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l12' n='N012'/>white woman assumes l&apos;d be interested in some¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l13' n='N013'/>thing just because l&apos;m a Black person, Iwithdraw
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l14' n='N014'/>one giant step inside. I&apos;m dismayed when I see
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l15' n='N015'/>women at concerts or poetry readings knowing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l16' n='N016'/>how to clap in all the right places and saying a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l17' n='N017'/>nervous &quot;yeah&quot;—as if by verbal affirmation of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l18' n='N018'/>Black women&apos;s performance their guilt can be
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l19' n='N019'/>discharged and penance done so blame is de¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l20' n='N020'/>flected from them.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l21' n='N021'/>Today, white women see a lot of Black women
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l22' n='N022'/>who want to give their energy solely to Black
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l23' n='N023'/>women rather than deal with whites. I imagine
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l24' n='N024'/>white women often don’t know what to do and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l25' n='N025'/>feel perplexed. A good number of Black women
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l26' n='N026'/>don’t want to be bothered teaching or working
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l27' n='N027'/>with them because whites aren&apos;t as innocent in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l28' n='N028'/>their racism as they put out. Others get mad at
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l29' n='N029'/>whites for trying to include Black people. It seems
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l30' n='N030'/>like you&apos;re damned if you do and damned if you
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l31' n='N031'/>don&apos;t—so what&apos;s a poor little white girl to do?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l32' n='N032'/>This thinking is, of course, not leading to the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l33' n='N033'/>real truth. I think the answer to the seeming
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l34' n='N034'/>paradox is for the white women to do their own
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l35' n='N035'/>consciousness-raising and examine what they
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l36' n='N036'/>come up with among themselves. The working
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l37' n='N037'/>out of racist attitudes is process work for white
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l38' n='N038'/>women to do for themselves, with one another.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l39' n='N039'/>Once they can see themselves through the rough
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l40' n='N040'/>stuff, they will actually be freer and truer to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l41' n='N041'/>themselves. I appreciate that kind of honesty in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l42' n='N042'/>an individual more than a correct line. Honesty is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l43' n='N043'/>something Isense, can open up to and trust. Race
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l44' n='N044'/>differences are real, but they&apos;re not everything.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l45' n='N045'/>We work out our real differences from honesty.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l46' n='N046'/>But after they&apos;ve done their own CR, I hope
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l47' n='N047'/>these whites don&apos;t come to me for a stamp of ap¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l48' n='N048'/>proval. I&apos;m having a hard enough time dealing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l49' n='N049'/>with my own stuff and hoping my women will give
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l50' n='N050'/>me the pats on the back I crave. I don&apos;t think
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l51' n='N051'/>many Black women are going to credit whites for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l52' n='N052'/>doing their own homework. Whites seem to want
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l53' n='N053'/>this at some level and when it doesn&apos;t come, they
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l54' n='N054'/>feel pissed and neglected. Well, that&apos;s not enough
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l55' n='N055'/>for Black women who have other concerns and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l56' n='N056'/>don&apos;t want to play nanny in any mode. I&apos;ve been
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l57' n='N057'/>brought up to feel I should be grateful for every
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l58' n='N058'/>little bit of progress, but I frankly do get angry at
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l59' n='N059'/>white women who are actively trying to deal with
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l60' n='N060'/>their racism and the new trips they lay on me in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l61' n='N061'/>their growth process. Those white women who
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l62' n='N062'/>aren&apos;t so anxious and eager to clean up their acts
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l63' n='N063'/>and attitudes around race are the ones I can
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l64' n='N064'/>have friendships with. It&apos;s a tricky balance to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l65' n='N065'/>find, but I think the important personal quality I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l66' n='N066'/>respond to is honesty.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l67' n='N067'/>What is going on with all our concerns about
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l68' n='N068'/>racism is, indeed, change. There is a willingness
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l69' n='N069'/>among some white women to do some work, but
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l70' n='N070'/>the transformation isn’t complete yet. Racist atti¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l71' n='N071'/>tudes linger because the job isn’t all the way
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l72' n='N072'/>done. People who haven’t seen that change is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l73' n='N073'/>possible can’t wholeheartedly believe in it. If
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l74' n='N074'/>they haven’t lived it in their personal lives, it&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l75' n='N075'/>hard to see change in political terms. It won&apos;t all
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l76' n='N076'/>come together in one fell swoop. After the major
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l77' n='N077'/>reconstruction, there will be corners to straight¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l78' n='N078'/>en out and the maintenance work will be a day¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l79' n='N079'/>to-day job. But this is Life Work. Any attempt to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l80' n='N080'/>make it better can only come to good.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
