<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Ladden_42-44_duplicated</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: hmb010@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l1' n='N001'/>Foys, Floozies ond
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l2' n='N002'/>Philosophical Flaws
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l3' n='N003'/>Arlene Lodden
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l28' n='N004'/>The smile of my gracious lady makes me happier
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l29' n='N005'/>than if four hundred angels laughed at me from
				<lb facs='#facs_1_line_1645461568852_7' n='N006'/>the heavens (Raimbaut d&apos;Orange, while some
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l32' n='N007'/>less gracious ladies chuckled from
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l33' n='N008'/>the wings.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l34' n='N009'/>The attitudes in True Romances (and in most
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l35' n='N010'/>of our pasts) originally shone forth from 12th-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l36' n='N011'/>century troubadour poetry and even then they
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l37' n='N012'/>were a little tarnished. Chaste, idealistic and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l38' n='N013'/>upper-ciass, medieval troubadour poetry sup-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l39' n='N014'/>posedly countered a strong tradition of misog-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l40' n='N015'/>yny. It also supposedly elevated woman by up-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l41' n='N016'/>holding that same feminine mystique which, for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l42' n='N017'/>centuries, the Christian fathers had diligently)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l43' n='N018'/>tried to demolish: “Corporeal beauty is nothing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l44' n='N019'/>else but phlegm, and blood, and humor, and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l45' n='N020'/>bile, and the fluid of masticated food.... &quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l46' n='N021'/>said John Chrysostom, a saint, in the 4th cen-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l47' n='N022'/>tury. &quot;When you see a rag with any of these
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l1' n='N001'/>things on it, such as phlegm, or spittle, you
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l2' n='N002'/>cannot bear to touch it even with the tips of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l3' n='N003'/>your fingers. . . . Are you in a flutter of excite-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l4' n='N004'/>ment about the storehouses and depositories of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l6' n='N005'/>these things?&quot;1
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l7' n='N006'/>Woman was so many layers of mucous mem-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l8' n='N007'/>brane. And writings from 6 and 7 centuries later
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l9' n='N008'/>attest to the muddy strides saints and clerics
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l10' n='N009'/>had taken in the interim: &quot;If her bowels and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l11' n='N010'/>flesh were cut open, you would see what filth is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l12' n='N011'/>covered by her white skin. If a fine crimson
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l13' n='N012'/>cloth covered a pile of foul dung, would anyone
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l14' n='N013'/>be foolish enough to love the dung because of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l15' n='N014'/>it?&quot;2 Now, woman was simply so much manure
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l16' n='N015'/>smattered across the coprophagous pages of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l17' n='N016'/>Christian doctrine.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l18' n='N017'/>The wheels of progress kept on turning. A
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l19' n='N018'/>3th-century work addressed itself specifically
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l20' n='N019'/>to women—three worthy recluses: &quot;What fruit
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l21' n='N020'/>does your flesh yield from all its openings?&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l22' n='N021'/>began their catechism. “Between the taste of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l23' n='N022'/>mouth and smell of nose, aren’t there holes like
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l24' n='N023'/>two privy holes? Aren’t you born of foul slime?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l25' n='N024'/>Arent you worm-food?3 To the Church, wom-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l26' n='N025'/>an was simply full of shit. Yet this was the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l27' n='N026'/>legacy bequeathed to the Middle Ages where
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l28' n='N027'/>the love of woman was a cult—an absolute pre-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l29' n='N028'/>requisite for respectability. And love flourished.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l30' n='N029'/>Of course, misogyny continued to flourish
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l31' n='N030'/>too. Woman would still be called &quot;a stinking
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l32' n='N031'/>rose&quot; and &quot;glittering mud” and “a temple built
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l33' n='N032'/>over a sewer.&quot;4 But, as sister to Mary, she was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l34' n='N033'/>also the mystical elevator of the masculine soul
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l35' n='N034'/>which, by its nature, gravitated toward perfec-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l36' n='N035'/>tion. By merely contemplating woman in her
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l37' n='N036'/>golden radiance, man could rise to spiritual
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l38' n='N037'/>heights in a kind of &quot;gilt” by association. For
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l39' n='N038'/>somewhere between the muddy slime and the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l40' n='N039'/>hazy castle spire, a new woman had been
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l41' n='N040'/>spawned. Like the enchanted fay (fairy) of Celt-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l42' n='N041'/>ic lore, she moved softly, gliding over but never
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l43' n='N042'/>touching terra firma, surrounded by auras so
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l44' n='N043'/>fragile that they were better left unpenetrated.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l45' n='N044'/>But these were beautiful, mysterious and prom-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l46' n='N045'/>ising auras, and scribes feverishly copied down
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l47' n='N046'/>the formulas for keeping them intact: &quot;If you
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l48' n='N047'/>have ugly teeth, dort laugh with your mouth
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l49' n='N048'/>open. &quot; &quot;Practice making pretty speeches. “ &quot;Dye
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l50' n='N049'/>your hair; wear false hair if you have lost your
				<lb facs='#facs_1_line_1644430456497_119' n='N050'/>own.&quot;5
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l53' n='N051'/>Andreas Capellanus, Jacques D&apos;Amiens Rob-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l54' n='N052'/>ert le Blois, Garin le Brun, Drouart la Vache,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l55' n='N053'/>Ermangau and de Fournival —all added their
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l56' n='N054'/>instructions to the heap: Lie. Cheat. Drop
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l57' n='N055'/>names, if you have to. Drop dead, if you have
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l58' n='N056'/>to. Anything.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l59' n='N057'/>Maintaining the mystique was the important
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l60' n='N058'/>thing, and that meant keeping the distance. It
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l61' n='N059'/>meant the ecstasy was in the wooing while sex
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l62' n='N060'/>lay in the winding down. Even the ladies under-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l63' n='N061'/>stood that attainment decreased their value,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l64' n='N062'/>and many who loftily kept their suitors well
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l65' n='N063'/>below thigh level would rather have had it
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r4l66' n='N064'/>otherwise. After all, as even the ladies knew: a
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l1' n='N001'/>lover is a vision surrounded by auras. But flesh
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l2' n='N002'/>and blood is flesh and blood... and phlegm and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l3' n='N003'/>dung and mucous and bile and etc.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l4' n='N004'/>Once woman ceased to be a symbol, she
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l5' n='N005'/>became a person, a passion, a robber of reason
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l6' n='N006'/>—a literal and metaphorical scum-bag.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l7' n='N007'/>No wonder the ladies were afraid to submit.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l8' n='N008'/>With submission,  love and its raison d&apos;être be-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l9' n='N009'/>came the discarded backdrop for a fait accom-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l10' n='N010'/>pli. The love was no longer ennobling (ergo: the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l11' n='N011'/>animal soul pawed and dragged down its ration-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l12' n='N012'/>al counterpart), and the woman was no longer
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l13' n='N013'/>mounted on a pedestal (ergo: with the man on
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l14' n='N014'/>top, she was mounted, period). And man’s de-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l15' n='N015'/>sire—well, that often died along with his
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l16' n='N016'/>suffering.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l17' n='N017'/>t’s natural, then, that the really legendary
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l18' n='N018'/>lovers chose the most distant and unattainable
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l19' n='N019'/>objects they couid conceive of. Guilhem de la
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l20' n='N020'/>Tour, for instance, loved the woman he lived
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l21' n='N021'/>with.6 Now such women were worn on every-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l22' n='N022'/>day occasions and were inevitably mundane.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l23' n='N023'/>But Guilhem’s enamorata was unearthly; in fact,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l24' n='N024'/>she was dead. On the eve of her burial, Guilhem
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l25' n='N025'/>visited her grave and, after ten days of morbid
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l26' n='N026'/>embracing and poignant conversation (she was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l27' n='N027'/>a good listener), he went home firm in the belief
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l28' n='N028'/>that she would rise from her tomb and come
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l29' n='N029'/>back to him. She didn&apos;t. But for years, it was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l30' n='N030'/>only Beatrix he longed for. She was the perfect
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l31' n='N031'/>lover—mystical ethereal and unobtrusive. It
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l32' n='N032'/>was a passion that rivaled even Jaufre Rudel&apos;s.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l33' n='N033'/>Jaufre Rudel was ingenious. In an age which
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l34' n='N034'/>valued prolonged desire, he contrived a won-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l35' n='N035'/>derful device. He fell in love with the Countess
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l36' n='N036'/>of Tripoli—a woman he had never seen but
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l37' n='N037'/>whose beauty had filled his imagination so en-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l38' n='N038'/>chantingly that southern France became a glo-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l39' n='N039'/>rious vantage point. And so it remained for
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l40' n='N040'/>several years until, despite the protests of his
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l41' n='N041'/>friends and patron, he resolved at last to cross
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l42' n='N042'/>the ocean to be near her.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l1' n='N001'/>Maybe he just got sick. Or maybe, as his
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l2' n='N002'/>biographers prefer to believe, the anticipation
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l3' n='N003'/>of seeing her was too much for his little heart to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l4' n='N004'/>bear. In any case, as the boat was approaching
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l5' n='N005'/>Tripoli, he apparently expired. But only appar-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l6' n='N006'/>ently. For as the countess rushed to his side, her
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l7' n='N007'/>presence revived him and he pronounced him-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l9' n='N009'/>self fulfilled at last and died again in her arms—
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l10' n='N010'/>a self-extinction metaphorically equivalent to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l11' n='N011'/>orgasm, but which Jaufre seems to have taken
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l12' n='N012'/>much too literally, since Petrarch and other
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l13' n='N013'/>chroniclers affirm that this time he actually did
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l14' n='N014'/>die, and in all probability with his pants on.7
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l15' n='N015'/>True, Jaufre was a strange and nearly legend-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l16' n='N016'/>ary breed. But while to him sex must have
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l17' n='N017'/>seemed an unspeakable defilement, most were
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l18' n='N018'/>not so theoretical. Even troubadours who con-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l19' n='N019'/>stantly reminded women that sex was debasing
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l20' n='N020'/>and honor was all had an ultimately sensua
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l21' n='N021'/>physicality in mind. Woman was like a fine
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l22' n='N022'/>wine. A man twirls it about, observes its color,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l23' n='N023'/>its clarity, savoring its bouquet and rolling it
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l24' n='N024'/>around on his languishing taste-buds. And
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l25' n='N025'/>though the swallow is only the means to the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l26' n='N026'/>end, the end is still very definitely in view. Most
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l27' n='N027'/>pleas for chastity were only lip-service. Even
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l28' n='N028'/>Sordello, a troubadour who repeatedly swore
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l29' n='N029'/>he’d rather die than see a lady even taint her
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l30' n='N030'/>honor, happened to kidnap a Veronese countess
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l31' n='N031'/>and that didn’t help her honor a bit. Nor did it
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l32' n='N032'/>discredit his poetry. Such scandal was irrele-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l33' n='N033'/>vant. In fact, women were irrelevant. Love was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l34' n='N034'/>the important thing and the trick was to keep it
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l35' n='N035'/>alive as long as possible, feeding it little by
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l36' n='N036'/>ever-so-little in an extended and delicious
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l37' n='N037'/>tease. Men could nudge at the gates to the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l38' n='N038'/>ovarian fortress, but entrance, they knew
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l39' n='N039'/>should be delayed. The uitimate object was sex;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l40' n='N040'/>men wanted what they waited for. They just
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l41' n='N041'/>didn’t want it right away. And this largely ex-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l42' n='N042'/>plains why other men’s wives proved such
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l43' n='N043'/>suitable candidates for adoration. Forbidden,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l44' n='N044'/>llicit, deliciously dangerous —yet slightly
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l45' n='N045'/>damaged, they promised all the more to be
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l46' n='N046'/>ultimately affordable. They were perfectly
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l47' n='N047'/>fashioned for desire
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l48' n='N048'/>Desire is a tricky business. In Greece Plu-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l49' n='N049'/>tarch had admired Spartan marriages where, for
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l50' n='N050'/>years, man approached his wife in darkness in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l51' n='N051'/>secret and in haste &quot;so as not to be satiated...
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l52' n='N052'/>there was still place for unextinguished desire.&quot;8
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l53' n='N053'/>It was a useful formula and was later picked up
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l54' n='N054'/>in the Middle Ages when the notion of infre-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l55' n='N055'/>quent and clandestine meetings was embraced
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l56' n='N056'/>a lot more than the ladies were. The medieval
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l57' n='N057'/>magic of love was uncertainty. Even the ro-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l58' n='N058'/>mances preserved this ideal. The lady could
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l59' n='N059'/>be snatched away at any moment by a darken-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l60' n='N060'/>ing scandal or a jealous husband, or be ab-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l61' n='N061'/>sorbed into the ethers which spawned her dis-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l62' n='N062'/>appearing into the mist on a white palfrey. The
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l63' n='N063'/>knight wanted her like that: distant, pure, mys-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l64' n='N064'/>terious, virginal —a blonde Mary ascending into
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l1' n='N001'/>heaven, looming over the castle horizon with
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l2' n='N002'/>only a little soot on her feet suggesting that she
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l3' n='N003'/>didn’t belong there.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l4' n='N004'/>Never mind that the only pure-white creature
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l5' n='N005'/>was the post-menopausal albino rabbit—or that
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l6' n='N006'/>even the ladies depicted in romance were
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l7' n='N007'/>potentially swivers of heroic proportions. Since
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l8' n='N008'/>sex distinguished the distant fay from the dung-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l9' n='N009'/>filled floozy, relatively sexless love became
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l10' n='N010'/>prevalent, and many women—whether they
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l11' n='N011'/>liked it or not—played along
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l12' n='N012'/>There were advantages, of course. Love be-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l13' n='N013'/>came a rare delicacy whereas before it had been
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l14' n='N014'/>something like yesterday’s leftovers. As Ovid&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l15' n='N015'/>classical formula goes: &quot;Pleasure coming slow is
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l16' n='N016'/>the best”9; meaning, the longer the foreplay the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l17' n='N017'/>better the orgasm; meaning, some courtly
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l18' n='N018'/>couples, when they finally did come, must very
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l19' n='N019'/>nearly have blown their brains out
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l20' n='N020'/>But some, for sure, were disappointed. Wom-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l21' n='N021'/>en were dropped, men bumbled like Perceval or
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l22' n='N022'/>—like some knights in the bawdier tales—
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l23' n='N023'/>they&apos;d win their ladies with lots of pomp and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l24' n='N024'/>peter out before they could even open the pack-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l25' n='N025'/>age, their worlds ending not with a bang but a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l26' n='N026'/>whimper. These were particularly grateful for
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l27' n='N027'/>courtly love.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l28' n='N028'/>Courtly love was a game of foreplay whose
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l29' n='N029'/>rule was often touch and go; it was an answet
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l30' n='N030'/>(and a spur) to impotence. Some knights were
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l31' n='N031'/>barely post-pubescent and many were sexually
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l32' n='N032'/>insecure, preferring rich expectations to poor
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l33' n='N033'/>reputations and one-night stands. Better to tilt
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l34' n='N034'/>about the countryside, flaunting a passion and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l35' n='N035'/>flailing a sword (the sword had always been a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l36' n='N036'/>metaphor for penis—&quot;vagina” is merely Latin
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l37' n='N037'/>or &quot;sheath&quot;), imagining a truly magnificent sex-
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l1' n='N001'/>ual prowess when the real thing was maybe limp
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l2' n='N002'/>by comparison. Love by its very nature was a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l3' n='N003'/>test, and knights were afraid to take the exam.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l4' n='N004'/>Or sometimes, it was better to put it off than to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l5' n='N005'/>put it in.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l6' n='N006'/>Love became formalized. The knight waxed
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l7' n='N007'/>and grew pale, and waxed, and waxed, and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l8' n='N008'/>waxed. It was blissful and aggrandizing antici-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l9' n='N009'/>pation. Too bad if a lady sometimes felt cheat
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l10' n='N010'/>ed—if watching her knight charging and gleam-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l11' n='N011'/>ing, she secretly wished hed get off his high
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l12' n='N012'/>horse and get down to business. What could the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l13' n='N013'/>women do? Their iron-clad men performed in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l14' n='N014'/>the tournaments. Ramming, sweating, thrusting
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l15' n='N015'/>and galloping. . . . Ah, those impervious men in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l16' n='N016'/>the metal suits.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l17' n='N017'/>...The only things naked were their swords.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l18' n='N018'/>I. “An Exhortation to Theodore after His Fail,&quot; in A Select
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l19' n='N019'/>Library of the Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers, ed. Philig
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l20' n='N020'/>chaff et af. (New York, 1889), IX, 103-104
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l21' n='N021'/>From the Carmen de Mundi contemptu, quoted in Not in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l22' n='N022'/>Cod’s Image, ed. J. Ofaolain and L. Martines (New
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l23' n='N023'/>York, Harper and Row 1973), p. xlij. St. Odo of Cluny
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l24' n='N024'/>had earlier phrased this with almost identical wording in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l25' n='N025'/>his Collationes, lib. 2, cap. 9 (in J. P. Migne’s Patrologia
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l26' n='N026'/>Latina (Paris, 1844-82). CXXXIII, 556), while Ancrene
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l27' n='N027'/>iwie (below) directly refers to a similar expression in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l28' n='N028'/>St. Bernards Meditationes Plissimae de Cognitione
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l29' n='N029'/>Humanae Conditionis, cap. 3 (Migne, op, cit., ClXXXIN
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l30' n='N030'/>489); The key phrases are &quot;stercoris saccum” and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l31' n='N031'/>saccus stercorum” —literally, a bag of shit.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l32' n='N032'/>The Early English Text Societys Ancrene Riwie, ed. E. j
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l33' n='N033'/>Dobson (London, 1972), pp. 202-203; authois transla
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l34' n='N034'/>tion.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l35' n='N035'/>salimbene, in From St. francis to Dante: Translations
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l36' n='N036'/>from the Chronicle of the Franciscan Salimbene (1221-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l37' n='N037'/>1288). End ed., ed. and trans. C.C. Coulton (London,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l38' n='N038'/>1907), p. 97. and Tertullian, quoted in G.L. Simons A His-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l39' n='N039'/>ory of Sex (London, New English Library, 1970). p. 71
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l40' n='N040'/>From La Cief damor and La Cour daimer in Nina Eptonts
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l41' n='N041'/>ove and the french (London, 1959), pp. 30ff
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l42' n='N042'/>For troubadour biographies, 1 have consulted jehan de
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l43' n='N043'/>Nostredame, les Vies des Plus Celebres et Ancien:
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l44' n='N044'/>Poetes Provencaux, ed. Camille Chabaneau (1913; rpt
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l45' n='N045'/>Geneve, 1970—first published in 1575); La Curne de
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l46' n='N046'/>Sainte-Pelaye, Histoire Litteraire des Troubadours (1774
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l47' n='N047'/>rpt. 3 vols. in 1, Genève, 1967); and Victor Balaguer, los
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l48' n='N048'/>Trovadores, 2nded. (Madrid, 1883). 4 vol.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l49' n='N049'/>aufre was not the onty fatality of romance. Andrieu of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l50' n='N050'/>France—eulogized by at least six troubadours —also fell
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l51' n='N051'/>victim to “too much love&quot; and hed never set eyes on hi
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l52' n='N052'/>lady either. See jehan de Nostredame, op. cit., pp. 166,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l53' n='N053'/>180
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l54' n='N054'/>Plutarch’s Lives, trans. Langhorne (London, Frederick
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l55' n='N055'/>Warne, n.d.). IV, 37
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l56' n='N056'/>Ovids Remedia Amoris, line 405; Rolfe Humphries
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l57' n='N057'/>translation in The Art of Love (Bloomington, 1957)
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l58' n='N058'/>p. 193
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l59' n='N059'/>Ariene Ladden is a poet, scholar and medievalist who
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l60' n='N060'/>teaches at LaCuardia Community College in New York. She
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l61' n='N061'/>is interested in “the forces motivating culture—especialiy
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l62' n='N062'/>the more absurd ones,&quot; and in this spirit is now working op
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l63' n='N063'/>a cultural history of sex and power. She is afso co-authoring
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l64' n='N064'/>a textbook series on literature and creative writing for
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l65' n='N065'/>children.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
