<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='81'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_1' n='N001'/>Architectural Icon
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_2' n='N002'/>Ine Shrine 1 ne Votive The Gesture
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_3' n='N003'/>Ann Wilson
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_1_1' n='N001'/>“The Icon, then, is not only an aesthetical entity. It is the result of the faith and of the prayer. It is
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_2_1' n='N002'/>the life. The saving truth is not communicated by the word alone, but by the fact of awakening
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_3_1' n='N003'/>vital forces of life through the presentation of beauty. The icon carries with it the love of this
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_4' n='N004'/>beauty, and the beauty of this love.&quot; (Byzantine Bible)
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_5' n='N005'/>The idea is simple. Gesture gives grace, space gives grace, image gives grace, sound gives grace.
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_6' n='N006'/>Icons give grace. Vital energy, electric impulse, passes through grace to the beholder. Behold, to
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_7' n='N007'/>be held. This vital energy is present in echoes, ancient shrines, whose purpose is now missing,
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_8' n='N008'/>whisper. Walls built to enact transformations which poets feel when they are impelled—what
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_9' n='N009'/>music casts over the mind. Spirits that exalt and glorify, spirits usually rare and capricious
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_10' n='N010'/>should be permanently fixed, working miracles perpetually for every one. Spatial humanism¬
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_11' n='N011'/>humanity at magnitude—value in light and shadow—true perspective. That art whose attempt is
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_12' n='N012'/>delineation of the divine mirror. That subtlety which is more fine because it abjures extravagance
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_13' n='N013'/>or fantasy. Our need for votive architecture never died. Time changes the abstract order moti-
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_14' n='N014'/>vated by our need for intellectual security with which to summon inspiration. Inspiration sus¬
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_15' n='N015'/>tains the purpose of living. The demands of each epoch’s external pressures on the biological
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_16' n='N016'/>frames encasing our spirits press from us an architecture of expedience like wine from grapes
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_17' n='N017'/>“Every epoch is a sphinx which plunges into the abyss as soon as its problem is solved.&quot; Roman
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_18' n='N018'/>walled gardens yielded a further retreat within Romanesque cloisters. Roses bloom in secret
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_19' n='N019'/>spaces. Votive—fragment—a fragment of gesture—stones of a wall running through an empty
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_20' n='N020'/>plain to the rock mountain. Ridge—snow—votive—gesture. The gesture of respect. A marble
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_21' n='N021'/>seat for the priestess set in the center of the front circle of the ampitheater. Stone fall—blue sky¬
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_22' n='N022'/>empty space. A bench encircled the outer walls of a building and clay votive objects lay on it
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_23' n='N023'/>Hieroglyphs of information—puzzle pieces—spaces out of the architecture of gestures. Stones
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_24' n='N024'/>laid for liturgy—before the column came the gesture of the column. On the trail of imprints, of
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_25' n='N025'/>gestures left long ago in air. A sound, the corner of the stairway, the lock on a gate, flowers in the
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_26' n='N026'/>ruins. The way the foot fits in a stone path which loses outline in vanished direction. Cows
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_27' n='N027'/>within temple precincts, wandered from India. A roof given way to sky illuminates mosaic
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_28' n='N028'/>squares, formal elements—natural elements—the elements. When you look at the sphere of our
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_29' n='N029'/>sun is it conceived differently if you stand in the exact center of a square? If you separate candles
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_30' n='N030'/>into a red glass, a blue glass, and a yellow glass, does your perception give the retina a different
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_31' n='N031'/>neural message for each color? Are we always composing processional spaces to approach our
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_32' n='N032'/>intuition? When you walk between columns toward the center do you begin to feel the effect of
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_33' n='N033'/>your progress toward the conclusion? Is geometry perhaps the repository of ancient sacrificial
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_34' n='N034'/>gesture? The Chinese, who have had a long time to think, have over a hundred names for
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_35' n='N035'/>differing shades of blue. Where do colors come from? Who am 1? Where do I come from? Where
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_36' n='N036'/>am I going? Liturgies are a logical order for progressions toward their fullest possible human
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_37' n='N037'/>form—mundra. This is an invocation. A statement of presence within defined votive space. A
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_38' n='N038'/>rejoicing. A statement of belief. A blessing and a recessional. The perfect logic of respect. Bio¬
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_39' n='N039'/>technology. The body as media, simplifying and clarifying ways to receive natural energies.
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_40' n='N040'/>Images which travel from era to era and are electric. Human needs are warmed by that same
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_41' n='N041'/>ancient fire. The walls we create are the containers and guardians of our continued relation to the
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_42' n='N042'/>light source. Electric affinities. “Each mortal thing does one thing and the same: deals out that
				<lb facs='#facs_81_region_1675008943105_1420_tl_43' n='N043'/>being indoors each one dwells.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
