<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Lippard_Issue1_82-86_duplicated</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: hmb010@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l1' n='N001'/>The Pink Glass Swan:
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l2' n='N002'/>Upward ond Downward Mobility in the Art World
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l3' n='N003'/>Lucy R.Lippard
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l4' n='N004'/>The general alienation of contemporary
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l5' n='N005'/>avant-garde art from any broad audience has
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l6' n='N006'/>been crystallized in the women&apos;s movement.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l7' n='N007'/>From the beginning, both liberal feminists con-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l8' n='N008'/>cerned with changing women&apos;s personal lives
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l9' n='N009'/>and socialist feminists concerned with over-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l10' n='N010'/>throwing the classist/racist/sexist foundations
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l11' n='N011'/>of society have agreed that &quot;fine&quot; art is more or
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l12' n='N012'/>less irrelevant, though holding out the hope
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l13' n='N013'/>that feminist art could and should be different.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l14' n='N014'/>The American women artists&apos; movement has
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l15' n='N015'/>concentrated its efforts on gaining power within
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l16' n='N016'/>its own interest group-the art world, in itself
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l17' n='N017'/>an incestuous network of relationships between
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l18' n='N018'/>artists and art on the one hand and dealers
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l19' n='N019'/>publishers, buyers on the other. The &quot;public,&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l20' n='N020'/>the &quot;masses,&quot; or the &quot;audience&quot; is hardly
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l21' n='N021'/>considered.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l22' n='N022'/>The art world has evolved its own curious
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l23' n='N023'/>class system. Externally this is a microcosm of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l24' n='N024'/>capitalist society, but it maintains an internal
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l25' n='N025'/>dialectic (or just plain contradiction) that at-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l26' n='N026'/>tempts to reverse or ignore that parallel. Fame
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l27' n='N027'/>may be a higher currency than mere money, but
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l28' n='N028'/>the two tend to go together. Since the buying
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l29' n='N029'/>and selling of art and artists is done by the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l30' n='N030'/>ruling classes or by those chummy with them
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l31' n='N031'/>and their institutions, all artists or producers, no
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l32' n='N032'/>matter what their individual economic back-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l33' n='N033'/>grounds are dependent on the owners and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l34' n='N034'/>forced into a proletarian role-just as women,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l35' n='N035'/>in Engels&apos; analysis, play proletarian to the male
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l36' n='N036'/>ruler across all class boundaries. Looking at and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l37' n='N037'/>&quot;appreciating&quot; art in this century has been
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l38' n='N038'/>understood as an instrument (or at best a result)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l39' n='N039'/>of upward social mobility in which owning art is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l40' n='N040'/>the ultimate step. Making art is at the bottom of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l41' n='N041'/>the scale. This is the only legitimate reason to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l42' n='N042'/>see artists as so many artists see themselves-as
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l43' n='N043'/>&quot;workers.&quot; At the same time, artists/maker
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l44' n='N044'/>tend to feel misunderstood and, as creators,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l45' n='N045'/>innately superior to the buyers/owners. The
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l46' n='N046'/>innermost circle of the art-world class system
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l47' n='N047'/>thereby replaces the rulers with the creators,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l48' n='N048'/>and the contemporary artist in the big city (read
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l49' n='N049'/>New York) is a schizophrenic creature. S/he is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l50' n='N050'/>persistently working &quot;up&quot; to be accepted, not
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l51' n='N051'/>only by other artists but also by the hierarchy
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l52' n='N052'/>that exhibits, writes about, and buys her/his
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l53' n='N053'/>work. At the same time s/he is often ideologi-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l54' n='N054'/>cally working &quot;down&quot; in an attempt to identify
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l55' n='N055'/>with the workers outside of the art context, and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r2l56' n='N056'/>to overthrow the rulers in the name of art. This
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l4' n='N001'/>conflict is augmented by the fact that most
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l6' n='N002'/>artists are originally from the middle class, and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l7' n='N003'/>their approach to the bourgeoisie includes a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l8' n='N004'/>touch of adolescent rebellion against authority.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l9' n='N005'/>Those few who have actually emerged from the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l10' n='N006'/>working class sometimes use this-their very
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l11' n='N007'/>lack of background privilege-as privilege in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l12' n='N008'/>itself, while playing the same schizophrenic
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l13' n='N009'/>foreground role as their solidly middle-class
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l14' n='N010'/>colleagues.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l15' n='N011'/>Artists, then, are workers or at least producers
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l16' n='N012'/>even when they don&apos;t know it. Yet artists
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l17' n='N013'/>dressed in work clothes (or expensive imitations
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l18' n='N014'/>thereof) and producing a commodity accessible
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l19' n='N015'/>only to the rich differ drastically from the real
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l20' n='N016'/>working class in that artists control their pro-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l21' n='N017'/>duction and their product-or could if they
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l22' n='N018'/>realized it and if they had the strength to main-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l23' n='N019'/>tain that control. In the studio, at least, unlike
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l24' n='N020'/>the farm, the factory, and the mine, the unor-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l25' n='N021'/>ganized worker is in superficial control and can,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l26' n='N022'/>if s/he dares, talk down to or tell off the boss -
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l27' n='N023'/>the collector, the curator, etc. For years now,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l28' n='N024'/>with little effect, it has been pointed out to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l29' n='N025'/>artists that the art-world superstructure cannot
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l30' n='N026'/>run without them. Art, after all, is the product
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l31' n='N027'/>on which all the money is made and the power
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l32' n='N028'/>based.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l33' n='N029'/>During the 1950s and 1960s most American
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l34' n='N030'/>artists were unaware that they did not control
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l35' n='N031'/>their art, that their art could be used not only
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l36' n='N032'/>for esthetic pleasure or decoration or status
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l37' n='N033'/>symbols, but also as an educational weapon. In
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l38' n='N034'/>the late 1960s, between the Black, the student,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l39' n='N035'/>the anti-war and the women&apos;s movements, the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l40' n='N036'/>facts of the exploitation of art in and out of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l41' n='N037'/>art world emerged. Most artists and artworkers
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l42' n='N038'/>still ignore these issues because they make us
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l43' n='N039'/>feel too uncomfortable and helpless. Yet if
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l44' n='N040'/>there were a strike against museums and gal -
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l45' n='N041'/>leries to allow artists control of their work, the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l46' n='N042'/>scabs would be out immediately in full force,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l47' n='N043'/>with reasons ranging from self-interest to total
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l48' n='N044'/>lack of political awareness to a genuine belief
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l49' n='N045'/>that society would crumble without art, that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l50' n='N046'/>art is &quot;above it all.&quot; Or is it in fact below it all,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l51' n='N047'/>as most political activists seem to think?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l52' n='N048'/>Another aspect of this conflict surfaces in dis-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l53' n='N049'/>cussions around who gets a &quot;piece of the pie&quot; -
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l54' n='N050'/>a phrase which has become the scornful desig-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l55' n='N051'/>nation for what is actually most peoples goal.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l56' n='N052'/>(Why shouldn&apos;t artists be able to make a living
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r3l57' n='N053'/>in this society like everybody else? Well, almost
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l1' n='N001'/>everybody else.) Those working for &quot;cultural
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l2' n='N002'/>change&quot; through political theonizing and occa -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l3' n='N003'/>sional actions are opposed to anybody getting a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l4' n='N004'/>piece of the pie, though politics appears to be
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l5' n='N005'/>getting fashionable again in the art world and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l6' n='N006'/>may itself provide a vehicle for internal success;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l7' n='N007'/>today one can refuse a piece of the pie and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l8' n='N008'/>simultaneously be getting a chance at it. Still,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l9' n='N009'/>the pie is very small and there are a lot of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l10' n='N010'/>hungry people circling it. Things were bad
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l11' n='N011'/>enough when only men were allowed to take a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l12' n='N012'/>bite. Since &quot;aggressive women&quot; have gotten in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l13' n='N013'/>there too, competition, always at the heart of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l14' n='N014'/>the art-world class system, has peaked.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l15' n='N015'/>Attendance at any large art school in the U.S.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l16' n='N016'/>takes students from all classes and trains them
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l17' n='N017'/>for artists&apos; schizophrenia. While being cool and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l18' n='N018'/>chicly grubby (in the &quot;uniform&quot; of mass produc -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l19' n='N019'/>tion), and knowing what&apos;s the latest in taste and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l20' n='N020'/>what&apos;s the kind of art to make and the right
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l21' n='N021'/>names to drop is clearly &quot;upward mobility&quot; -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l22' n='N022'/>from school into teaching jobs and/or the art
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l23' n='N023'/>world-the lifestyle accompanying these habits
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l24' n='N024'/>is heavily weighted &quot;downward.&quot; The working -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l25' n='N025'/>class girl who has had to work for nice clothes
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l26' n='N026'/>must drop into frayed jeans to make it into the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l27' n='N027'/>art middle ciass, which in turn considers itself
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l28' n='N028'/>both upper and lower class. Choosing poverty is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l29' n='N029'/>a confusing experence for a child whose
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l30' n='N030'/>parents (or more likely mother) have tried des -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l31' n='N031'/>perately against great odds to keep a clean and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l32' n='N032'/>pleasant home.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l33' n='N033'/>The artist who feels superior to the rich be -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l34' n='N034'/>cause s/he is disguised as someone who is poor
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l35' n='N035'/>provides a puzzle for the truly deprived. A par-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l36' n='N036'/>allel notion, rarely admitted but pervasive, is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l38' n='N037'/>that a person can&apos;t understand &quot;art&quot; if their
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l39' n='N038'/>house is full of pink glass swans or their lawn is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l40' n='N039'/>inhabited by gnomes and flamingos, or if they
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l41' n='N040'/>even care about house and clothes at all. This is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l42' n='N041'/>particularly ridiculous now, when art itself uses
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l43' n='N042'/>so much of this paraphernalia (and not always
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l44' n='N043'/>satirically); or, from another angle, when even
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l45' n='N044'/>artists who have no visible means of profes-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l46' n='N045'/>sional support live in palatial lofts and sport
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l47' n='N046'/>beat-up $100 boots while looking down on the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l48' n='N047'/>&quot;tourists&quot; who come to SoHo to see art on
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l49' n='N048'/>Saturdays; SoHo is, in fact, the new suburbia.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l50' n='N049'/>One reason for such callousness is a hangover
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l51' n='N050'/>from the 1950s, when artists really were poor
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l52' n='N051'/>and proud of being poor because their art, the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l53' n='N052'/>argument went, must be good if the bad guys -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l54' n='N053'/>the rich and the masses- didn&apos;t like it.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l55' n='N054'/>In the 1960s the choice of poverty, often
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l56' n='N055'/>excused as anti-consumerism, even infiltrated
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l57' n='N056'/>the esthetics of art. 2 First there was Pop Art,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l58' n='N057'/>modeled on kitsch, on advertising and consu -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l59' n='N058'/>merism, and equally successful on its own level.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l60' n='N059'/>(Women, incidentally, participated little in Pop
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l61' n='N060'/>Art, partly because of its blatant sexism, some -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l62' n='N061'/>times presented as a parody of the image of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l63' n='N062'/>woman in the media - and partly because the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r2l64' n='N063'/>subject matter was often &quot;women&apos;s work,&quot; en -
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l1' n='N001'/>nobled and acceptable only when the artists
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l2' n='N002'/>were men.) Then came Process Art-a rebellion
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l3' n='N003'/>against the &quot;precious object&quot; traditionally de -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l4' n='N004'/>sired and bought by the rich. Here another kind
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l5' n='N005'/>of co-optation took place, when temporary
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l6' n='N006'/>piles of dirt, oil, rags and filthy rubber began to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l7' n='N007'/>grace carpeted living rooms. The Italian branch
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l8' n='N008'/>was even called Arte Povera. Then came the rise
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l9' n='N009'/>of a third-stream medium called &quot;conceptual
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l10' n='N010'/>art&quot; which offered &quot;anti-objects&quot; in the form of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l11' n='N011'/>ideas-books or simple xeroxed texts and photo-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l12' n='N012'/>graphs with no inherent physical or monetary
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l13' n='N013'/>value (until they got on the market, that is).
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l14' n='N014'/>Conceptual art seemed politically viable be-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l15' n='N015'/>cause of its notion that the use of ordinary,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l16' n='N016'/>inexpensive, unbulky media would lead to a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l17' n='N017'/>kind of socialization (or at least democratiza-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l18' n='N018'/>tion) of art as opposed to gigantic canvases and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l19' n='N019'/>huge chrome sculptures costing five figures and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l20' n='N020'/>filling the world with more consumer fetishes.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l21' n='N021'/>Yet the trip from of on canvas to ideas on
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l22' n='N022'/>xerox was, in retrospect, yet another instance of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l23' n='N023'/>&quot;downward mobility&quot; or middle-class guilt. It
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l24' n='N024'/>was no accident that conceptual art appeared at
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l25' n='N025'/>the height of the social movements of the late
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l26' n='N026'/>1960s nor that the artists were sympathetic to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l27' n='N027'/>those movements (with the qualified exception
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l28' n='N028'/>of the women&apos;s movement). All of the esthetic
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l29' n='N029'/>tendencies listed above were genuinely insti -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l30' n='N030'/>gated as rebellions by the artists themselves, yet
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l31' n='N031'/>the fact remains that only rich people can afford
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l32' n='N032'/>to 1) spend money on art that won&apos;t last; 2) live
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l33' n='N033'/>with &quot;ugly art&quot; or art that is not decorative,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l34' n='N034'/>because the rest of their surroundings are beau -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l35' n='N035'/>tiful and comfortable; 3) like &quot;non-object art&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l36' n='N036'/>which is only handy If you already have too
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l37' n='N037'/>many possessions-when it becomes a reaction -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l38' n='N038'/>ary commentary: art for the overprivileged in a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l39' n='N039'/>consumer society.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l40' n='N040'/>As a child, I was accused by my parents of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l41' n='N041'/>being an &quot;anti-snob snob&quot; and I&apos;m only begin -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l42' n='N042'/>ning to see the limitations of such a rebellion.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l43' n='N043'/>Years later I was an early supporter of and pros -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l44' n='N044'/>elytizer for conceptual art as escape from the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l45' n='N045'/>commodity orientation of the art world, a way
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l46' n='N046'/>of communicating with a broader audience via
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l47' n='N047'/>inexpensive media. Though I was bitterly dis -
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l48' n='N048'/>appointed (with the social, not the esthetic
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l49' n='N049'/>achievements) when I found that this work
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l50' n='N050'/>could be so easily absorbed into the system, it is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l51' n='N051'/>only now that I&apos;ve realized why the absorption
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l52' n='N052'/>took place. Conceptual art&apos;s democratic efforts
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l53' n='N053'/>and physical vehicles were cancelled out by its
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l54' n='N054'/>neutral, elitist content and its patronizing ap-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l55' n='N055'/>proach. From around 1967 to 1971, most of us
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l56' n='N056'/>involved in conceptual art saw that content as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l57' n='N057'/>pretty revolutionary and thought of ourselves as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l58' n='N058'/>rebels against the cool, hostile artifacts of the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l59' n='N059'/>prevailing formalist and minimal art. But we
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l60' n='N060'/>were so totally enveloped in the middle-class
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l61' n='N061'/>approach to everything we did and saw, we
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l62' n='N062'/>couldn&apos;t perceive how that pseudo-academic
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r3l63' n='N063'/>narrative piece or that art-world-oriented action
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l1' n='N001'/>in the streets was deprived of any revolutionary
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l2' n='N002'/>content by the fact that it was usually incom -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l3' n='N003'/>prehensible and alienating to the people &quot;out
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l4' n='N004'/>there,&quot; no matter how fashionably downwardly
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l5' n='N005'/>mobile it might be in the art world. The idea
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l6' n='N006'/>that if art is subversive in the art world it will
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l7' n='N007'/>automatically appeal to a general audience now
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l8' n='N008'/>seems absurd.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l9' n='N009'/>The whole evolutionary basis of modernist
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l10' n='N010'/>innovation, the idea of esthetic &quot;progress,&quot;  the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l11' n='N011'/>&quot;I-did-it-first&quot; and &quot;it&apos;s-been-done-already&quot; syn -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l12' n='N012'/>dromes which pervade contemporary avant -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l13' n='N013'/>garde art and criticism, are also blatantly class-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l14' n='N014'/>ist, and have more to do with technology than
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l15' n='N015'/>with art. To be &quot;avant-garde&quot; is inevitably to be
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l16' n='N016'/>on top or to become upper-middle-class, be -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l17' n='N017'/>cause such innovations take place in a context
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l18' n='N018'/>accessible only to the educated elite. Thus
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l19' n='N019'/>socially conscious artists working in or with
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l20' n='N020'/>community groups and muralists try to dis -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l21' n='N021'/>associate themselves from the art world, even
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l22' n='N022'/>though its values (&quot;quality&quot;) remain to haunt
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l23' n='N023'/>them personally.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l24' n='N024'/>The value systems are different in and out of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l25' n='N025'/>the art world, and anyone attempting to strad -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l26' n='N026'/>dle the two develops another kind of schizo -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l27' n='N027'/>phrenia. For instance, in the inner-city com -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l28' n='N028'/>munity murals, as Eva Cockcroft points out else -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l29' n='N029'/>where in this publication, the images of woman
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l30' n='N030'/>are the traditional ones-a beautiful, noble
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l31' n='N031'/>mother and housewife or worker, and a re -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l32' n='N032'/>bellious young woman striving to change her
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l33' n='N033'/>world-both of them celebrated for their cour -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l34' n='N034'/>age to be and to stay the way they are and to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l35' n='N035'/>support their men in the face of horrendous
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l36' n='N036'/>odds. This is not the art-world or middle-class
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l37' n='N037'/>&quot;radical&quot; view of future feminism, nor is it one
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l38' n='N038'/>which radical feminists hoping to &quot;reach out&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l39' n='N039'/>across the classes can easily espouse. Here, in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l40' n='N040'/>the realm of aspirations, is where upward and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l41' n='N041'/>downward mobility and status quo clash, where
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l42' n='N042'/>the economic class barriers are established. As
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l43' n='N043'/>Michele Russell has noted, 3 the Third-World
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l44' n='N044'/>woman is not attracted to the &quot;Utopian experi -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l45' n='N045'/>mentation&quot; of the left (in the art world, the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l46' n='N046'/>would-be Marxist avant-garde) or to the &quot;prag-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l47' n='N047'/>matic opportunism&quot; of the right (in the art
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l48' n='N048'/>world, those who reform and co-opt the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l49' n='N049'/>&quot;radicals&quot;).
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l50' n='N050'/>Many of the subjects touched on here come
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l51' n='N051'/>back to Taste. To a poor woman, art, or a beau -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l52' n='N052'/>tiful object, might be defined as something she
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l53' n='N053'/>cannot have. Beauty and art have been defined
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l54' n='N054'/>before as the desirable. In a consumer society,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l55' n='N055'/>art too becomes a commodity rather than a life-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l56' n='N056'/>enhancing experience. Yet the Van Gogh repro -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l57' n='N057'/>duction or the pink glass swan-the same
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l58' n='N058'/>beautiful objects that may be &quot;below&quot; a middle -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l59' n='N059'/>class woman (because she has, in moving up-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l60' n='N060'/>ward, acquired upper-class taste, or would like
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l61' n='N061'/>to think she has)-may be &quot;above&quot; or inacces -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r2l62' n='N062'/>sible to a welfare mother. The phrase &quot;to dictate taste&quot; has its own political connotations.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l1' n='N001'/>Minneapolis worker Interviewed by students of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l2' n='N002'/>artist Don Celender said he liked &quot;old art works
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l3' n='N003'/>because they&apos;re more classy,&quot; 4
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l4' n='N004'/>and class does
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l5' n='N005'/>seem to be what the traditional notion of art is
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l6' n='N006'/>all about. Yet contemporary avant-garde art, for
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l7' n='N007'/>all its attempts to break out of that gold frame, is
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l8' n='N008'/>equally class-bound, and even the artist aware
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l9' n='N009'/>of these contradictions in her/his own life and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l10' n='N010'/>work is hard-put to resolve them. It&apos;s a vicious
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l11' n='N011'/>circle If the artist/producer is upper-middle-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l12' n='N012'/>class, and our standards of art as taught in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l13' n='N013'/>schools are persistently upper-middle-class,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l14' n='N014'/>how do we escape making art only for the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l15' n='N015'/>upper-middle-class?
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l16' n='N016'/>The alternatives to &quot;quality,&quot; to the &quot;high&quot; art
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l17' n='N017'/>shown in art-world galleries and magazines
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l18' n='N018'/>have been few, and for the most part unsatis-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l19' n='N019'/>fying, although well-intended. Even when
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l20' n='N020'/>kitsch, politics or housework are absorbed into
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l21' n='N021'/>art, contact with the real world is not neces -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l22' n='N022'/>sarily made. At no time has the avant garde,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l23' n='N023'/>though playing in the famous &quot;gap between art
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l24' n='N024'/>and life,&quot; moved far enough out of the art con -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l25' n='N025'/>text to attract a broad audience-that audience
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l26' n='N026'/>which has, ironically, been trained to think of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l27' n='N027'/>art as something that has nothing to do with life
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l28' n='N028'/>and, at the same time, tends only to like that art
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l29' n='N029'/>which means something in terms of its own life,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l30' n='N030'/>or fantasies. The dilemma for the leftist artist in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l31' n='N031'/>the middle class is that her/his standards seem
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l32' n='N032'/>to have been set irremediably. No matter how
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l33' n='N033'/>much we know about what the broader public
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l34' n='N034'/>wants, or needs, it is very difficult to break
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l35' n='N035'/>social conditioning and cultural habits. Hope -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l36' n='N036'/>fully, a truly feminist art will provide other
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l37' n='N037'/>standards.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l38' n='N038'/>To understand the woman artist&apos;s position in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l39' n='N039'/>this complex situation between the art world
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l40' n='N040'/>and the real world, class and gender, it is neces -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l41' n='N041'/>sary to know that in America artists are rarely
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l42' n='N042'/>respected unless they are stars or rich or mad or
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l43' n='N043'/>dead. Being an artist is not being &quot;somebody.&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l44' n='N044'/>Middle-class families are happy to pay lip ser -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l45' n='N045'/>vice to art but god forbid their own children
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l46' n='N046'/>take it so seriously as to consider it a profession.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l47' n='N047'/>Thus a man who becomes an artist is asked
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l48' n='N048'/>when he is going to &quot;go to work,&quot; and he is not- 
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l49' n='N049'/>so-covertly considered a child, a sissy (a wom -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l50' n='N050'/>an), someone who has a hobby rather than a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l51' n='N051'/>vocation, someone who can&apos;t make money and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l52' n='N052'/>therefore cannot hold his head up in the real
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l53' n='N053'/>world of men—at least until his work sells, at
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l54' n='N054'/>which point he may be welcomed back. Male
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l55' n='N055'/>artists, bending over backward to rid them -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l56' n='N056'/>selves of this stigma, tend to be particularly
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l57' n='N057'/>susceptible to insecurity and machismo. So
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l58' n='N058'/>women daring to insist on their place in the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l59' n='N059'/>primary rank-as art makers rather than as art
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l60' n='N060'/>housekeepers (curators, critics, dealers, &quot;pa -
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l61' n='N061'/>trons&quot;)-inherit a heavy burden of male fears in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r3l62' n='N062'/>addition to the economic and psychological
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l1' n='N001'/>discrimination still rampant in a patriarchal,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l2' n='N002'/>money-oriented society.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l3' n='N003'/>Most art being shown now has lttle to do
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l4' n='N004'/>with any woman&apos;s experience, in part because
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l5' n='N005'/>women-rich ones as &quot;patrons,&quot; others as
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l6' n='N006'/>decorators and &quot;home-makers&quot; —are in charge
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l7' n='N007'/>of the private sphere, while men identify more
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l8' n='N008'/>easily with public art-art that has become
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l9' n='N009'/>public through economic validation (the mil -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l10' n='N010'/>lion-dollar Rembrandt). Private art is often seen
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l11' n='N011'/>as mere ornament; public art is associated with
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l12' n='N012'/>monuments and money, with &quot;high&quot; art and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l13' n='N013'/>its containers, including unwelcoming white -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l14' n='N014'/>walled galleries and museums with classical
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l15' n='N015'/>courthouse architecture. Even the graffiti art -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l16' n='N016'/>ists, whose work was unsuccessfully transferred
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l17' n='N017'/>from subways to art galleries, were all men,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l18' n='N018'/>concerned with facades, with having their
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l19' n='N019'/>names in spray paint, in lights, in museums.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l21' n='N020'/>Private art is visible only to intimates.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l23' n='N021'/>I suspect the reason so few women &quot;folk&quot; artists
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l24' n='N022'/>work outdoors in large scale (like Simon Rodia&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l25' n='N023'/>Watts Towers and other &quot;naives and visionaries&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l26' n='N024'/>with their cement and bottles) is not only be-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l27' n='N025'/>cause men aspire to erections and know how to
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l28' n='N026'/>use the necessary tools, but because women
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l29' n='N027'/>can and must assuage these same creative urges
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l30' n='N028'/>inside the house, with the pink glass swan as an
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l31' n='N029'/>element in their own works of art-the living
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l32' n='N030'/>room or kitchen. In the art world the situation is
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l33' n='N031'/>doubly paralleled. Women&apos;s art until recently
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l34' n='N032'/>was rarely seen in public and all artists are
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l35' n='N033'/>voluntarily &quot;women&quot; because of the social atti -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l36' n='N034'/>tudes mentioned above; the art world is so small
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l37' n='N035'/>that it is &quot;private.&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l38' n='N036'/>Just as the living room is enclosed by the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l39' n='N037'/>building it is in, art and artist are firmly im -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l40' n='N038'/>prisoned by the culture which supports them.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l41' n='N039'/>Artists claiming to work for themselves alone,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l42' n='N040'/>and not for any audience at all, are passively
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l43' n='N041'/>accepting the upper-middle class audience of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l44' n='N042'/>the internal art world. This is compounded by
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l45' n='N043'/>the fact that to be middle-class is to be passive,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l46' n='N044'/>to live with the expectation of being taken care
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l47' n='N045'/>of and entertained. But art should be a con -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l48' n='N046'/>sciousness-raiser; it partakes of and should fuse
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l49' n='N047'/>the private and the public spheres. It should be
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l50' n='N048'/>able to reintegrate the personal without being
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l51' n='N049'/>satisfied by the merely personal. One good test
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l52' n='N050'/>is whether or not it communicates, and then, of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l53' n='N051'/>course, what and how it communicates. If it
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l54' n='N052'/>doesn&apos;t communicate it may just not be very
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l55' n='N053'/>good art from anyone&apos;s point of view; or it may
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l56' n='N054'/>be that the artist is not even aware of the needs
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l57' n='N055'/>of others, or simply doesn&apos;t care.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l58' n='N056'/>For there is a need out there, a need vaguely
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l59' n='N057'/>satisfied at the moment by &quot;schlock.&quot; 5 And it
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l60' n='N058'/>seems that one of the basic tenets of the femin -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l61' n='N059'/>ist arts should be a reaching out from the private
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l62' n='N060'/>sphere to transform that &quot;artificial art&quot; and to
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l63' n='N061'/>more fully satisfy that need. For the art-world
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l64' n='N062'/>artist has come to consider her/his private
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l65' n='N063'/>needs paramount, and has too often forgotten
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l1' n='N001'/>about those of the audience, any audience.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l2' n='N002'/>Work that communicates to a dangerous num -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l3' n='N003'/>ber of people is derogatorily called a &quot;crowd
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l4' n='N004'/>pleaser.&quot; This is a blatantly classist attitude,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l5' n='N005'/>taking for granted that most people are by na -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l6' n='N006'/>ture incapable of understanding good art (ie.,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l7' n='N007'/>upper-class or quality art). At the same time,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l8' n='N008'/>much ado is made about art-educational theo -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l9' n='N009'/>ries that claim to &quot;teach people to see&quot; (con -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l10' n='N010'/>sider the political implications of this notion)
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l11' n='N011'/>and muffle all issues by stressing the &quot;universal-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l12' n='N012'/>ity&quot; of great art.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l13' n='N013'/>It may be that at the moment the possibilities
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l14' n='N014'/>are slim for a middle-class art world&apos;s under -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l15' n='N015'/>standing or criticism of the little art we see that
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l16' n='N016'/>reflects working-class cultural values. Perhaps
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l17' n='N017'/>our current responsibility lies in humanizing our
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l18' n='N018'/>own activities so that they will communicate
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l19' n='N019'/>more effectively with all women. Hopefully we
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l20' n='N020'/>will aspire to more than women&apos;s art flooding
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l21' n='N021'/>the museum and gallery circuit. Perhaps a femi -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l22' n='N022'/>nist art will only emerge when we become whol -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l23' n='N023'/>ly responsible for our own work, for what be -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l24' n='N024'/>comes of it, who sees it, and who is nourished
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l25' n='N025'/>by it. For a feminist artist, whatever her style,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l26' n='N026'/>the prime audience at this time is other women.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l27' n='N027'/>So far, we have tended to be satisfied with com -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l28' n='N028'/>municating with those women whose social
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l29' n='N029'/>experience is close to ours. This is natural
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l30' n='N030'/>enough, since this is where we will get our
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l31' n='N031'/>greatest support, and we need support in taking
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l32' n='N032'/>this risk of trying to please women, knowing
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l33' n='N033'/>that we are almost certain to displease men in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l34' n='N034'/>the process. In addition, it is embarrassing to
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l35' n='N035'/>talk openly about the class system which divides
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l36' n='N036'/>us, hard to do so without sounding more bour -
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l37' n='N037'/>geois than ever in the implications of superiority
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l38' n='N038'/>and inferiority inherent in such discussions
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l39' n='N039'/>(where the working class is as often considered
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l40' n='N040'/>superior as the middle class).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l41' n='N041'/>A book of essays called Class and Feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l42' n='N042'/>written by The Furies, a lesbian feminist collec-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l43' n='N043'/>tive, makes clear that from the point of view of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l44' n='N044'/>working-class women, class is a definite prob-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l45' n='N045'/>lem within the women&apos;s movement. As Nancy
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l46' n='N046'/>Myron observes, middle-class women:
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l47' n='N047'/>can intellectualize, politicize, accuse, abuse
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l48' n='N048'/>and contribute money in order not to deal with
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l49' n='N049'/>their own classism. Even if they admit that
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l50' n='N050'/>class exists, they are not likely to admit that
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l51' n='N051'/>their behavior is a product of it. They will go
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l52' n='N052'/>through every painful detail of their lives to
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l53' n='N053'/>prove to me or another working-class woman
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l54' n='N054'/>that they really didn&apos;t have any privilege, that
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l55' n='N055'/>their family was exceptional, that they actually
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l56' n='N056'/>did have an uncle who worked in a factory. To
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l57' n='N057'/>ease anyone&apos;s guilt is not the point of talking
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l58' n='N058'/>about class... You don&apos;t get rid of oppression
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l59' n='N059'/>just by talking about it.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l61' n='N060'/> 
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r2l62' n='N061'/>shlhtll ii
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r3l1' n='N001'/>85
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l1' n='N001'/>Women are more strenuously conditioned
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l2' n='N002'/>toward upward cultural mobility or &quot;gentility&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l3' n='N003'/>than men, which often results in the woman
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l4' n='N004'/>consciously betraying her class origins as a mat -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l5' n='N005'/>ter of course. The hierarchies within the whole
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l6' n='N006'/>span of the middle class are most easily demar -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l7' n='N007'/>cated by lifestyle and dress. For instance, the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l8' n='N008'/>much-scorned &quot;Queens housewife&quot; may have
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l9' n='N009'/>enough to eat, may have learned to consume
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l10' n='N010'/>the unnecessities, and may have made it to a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l11' n='N011'/>desired social bracket in her community, but if
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l12' n='N012'/>she ventures to make art (not just own it), she
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l13' n='N013'/>will find herself back at the bottom in the art
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l14' n='N014'/>world, looking wistfully up to the plateau where
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l15' n='N015'/>the male, the young, the bejeaned seem so at
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l16' n='N016'/>ease.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l17' n='N017'/>For middle-class women in the art world not
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l18' n='N018'/>only dress &quot;down,&quot; but dress like working-class
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l19' n='N019'/>men. They do so because housedresses, pedal
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l20' n='N020'/>pushers, polyester pantsuits, perrnanents, the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l21' n='N021'/>wrong accents are not such acceptable disguis -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l22' n='N022'/>es for women as the boots, overalls and wind -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l23' n='N023'/>breaker syndromes are for men. Thus young
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l24' n='N024'/>middle-class women tend to deny their female
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l25' n='N025'/>counterparts and take on &quot;male&quot; (unisex) attire.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l26' n='N026'/>It may at times have been chic to dress like
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l27' n='N027'/>a native American or a Bedouin woman, but it
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l28' n='N028'/>has never been chic to dress like a working -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l29' n='N029'/>class woman, even if she&apos;s trying to look like
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l30' n='N030'/>Jackie Kennedy. Young working-class women
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l31' n='N031'/>(and men) spend a large amount of avallable
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l32' n='N032'/>money on clothes; it&apos;s a way to forget the rats
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l33' n='N033'/>and roaches by which even the cleanest tene -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l34' n='N034'/>ment-dwellers are blessed, or the mortgages by
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l35' n='N035'/>which even the hardest-working homeowners
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l36' n='N036'/>are blessed, and to present a classy facade.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l37' n='N037'/>Artists dressing and talking &quot;down&quot; insult the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l38' n='N038'/>hardhat much as rich kids in rags do; they insult
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l39' n='N039'/>people whose notion of art is something to work
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l40' n='N040'/>for-the pink glass swan.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l41' n='N041'/>Yet women, as evidenced by the Furies&apos; publi -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l42' n='N042'/>cation, and as pointed out elsewhere (most not-
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l43' n='N043'/>ably by Bebel), have a unique chance to com -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l44' n='N044'/>municate with women across the boundaries of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l45' n='N045'/>economic class because as a &quot;vertical class&quot; we
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l46' n='N046'/>share the majority of our most fundamental
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l47' n='N047'/>experiences-emotionally, even when econom -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l48' n='N048'/>cally we are divided. Thus an economic analy -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l49' n='N049'/>sis does not adequately explore the psychologi -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l50' n='N050'/>cal and esthetic ramifications of the need for
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l51' n='N051'/>change within a sexually oppressed group. Nor
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l52' n='N052'/>does it take into consideration that women&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l53' n='N053'/>needs are different from men&apos;s-or so it seems
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l54' n='N054'/>at this still unequal point in history. The vertical
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l55' n='N055'/>class cuts across the horizontal economic class -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l56' n='N056'/>es in a column of injustices. While heightened
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l57' n='N057'/>class consciousness can only clarify the way we
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l58' n='N058'/>see the world, and all clarification is for the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l59' n='N059'/>better, I can&apos;t bring myself to trust hard lines
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l60' n='N060'/>and categories where fledgling feminism is
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l61' n='N061'/>concerned.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l62' n='N062'/>Even in the art world, the issue of feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l63' n='N063'/>has barely been raised in mixed political groups.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r2l64' n='N064'/>In 1970, women took our rage and our energies
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l1' n='N001'/>to our own organizations, or directly to the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l2' n='N002'/>public by means of picketing and protests.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l3' n='N003'/>While a few men supported these, and most
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l4' n='N004'/>politically conscious male artists now claim to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l5' n='N005'/>be feminists to some degree, the political and
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l6' n='N006'/>apolitical art world goes on as though feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l7' n='N007'/>didn&apos;t exist-the presence of a few vociferous
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l8' n='N008'/>feminist artists and critics not withstanding. And
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l9' n='N009'/>in the art world, as in the real world, political
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l10' n='N010'/>commitment frequently means total disregard
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l11' n='N011'/>for feminist priorities. Even the increasingly
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l12' n='N012'/>Marxist group ironically calling itself Art-
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l13' n='N013'/>Language is unwilling to stop the exclusive use
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l14' n='N014'/>of the male pronoun in its theoretical publica -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l15' n='N015'/>tions. 6
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l16' n='N016'/>Experiences like this one and dissatisfaction
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l17' n='N017'/>with Marxism&apos;s lack of interest in &quot;the woman
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l18' n='N018'/>question&quot; make me wary of merging Marxism
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l19' n='N019'/>and feminism. The notion of the non-economic
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l20' n='N020'/>or &quot;vertical&quot; class is anathema to Marxists and
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l21' n='N021'/>confusion is rampant around the chicken-egg
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l22' n='N022'/>question of whether women can be equal be -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l23' n='N023'/>fore the establishment of a classless society or
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l24' n='N024'/>whether a classless society can be established
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l25' n='N025'/>before women are liberated. As Sheila Row -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l26' n='N026'/>botham says of her own Marxism and feminism:
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l27' n='N027'/>They are at once incompatible and in real need
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l28' n='N028'/>of one another. As a feminist and a Marxist I
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l29' n='N029'/>carry their contradictions within me and it is
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l30' n='N030'/>tempting to opt for one or the other in an effort
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l31' n='N031'/>to produce a tidy resolution of the commotion
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l32' n='N032'/>generated by the antagonism between them.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l33' n='N033'/>But to do that would mean evading the social
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l34' n='N034'/>reality which gives rise to the antagonism.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l35' n='N035'/>As women, therefore, we need to establish far
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l36' n='N036'/>more strongly our own sense of community, so
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l37' n='N037'/>that all our arts will be enjoyed by all women in
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l38' n='N038'/>all economic circumstances. This will happen
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l39' n='N039'/>only when women artists make conscious ef -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l40' n='N040'/>forts to cross class barriers, to consider their
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l41' n='N041'/>audience, to see, respect, work with the women
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l42' n='N042'/>who create outside the art world-whether in
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l43' n='N043'/>suburban crafts guilds or in offices and factories
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l44' n='N044'/>or in community workshops. The current femi -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l45' n='N045'/>nist passion for women&apos;s traditional arts, which
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l46' n='N046'/>influences a great many women artists, should
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l47' n='N047'/>make this road much easier, undess it too be -
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l48' n='N048'/>comes another commercialized rip-off. Despite
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l49' n='N049'/>the very real class obstacles, I feel strongly that
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l50' n='N050'/>women are in a privileged position to satisfy the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l51' n='N051'/>goal of an art which would communicate the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l52' n='N052'/>needs of all classes and sexes to each other, and
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l53' n='N053'/>get rid ofthe we/they dichotomy to as great an
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l54' n='N054'/>extent as is possible in a capitalist framework.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l55' n='N055'/>Our sex, our oppression and our female experi-
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l56' n='N056'/>ence-our female culture, just being explored
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l57' n='N057'/>- offer access to all of us by these common
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l58' n='N058'/>threads.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l59' n='N059'/>Cass and feminfsm, ed. Charlotte Bunch and Nandy
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l60' n='N060'/>Myron (Baltimore, 1974). This book contains some ex-
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l61' n='N061'/>crutiating insights forthe middle class feminist, jt raised
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l62' n='N062'/>ny consciousness and inspired this essay (along with
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r3l63' n='N063'/>other recent experiences and conversations)
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
