<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='68'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Natalie Barney stood at the center of that group we</l>
					<l>usually refer to as &quot;the Paris lesbians.&quot; Famous for both</l>
					<l>her love affairs and her literary salon, Barney&apos;s circle</l>
					<l>included Gertrude Stein, Romaine Brooks, Djuna</l>
					<l>Barnes and Colette, as well as Jean Cocteau, Andre</l>
					<l>Gide, Ezra Pound, and others.</l>
					<l>Barney was a writer herself but little of her work has</l>
					<l>appeared in English, and she is more talked about than</l>
					<l>read. She was alive until 1972 but remains enigmatic, a</l>
					<l>&quot;legend,&quot; the blonde Amazon who rode horseback in</l>
					<l>the Bois de Boulogne every morning. “She was</l>
					<l>charming, wrote Sylvia Beach in Shakespeare and</l>
					<l>Company. “Many of her sex found her fatally so...</l>
					<l>The following excerpt from one of her last books</l>
					<l>chronicles an important relationship in Barney&apos;s life,</l>
					<l>that with poet Renée Vivien.</l>
					<l>In the article, Barney first describes her own girlhood</l>
					<l>in Cincinnati and Paris, then a love affair with Liane de</l>
					<l>Pougy, a courtesan. As this affair is ending, she is intro¬</l>
					<l>duced to Renée Vivien by a mutual friend, Violette Shi¬</l>
					<l>letto. Both women are about twenty years old at this</l>
					<l>time, and Barney, absorbed with thoughts of Liane,</l>
					<l>pays little attention to Renée until she hears some of her</l>
					<l>poetry..</l>
					<l>One evening Renée invited me for the first time into</l>
					<l>her room at the family boarding house, rue Crevaux.</l>
					<l>“To render it worthy of my coming&quot; she had filled il</l>
					<l>with lilies, the flower that she had dedicated to me:</l>
					<l>&quot;You will wither one day, ah! My lily!</l>
					<l>Meanwhile, it was the lilies which were withering.</l>
					<l>l’here were some of them in a too narrow jar of water</l>
					<l>and even on her bed. Their whiteness illuminated the</l>
					<l>somber corners of the room: it was a splendor, a suffo¬</l>
					<l>cation, transforming this ordinary room into an ardent</l>
					<l>and virginal chapel inclining us toward genuflection¬</l>
					<l>she before me, I before her.</l>
					<l>I left her at dawn. The snow, last innocence of winter,</l>
					<l>had disappeared, but a light frost covered the ground</l>
					<l>where my footsteps imprinted themselves on this pallor</l>
					<l>between her street and mine.</l>
					<l>Disturbing beginnings where two young girls sought</l>
					<l>each other by way of a love badly shared.</l>
					<l>The yet somnolent senses of Renée scarcely responded</l>
					<l>to my desires; her budding love, exalted by imagina¬</l>
					<l>tion, appropriated my role of lover-poet. After each</l>
					<l>rendezvous, &quot;for the night was to us as to others the</l>
					<l>day,&quot; I received from her flowers and poems, from</l>
					<l>which 1 choose these several fragments as so many</l>
					<l>avowals retracing the beginnings of our strange liaison:</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Natalie Barney on Renée Viwen</l>
					<l>Translated by Margaret Porter</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>See, I am of the age when the virgin abandons her hand</l>
					<l>To the man that her weakness looks for and fears</l>
					<l>And 1 have not chosen a companion of the route</l>
					<l>Because you appeared at the turning of the way.</l>
					<l>I feel tremble on my mute lips</l>
					<l>The gentleness and fright of your first kiss.</l>
					<l>Under your step, I hear the breaking of lyres...</l>
					<l>With what kisses charm the languor of your soul...</l>
					<l>With what rhythms of love, with what fervent poem</l>
					<l>Honor worthily her whose beauty</l>
					<l>Wears Desire on her forehead like a diadem?</l>
					<l>Embarrassed by this excess of adoration, to which 1</l>
					<l>would have preferred joys better shared, I loved how-</l>
					<l>ever the verses that she wrote to me. 1 rendered count</l>
					<l>that this attitude of adoration, for which I was the pre¬</l>
					<l>text, was necessary to her, and that without really</l>
					<l>knowing me, she found, thanks to me, a new theme of</l>
					<l>inspiration to succeed death and solitude: love—but</l>
					<l>love under an aspect which, since Sappho, had scarcely</l>
					<l>found a poet.</l>
					<l>Renée Vivien had just offered me a whole notebook</l>
					<l>written in the hand of a good scholar whose writing had</l>
					<l>not yet taken flight. Under the cover on parchment</l>
					<l>where figured a lily and a lyre of doubtful taste, she had</l>
					<l>inscribed: “To Natalie, for her alone.&quot; After reading</l>
					<l>and rereading her verses, inspired by me and surpassing</l>
					<l>my own, I wanted them to be published. Renée, who</l>
					<l>however &quot;aspired to glory”—for she had a more lofty</l>
					<l>idea of it than I—consented to see them appear, but on</l>
					<l>condition that she sign her book only “R. Vivien.</l>
					<l>When this first collection of verse appeared, from</l>
					<l>Alphonse Lemerre, and under this initial could pass for</l>
					<l>that of a masculine first name, a young lecturer who</l>
					<l>flattered himself on discovering and launching future</l>
					<l>geniuses, took as subject these Etudes et Preludes and</l>
					<l>declared to his audience “how one feels the verses</l>
					<l>vibrant with love written by a very young man idola¬</l>
					<l>There was, in fact, cause to</l>
					<l>trous of a first mistress.</l>
					<l>misunderstand:</l>
					<l>You touch without embracing like the chimera...</l>
					<l>Your form is a gleam that leaves the hands empty...</l>
					<l>As he continued his lecture on this gift, Renée and I</l>
					<l>seized with foolish laughter, had to precipitously leave</l>
					<l>the hall. No one in the audience could guess the cause of</l>
					<l>this brusque departure.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='69'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>As they began to ask my poetess for interviews and</l>
					<l>meetings, she feared being invaded and had herself</l>
					<l>represented by a governess of an aspect as anti-poetic as</l>
					<l>possible. This one had to make herself pass for Renée</l>
					<l>Vivien, which discouraged future pursuits and enthu-</l>
					<l>siasms, for the rumor spread that the author of a work</l>
					<l>so troubling was deprived of all charm, eloquence or</l>
					<l>physical attraction.</l>
					<l>A short time after, she took me to her home in</l>
					<l>London, where I was able to find in the celebrated book-</l>
					<l>store of Bodley Head a copy of the fragments of</l>
					<l>Sappho, translated by Wharton (no connection with my</l>
					<l>compatriot the novelist Edith Wharton, who would</l>
					<l>have trembled with horror at the idea of a possible con¬</l>
					<l>fusion). This precious collection served Renée Vivien for</l>
					<l>comparison with her French translation; it became her</l>
					<l>bedside book and the source from which she drew the</l>
					<l>pagan inspiration for several of her books to come. One</l>
					<l>is not pagan who wishes to be: I felt already in her a</l>
					<l>Christian soul which was ignored. While I leafed</l>
					<l>through other books, John Lane, the editor-publisher</l>
					<l>pointed out Opale, the first book of verse of a young</l>
					<l>poetess of Norfolk, whose second collection he was</l>
					<l>going to publish soon.</l>
					<l>Several of these poems pleased me to the point that l</l>
					<l>wrote to their author, adding to my word of admiration</l>
					<l>Etude et Preludes and Quelques Portraits—Sonnets de</l>
					<l>Femmes. Opale responded with fire:</l>
					<l>..For I would dance to make you smile, and sing</l>
					<l>Of those who with some sweet mad sin have played,</l>
					<l>And how Love walks with delicate feet afraid</l>
					<l>Twixt maid and maid.</l>
					<l>&quot;Why,&quot; I said to Renée, “shouldn’t we assemble</l>
					<l>around us a group of poetesses like those who sur¬</l>
					<l>rounded Sappho at Mytilene and who mutually inspired</l>
					<l>each other?</l>
					<l>This project pleased her so much that we began to</l>
					<l>realize it by suggesting to Opale to come to be near us in</l>
					<l>Paris, where we were returning to install ourselves in a</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>small hotel on the rue Alphonse-de-Neuville, next to</l>
					<l>that of the Rostands. My parents reluctantly let me do</l>
					<l>it, but only after imposing on me, as chaperone, a</l>
					<l>housekeeper who had already been mine in a pension</l>
					<l>where I stayed when I was in transit at Paris. It is she,</l>
					<l>besides, who presented herself under the name of Renée</l>
					<l>to discourage the curious. The sympathetic Professor</l>
					<l>B.C. was also hired to teach Greek to Renée in view of a</l>
					<l>translation into French verse that she wished to do of</l>
					<l>the fragments of Sappho. After her lesson, he corrected</l>
					<l>for me a new book that 1 was preparing: Five Little</l>
					<l>Greek Dialogues. I made use also of his learned and</l>
					<l>difficult penmanship for a transcription of my Letters to</l>
					<l>a Known, in which I resumed my adventure with Liane.</l>
					<l>This work finished, I removed the ring that she had</l>
					<l>ordered for me at Lalique, and which carried, engraved</l>
					<l>on the inside: &quot;It pleases me so much that you endure to</l>
					<l>understand and love me.</l>
					<l>Renée wrote two versions of our novel lived: A</l>
					<l>Woman Appeared to Me. Influenced by the bad taste of</l>
					<l>our &quot;belle epoque, she gave me the impression of</l>
					<l>ceding to the worst weaknesses of the “art nouveau.</l>
					<l>This poet hardly possesses the gift of a novelist and</l>
					<l>cannot, consequently, lend life either to the one or to</l>
					<l>the other of her heroines.</l>
					<l>The first version, Vally, was composed when we were</l>
					<l>entangled, and the second when she restored to me the</l>
					<l>name &quot;Lorely.</l>
					<l>Vally and Lorely have the same undulating body and</l>
					<l>similar eyes “of ice under hair like moonlight.</l>
					<l>The author doubtless wished to create an impression</l>
					<l>of magic, but the magic refused to operate and it was</l>
					<l>absurdity that replaced it. To give weight to this</l>
					<l>afflicting affirmation, I pick this detail of a decor that</l>
					<l>she must have believed bewitching: A dried-out ser¬</l>
					<l>pent entwined itself around a vase wherein some black</l>
					<l>irises withered.&quot; While “dressed in a white robe that</l>
					<l>veiled me while revealing me, 1 unstrung some opals,</l>
					<l>plucked petals from some orchids...</l>
					<l>I should reproach Renée for the first of these fatal and</l>
					<l>artificial women made to resemble me, for in her second</l>
					<l>novel, from the mouth of this heroine, she makes me</l>
					<l>say, &quot;In truth, each being becomes parallel to the</l>
					<l>appearance that our perversity forms of her: fear, by</l>
					<l>force of not comprehending me, to render me incompre¬</l>
					<l>hensible.&quot; In one of these books, she declares me &quot;inca¬</l>
					<l>pable of loving. I who have never been capable of</l>
					<l>anything but that! Opposing my love of love against her</l>
					<l>love of death, Renée esteems that I have had, by access</l>
					<l>only, to submit to this evil of the nineteenth century,</l>
					<l>spleen, while she herself has made it the leitmotif of</l>
					<l>her life and her work.</l>
					<l>That she had wished to go astray to such a point in</l>
					<l>suffering, proves to me how much her poetic genius had</l>
					<l>need of it.</l>
					<l>Throughout the false mysticism by which she seems</l>
					<l>haunted, in a flash of lucidity she recognizes in me a</l>
					<l>reposing pagan soul. She recounts, in A Woman</l>
					<l>Appeared to Me, that I asked her on the day preceding</l>
					<l>Christmas, “What is this festival of Christmas? Does it</l>
					<l>commemorate the birth or the death of Christ?” Exag¬</l>
					<l>geration for exaggeration, I prefer that to other dis¬</l>
					<l>tortions.</l>
					<l>On rereading these two novels, I have the painful</l>
					<l>impression of having posed for a bad portraitist.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='70'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Barney relates next how she and Vivien traveled to</l>
					<l>New York and to the Barney home in Bar Harbor after</l>
					<l>the death of their friend Violette. Renee was deeply</l>
					<l>depressed. She continued her study of classical Greek</l>
					<l>with the hope of translating Sappho, while Barney</l>
					<l>attended dinners and balls at the will of her parents.</l>
					<l>After a visit to Bryn Mawr College, the two sepa¬</l>
					<l>rated in tears—Vivien to return to Europe and Barney to</l>
					<l>go to her parents home in Washington, D.C., for she</l>
					<l>had promised to spend the winter with them.</l>
					<l>I wrote in vain to Renée who, according to Mary S.,</l>
					<l>had just installed herself in the large apartment on the</l>
					<l>ground floor and not in the little apartment planned and</l>
					<l>prepared at great expense by our governess. Mary S.</l>
					<l>saw her only in passing, so greatly busy was Renée with</l>
					<l>furnishing it in an original manner.</l>
					<l>Was it this moving which prevented Renée from</l>
					<l>answering my letters? Or was it her book Evocations</l>
					<l>which had just appeared and which she had sent to me?</l>
					<l>Uneasy, I tried to understand through this book what</l>
					<l>could have provoked her silence: sometimes, reassured</l>
					<l>by her poems &quot;for Atthis&quot;—Atthis being one of the little</l>
					<l>names that she had given me—but surprised at being</l>
					<l>evoked in the past tense:</l>
					<l>For 1 remember divine expectations,</l>
					<l>The shadow, and the feverish evenings of yesterday...</l>
					<l>Amidst sighs and ardent tears,</l>
					<l>Iloved you, Atthis.</l>
					<l>Several descriptive stanzas followed preceding this</l>
					<l>finale:</l>
					<l>Here is what breathes and mounts with the flame,</l>
					<l>And the flight of songs and the breath of lilies,</l>
					<l>The intimate sob of the soul of my soul:</l>
					<l>Iloved you, Atthis.</l>
					<l>What is it that prevented a like feeling for living? I</l>
					<l>chafed with impatience and apprehension, attached to</l>
					<l>my duty of worldly frivolities without personal</l>
					<l>resources to escape. Finally, in the springtime, Ireturned</l>
					<l>to Paris with my family. Before even going up to my</l>
					<l>room in the Hotel D’Albe, I precipitated myself to</l>
					<l>Avenue du Bois, where the concierge informed me that</l>
					<l>Mademoiselle went out just a moment ago.</l>
					<l>I waited in the courtyard of Number 23. My heart</l>
					<l>beating, I perceived her finally arriving in an automo¬</l>
					<l>bile and ran before it, when she gave the order to her</l>
					<l>chauffeur to go out again by the court at the end</l>
					<l>without stopping. Was it possible that she had not seen</l>
					<l>me? Or that she did not wish to see me? With a leap, I</l>
					<l>went to Violette’s sister’s house. Mary received me</l>
					<l>gently, but could not or would not inform me on this</l>
					<l>mystery. I spent some hours near her, in the hope that</l>
					<l>Renée would come up unexpectedly, and from this</l>
					<l>apartment situated just above that of Renée, I spied her</l>
					<l>apparition in the little garden. Fearing that the perfidi¬</l>
					<l>ous governess had intercepted the letter in which 1</l>
					<l>announced my coming, I wished to have my heart clear</l>
					<l>about it and I had it, in fact, that same evening. Renee</l>
					<l>descended into her little garden accompanied by é</l>
					<l>sturdy person. The manner in which this person sur¬</l>
					<l>rounded her with her arm left no ambiguity about their</l>
					<l>intimacy. She had then conquered Renée, but how?</l>
					<l>Certainly not by her physical appearance. Perhaps,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>under all that fat had she not only the authoritarian</l>
					<l>visage of a Valkyrie but a heart of gold? Renée had</l>
					<l>never aspired to all the useless luxury with which the</l>
					<l>new chosen one was surrounding her, her personal for¬</l>
					<l>tune having always more than sufficed for her needs.</l>
					<l>Who then could profit from this prodigality, if not our</l>
					<l>astute governess?</l>
					<l>I prayed my friend Emma Calve—who suffered</l>
					<l>equally from an abandonment and whom 1 had sought</l>
					<l>to comfort at the time of her triumphal tour in Carmen</l>
					<l>in the United States—to lend me her irresistible voice</l>
					<l>and when night came, we disguised ourselves as street</l>
					<l>singers. She sang under the French windows of Renee</l>
					<l>Vivien: &quot;I have lost my Eurydice, nothing can match</l>
					<l>my sorrow, while 1 pretended to pick up the pieces of</l>
					<l>money thrown from the other floors. Finally, Renée</l>
					<l>partly opened her glass door to better listen to this sur¬</l>
					<l>prising voice which was attacking the celebrated aria:</l>
					<l>Love is the child of Bohemia which has never known</l>
					<l>law. The moment having come, 1 threw my poem</l>
					<l>attached to a bouquet over the gate of the garden, so</l>
					<l>that she could see and pick it up. But as some passers¬</l>
					<l>by began to surround us, we had to eclipse ourselves in</l>
					<l>the shadow before my chanteuse, recognized in the</l>
					<l>shadow thanks to her voice, was pursued by applause.</l>
					<l>I soon received a reply to my sonnet from the govern¬</l>
					<l>ess, and not from Renée as I had hoped. Having col¬</l>
					<l>lected verses and bouquets “destined to a person whom</l>
					<l>she had the good fortune to have in charge, the govern¬</l>
					<l>ess “prayed me to cease these dispatches, as distressing</l>
					<l>as they are useless.</l>
					<l>If it is true that sentiments are not commanded on</l>
					<l>order, it is even more true that they are not counter¬</l>
					<l>manded! My rage having no equal but my anguish.</l>
					<l>sent an S.O.S. to Eva, who arrived at once to be near</l>
					<l>me. Horrified to find me in such a state of despair, she</l>
					<l>went to plead my cause with Renée, who refused to see</l>
					<l>*A childhood friend of Natalie’s, probably her first lover.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='71'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>me again. Her existence (&quot;since it is, it appears, neces¬</l>
					<l>sary to live”) must suit her so according to all appear¬</l>
					<l>ances, for she knew me bound to her flight and obsessed</l>
					<l>by her verses, while she, inspired by my memory, had</l>
					<l>no further need to be troubled by my presence.</l>
					<l>I learned then the machinations of our governess.</l>
					<l>Abusing the credulous jealousy of Renée, she had per¬</l>
					<l>suaded her—with proofs to give it weight—that one of</l>
					<l>my suitors, the Count de la Palisse, had gone to the</l>
					<l>United States for the unique purpose of marrying me.</l>
					<l>How had Renée been able to believe such an absurdity?</l>
					<l>Perhaps because she violently repulsed the least advance</l>
					<l>of her suitors she understood nothing of my complai¬</l>
					<l>sances, and more, that the company of intelligent men</l>
					<l>interested and pleased me often more than that of a</l>
					<l>pretty woman? In general, I remained the fraternal</l>
					<l>friend of men. Why, besides, this “angry opposition&apos;</l>
					<l>between Sodom and Gomorrah, instead of a sympathy</l>
					<l>without equivocation?</l>
					<l>Balanced and sociable, I could not foresee the unrea¬</l>
					<l>sonable changes of Renée, and I remained profoundly</l>
					<l>afflicted by them.</l>
					<l>The crude ruse of our governess had moreover suc¬</l>
					<l>ceeded in throwing the poor and unhappy Renée into</l>
					<l>the arms of another! By what intrigues or what chance</l>
					<l>had those arms proved to be those of one of the richest</l>
					<l>women of the Israelite world? This strong and willful</l>
					<l>person was not only known for her prejudiced tastes,</l>
					<l>but for endowing her successive mistresses with a</l>
					<l>sumptuous dwelling and a life annuity. This prodigality</l>
					<l>did not explain to me why Renée, who already had a</l>
					<l>considerable fortune, had fallen into this gilded trap.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Our governess, after expensively furnishing the little</l>
					<l>apartment chosen and abandoned, had presided over</l>
					<l>the luxurious fitting-out of this large ground floor where</l>
					<l>all passed through her intervention, which did not</l>
					<l>prevent her from touching some wages as watch dog of</l>
					<l>the captive. A voluntary captive perhaps and one who,</l>
					<l>after the death of Violette and the lies adroitly accumu¬</l>
					<l>lated against me, had immense need of quiet and</l>
					<l>security.</l>
					<l>It was then that I received a dispatch from an</l>
					<l>Austrian princess, with whom Eva and I were connected.</l>
					<l>She alerted me that she had just arrived alone at Bay¬</l>
					<l>reuth. We departed then for the Wagnerian Festival,</l>
					<l>where we were able to procure two seats, thanks to</l>
					<l>connections of the princess. From the first presentation</l>
					<l>of the Tetralogy, I spotted Renée and contemplated her</l>
					<l>from our balcony. Eva went down right away to tell her</l>
					<l>that I was waiting for her up above. Renée, giving her</l>
					<l>place to Eva, came to sit beside me. Both being invaded</l>
					<l>by this music, our eyes, then our hands met in the</l>
					<l>shadow, and we found ourselves so again each evening.</l>
					<l>On telling me farewell she promised me, tears in her</l>
					<l>eyes, to arrange to find me again before the end of this</l>
					<l>same month of August. Our rendezvous was set at</l>
					<l>Vienna, from where we would continue the trip together</l>
					<l>on the Orient Express toward Mytilene, by way of</l>
					<l>Constantinople.</l>
					<l>This time she kept her word and I found her again</l>
					<l>with an unbounded exaltation but I had to hold back,</l>
					<l>for she remained on the defensive. However, she identi¬</l>
					<l>fied me with her cult for Lesbos, in writing:</l>
					<l>Sweetness of my songs, let us go toward Mytilene.</l>
					<l>Here is where my soul has taken its flight.</l>
					<l>Let us go toward the welcome of the adored virgins.</l>
					<l>Our eyes will know the tears of returnings;</l>
					<l>We shall see at last fade away the countries</l>
					<l>Of the lifeless loves.</l>
					<l>How important to her was this decor! But then I</l>
					<l>would have been content to be with her no matter</l>
					<l>where, away from the world, on condition that I found</l>
					<l>her there completely.</l>
					<l>Thus I was less disappointed than she in perceiving</l>
					<l>that isle that Countess Sabini had described to us as</l>
					<l>having &quot;the shape of a lyre spread on the sea. At the</l>
					<l>approach to Mytilene we heard a phonograph from the</l>
					<l>port nasalizing, “Come poupoule, come poupoule,</l>
					<l>come.&quot; Renée, who had been waiting since dawn on the</l>
					<l>bridge, paled with horror. When we trod that dust con¬</l>
					<l>secrated by the sandals of Sappho and her poetesses we</l>
					<l>regained awareness of our pilgrimage, despite the</l>
					<l>modern eruptions.</l>
					<l>I kept myself from remarking to her that at Lesbos,</l>
					<l>far from encountering the Greek type of the beautiful</l>
					<l>companions of Sappho, we saw not a single woman of</l>
					<l>that lineage, but only some handsome stevedores, fisher¬</l>
					<l>men and shepherds. The remainder of the population</l>
					<l>had their traits as bastardized as their language, in</l>
					<l>which Renée found no longer the accent of classic</l>
					<l>Greek.</l>
					<l>But the little rustic hotel which received us kept an</l>
					<l>ancient simplicity, with its water pots of baked clay and</l>
					<l>its good cooking in olive oil, served by an old domestic</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='72'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>who had her head encircled by a band and was followed</l>
					<l>by a bald dog without age.</l>
					<l>The nights were more beautiful than all those we had</l>
					<l>known, and from the first, what a cry of victory l had to</l>
					<l>stifle!</l>
					<l>Receive into your orchards a feminine couple,</l>
					<l>Isle melodious and friendly to caresses..</l>
					<l>Amidst the Asiatic odor of heavy jasmine,</l>
					<l>You have not at all forgotten Sappho nor her Mistresses...</l>
					<l>Isle melodious and friendly to caresses,</l>
					<l>Receive in your orchards a feminine couple...</l>
					<l>The next day the entire island offered itself to us like</l>
					<l>an open bed. Spread out in the sun on some wide banks</l>
					<l>of soft algae, breathing the salt air, we continued to</l>
					<l>dream on this murmuring shore of the Aegean Sea.</l>
					<l>Renee, in her poem on Mytilene, describes it :</l>
					<l>When disposing their bodies on beds of dry algae</l>
					<l>The lovers fling tired and broken words,</l>
					<l>You mingled your odors of roses and peaches</l>
					<l>With the long whisperings that follow kisses..</l>
					<l>In our turn tossing words tired and broken,</l>
					<l>We dispose our bodies on your beds of dry algae...</l>
					<l>Without the community of Orientals installed in their</l>
					<l>summer villas, we would have been able to believe our-</l>
					<l>selves in the fifth century B.C. Renée acquired some</l>
					<l>medals of that epoch, struck in the image of Sappho.</l>
					<l>In the enchantment of this sojourn, without messen¬</l>
					<l>ger and without other souvenir, we rented two little</l>
					<l>villas joined by the same orchard, for Renée had</l>
					<l>resolved to never leave Mytilene. She would wait for me</l>
					<l>&quot;faithfully and without budging&quot; if, later, I had business</l>
					<l>elsewhere.</l>
					<l>&quot;I have yet less business elsewhere than you,</l>
					<l>replied imprudently, for this reminder made her con¬</l>
					<l>tract her fine eyebrows. I then came up with an idea 1</l>
					<l>knew worthy of pleasing her: &quot;Why shouldn’t we form</l>
					<l>here that school of poetry so dreamed of where those</l>
					<l>who vibrate with poetry, youth and love would come</l>
					<l>to us, such as those poets of yesterday arriving from all</l>
					<l>parts to surround Sappho?</l>
					<l>Renée was in fact seduced by that perspective.</l>
					<l>Installed in the larger of the two villas, she worked</l>
					<l>again on her translation of Sappho, which was nearly</l>
					<l>finished.</l>
					<l>But Atthis, where is she?&quot; I said.</l>
					<l>Atthis is present here, she replied, taking out of her</l>
					<l>bag Five Little Greek Dialogues and also the manuscript</l>
					<l>of Je me Souviens that I had sent to her at Bayreuth.</l>
					<l>This manuscript had neighbored with her cold cream</l>
					<l>and carried the trace of it on the parchment of the cover.</l>
					<l>Before it gets damaged more, it is necessary that we</l>
					<l>publish it.</l>
					<l>&quot;Iwrote it for you alone</l>
					<l>Also, you see, it has not left me.</l>
					<l>Opening my little book of Dialogues, I saw that she</l>
					<l>had underlined there certain passages concerning</l>
					<l>Sappho and, intrigued, I reread:</l>
					<l>Do you believe that she was so irresistible as they</l>
					<l>have said?</l>
					<l>&quot;She was irresistible as all those who have followed</l>
					<l>their nature. She is as all those who have dared to live.</l>
					<l>She is as irresistible as Destiny itself.</l>
					<l>&quot;Why did she truly love only women?&quot;</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>&quot;Because only women are complex enough to attract</l>
					<l>her and fleeting enough to hold her. They alone know</l>
					<l>how to give her all the ecstasies and all the torments....</l>
					<l>It is in ourselves that we lose ourselves and in others</l>
					<l>that we find ourselves again. I believe her more faithful</l>
					<l>in her inconstancy than the others in their constant</l>
					<l>fidelity.</l>
					<l>Leaning on my shoulder to read the text with me,</l>
					<l>Renée murmured in my ear:</l>
					<l>&quot;That Sappho there, she is you.</l>
					<l>&quot;That which describes one is not what one is, but that</l>
					<l>which one would wish to be.</l>
					<l>That which we shall become, and so that ’someone</l>
					<l>in the future will remember us.</l>
					<l>&quot;Thanks to your translation of Sappho and also to</l>
					<l>that of her poetesses, I shall write a play for which I</l>
					<l>have already determined the plot and which will destroy</l>
					<l>the myth of Phaon, for Sappho will die in it as she</l>
					<l>ought: because the most beloved of her friends will have</l>
					<l>betrayed her.</l>
					<l>&quot;Do not speak of betrayal nor of mourning ’in the</l>
					<l>house of the poet where mourning does not enter.</l>
					<l>We knew that at the hotel our mail waited for us.</l>
					<l>Avoid it? But then where spend the night? From our</l>
					<l>entry into the hotel, a parrot greeted us with a strident</l>
					<l>and mocking voice, and the concierge, taking our</l>
					<l>names, handed us our mail. Throw it in the sea without</l>
					<l>even taking cognizance of it? But then, uneasy at our</l>
					<l>silence, would they not come to disturb us? Would it</l>
					<l>not be better to open it and perhaps respond to it? A</l>
					<l>letter from Renée’s friend announced her desire to visit</l>
					<l>this celebrated island and make to rendezvous shortly at</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='73'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Constantinople. Renée had only time to send her a tele¬</l>
					<l>gram to prevent her from taking the Orient Express,</l>
					<l>advising her that she was already on the return route.</l>
					<l>Was it not more loyal to have her learn in person of</l>
					<l>Renée’s intention of breaking with her than to give her</l>
					<l>the shock of such a decision in a telegram which, at any</l>
					<l>rate, would not stop her? She was of those who will not</l>
					<l>let loose or be deceived without struggle. She would</l>
					<l>arrive, therefore, and then what scenes would we have</l>
					<l>to undergo? I suggested hiding ourselves &quot;no matter</l>
					<l>where away from the world.</l>
					<l>&quot;She would alert the consulate, the secret police of the</l>
					<l>entire world. Her power, like her fortune, is unlimited</l>
					<l>and even if you went away and 1 let her come, instead of</l>
					<l>tiring of such a life, she would clamp onto it. If she sus</l>
					<l>pected anything she would install herself in your place.</l>
					<l>And that, I would not endure.</l>
					<l>It was necessary then to leave in order to return to</l>
					<l>living in peace and to developing without fear or con¬</l>
					<l>straint our beautiful project. But meanwhile, from the</l>
					<l>next day, we had to resign ourselves to once again</l>
					<l>taking the boat which had brought us.</l>
					<l>Like so many other lovers, we still had those &quot;bad</l>
					<l>farewells from which one returns” and those recoveries</l>
					<l>exultant and without duration.</l>
					<l>Unattached, then irresistibly attracted one toward the</l>
					<l>other only to lose each other anew, our persistent love</l>
					<l>underwent all the phases of a mortal attachment that</l>
					<l>perhaps death alone would be able to conclude.</l>
					<l>I always loved Renée but with a vanquished love,</l>
					<l>enslaved by the circumstances that she had permitted to</l>
					<l>get the better of us:</l>
					<l>Your clear gaze troubles and confuses me..</l>
					<l>Yes, I know it, 1 was wrong in many circumstances,</l>
					<l>And very piteously, I blush before you,</l>
					<l>But everywhere sorrow has hemmed me in and pursued me.</l>
					<l>Do not blame me anymore then! rather console me</l>
					<l>For having so badly lived my lamentable life.</l>
					<l>Thanks to that “lamentable life,&quot; and to the happiness</l>
					<l>that she lacked, she has become what she has always</l>
					<l>wished to be: a great poet.</l>
					<l>In reading, “La Venus des Aveugles&quot; and “Aux Heures</l>
					<l>des mains jointes” I found how much these verses had</l>
					<l>strengthened. They no longer dragged “perfumed pal¬</l>
					<l>lors and other mawkishness. They were no longer</l>
					<l>languid but heavy with lived images, reflecting the</l>
					<l>cruelty of an existence undergone at first not withous</l>
					<l>revolt, then with resignation and grandeur.</l>
					<l>My verses have not attained calm excellence,</l>
					<l>I have understood it, and no one will read them ever...</l>
					<l>There remain to me the moon and near silence,</l>
					<l>And the lilies, and especially the woman that I loved...</l>
					<l>My hands keep the odor of beautiful hair</l>
					<l>Let them bury me with my souvenirs, as</l>
					<l>They buried with queens, their jewels...</l>
					<l>I shall carry there my joy and my worry...</l>
					<l>Isis, I have prepared the funeral barque</l>
					<l>Which they have filled with flowers spices and nard,</l>
					<l>And whose sail floats in folds of shrouds</l>
					<l>The ritual rowers are ready... It is growing late...</l>
					<l>Increasingly appreciated in numerous milieus, Renée</l>
					<l>consented to unite her admirers and friends around her,</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>and we assisted at some very strange soirees where 1</l>
					<l>found Colette, Moreno, the Ernest Charles, the Lesdrain</l>
					<l>and our old Professor, assiduous and rejuvenated¬</l>
					<l>without our governess, who some time ago had been</l>
					<l>thanked for her diverse offices. At these reunions I was</l>
					<l>accompanied by an actress with golden eyes, brown</l>
					<l>hair and a difficult character, whose presence dissipated</l>
					<l>all suspicion for Renée’s friend—who did not appear at</l>
					<l>any of these fetes, but had herself informed on all that</l>
					<l>happened there.</l>
					<l>One evening when I found myself at Renée’s she</l>
					<l>announced to me that her friend, who had no more</l>
					<l>uneasiness about us, had a wish to meet me and would</l>
					<l>come to dine with us. 1 manifested the intention to flee,</l>
					<l>but Renée begged me to stay. Her friend would interpret</l>
					<l>my refusal badly. She arrived promptly, arrayed in an</l>
					<l>evening gown that she had ordered from Laferriere, a</l>
					<l>dress which I had to admire. Since this meeting would</l>
					<l>facilitate Renée’s life, I had no choice but to resign</l>
					<l>myself to it.</l>
					<l>While waiting to find myself face to face with my</l>
					<l>rival—she whom the Princess H. disrespectfully named</l>
					<l>’the blunder&quot;—I asked Renée why she evidently</l>
					<l>attached so much importance to questions of costume</l>
					<l>where it concerned her friend, while she accorded them</l>
					<l>so little when they concerned herself?</l>
					<l>I like better to leave that bore to others and to orna¬</l>
					<l>ment only my dwelling, she had told me, adding,</l>
					<l>hate the fittings and have not enough personality to</l>
					<l>triumph over them. I did however wish to be party to it</l>
					<l>by ordering a dress at one of the great couturieres, and</l>
					<l>went, before the appointed time for the fitting, to wait</l>
					<l>in a corner of the big salon till someone came to</l>
					<l>announce my turn. Having taken along a good book to</l>
					<l>keep me company, 1 read it without paying attention to</l>
					<l>what was going on around me. But when the evening</l>
					<l>obliged me to lift my head toward the light that they</l>
					<l>had just lit, I closed my book and got ready to go. My</l>
					<l>saleswoman, panic-stricken, tried to stop me. I replied</l>
					<l>to her, too happy to have an excellent pretext, and</l>
					<l>despite her excuses, ’that a similar inadvertence arrived</l>
					<l>only to the most patient...to the best clients....</l>
					<l>Resolute, 1 got out the door, assuring her, with a smile,</l>
					<l>that I would never return....</l>
					<l>When that opulent person entered, her hand extended,</l>
					<l>I remarked how that blue robe covered with little</l>
					<l>islands cut into a cloth of silver, surrounded with dia¬</l>
					<l>monds, seemed to evoke the islands of the Aegean Sea¬</l>
					<l>an allusion at which we all smiled differently. After</l>
					<l>the dinner, the Chinese butler brought Renée tea,</l>
					<l>which in place of drinking she threw with saucer, cup</l>
					<l>and spoon into the fireplace burning before us. Ithought</l>
					<l>in spite of myself of her prayer: “Who then will bring</l>
					<l>me the hemlock in his hands?</l>
					<l>Did she throw that cup because it contained or did</l>
					<l>not contain the hemlock? Or because she judged this</l>
					<l>remedy derisory of her pain?</l>
					<l>An instant interrupted by the violent nervousness of</l>
					<l>her gesture, we took up again a conversation on horses,</l>
					<l>whereon her friend and I had found a ground for under-</l>
					<l>standing. She explained to me that a neighbor had pro¬</l>
					<l>posed to buy from her a grey dappled horse of a breed</l>
					<l>that her stable was the only one to possess and which</l>
					<l>would match so well with one which the buyer already</l>
					<l>owned. Ought she to accept? She was hesitating, for to</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='74'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>sell one of her horses pained her as much as the offer</l>
					<l>flattered her. On this, the hour to withdraw having</l>
					<l>sounded, she offered to drive me back. With a glance,</l>
					<l>Renée prayed me to accept. We left then together</l>
					<l>through the Bois as far as my pavilion, where she</l>
					<l>wished to enter with me. 1 excused myself, making pre¬</l>
					<l>text of an unsupportable headache (a malady that I have</l>
					<l>never in my life felt). She could only leave with a look</l>
					<l>of reproach.</l>
					<l>Some time after that evening—in the course of which</l>
					<l>she had tried in vain to teach me to smoke—the lady</l>
					<l>sent me a little cigarette case in enamel filled with tiny</l>
					<l>cigarettes, under the cover of which she had had</l>
					<l>engraved: “Always to the extreme, is it not, Mademoi¬</l>
					<l>selle?&quot; Since I had done nothing to encourage the</l>
					<l>sending of this unusable gift—unless it was to ironically</l>
					<l>admire her dress—I supposed her on the look-out for</l>
					<l>adventure. I learned very soon after that the neighbor</l>
					<l>who had offered to buy her horse had made the bet</l>
					<l>before several persons of which she who reported the</l>
					<l>wager to me said, “Not only to possess this horse, but</l>
					<l>the owner along with. I right away advised Renée of</l>
					<l>this who, after having made her own investigation, had</l>
					<l>to recognize that the neighbor in question had won her</l>
					<l>bet. As she showed herself more indignant than pained</l>
					<l>by this affair, I tried to reason with her:</l>
					<l>Look, Renée, have you the right to get indignant on</l>
					<l>this point?</l>
					<l>&quot;It is as if I had consented to marry a horse-dealer and</l>
					<l>that after sacrificing myself to someone so vile, this</l>
					<l>horse-dealer dared to deceive me. I will not endure this</l>
					<l>injury.</l>
					<l>Uneasy at the excessive way in which she resented this</l>
					<l>adventure that I considered harmless, after several years</l>
					<l>of a rare fidelity on the part of her companion, I</l>
					<l>questioned our Professor, still devoted to Renée. He</l>
					<l>informed me that she had decided to break “with this</l>
					<l>banal and hypocritical life. She put this project into</l>
					<l>execution. First wrapping up her favorite knick-knack,</l>
					<l>a jade Buddha, she liquidated her bank account and</l>
					<l>took away all her money. In the train which took her to</l>
					<l>Marseilles, while looking for her ticket for the condut¬</l>
					<l>tor, she let fall a packet of bank notes in front of the</l>
					<l>other travellers. Fearing to be followed and robbed, she</l>
					<l>let herself be “picked up by the secretary of her</l>
					<l>friend—a friend who shortly following sent me a card,</l>
					<l>where I read this single word: “Judas.</l>
					<l>After this debacle and this humiliation, I do not know</l>
					<l>to what excess Renée gave herself up, without so much</l>
					<l>as renouncing her plan of voyage. She escaped anew.</l>
					<l>having this time better combined her departure with</l>
					<l>some relatives who accompanied her on a world tour.</l>
					<l>After her first stop, I received in fact a word from her,</l>
					<l>informing me that she had taken to the open sea to</l>
					<l>reflect, far from all that she had loved, on the continua¬</l>
					<l>tion that she would give to her “miserable existence.</l>
					<l>Wounded on all sides, she had already withdrawn her</l>
					<l>books from sale. Some carping critics had decided her.</l>
					<l>The aspersions, the gross attacks, through her ima¬</l>
					<l>gination, motivated three of her most beautiful poems:</l>
					<l>On the Public Place,““The Pilory, and “Vanquished.</l>
					<l>In the face of such results, I could only blame exag¬</l>
					<l>gerated sensibility and susceptibility. But I deplored</l>
					<l>that, by my insensitivity in precipitating the separation</l>
					<l>from her friend, I had added the drop of fatal bitterness.</l>
					<l>I feared for her health, already so damaged and which</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>could not tolerate the least shock or the least reproach.</l>
					<l>At the time of a visit to her house, probably just</l>
					<l>before her voyage toward the Orient, Marcelle Tinayre</l>
					<l>saw her so:</l>
					<l>She entered like a phantom. Already very ill, she wished to</l>
					<l>see me again.... Her body more fragile than formerly</l>
					<l>revealed nothing of its contours under the very simple dress of</l>
					<l>black muslin. How she has changed, alas!</l>
					<l>Always I shall re-see her, shadow in the shadow, recounting</l>
					<l>not her life, but her soul. She was speaking of the other</l>
					<l>world.... And all of a sudden, she said, “When I am so sad,</l>
					<l>so alone, so ill, I think that I would like to die Catholic. It is</l>
					<l>the sole religion where there is poetry and beauty. She added,</l>
					<l>smiling, “But no priest would permit me to keep my little</l>
					<l>Buddhist idols....</l>
					<l>How all this contrasts with the artificial Renée whom</l>
					<l>Colette presents in Ces Plaisirs!</l>
					<l>Though feeling that her despair surpassed all human</l>
					<l>aid, I wished to leave my house at Neuilly in order to</l>
					<l>wait for her return in a new place, where no bad</l>
					<l>memories had collected. I had then searched and finally</l>
					<l>found a dwelling between courtyard and garden, on rue</l>
					<l>Jacob, where I became the vestal of a little Temple of</l>
					<l>Friendship. In order to escape the moving, I rejoined</l>
					<l>that actress whom I had let depart with relief. From my</l>
					<l>arrival at Saint Petersburg, Ilearned that I was replaced:</l>
					<l>first by an attache of the French embassy, then by a</l>
					<l>Russian colonel. When I took the train again for the</l>
					<l>long return, an old diplomatic friend who had put me</l>
					<l>current with my misfortune brought me Voltaire&apos;s</l>
					<l>Candide</l>
					<l>Scarcely installed in my new dwelling, I learned that</l>
					<l>Renée was ill “of a malady traversed by agonizing crises</l>
					<l>and that she no longer wishes to see anyone. However,</l>
					<l>that same evening I went to ask news of her, a bouquet</l>
					<l>of violets in my hand. Half-opening the door, a butler</l>
					<l>that I had never seen replied: &quot;Mademoiselle just died.</l>
					<l>This announcement was made in the tone of &quot;Mademoi¬</l>
					<l>selle just went out.&quot; I had not the presence of mind to</l>
					<l>insist that someone put these violets near her. Then,</l>
					<l>staggering, I regained the Avenue du Bois and fainted</l>
					<l>on one of its first benches.</l>
					<l>When I regained consciousness, I returned home and</l>
					<l>shut myself in my bedroom. Neither able nor wishing to</l>
					<l>see her dead, it was necessary at once to make contact</l>
					<l>again with all of her that remained to me. Like a grave</l>
					<l>robber, I took hold of the precious little box that she</l>
					<l>had given me. Its key lost, I had to open it by force. It</l>
					<l>contained so many tangible souvenirs that I felt her</l>
					<l>presence wander around me. They could then no longer</l>
					<l>prevent me from rejoining her. That this haunting not</l>
					<l>abandon me! For if 1 were no longer haunted, what</l>
					<l>would remain for me? Forgetfulness. But what lover,</l>
					<l>what poet, would wish it?</l>
					<l>I replunged into all her relics: the manuscript of the</l>
					<l>poems written for me, accepting life—a vacillating</l>
					<l>life—through my tears....</l>
					<l>The day after the next, I followed her internment like</l>
					<l>a somnabulist for it was not in this tomb that I could</l>
					<l>search for her, but well elsewhere and within myself.</l>
					<l>Margaret Porter is a poet and translator who wrote for</l>
					<l>years under the name &quot;Gabrielle L&apos;’Autre. She was a founding</l>
					<l>member of Tres Femmes. The Muse of the Violets, a selection</l>
					<l>of Renee Vivien’s poetry, has been translated by her and</l>
					<l>Catharine Kroger and published by Naiad Press.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
