<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Issue4_Bovenschen10-12</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>Is There a Feminine Aesthetic?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>Silvia Bovenschen
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>This article was first published in German in Aesthetik und Kommunika-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>tion, No. 25, September 1976. We are reprinting excerpts from the article
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>transtated into English by Beth Weckmueller and originally published in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>New German Critique, No. 10, Winter 1977. Permission to reprint has been
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>granted by the Editors of New German Critique, University of Wisconsin-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>Milwaukee. German Department, P.O. Box 413, Milwaukee, Wis. 53201.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>Old and new appraisals of women’s artistic production
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>The time has come for a campaign against all the weeping and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>wailing. Even the media have got the hang of it—with their usual
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>inconsequence. Women are oppressed, exploited, degraded...
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>Although this state of affairs has hardly changed since it was first
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>articulated, to continue to proclaim it now in the artistic realm
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>seems almost pointless. But this need not necessarily be the case.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>As can be seen on closer examination, it is the tone of the lament
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>that makes it seem inadequate. The form the lament takes still
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>acknowledges its addressee. Traditionally it was women—profes-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>sional mourners—who rendered grief public, be it in regard to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>death, to suffering or to the victims of massacres; this was one of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>their rare opportunities to assume a public function. But precisely
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>for this reason it was not at all startling, indeed, no one particu-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>larly noticed, when women began publicizing and decrying their
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>own lot, that of their sisters, their female ancestors and, should
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>women’s fate not improve, the lot of future women. Clearly,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>Cassandra was not a false prophet. She was simply not heard. No
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>one paid attention to her.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>For this reason I thought it tedious to enumerate once again the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>entire battery of obstacles constructed to frighten off and exclude
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>women from the artistic realm. Yet the handicaps and the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>absences are also part of women&apos;s history, and perhaps even the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>greater part, since women did not clomp through history in com-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>bat boots, and their traces are fleeting and obscured. To be sure,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>we do not complain as much today because we have a movement
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>making demands that will change the future. Nevertheless, in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>respect to the question of a feminine aesthetic,&quot; we need to re-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>examine its traditional assessments once again, if only for the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>reason that we lack a viable conceptual basis to work from.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>Repeatedly and rightfully women have bemoaned the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>deformations of even their own cultural taste&quot;:I would ... far
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>sooner have been caught dead with Hemingway than with Virginia
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>Woolf in my hands,&quot; says Shulamith Firestone about her
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>development. The pursuit of art, often based on the search for a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>realm of sensitivity in hopes of thereby escaping the confines of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>home, may become a trap for women just as easily as other pur-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>suits. When discussing that which we associate with patriarchal
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>structures in the cultural realm, we immediately take note of a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>scandalous situation which, along with many others, was un-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l49' n='N049'/>covered long ago but still prevails. Just to refresh our memory,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l50' n='N050'/>Simone de Beauvoir established long ago that men mistake their
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l51' n='N051'/>descriptive perspective for absolute truth. The scandalous situa-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l52' n='N052'/>tion, then, is: the equation of truth with the masculine perspective,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l53' n='N053'/>that is, with everything observed, examined and portrayed from a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l54' n='N054'/>male point of view, which we were made to adopt very early in life.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l55' n='N055'/>This false equation not only predominated in the production and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l56' n='N056'/>reception of art. It also guaranteed that, despite our fervent
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l57' n='N057'/>endeavor, this sphere remained external, foreign and remote. This
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l58' n='N058'/>was but one reason for our exclusion among the many overt and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l59' n='N059'/>lucid strategies employed by men to repress us when they found
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l60' n='N060'/>that our perceptive powers had not been sufficiently blunted.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l61' n='N061'/>George Sand, Histoire de ma Vie:2
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l62' n='N062'/>Mr. de Keraty followed me into the anteroom in order to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l63' n='N063'/>debate with me, at yet greater length, his theory concerning
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l64' n='N064'/>the intellectual inferiority of women. It would be impossible
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l65' n='N065'/>for even the most intelligent woman to write a good work.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l66' n='N066'/>And as I wanted to leave then, he ended his speech with a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l67' n='N067'/>Napoleonic stroke, which was to shatter me. &quot;Believe me,&quot; he
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l68' n='N068'/>said in a weighty tone, as I was about to open the last door of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l69' n='N069'/>his sanctuary, &quot;bring children into the world instead of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l70' n='N070'/>10
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>books!&quot; &quot;My dear &quot; I answered, thinking I would choke on
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>my laughter and slamming the door shut in his face, &quot;follow
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>your advice yourself, as well as you can!&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>The classic notions about women&apos;s artistic competence are all
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>too familiar. Though she is the great theme of art, woman as em-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>pirical being is acceptable only by virtue of her supposed inspir-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>ational powers. In an Amazon society there could be neither
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>culture nor history nor art, since art is not essential to woman.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>We know today, though only because we bothered to look into the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>matter ourselves, that it is not difficult to prove that such state-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>ments are historically incorrect. They show (and help justify) that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>the masculine realm of artistic production, and often the artistic
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>products themselves, are not only inaccessible to women, but are
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>also fundamentally foreign to us.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>Critics have always regarded the female producers of literature,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>art and music, few and far between as they are, as exotic aber-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>rations. From a purely quantitative point of view, this indeed was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>and still is the case, although we have yet to rediscover the many
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>women artists who were consciously forgotten.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>To be sure, women&apos;s representation in the arts is a rarity. And
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>even this rarity is always measured in terms of production norms
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>within the established framework defining the division of artistic
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>labor, a framework which does not encompass forms of social
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>creativity. And when a few works do manage to find their way to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>the public despite all obstacles placed in their path, they tend to be
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>viewed in the following manner: Though women may have ac-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>complished some rather nice and enjoyable things now and then,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>all the major innovative achievements have nonetheless remained
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>the exclusive territory of the great masters of the pen, the brush or
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>the keyboard. (Thus any mounting anxiety can be quickly and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>easily quelled.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>But now there is a threat from the other front: the theoretician
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>of equality. Today the line of argument emphasizing equality
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>belongs to the repertoire of the man who moves in  progressive&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>circles. He says that since they can no longer be kept completely
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>ignorant, women should at least turn out to be what men already
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>are. One need only open the floodgates, and women will stream in-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>to the spheres dominated by men. But what if we no longer view
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>the difference as deficiency, loss, self-effacement and deprivation,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>but rather as opportunity? Around the turn of the century, the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>statement &quot; We women can do just as much as men&apos; served as a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>beckoning light. Today it is no longer so terribly impressive. Of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>course we could do just as much. The question is, do we want to do
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>just as much as men, or the same thing as men? Here we have
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>come full circle. So it would seem.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>Chantal Akerman, Interview in Frauen und Film (Women
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>and Film):
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>If women imitate men&apos;s battles they will become weaker and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>weaker. They must find new forms of struggle. This became
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>evident in Hendave where women demonstrated against the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>death sentence in Spain. Some women shouted and clenched
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>their fists, while others just hummed. They went &quot;mmmm-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l53' n='N053'/>mmm&quot; with their lips pressed together, and moved forward
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l54' n='N054'/>in a row. That is a new way of demonstrating which can be a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l55' n='N055'/>hundred times stronger than fists. We have had a virtual in-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l56' n='N056'/>flation of shouting with raised fists, and I, for one, simply
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l57' n='N057'/>walk by when I hear it. In film and in the arts we must also
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l58' n='N058'/>find a language which is appropriate to us, one which is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l59' n='N059'/>neither black nor white.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l60' n='N060'/>Art has been primarily produced by men. Men have dominated
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l61' n='N061'/>the neatly segregated public sector that controls it, and men have
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l62' n='N062'/>defined the normative standards for evaluation. Moreover, insofar
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l63' n='N063'/>as they came into contact with this sector at all, women have for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l64' n='N064'/>the most part acquiesced to its value system. These realizations led
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l65' n='N065'/>Firestone to the conclusion that &quot;It would take a denial of all
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l66' n='N066'/>cultural tradition for women to produce even a true female&apos; art.&apos;&apos;5
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l67' n='N067'/>Such a statement is easily made. Indeed, aesthetic norms and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l68' n='N068'/>cultural standards have meaning only in their sublation. But those
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l69' n='N069'/>standards and those norms were not even our own. What is the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l70' n='N070'/>ground that we are working? From where does a feminine&apos; art
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l71' n='N071'/>get its identity? Or does it not need to do that? Is art, then, still art
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>in the traditional sense, no matter how far it has gone to the dogs?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>Isfeminine&apos; a criterion of substance, an ontological entity?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>Let us then radically negate all the masculine cultural achieve-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>ments and begin anew at the point where we once left off, tilling
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>the soil as our female ancestors did before the great male putsch.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>That is not very funny, even as a powder room joke. Perhaps we
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>would enjoy that—linking ourselves directly to bygone power, but
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>we should be wary of construing a direct connection where none
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>exists. Making such a connection can raise false hopes of finding
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>help.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>Call as often as we might to the old mother goddesses—Aphro-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>dite, Demeter, Diana and all the rest of those Amazons of long lost
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>female empires—their power cannot reach this far, for their em-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>pires have been extinguished. Only the important consciousness
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>that things were once different eases our burden a bit. To be sure,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>it is very important that we reappropriate moments of female
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>potential from past cultures which have been silenced in organized
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>fashion by male history. And the work to be done in this area is im-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>mense. (I emphasize this to avoid any misunderstanding.) But any
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>attempt to link them directly to our experiences in the twentieth
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>century will be unsuccessful. And if we nonetheless force a direct
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>connection, the results will be downright pitiful. We will be left
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>with parsley as a method of inducing abortion, and here and there
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>a herbal home remedy.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>The desire to tailor a positive (female) counterpart to the world
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>that was constructed and interpreted by men is not satisfied in this
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>manner. Let us rather quote the women of the past as we wish,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>without being pressured into retroactively fabricating continuity.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>On the other hand, though, a historical archeology in search of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>women past and forgotten, their obscured activities, living condi-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>tions and forms of resistance, is not just nostalgia. The hidden
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>story of women, which reveals itself to us as primarily one of suf-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>fering and subjugation (now here is continuity!), is the dark side of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>cultural history—or better: the dark side of its idealized version.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>Women artists waît through history as mere shadows, separated
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>from each other. Since their deeds remained for the most part
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>without effect and their creations were, with rare exception, ab-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>sorbed into the masculine tradition, it is not possible to retro-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>spectively construct an independent countertradition. Only female
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>martyrs are not in short supply. All of this would certainly seem to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>be grounds enough for avoiding even the most trifling involvement
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>with the problems of art and cultural history.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>But the Great Refusal is not the solution either. To believe that
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>feminine spontaneity need be creative in every case is to fail to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>recognize the powerful effect that cultural and historical deforma-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>tion also had on the subjectivity of women, as mentioned by
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>Firestone. Can women just be women,&quot; reduced to some elemen-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>tal Being? We are in a terrible bind. How do we speak? In what
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l49' n='N049'/>categories do we think? Is even logic a bit of virile trickery? Or to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l50' n='N050'/>put it even more heretically, how do we feel? Are our desires and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l51' n='N051'/>notions of happiness so far removed from cultural traditions and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l52' n='N052'/>models? Feminism cannot ultimately imply that we are to stop
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l53' n='N053'/>thinking, feeling, longing. No one ever claimed that. On the con-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l54' n='N054'/>trary, we are consciously just beginning to do these things. No
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l55' n='N055'/>doubt, we have always done these things differently than men.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l56' n='N056'/>(We are dealing with a sort of double exposure here.) But the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l57' n='N057'/>means of expression most readily available to us for communica-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l58' n='N058'/>ting our perceptions, our thought processes—language, forms, im-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l59' n='N059'/>ages—are for the most part not originally our own, not of our own
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l60' n='N060'/>choosing. Here we are still at the beginning. Sensitivity to the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l61' n='N061'/>patriarchal structures common to language usage“ is certainly a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l62' n='N062'/>step in this direction.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l63' n='N063'/>Lucy Lippard: &quot;Why a separate women&apos;s art?&quot;?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l64' n='N064'/>What seems to be most important in this whole matter is that
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l65' n='N065'/>we focus our eyes and our feelings upon the flashes of insight
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l66' n='N066'/>which our feminine sensitivity affords us.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l67' n='N067'/>Frieda Grafe, in Filmkritik:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l68' n='N068'/>Language, the medium of my work, is for me already so
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l69' n='N069'/>generalized and mute that I cannot strive for even further
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l70' n='N070'/>generalities. Instead, I direct all my energies toward making
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l71' n='N071'/>the wall of generalities so thin that something will be able to
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>break through the barrier, something can come from within
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>my body and enter the overarticulated linguistic sphere.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>want to show the generative base of language before it
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>atrophies in communicable form.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>We ought to rid ourselves of the notion of a historically ever-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>present female counterculture. And yet, on the other hand, the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>very different way in which women experience things, their very
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>different experiences themselves, enable us to anticipate different
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>imaginations and means of expression.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>No matter which tack I take, I am left with the frustrations and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>difficulties inherent in positive definitions.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>The pre-aesthetie realms
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>Even in the past, I contend, the exclusion of women from the ar-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>tistic realm could not extinguish all their aesthetic needs. These
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>creative impulses, however, were shunted off into the &quot;pre-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>aesthetic&apos; realms, where they evaporated under the strain of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>women&apos;s daily routine. Women furnished the living quarters, set
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>the tables, arranged, decorated and adorned their clothing and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>above all themselves.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>That was allowed, as long as it was being done to please the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>man. These activities quickly corrupted women. They set the table
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>for the man, they dressed and adorned themselves for the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>man—not for themselves or for each other, but rather in compe-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>tition with each other. They busied themselves weaving and knit-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>ting, but such functional artworks, handicrafts and decorations
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>have always been considered inferior, commonplace. This verdict
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>is of course not entirely unfair, especially in those cases where even
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>these most timid efforts were channeled into subservient obsequi-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>ousness and excessive affection-seeking.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>Sylvia Plath, in The Bell Jar:&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>Once when I visited Buddy I found Mrs. Willard braiding a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>rug out of strips of wool from Mr. Willard&apos;s old suits. She&apos;d
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>spent a week on that rug, and I had admired the tweedy
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>browns and greens and blues patterning the braid, but after
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>Mrs. Willard was through, instead of hanging the rug on the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>wall the way I would have done, she put it down in place of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>her kitchen mat, and in a feu days it was soiled and dull and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>indistinguishable from any mat you could buy for under a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>dollar in the Five and Ten.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>Here the ambivalence once again: on the one hand we see
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>aesthetic activity deformed, atrophied, but on the other we find,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>even within this restricted scope, socially creative impulses which,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>however, have no outlet for aesthetic development, no oppor-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>tunities for growth.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>It is true that these activities never had to become static, un-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>changing artistic norms. They never became obsolete products;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>they remained bound to everyday life, feeble attempts to make this
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>sphere more aesthetically pleasing. But the price for this was nar-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>rowmindedness. The object could never leave the realm in which it
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>came into being, it remained tied to the household, it could never
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>break loose and initiate communication.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>But what would happen if someday we cleared out this realm
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l53' n='N053'/>and opened it only to ourselves and other women? What if we
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l54' n='N054'/>alternated painting our faces with painting on canvas? What if we
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l55' n='N055'/>turned recipes into poetry? What if all these activities were to shed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l56' n='N056'/>their utilitarian rationale of male approval?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l57' n='N057'/>Ann Anders: &quot;On Unravelling and Reknitting a Sweater&quot;:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l58' n='N058'/>The old one was the first self-made
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l59' n='N059'/>Grown too large.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l60' n='N060'/>The wound up time of urgent experience
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l61' n='N061'/>Still fills it out.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l62' n='N062'/>Weeks of work and sensuality
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l63' n='N063'/>Not divided into days and nights
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l64' n='N064'/>Alone or entwined with many others.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l65' n='N065'/>The increase and decrease of tension
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l66' n='N066'/>Attests to density in memory.
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>Fetched forth again the largeness appears,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>tucks bear witness: from the beginning.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>Grown thinner, experience more fragmented
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>The smooth stitches turn into difficult cable,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>Growing upward, lending strength.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>Though I knitted narrow strips of blue into the grey,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>There was hardly enough wool.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>[3/9/76]
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>Perhaps that is all too simple, too superficial. Attempting to knit
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>the gap between the artistic realm and social reality is problematic
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>in that this gap is not simply the result of foolish blunder, but is
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>rather the result of particular preconditions.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>Women succeeded in entering the artistic realm when they
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>gained access to it via the adjoining pre-aesthetic&apos; realms. In the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>eighteenth century women were able to enter the realm of lit-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>erature by means of letters (the epistolary novel), since this was an
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>age in which letters and novels were gaining dignity and the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>dissolution of rigid formal rules allowed greater flexibility. Ex-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>perience could be gained in writing private letters. Since letters
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>and diaries have no clearly defined literary niche, it was all right
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>for women to practice on them. Only the Romantics considered
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>conversation—another feminine domain in literature—to be aes-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>thetic activity. Men were amazed by the new tenor, the new tone,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>the irreverence and more sensual descriptions unique to women&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>letters, and on occasion they even showed open admiration. It did
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>not take long for this medium to be included in the literary canon.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>But it is difficult to merely reach back and link up to these
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>feminine&quot; media—letters, weaving. It is, in fact, almost more
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>difficult to do this than to work with the unfeminine&apos; technica.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>media such as film, since these need not contend with being tra-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>ditionally relegated to the domain of the housewife. We should not
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>foster the false assumptions that our sewing teachers indeed
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>pointed us in the right direction. There is no direct path from the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>decorative potholder to the tapestries of Abakanovicz. Besides, I
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>am still horrified by the whole ruffles-and-sewing basket business
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>we were subjected to as young girls.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>I believe that feminine artistic production takes place by means
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>of a complicated process involving conquering and reclaiming, ap-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>propriating and formulating, as well as forgetting and subverting.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>In the works of those female artists who are concerned with the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>women’s movement, one finds artistic tradition as well as the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>break with it. It is good—in two respects—that no formal criteria
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>for feminist art&apos; can be definitively laid down. It enables us to re-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>ject categorically the notion of artistic norms, and it prevents
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>renewal of the calcified aesthetics debate, this time under the guise
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>of the feminist  approach.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>If, however, women have different assumptions with regard to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>their sensory approach, their relationship to matter and material,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l49' n='N049'/>their perception, their experience, their means of processing tac-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l50' n='N050'/>tile, visual and acoustic stimuli, their spatial orientation and tem-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l51' n='N051'/>poral rhythm—and all these things are what aesthetics meant at
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l52' n='N052'/>one time, according to its original definition as a theory of sensory
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l53' n='N053'/>perception—then one could logically expect to find these things ex-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l54' n='N054'/>pressed in special forms of mimetic transformation. Put em
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l55' n='N055'/>phatically, this would mean that within the framework of a female
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l56' n='N056'/>cosmology there would be a changed relationship between the sub-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l57' n='N057'/>jective artistic appropriation of reality on the one hand, and formal
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l58' n='N058'/>suggestiveness and receptive perception on the other. But it will be
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l59' n='N059'/>nearly impossible to find categorical evidence for this changed
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l60' n='N060'/>relationship: reality is not that logical, and there is no female
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l61' n='N061'/>cosmology either.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l62' n='N062'/>There is no proof of a different (female) relationship to detail
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l63' n='N063'/>and generality, to motionlessness and movement, to rhythm and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l64' n='N064'/>demeanor., I find the only sensible approach to be the search for
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l65' n='N065'/>evidence within individual, concrete texts (pictures, films, etc.), as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l66' n='N066'/>Virginia Woolf once attempted with Dorothy Richardson&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l67' n='N067'/>writing.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l68' n='N068'/>Virginia Woolf on the language of Dorothy Richardson:!
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l69' n='N069'/>She has invented, or, if she has not invented, developed and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l70' n='N070'/>applied to her own uses, a sentence which we might call the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l71' n='N071'/>psychological sentence of the feminine gender. It is of a more
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l72' n='N072'/>elastic fibre than the old, capable of stretching to the ex-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l73' n='N073'/>12
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>treme, of suspending the frailest particles, of enveloping the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>vaguest shapes. Other writers of the opposite sex have used
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>sentences of this description and stretched them to the ex-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>treme. But there is a difference. Miss Richardson has
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>fashioned her sentence consciously, in order that it may des-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>cend to the depths and investigate the crannies of Miriam
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>Henderson&apos;s consciousness. It is a woman&apos;s sentence, but on-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>ly in the sense that it is used to describe a woman&apos;s mind by a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>writer who is neither proud nor afraid of anything that she
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>may discover in the psychology of her sex.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>Dorothy Richardson on the masculine manner of writing:
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>The self-satisfied, complacent, know-all condescendingness
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>of their handling of their material. . .. The torment of all
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>novels is what is left out. The moment you are aware of it
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>there is torment in them. Bang, bang, bang, on they go, these
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>men&apos;s books, like an L.L.C. tram, yet unable to make you
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>forget them, the authors, for a moment.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>The exclusion of women from vast areas of production and the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>public sphere and the fact that most women have been responsible
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>for the biological and social reproduction of the species, as well as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>the economic, if they are working, has directed women&apos;s imagina-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>tion along other lines. Moreover, the much touted &quot;ahistoricity&quot; of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>women kept the polarity between intellectual labor and manual
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>labor from becoming too traumatic. The disparate development of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>the sexes, though origin of so much of women&apos;s suffering, for-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>tunately has not yet allowed women&apos;s behavior and needs to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>become reified to the degree found in advanced capitalism. But
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>generations of women paid for this with their banishment into the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>marital ghetto.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>Is there a feminine aesthetic? Certainly there is, if one is talking
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>about aesthetic awareness and modes of sensory perception. Cer-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>tainly not, if one is talking about an unusual variant of artistic pro-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>duction or about a painstakingly constructed theory of art.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>Women&apos;s break with the formal, intrinsic laws of a given medium,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>the release of their imagination -- these are unpredictable for an art
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>with feminist intentions. There is, thank heavens, no premed-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>iated strategy which can predict what happens when femail sen-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>suality is freed. Because it is a process and historically tentative,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>we cannot verbally anticipate this freeing of feminine sensuality
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>either at its traditional erotic center (even though there&apos;s a lot go-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>ing on there every month) or in the context of individual 
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>choice. We can do it only on the basis of a movement by women for
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>women.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>The important thing is that women artists will not let themselves
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>be kept back anymore. They work on canvas, they make films and 
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>videotapes, they write and sculpt, they work with metal and with
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>fabric, they are on stage. So let us take a look at what they are 
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>doing.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>-ilm,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>7 (March, 19761.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>5. Firestone, Dialectic of Sex, p. 159.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>6. Verena Stefan, Hautungen (1975), English translation under the title
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>Shedding (translation by Johanna Moore and Beth Weckmueller to be
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>ublished in Spring, 1978 by Daughters, Inc., New York.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>7. Lucy Lippard,  Warum separierte Frauenkunst? in Feminismus:
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>Kunst und Kreativitat.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>8. Frieda Grafe.Ein anderer Eindruck vom Begriff meines Korpers, in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>Filmkritik (March, 1976).
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>9. Sylvia Plath, The Bell Jar (London, 1963), p. 88.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>0. Virginia Woolf, Romance and the Heart in Contemporary Writers.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>p. 124f.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>11. Dorothy Richardson, Dawn s Lest Hand, p. 202f.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>Silvia Bovenschen is finishing her dissertation at the University of Frankfurt on a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>related subject: it will be published by Suhrkamp. She is the only moman on the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>oditorial staff of Aesthetik Und Kommunikation. an independent left journal and was
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>editor for their seminist issue.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
