<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>&quot;About two miles below Greenville, on the road to Freehold, there lived, early in the present
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>century, two old maids.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>“They owned a little log hut there, and a small piece of property surrounding it, in common. They
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>were supposed to be sisters, but in fact were not related by the ties of blood in any way. They had
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>both of them, in their younger days, experienced a romance that had broken their hearts, and the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>bond of sorrow between them had drawn the two close to each other in womanly sympathy
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>Together they had come from the old country to Connecticut, and from there to this place, seeking
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>peace and forgetfulness in the wilderness. They never told their story or anything in fact relating to
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>themselves that could serve as a clue to their identity or past life.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>“They spent their time in the necessary work about the log house and garden which was filled with
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>wild flowers and ferns, and in painting water color pictures which they sold among the neighboring
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>settlers for small sums; the highest price being asked was twenty-five cents. These paintings. ..are
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>unique in the extreme, showing great originality in conception, drawing and color, as well as in the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>medium employed for their production. Their subjects were generally selected from the Bible or pro-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>fane history, in which they seemed to have been well-versed. The paper they used was the wrapping
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>of candles and tea boxes, or something of that sort. The pigments were of home manufacture. They
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>would hunt through the woods and fields for certain flowers, berries and weeds, which they woulc
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>boil or bruise to obtain the color they desired. These crude materials were sometimes helped with the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>addition of brick dust, and in fact by anything that these primitive artists found suitable for the work
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>in hand.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>“The lady known as Miss Wilson (sic) was the artist-in-chief; the other, Miss Brundage (sic), the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>farmer and housekeeper.... Their paintings are scattered, by purchase, from Canada to Mobile and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>are now highly prized by the owners.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>Mary Ann Willson and Miss Brundidge are more familiar to lesbians as &quot;Patience” and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>&quot;Sarah,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>subjects of the fictional biography by Alma Routsong (pseudonym Isabel Miller), self-published for
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_27' n='N027'/>the first time in 1967 as A Place For Us. Information about these women is hard to find; a few of the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_28' n='N028'/>paintings are reproduced in the December, 1955, issue of American Heritage; the New York Histori-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_29' n='N029'/>cal Society owns “Mare Maid,” but has no supporting documents on Willson’s life. Most of the avail¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_30' n='N030'/>able information was included in a 1976 issue of Antiques magazine
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_31' n='N031'/>In an interview with Jonathan Katz which appears in Gay American History, Alma Routsong
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_32' n='N032'/>describes her discovery of Willson and Brundidge and discusses the problems she faced in trying to
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_33' n='N033'/>market a positive lesbian novel in the 1960’s. The following is an excerpt from their conversation:
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_34' n='N034'/>&quot;My lover and I were touring New York State and were visiting the folk art museum at
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_35' n='N035'/>Cooperstown. I was wandering through it, not really concentrating on anything, when my lover.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_36' n='N036'/>called me back, pointing to this picture of a mermaid by Mary Ann Willson. There was a card beside
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_37' n='N037'/>it that said Miss Willson and her ’farmerette&apos; companion lived and worked together in Greenville
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_38' n='N038'/>Town, Greene County, New York, circa 1820. Then we went into the next room—a small library-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_39' n='N039'/>and found a book by Lipman and Winchester, called Primitive Painters in America, with a shor
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_40' n='N040'/>piece about Mary Ann Willson. It said that she and Miss Brundidge had a “romantic attachment.&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_41' n='N041'/>was absolutely taken by it. I didn’t want to travel any more. I didn’t want to see Harriet Tubman’s
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_42' n='N042'/>bed. I wanted to go home and research Willson and Brundidge, find out all about them, and write a
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_43' n='N043'/>book about them.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_44' n='N044'/>L
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_4_1_tl_45' n='N045'/>Sen
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1' n='N001'/>From The Lesbian Issue Collective:
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1_1' n='N001'/>l’m a writer who struggles constantly with the urge to re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_2' n='N002'/>main silent.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_3' n='N003'/>And I understood our collective process as a struggle with
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_4' n='N004'/>silence. Like an individual isolated lesbian, we worked first on
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_5' n='N005'/>self-validation. We talked about the famous respected closet
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_6' n='N006'/>cases—could we get them to come out or figure some way to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_7' n='N007'/>claim them. (Claiming the &quot;great ones&quot; is a way for a despised
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_8' n='N008'/>group to feel good about itself.) And we spent many many
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_9' n='N009'/>meetings doing consciousness-raising on what it means to be
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_10' n='N010'/>lesbian artists—talking, some of us, about issues we had never
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_11' n='N011'/>discussed before. My excitement in working on this issue of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_12' n='N012'/>Heresies centered around the hope that many lesbian artists
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_13' n='N013'/>would write us, share their work, and contribute to this
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_14' n='N014'/>dialogue.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_15' n='N015'/>The standard I used in judging work was based on my wish
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_16' n='N016'/>to be inclusive—to present as much diversity as possible, to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_17' n='N017'/>present clearly articulated articles even if I disagreed with their
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_18' n='N018'/>content.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_19' n='N019'/>Others in the collective felt differently. This we discovered
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_20' n='N020'/>as we worked and worked and no longer had time just to talk
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_21' n='N021'/>to each other. We had been too busy when we started—dis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_22' n='N022'/>cussing our similarities, our struggles, our fears, and our op¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_23' n='N023'/>portunities as lesbian artists—to get very far in discussing our
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_24' n='N024'/>differences.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_25' n='N025'/>Cynthia Carr
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1_2' n='N001'/>The only talent I bring to the lesbian collective is my sexual
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_2_1' n='N002'/>preference, a scorn of self-important pretension, a nose for
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_3_1' n='N003'/>drivel, and a desire to see to it that we say it like it is. In the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_4_1' n='N004'/>past we have done ourselves and our work a terrible damage
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_5_1' n='N005'/>by lying about our experience. Driven by a need for the com-
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_6_1' n='N006'/>fort of a common political position, we have all too often
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_7_1' n='N007'/>allowed rhetoric to pass for truth. Seeking an accommodation
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_8_1' n='N008'/>with the straight world, we have lied about our essential dif-
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_9_1' n='N009'/>ference. And in a spirit of loyalty we have compromised our¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_10_1' n='N010'/>selves by supporting thinking and work which is simply bad.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_11_1' n='N011'/>There is very little sense of humor in us. We have, by this
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_12_1' n='N012'/>excusable example, leaned heavily on many closet doors
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_13_1' n='N013'/>which might otherwise have sprung open. It was my hope that
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_14_1' n='N014'/>with this issue we might present truly good work by lesbians.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_15_1' n='N015'/>Now, as I am about to be pasted up and mechanicaled, I can
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_16_1' n='N016'/>say that the effort has been exhausting and perilous. And cer¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_17_1' n='N017'/>tainly I am too close to the final product to say that we have
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_18_1' n='N018'/>succeeded.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_19_1' n='N019'/>Betsy Crowell
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1_3' n='N001'/>I usually think of myself as part scientist and part magician
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_2_2' n='N002'/>with certain skills that sometimes make art. Neither feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_3_2' n='N003'/>nor lesbianism determine the form and content of my work yet
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_4_2' n='N004'/>it was only with the security of the former and the coming to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_5_2' n='N005'/>terms with the latter (the muse) that my life and art began to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_6_2' n='N006'/>be uniquely and overtly me.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_7_2' n='N007'/>Initially I worked on the issue seeking a community to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_8_2' n='N008'/>explore in depth the relationship of lesbianism to the artist and
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_9_2' n='N009'/>to discover what would happen if lesbian art and artists were
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_10_2' n='N010'/>brought together. Our editorial collective’s discussions were
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_11_2' n='N011'/>some of the most provoking and intimate that I have experi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_12_2' n='N012'/>enced, yet after each I felt a sense of panic. I know that les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_13_2' n='N013'/>bians have made great art, I know that lesbians have been
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_14_2' n='N014'/>major contributors to culture, and I believe that lesbianism in
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_15_2' n='N015'/>the largest and most powerful sense of the word has been cen¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_16_2' n='N016'/>tral not peripheral to the creative world of woman, yet I was
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_17_2' n='N017'/>worried that we wouldn’t receive sufficient &quot;good” material. I
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_18_2' n='N018'/>also feared being viewed through society’s homophobic lenses
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1_4' n='N001'/>yet I will not obscure the importance of lesbianism to my life
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_2_3' n='N002'/>and art. The muse and I are inextricably entwined and she is a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_3_3' n='N003'/>woman. I struggle continually against any restrictions on my
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_4_3' n='N004'/>identity while questioning why this culture relentlessly omits
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_5_3' n='N005'/>and suppresses from discussion and history (even in the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_6_3' n='N006'/>feminist community) the essentialness of lesbianism to the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_7_3' n='N007'/>creative lives of women
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_8_3' n='N008'/>However, there was a far deeper reason for my panic. After
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_9_3' n='N009'/>nine months of working on this issue 1 felt that our greatest
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_10_3' n='N010'/>unfaced demon was our own homophobia absorbed by all of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_11_3' n='N011'/>us in different ways from a culture so homophobic that it ruth¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_12_3' n='N012'/>lessly suppresses and punished all exploration of female
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_13_3' n='N013'/>sexuality. This, coupled with the fact that lesbian artists des¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_14_3' n='N014'/>perately need visibility and credibility, gave us a common
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_15_3' n='N015'/>unexamined goal: visibility as matured and serious artists.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_16_3' n='N016'/>This is only a beginning. Omitted from the issue is any
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_17_3' n='N017'/>dialogue that examines the role of lesbianism as central to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_18_3' n='N018'/>women claiming full power over their sexuality and that such
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_19_2' n='N019'/>power is the root of strong and unique art. Do not for a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_20_1' n='N020'/>minute imagine that art has to be explicitly about sex or any¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_21_1' n='N021'/>thing so simplistic. I am speaking rather to the fact that a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_22_1' n='N022'/>person must be able to put the full force of herself behind her
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_23_1' n='N023'/>work. Fear of being seen as sexual, fear of the audience, fear of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_24_1' n='N024'/>offending heterosexual friends, fear of retribution for creating
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_25_1' n='N025'/>or being in the issue are only a few of the fears that are real
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_26' n='N026'/>and need to be faced before we can initiate a discussion that
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_27' n='N027'/>begins from a point that assumes that lesbianism is the key to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_28' n='N028'/>the powerfulness of all women.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_29' n='N029'/>Betsy Damon
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1_5' n='N001'/>I wanted an issue on lesbian art and artists that would pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_2_4' n='N002'/>voke me; an issue that would challenge all the assumptions I
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_3_4' n='N003'/>have about lesbians and art; an issue that would leave me
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_4_4' n='N004'/>filled with questions and with the energy with which to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_5_4' n='N005'/>explore the questions further. I wanted lesbians to be excited
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_6_4' n='N006'/>and disturbed by what they read here, finding glimpses of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_7_4' n='N007'/>themselves, as well as a sense of what is missing. What stories
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_8_4' n='N008'/>are still untold?
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_9_4' n='N009'/>What are lesbians? What are artists? In trying to reach a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_10_4' n='N010'/>working definition of these two most basic questions, a sense
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_11_4' n='N011'/>of my own alienation from the task before us began to grow.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_12_4' n='N012'/>This alienation came from being forced to examine sexuality
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_13_4' n='N013'/>from within a patriarchal context. A context which has
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_14_4' n='N014'/>created distinctions and categories in order to maintain its
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_15_4' n='N015'/>own power and privilege. The advantages gained by society&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_16_4' n='N016'/>&quot;power-brokers&quot; through perpetuating and emphasizing the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_17_4' n='N017'/>differences among racial, economic, sexual, and religious
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_18_4' n='N018'/>groups are clear. The most apparent difference between myself
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_19_3' n='N019'/>and a heterosexual woman; or myself (white, middle-class),
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_20_2' n='N020'/>and a Chicano working-class woman—is one of privilege.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_21_2' n='N021'/>And for me, as a lesbian, as white, as middle-class, to main¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_22_2' n='N022'/>tain and perpetuate differences that ultimately exist only to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_23_2' n='N023'/>deny privilege to some, seems wrong. One way I see myself as
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_24_2' n='N024'/>a lesbian perpetuating differences is in my focusing on what is
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_25_2' n='N025'/>and what is not a lesbian. &quot;A woman who does not sleep with
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_26_1' n='N026'/>men.&quot; “Any woman who calls herself a lesbian.” “A woman
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_27_1' n='N027'/>that loves and sleeps with other women.&quot; “What if she sleeps
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_28_1' n='N028'/>with a man one time? Is she still a lesbian?” “What if she used
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_29_1' n='N029'/>to sleep with men, used to be married to one, and doesn’t now,
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_30' n='N030'/>but can’t predict the future?&quot; “What is the difference between a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_31' n='N031'/>woman-identified-woman and a lesbian?” It was in trying to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_32' n='N032'/>answer questions like these that a sense of futility and absurd¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_33' n='N033'/>ity developed. I am not a lesbian. I make love only with
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_34' n='N034'/>women. I am in every way what society calls a lesbian. I will
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_35' n='N035'/>call myself and insist upon being called a lesbian as long as
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_36' n='N036'/>something called a heterosexual or bisexual exists. In all pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_37' n='N037'/>bability, 1 am referring to a sexuality that will never exist
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_38' n='N038'/>inside me. A simple sexuality, without reference to another’s
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
