<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='16'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_1' n='N001'/>Performance f2: A Street Event
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_2' n='N002'/>A description by Su Friedrich who assisted in the performance of the event
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_3' n='N003'/>Betsy’s magic circle:
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_4' n='N004'/>The 7000 year old woman’s Sacred Grove.
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_5' n='N005'/>My temporary refuge, my stage.
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_6' n='N006'/>Private activities becoming public, intimate gestures between Betsy and me being questioned, observed
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_7' n='N007'/>encouraged or debased by the fluctuating crowd. Westchester ladies, street tough boys, perplexed and absorbed
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_8' n='N008'/>girls, Soho thinkers and smirkers, women friends, Catholic grandmothers—a strange (re)union, our temporary
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_9' n='N009'/>bond being this massive cryptic 7000-year-old woman.
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_10' n='N010'/>Intimate gestures: tying the bags on Betsy’s chalk white body layer by layer, led along by whispered directions
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_11' n='N011'/>from her but gaining my own momentum as 1 absorb the colors and textures, the soft, firm, heavy bags laid out
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_12' n='N012'/>on the ground in front of her like offerings, like children’s clothes, like flowers, these useless but nevertheless
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_13' n='N013'/>significant treasures.
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_14' n='N014'/>Our theatre, our ritual of preparation reminded me of the decoration rituals shared by young girls, by my
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_15' n='N015'/>friends and me: brushing Veronica’s long blonde hair, helping my sister into her dress before the party, quiet
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_16' n='N016'/>conversations on our common “secrets” of what is pretty or strong or burdensome about ourselves; sharing
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_17' n='N017'/>nervous anticipation, mutual support for the eventual, inevitable journey outside our female circle; feeling
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_18' n='N018'/>positive about ourselves, feeling protected, so as to be strong outside, on the stage.
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_19' n='N019'/>I lost some of that inner tension and private interaction when I had to assume my more familiar public role of
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_20' n='N020'/>photographer as she continued the piece. Through the lens I observed the crowd, the same people who had just
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_21' n='N021'/>been watching me and therefore somehow had power over me. There was the enchanted young girl whose
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_22' n='N022'/>concentration and comfort was shattered when an egg landed nearby and soiled her dress; the greedy, arrogant
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_23' n='N023'/>boys who had no qualms about entering the space to take as many bags as possible (to be used down the streel
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_24' n='N024'/>later in a fight); and the many 20-30-40 year old men and women whose interests ranged from trying to guess her
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_25' n='N025'/>gender (&quot;no woman has a jawline like that”) to staring transfixed and delighted at the apparition of a woman,
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_26' n='N026'/>white faced and laden with sixty pounds of rose- and jonquil-colored bags making a substantial, private,
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_27' n='N027'/>controlled but romantic/theatrical space for herself.
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_28' n='N028'/>My immediate attraction to her visually is the direct reference (unconscious: Betsy has never seen them) to the
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_29' n='N029'/>beautiful “warrior vests” of certain African nations: cloth jackets heavily laden with magic tokens of leather,
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_30' n='N030'/>wood and stone, used essentially as “arrow proof” vests in war.
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_31' n='N031'/>Hugeness, protection, ponderous weight, gentle colors, sensuous textures, tenuous construction and so
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_32' n='N032'/>temporary as the bags were slashed open, letting the colors pour out and cover the ground, leaving a soft pink
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_33' n='N033'/>trail, a circular trail of footsteps and discarded bags.
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_34' n='N034'/>Betsy Damon is a performer, sculptor and mother who recently moved to New York City. Over the last five years she has
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_35' n='N035'/>been a visiting artist and lecturer at many universities, involved in feminist art programs, and founded a Feminist Studio in
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_36' n='N036'/>Ithaca, New York.
				<lb facs='#facs_16_region_1674861475716_526_tl_37' n='N037'/>Su Friedrich is a freelance photographer who is interested in doing projects which explore fantasy and deception.
			</p>
			<pb n='17'/>
			<pb n='18'/>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
