<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Feminism and the Revolt of Nature</title>
				<author>Ynestra King</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="13"/>
			<head>Feminism and the Revolt of Nature</head>
			<byline><persName>Yinestra King</persName></byline>

			<p> The problem with both analyses, however, is that gender identity is neither fully
				natural nor fully cultural. And it is neither inherently oppressive nor inherently
				liberating. It depends on other historical factors, and how we consciously
				understand woman-identification and feminism.</p>
			<p>Socialist Feminism and Ecology: <note>4. For an overview of socialist feminist
					theory, see Zillah Eisenstein, Ed., Capitalist Patriarchy and the Case for
					Socialist Feminism (New York: Monthly Review Press, 1979).</note> Socialist
				feminists have for the most part yet to enter feminist debates on "the ecology
				question." They tend to be uneasy with ecological feminism fearing that it is based
				on an ahistorical, anti-rational woman/ nature identification; or they see the
				cultural emphasis in ecological feminism as "idealist" rather than "materialist."
				The Marxist side of their politics implies a primacy of material transformation
				(economic/structural transformation precedes changes in
				ideas/culture/consciousness). Cultural and material changes are not completely
				separate. There is a dialectical interaction between the two, but in the last
				instance the cultural is part of the superstructure and the material is the
				base.</p>
			<p>Historically socialism and feminism have had a curious courtships <note>5. See Batya
					Weinbaum, The Curious Courtship of Women's Liberation and Socialism (Boston:
					South End Press, 1978).</note> and a rather unhappy marriage,<note>6. See Heidi
					Hartman, "The Unhappy Marriage of Marxism and Feminism: Towards a More
					Progressive Union," Capital and Class, no. 8 (Summer 1979).</note> characterized
				by a tug of war over which is the primary contradiction-sex or class. In an uneasy
				truce, socialist feminists try to overcome the contradictions, to show how the
				economic structure and the sex-gender system<note>7. The notion of a "sex-gender
					system" was first developed by Gayle Rubin in "The Traffic in Women," Toward an
					Anthropology of Women, ed. R.R. Reiter (New York: Monthly Review Press,
					1975).</note> are mutually reinforced in historically specific ways depending on
				material conditions, and to show their interdependence. They suggest the need for an
				"autonomous" (as opposed to a "separatist"') women's movement, to maintain
				vigilance over women’s concerns within the production and politics of a mixed
				society. They see patriarchy as different under feudalism, capitalism and even under
				socialism without feminism.<note>8. See Hilda Scott, Does Socialism Liberate
					Women? (Boston : Beacon Press, 1976).</note> And they hold that nobody is free
				until everybody is free.</p>
			<p>Socialist feminists see themselves as integrating the best of Marxism and radical
				feminism. They have been weak on radical cultural critique and strong on helping
				us to understand how people’s material situations condition their consciousnesses
				and their possibilities for social transformation. But adherence to Marxism with its
				economic orientation means opting for the rationalist severance of the woman/nature
				connection and advocating the integration of women into production. It does not
				challenge the culture-versus-nature formulation itself. Even where the issue of
				woman's oppression and its identification with that of nature has been taken up, the
				socialist feminist solution has been to align women with culture in culture’s
				ongoing struggle with nature.<note>9. See Sherry B. Ortner, “Is Woman to Nature as
					Man Is to Culture?," Woman, Culture, and Society, ed. M.Z. Rosaldo &amp; L.
					Lamphere (Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1974).</note></p>
			<p>Here We Go Again, This Argument Is at Least 100 Years Old! The radical
				feminist/socialist feminist debate does sometimes seem to be the romantic
				feminist/rationalist feminist debate of the late 19th century revisited. 10 We can
				imagine 19th-century women watching the development of robber-baron capitalism,
				"the demise of morality" and the rise of the liberal state which furthered
				capitalist interests while touting liberty equality and fraternity. Small wonder
				that they saw in the domestic sphere vestiges of a more ethical way of life, and
				thought its values could be carried into the public sphere. This perspective
				romanticized women, although it is easy to sympathize with it and share the
				abhorrence of the pillage and plunder imposed by the masculinist mentality in modern
				industrial society. But what 19th-century women proclaiming the virtues of womanhood
				did not understand was that they were a repository of organic social values in an
				increasingly inorganic world. Women placed in male-identified power positions can be
				as warlike as men. The assimilation or neutralization of enfranchised women into
				the American political structure has a sad history.</p>
			<p>Rationalist feminists in the 19th century, on the other hand, were concerned with
				acquiring power and representing women’s interests. They opposed anything that
				reinforced the idea that women were “different" and wanted male prerogatives
				extended to women. They were contemptuous of romantic feminists and were
				themselves imbued with the modern ethic of Progress. They opposed political activity
				by women over issues not seen as exclusively feminist for the same reasons
				rationalist radical feminists today oppose the feminism/ ecology connection.</p>
			<p>The Dialectic of Modern Feminism: According to the false dichotomy between subjective
				and objective-one legacy of male Western philosophy to feminist thought-we must root
				our movement either in a rationalist-materialist humanism or in a
				metaphysical-feminist naturalism. This supposed choice is crucial as we approach the
				ecology issue. Either we take the anthropocentric position that nature exists solely
				to serve the <pb n="14"/> needs of the male bourgeois who has crawled out of the
				slime to be lord and master of everything, or we take the naturalist position that
				nature has a purpose of its own apart from serving "man." We are either concerned
				with the "environment because we are dependent on it, or we understand ourselves to
				be of it, with human oppression part and parcel of the domination of nature. For
				some radical feminists, only women are capable of full consciousness.! Socialist
				feminists tend to consider the naturalist position as historically regressive, anti¬
				rational and probably fascistic. This is the crux of the anthro¬
				pocentric/naturalist debate, which is emotionally loaded for both sides, but
				especially for those who equate progress and rationality.</p>
			<p>However, we do not have to make such choices. Feminism is both the product and
				potentially the negation of the modern rationalist world view and capitalism. There
				was one benefit for women in the "disenchantment of the world,"12 the process by
				which all magical and spiritual beliefs were denigrated as superstitious nonsense
				and the death of nature was accomplished in the minds of men.13 This process tore
				asunder women’s traditional sphere of influence, but it also undermined the ideology
				of "natural"' social roles, opening a space for women to question what was "natural"
				for them to be and to do. In traditional Western societies, social and economic
				relationships were connected to a land-based way of life. One was assigned a special
				role based on one's sex, race, class and place of birth. In the domestic sphere
				children were socialized, food prepared and men sheltered from their public cares.
				But the 19th-century "home" also encompassed the production of what people ate,
				used and wore. It included much more of human life and filled many more human needs
				than its modern corollary-the nuclear family-which purchases commodities to meet its
				needs. The importance of the domestic sphere, and hence women’s influence,
				declined with the advent of market society.</p>
			<p>Feminism also negates capitalist social relations by challenging the lopsided
				male-biased values of our culture. When coupled with an ecological perspective, it
				insists that we remember our origins in nature, our connections to one another as
				daughters, sisters and mothers. It refuses any longer to be the unwitting powerless
				symbol of all the things men wish to deny in themselves and project onto us-the
				refusal to be the “other.”14 It can heal the splits in a world divided against
				itself and built on a fundamental lie: the defining of culture in opposition to
				nature.</p>
			<p>The dialectic moves on. Now it is possible that a conscious visionary feminism could
				place our technology and productive apparatus in the service of a society based on
				ecological principles and values, with roots in traditional women's ways of being
				in the world. This in turn might make possible a total cultural critique. Women can
				remember what men have denied in themselves (nature), and women can know what men
				know (culture). Now we must develop a transformative feminism that sparks our
				utopian imaginations and embodies our deepest knowledge-a feminism that is an
				affirmation of our vision at the same time it is a negation of patriarchy. The
				skewed reasoning that opposes matter and spirit and refuses to concern itself with
				the objects and ends of life, which views internal nature and external nature as one
				big hunting ground to be quantified and conquered is, in the end, not only irra¬
				tional but deadly. To fulfill its liberatory potential, feminism needs to pose a
				rational reenchantment that brings together spiritual and material, being and
				knowing. This is the promise of ecological feminism.</p>
			<p>Dialectical Feminism: Transcending the Radical Feminist/ Socialist Feminist Debate:
				The domination of external nature has necessitated the domination of internal
				nature. Men have denied their own embodied naturalness, repressed memories of
				infantile pleasure and dependence on the mother and on nature.1s Much of their
				denied self has been projected onto women. Objectification is forgetting. The ways
				in which women have been both included in and excluded from a culture based on
				gender differences provide a critical ledge from which to view the artificial chasm
				male culture has placed between itself and nature. Woman has stood with one foot on
				each side. She has been a bridge for men, back to the parts of themselves they have
				denied, despite their need of women to attend to the visceral chores they consider
				beneath them.</p>
			<p>An ecological perspective offers the possibility of moving beyond the radical
				(cultural) feminist/socialist feminist impasse. But it necessitates a feminism
				that holds out for a separate cultural and political activity so that we can
				imagine, theorize or envision from the vantage point of critical otherness. The
				ecology question weights the historic feminist debate in the direction of
				traditional female values over the overly rationalized, combative male way of being
				in the world. Rationalist feminism is the Trojan horse of the women's movement.
				Its piece-of-the-action mentality conceals a capitulation to a culture bent on the
				betrayal of nature. In that sense it is unwittingly both misogynist and
				anti-ecological. Denying biology, espousing androgyny and valuing what men have
				done over what we have done are all forms of self-hatred which threaten to derail
				the teleology of the feminist challenge to this violent civilization.</p>
			<p>The liberation of women is to be found neither in severing <pb n="15"/> all
				connections that root us in nature nor in believing ourselves to be more natural
				than men. Both of these positions are unwittingly complicit with nature/culture
				dualism. Women's oppression is neither strictly historical nor strictly biological.
				It is both. Gender is a meaningful part of a person's identity. The facts of
				internal and external genitalia and women's ability to bear children will continue
				to have social meaning. But we needn’t think the choices are external sexual warfare
				or a denatured (and boring) androgyny. It is possible to take up questions of
				spirituality and meaning without abandoning the important insights of materialism.
				We can use the insights of socialist feminism, with its debt to Marxism, to
				understand how the material conditions of our daily lives interact with our bodies
				and our psychological heritages. Materialist insights warn us not to assume an
				innate moral or biological superiority and not to depend on alternative culture
				alone to transform society. Yet a separate radical feminist culture within a
				patriarchal society is necessary so we can learn to speak our own bodies and our own
				experiences, so the male culture representing itself as the "universal" does not
				continue to speak for us.<note>16. See de Beauvoir, The Second Sex.</note>
			</p>
			<p>We have always thought our lives and works, our very beings, were trivial next to
				male accomplishments. Women's silence is deafening only to those who know it's
				there. The absence is only beginning to be a presence. Writers like Zora Neale
				Hurston, Tillie Olsen, Grace Paley and Toni Morrison depict the beauty and dignity
				of ordinary women's lives and give us back part of ourselves. Women artists begin to
				suggest the meanings of female bodies and their relationships to nature.<note>17.
					See Lucy Lippard, "Quite Contrary: Body, Nature and Ritual in Women's Art,"
					Chrysalis, no. 2 (1977).</note> Women musicians give us the sounds of loving
				ourselves. <note>18. Alive, Sweet Honey in the Rock, Meg Christian, Holly Near,
					Margie Adam-the list is long and growing.</note> The enormous and growing
				lesbian feminist community is an especially fertile ground for women's culture.
				Lesbians are pioneering in every field and building communities with ecological
				feminist consciousness. Third World women are speaking the experience of multiple
				otherness - of race, sex and (often) class oppression. We are learning how women’s
				lives are the same and different across these divisions, and we are beginning to
				engage the complexities of racism in our culture, our movement and our theory.</p>
			<p>There is much that is redemptive for humanity as a whole in women’s silent
				experience, and there are voices that have not yet been heard. Cultural feminism’s
				concern with ecology takes the ideology of womanhood which has been a bludgeon of
				oppression-the woman/nature connection-and transforms it into a positive factor. If
				we proceed dialectically and recognize the contributions of both socialist
				feminism and radical cultural feminism, operating at both the structural and
				cultural levels, we will be neither materialists nor idealists. We will understand
				our position historically and attempt to realize the human future emerging in the
				feminist present. Once we have placed ourselves in history, we can move on to the
				interdependent issues of feminist social transformation and planetary
				survival.</p>
			<p>Towards an Ecological Culture: Acting on our own consciousness of our own needs, we
				act in the interests of all. We stand on the biological dividing line. We are the
				less rationalized side of humanity in an overly rationalized world, yet we can think
				as rationally as men and perhaps transform the idea of reason itself. As women, we
				are naturalized culture in a culture defined against nature. If nature/culture
				antagonism is the primary contradiction of our time, it is also what weds feminism
				and ecology and makes woman the historic subject. Without an ecological perspective
				which asserts the interdependence of living things, feminism is disembodied. Without
				a more sophisticated dialectical method which can transcend historic debates and
				offer a nondualistic theory of history, social transformation and nature/culture
				interaction, feminism will continue to be mired in the same old impasse. There is
				more at stake in feminist debates over "the ecology question" than whether feminists
				should organize against the draft, demonstrate at the Pentagon or join mixed
				anti-nuke organizations. At stake is the range and potential of the feminist social
				movement.</p>
			<p>Ecological feminism is about reconciliation and conscious mediation, about
				recognition of the underside of history and all the invisible voiceless activities
				of women over millennia. It is about connectedness and wholeness of theory and prac¬
				tice. It is the return of the repressed-all that has been denigrated and denied to
				build this hierarchal civilization with its multiple systems of dominance. It is
				the potential voice of the Ellen Lanyon. Transformations II (Endangered). Detail.
				denied, the ugly and the speechless-all those things called feminine." So it is no
				wonder that the feminist movement rose again in the same decade as the ecological
				crisis. The implications of feminism extend to issues of the meaning, purpose
				and survival of life.</p>
			<lg>
				<l>Never to despise in myself what 1 have been taught</l>
				<l>to despise. Not to despise the other.</l>
				<l>Not to despise the it. To make this relation</l>
				<l>with it: to know that ! am it.</l>
				<l>-Muriel Rukeyser, "Despisals" <note>19. Muriel Rukeyser, The Compiete Poems of
						Muriel Rukeyser (New York: McGraw-Hill, 1978).</note></l>
			</lg>
			<pb n="16"/>
			<p> 1. Ellen Willis, The Village Voice (June 23, 1980). In the Voice (July 16-22, 1980),
				Willis began with the question: "Is ecology a feminist issue?" and was more
				ambiguous than in her earlier column, although her theoretical position was the
				same. 2. Mary Daly, Gyn/Ecology: The Meta-Ethics of Radical Feminism (Boston: Beacon
				Press, 1978). 3. Susan Griffin, Woman and Nature : The Roaring Inside Her (New York;
				Harper &amp; Row, 1979). 10. For a social history of the 19th-century
				romanticist/rationalist debate see Barbara Ehrenreich and Dierdre English, For Her
				Own Good (New York: Doubleday/Anchor, 1979) 11. Mary Daly comes very close to this
				position. Other naturalist feminists have a less clear stance on essential
				differences between women and men. </p>
			<p> 12. The "disenchantment of the world" is another way of talking about the process of
				rationalization discussed above. The term was coined by Max Weber. 13. See Carolyn
				Merchant, The Death of Nature: Women, Ecology and the Scientific Revolution (San
				Francisco: Harper &amp; Row, 1980). 14. For a full development of the idea of "woman
				as other," see Simone de Beauvoir, The Second Sex (New York: Modern Library, 1968).
				15. Dorothy Dinnerstein in The Mermaid and the Minotaur (New York: Harper &amp; Row,
				1977) makes an important contribution to feminist understanding by showing that
				although woman is associated with nature because of her mothering role, this does
				not in itself explain misogyny and the hatred of nature.</p>


			<p>Ynestra King, based in Northampton, Mass., is writing a book on feminism, ecology
				and suwival entitled Feminism and the Reenchantment of the Worfd. She works with
				Women and Life on Earth and the Women’s Pentagon Action and teaches in the Goddard
				College "Feminism and Ecology" summer program. Ellen Lanyon is a painter, printmaker
				and educator in Chicago and NYC. Her imagery involves science versus magic,
				transformations, and phenomena of the natural world.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
