<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Cliff_issue15_34-40</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: hmb010@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l1' n='N001'/>In my room thère is a postcard of a sculpture
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l2' n='N002'/>by the Venetian artist Danese Cattaneo, done in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l3' n='N003'/>the mid-16th century—Black Venus. The full¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l4' n='N004'/>length nude figure is bronze. In one hand she
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l5' n='N005'/>holds a hand-mirror in which she is looking at
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l6' n='N006'/>herself. On her head is a turban, around the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l7' n='N007'/>edges of which her curls are visible. In her other
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l8' n='N008'/>hand she carries a cloth—or at least what ap¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l9' n='N009'/>pears to be a cloth. Who was she? A slave? Per¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l10' n='N010'/>haps in the artist&apos;s own household, or maybe that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l11' n='N011'/>of his patron—one of the many Black women
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l12' n='N012'/>dragged from Africa to enter the service of white
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l13' n='N013'/>Europeans. I have no idea who she actually was:
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l14' n='N014'/>she was an object, then as now.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l15' n='N015'/>Around this image are other images of Black
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l16' n='N016'/>women: Bernadette Powell, who killed the man
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l17' n='N017'/>who beat her and is now in Bedford Hills; Fannie
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l18' n='N018'/>Lou Hamer; Billie Holiday; Elizabeth Freeman,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l19' n='N019'/>who sued for her freedom and won it, in Massa¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l20' n='N020'/>chusetts in the 19th century; Josephine Baker;
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>Harriet Tubman, portrayed in a linocut by Eliza¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>beth Catlett; women students making basket fur¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>niture at the Hampton Institute; Lucy Parsons;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>Ida B. Wells-Barnett; Audre Lorde; Phillis Wheat¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>ley; two women in Botswana seated around a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>gourd; Sojourner Truth; women in the Black Lib¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>eration Movement in England; Betye Saar&apos;s Aunt
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>Sally HooDoo; a girlchild balancing a basin on
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>her head in southern Africa.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>My moving toward the study of the work¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>written and visual—of Black women has been a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>moving toward my own wholeness. My interest in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>this work is a deeply personal interest, because
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>through these words and images I begin to cap¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>ture part of who I am.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>I should begin with my title—“Object into
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>Subject.&quot; What does it mean? We live in a society
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>whose history is drenched in the philosophy and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>practice of racism, the oppression of Black and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>other Third World peoples. This is the point at
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>which my definition begins: If you study racism—
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>if you understand the history of the United States
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>—you will find that under racism the person who
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>is oppressed is turned into an object in the mind
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>of the oppressor.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>The white anti-racist southern writer Lillian
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>Smith was among the first to offer a metaphysical
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>and psychological explanation of racism as a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>personal and political American practice.! One
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>essential to the maintenance of things as they are
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>in this society. Smith—whose influences included
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>Kierkegaard, Jung, Freud, and Sartre—traced
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>the origins of racism, and its more apparent
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>manifestation, segregation, to that place in the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>human mind she called &quot;mythic&quot;: that place
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>where dreams, fantasies, and images begin;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>where they continue and take form as art, litera¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l1' n='N001'/>ture, politics, religion. The mythic mind is a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l2' n='N002'/>source of psychic energy—it contributes the mo
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l3' n='N003'/>tion necessary for sustained thought. But the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l4' n='N004'/>mythic mind needs a structure in which to func
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l5' n='N005'/>tion, so that its products will be understood. This
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l6' n='N006'/>structure is provided by reason. Reason, Smith
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l7' n='N007'/>argued, is merely a technic, an enabler; its sole
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>purpose is to create the form which will support
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>the ideas moving out of the mythic mind. Reason
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>is incapable of moral judgment, and therefore
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>will support any idea or image, regardless of its
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>moral basis.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>When the mythic idea of whiteness, the ob¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>session with skin color which is the irrational
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>and immoral basis of racism, is given a construct
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>from which the myth takes its form—i.e., the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>philosophy of white supremacy—the result is cul¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>tural or institutionalized racism, contained in the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>politics, literature, art, and religion of the domi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>nant culture. An insane idea now exists within a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>reasonable reality, not an irrational dream.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>Whatever we may feel about Smith&apos;s analysis,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l16' n='N016'/>or her sources for that matter, her treatment of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l17' n='N017'/>American racism as something embedded in the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l18' n='N018'/>white mind, regenerating itself within a psycho¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l19' n='N019'/>logical construct, is extremely important. She
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l20' n='N020'/>recognized early on the character of racism as in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l21' n='N021'/>a sense  larger than life,&quot; something which could
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l22' n='N022'/>not be removed by congressional legislation or
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l23' n='N023'/>Supreme Court decisions, unless these actions
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l24' n='N024'/>were the result of a completely radicalized mind¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l25' n='N025'/>set within the dominant culture. I think that the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l26' n='N026'/>resurgence of white racism in this country today
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l27' n='N027'/>bears witness to her understanding.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l28' n='N028'/>Within the rationale reason lends to racism,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l29' n='N029'/>Smith argued, is the practice of objectification,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l30' n='N030'/>an absolute necessity in the racist effort to op¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l31' n='N031'/>press. (I use the word &quot;effort&quot; because it is and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l32' n='N032'/>has been so; one which has been carried on on
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l33' n='N033'/>every level of this society, against constant, his¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l34' n='N034'/>toric opposition.) Through objectification—the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l35' n='N035'/>process by which people are dehumanized, made
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l36' n='N036'/>ghostlike, given the status of Other—an image
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l37' n='N037'/>created by the oppressor replaces the actual
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l38' n='N038'/>being. The actual being is then denied speech;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l39' n='N039'/>denied self-definition, self-realization; and over¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l40' n='N040'/>arching all this, denied selfhood—which is after
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l41' n='N041'/>all the point of objectification. A group of human
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l42' n='N042'/>beings—a people—are denied their history, their
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l43' n='N043'/>language, their music. Their cultural values are
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l1' n='N001'/>ignored. This history, this language, this music,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l2' n='N002'/>these values exist in the subculture, but in the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l3' n='N003'/>dominant culture only certain elements are cho¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l4' n='N004'/>sen, recast, co-opted, and made available to the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l5' n='N005'/>definition of these people. And these elements
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l6' n='N006'/>presented by the dominant culture tend to serve
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l7' n='N007'/>the purpose of objectification and, therefore,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l8' n='N008'/>oppression.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l9' n='N009'/>The practice of objectification stands be¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l10' n='N010'/>tween all Black people and full human identity
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_10_1l11' n='N011'/>under the white supremacist system: racism re¬
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>quires that Black people be thought different
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>from white; and this difference is usually trans¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>lated as less than. This requirement has been
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>stated in various ways throughout the history of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>America. Did you know, for example, that Thomas
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>Jefferson held the popular view that the Black
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>race was created when Black women mated with
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>orangutans?? (I do not know where the original
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>Black women were supposed to have come from.)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>Last October on my local PBS station I watched
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>the film Birth of a Nation, introduced by a rather
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>hearty film buff as an American classic, the work
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>of a &quot;tragic poet.&quot; I had never seen the movie,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>nor had I read the book The Clansman, upon
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>which it is based. I felt I &quot;had to watch it.&quot; The
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>first thing I noticed was that all the Black charac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>ters were portrayed by white actors in &quot;black¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>face.&quot; Throughout the film the thing most evident
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>to me was that this was a playing-out of a white
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>American&apos;s image of Black people, crude and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>baroque to be sure, but not that far removed from
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>Gone with the Wind (another American classic),
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>or even from such white-inspired television pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>grams as The Jeffersons.&quot; If anything, the very
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>coarse brutality of Birth of a Nation is closer to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>the history of the slavocracy than perhaps any
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>other American film. I could see as I watched this
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>film how white people were capable of commit¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>ting both the acts of the slave period and the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>lynchings which flourished during Reconstruc¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>tion and thereafter. D. W. Griffiths&apos;s imaginings
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>of Black women and men attempted to justify this
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>history by replacing a people with the fantasies
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>of his tragically racist mind. The very title gives
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>his intention away.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>The playwright and activist Lorraine Hans¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>berry, in her essay The New Paternalists,&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>observed:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>America long ago fell in love with an image. It is a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>sacred image, fashioned over centuries of time: this
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>image of the unharried, unconcerned, glandulatory,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>simple, rhythmic, amoral, dark creature who was,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>above all else, a miracle of sensuality. It was cre¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>ated, and it persists, to provide a personified pres¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>sure valve for fanciful longings in [white] American
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>dreams, literature, and life.... I think, for example,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>of that reviewer writing in a Connecticut news¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>paper about A Raisin in the Sun... and marvelling,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>in the rush of a quite genuine enthusiasm, that the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>play proved again that there was a quaint loveli¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>ness in how our  dusky brethren&quot; can come up with
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>a song and hum their troubles away. It did not seem
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>to disturb him one whit that there is no single allu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>sion to that particular mythical gift in the entire
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l12' n='N012'/>play. He did not need it there; it was in his head.3
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l13' n='N013'/>Just as this white reviewer could hear Black peo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l14' n='N014'/>ple humming as he watched Hansberry&apos;s play,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l15' n='N015'/>others could declare it a play about insurance
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l16' n='N016'/>money, one which proved that all Black people
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l17' n='N017'/>really wanted was to live alongside whites. Many
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l18' n='N018'/>white people perceived the ending of Raisin as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l19' n='N019'/>happy,&quot; unaware perhaps of what it meant for
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l20' n='N020'/>a Black family to move into a white neighborhood
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l21' n='N021'/>in Chicago in the post-World War II years. Did
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l22' n='N022'/>any of these white people know of Hansberry&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l23' n='N023'/>own childhood experience when her family moved
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l24' n='N024'/>into a white Chicago neighborhood? The response
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l25' n='N025'/>to this move was white violence: the eight-year¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l26' n='N026'/>old Hansberry had a brick thrown through her
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l27' n='N027'/>bedroom window by the white mob. Her father,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l28' n='N028'/>supported by the NAACP, took the case all the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l29' n='N029'/>way to the Supreme Court and established a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l30' n='N030'/>precedent for nondiscriminatory housing—but
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>nothing in Chicago actually changed.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>If anything, the ending of Raisin is hopeful,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>not happy. And the hopefulness one feels derives
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>not from any expectation of a white change-of¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>heart, but from the fact that Hansberry has
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>tested her characters throughout the play and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>they have emerged as people of integrity, capable
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>of facing reality and white racism. She was, I
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>think, attempting to create Black characters who
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>would disrupt white imagery of Black people. But
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>many in her audience could only see these char¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>acters through their own screen of objectifica¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>tion.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>It is objectification that gives the impression
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>of sanity to the process of oppression. The cen¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>turies-old image of which Hansberry speaks,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>actually a collection of images, is necessary to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>maintain racism. To hate with no justification for
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>hatred, to oppress with no reason for oppression,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>would be recognizably insane. Once an object is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>provided—an object endowed by the oppressor
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>with characteristics that allow hatred, that allow
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>oppression—then hatred and oppression of the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>object can be defended as logical. An insane idea
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>has been made rational. Lillian Smith portrayed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>this basic insanity of segregation in the South she
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>knew:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>As I sit here writing, I can almost touch that little
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>town, so close is the memory of it. There it lies, its
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>main street lined with great oaks, heavy with matted
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>moss that swings softly even now as I remember. A
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>little white town rimmed with Negroes, making a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>deep shadow on the whiteness. There it lies, broken
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>in two by one strange idea. Minds broken in tuen
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>Hearts broken. Conscience torn from acts. A culture
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>split into a thousand pieces. That is segregation. I
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>am remembering: a woman in a mental hospital
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>walking four steps out, four steps in, unable to go
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>any further because she has drawn an invisible line
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>around her small world and is terrified to take one
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>step beyond it.... A man in a Disturbed Ward as¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>signing places&quot; to the other patients and violently
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>insisting that each stay in his place.4
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>&quot;Segregation,&quot; for Smith, described a phenome¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l1' n='N001'/>non deeper than legal statute or town custom.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l2' n='N002'/>She saw segregation as a form of dichotomizing
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l3' n='N003'/>within the white Western male tradition. She ob¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l4' n='N004'/>served, for example, that white women are seg¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l5' n='N005'/>regated from Black women and also objectified
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l6' n='N006'/>within the dominant culture:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l7' n='N007'/>Another split took place.... Somehow much in the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l8' n='N008'/>white woman that (man] could not come to terms
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l9' n='N009'/>with, the schizophrenic split he had made in her
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l10' n='N010'/>nature—the sacred madonna and the bitch he had
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l11' n='N011'/>created of her—could now be projected, in part,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l12' n='N012'/>onto another female: under slavery, he could keep
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l13' n='N013'/>his pure white &quot;madonna&quot; and have his dark tem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l14' n='N014'/>pestuous &quot;prostitute.&quot;... Back of southern people&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l15' n='N015'/>fear of giving up segregation is this fear of giving up
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l16' n='N016'/>the dark woman&quot; who has become a symbol which
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l17' n='N017'/>the men no longer wish to attach to their own
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l18' n='N018'/>womens
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l19' n='N019'/>Smith&apos;s observation is important: White and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l20' n='N020'/>Black women were/are both objectified and split
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l21' n='N021'/>from one another. Ifeel that Smith oversimplified
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l22' n='N022'/>the split, however. For example, the sacred ma¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l23' n='N023'/>donna, in order to maintain her status (and most
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l24' n='N024'/>often she was intent on maintaining her status),
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l25' n='N025'/>had to objectify the Black woman according to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l26' n='N026'/>the white male imagination. The white woman on
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l27' n='N027'/>the slave plantation knew that white men used
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l28' n='N028'/>rape against Black women. She knew that Black
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l29' n='N029'/>women were for the most part fieldhands, work¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>ing alongside men—when they were pregnant,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>when they were nursing. The Black woman was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>made into a sex object, yes, but Smith&apos;s use of the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>word prostitute,&quot; even in quotes, suggests more
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>choice than any slave woman ever had. It also
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>denies or glosses over the use of rapism by white
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>men against Black women as an instrument of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>terror, of oppression.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>Black women have been doubly objectified—
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>as Black, as women; under white supremacy,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>under patriarchy. It has been the task of Black
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>woman artists to transform this objectification:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>to become the subject commenting on the mean¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>ing of the object, or to become the subject reject¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>ing the object and revealing the real experience
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>of being. In her essay In Search of Our Mother&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>Gardens,&quot; Alice Walker ponders the degree of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>difficulty faced by a Black woman in the United
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>States with artistic ambition: &quot;What did it mean
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>for a black woman to be an artist in our grand¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>mothers&apos; time? In our great-grandmothers&apos; day?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>It is a question with an answer cruel enough to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>stop the blood.&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>In her novel Sula, Toni Morrison makes the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>following observation about the seemingly de¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>structive nature of her main character:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>In a way, her strangeness, her naiveté, her craving
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>for the other half of her equation was the conse¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>quence of an idle imagination. Had she paints, or
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>clay, or knew the discipline of the dance, or strings;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>had she anything to engage her tremendous curi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>osity and her gift for metaphor, she might have ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>changed the restlessness and preoccupation with
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>whim for an activity that provided her with all she
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>yearned for. And like any artist with no art form,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>she became dangerous. 7
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>Sula&apos;s tragedy, and the tragedy she represents,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l38' n='N038'/>is &quot;cruel enough to stop the blood.&quot; Because of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l39' n='N039'/>her race, perhaps also because of her sex, she
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l40' n='N040'/>has been shut out from art and denied access to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l41' n='N041'/>art forms. She is an intelligent, thinking woman,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l42' n='N042'/>who ultimately has nowhere to go.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l43' n='N043'/>The objectification of Black women has taken
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l1' n='N001'/>many forms: The Mammy, Mama—wetnurse,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l2' n='N002'/>midwife, cook—usually large, usually dark, com¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l3' n='N003'/>bining humility and capability. The temptress,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l4' n='N004'/>sex-object, whore—sometimes mulatto (from the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l5' n='N005'/>Latin for mule, i.e., a creature unable to repro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l6' n='N006'/>duce herself)—misbegotten and tragic, the power
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l7' n='N007'/>of the master coursing through her powerless
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l8' n='N008'/>veins. These are but two examples which recur
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l9' n='N009'/>in white Western literature and art. And these
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l10' n='N010'/>have been repeated by white women as well as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l11' n='N011'/>white men. There is, of course, &quot;Mammy&quot; in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l12' n='N012'/>Gone with the Wind; and there is Julie, the woe¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l13' n='N013'/>begone quadroon in Edna Ferber&apos;s Showboat.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l14' n='N014'/>Another novel, Imitation of Life by Fanny Hurst,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l15' n='N015'/>attempts to &quot;deal with&quot; both Mammy and mu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l16' n='N016'/>latto.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l17' n='N017'/>By many accounts, Fanny Hurst was a well¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l18' n='N018'/>intentioned liberal. Much has been made, for ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l19' n='N019'/>ample, of the fact that she employed Zora Neale
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l20' n='N020'/>Hurston as her secretary in 1925. But some of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l21' n='N021'/>that history suggests Hurst&apos;s insensitivity to Hur¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l22' n='N022'/>ston&apos;s identity as a Black woman, not to mention
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l23' n='N023'/>a brilliant novelist and writer, among whose sub¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l24' n='N024'/>jects was the self-definition of Black women. On
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l25' n='N025'/>one occasion Hurst, intent on integrating a res¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l26' n='N026'/>taurant in Vermont, prevailed upon Hurston to
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>accompany her—passing Hurston off as an Af¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>rican princess.&quot; Hurston remarked, &quot;Who would
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>have thought that a good meal could be so bit¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>ter.&quot; In this incident Hurst, the would-be liber¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>ator, reveals herself as objectifier. This phenom¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>enon occurred over and again during the Civil
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>Rights Movement. It was most commonly ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>pressed in the notion that unless Black people
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>behaved in certain ways, allowing whites to over¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>see and control their access to liberation, that
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>liberation would not be achieved. What is pres¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>ent is the need for whites to maintain power, and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>limit the access of Black people to that power,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>which, finally, is the power of self-definition.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>Imitation of Life, published in 1933, concerns
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>the relationship between two dyads: a white
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>woman and her daughter and a Black woman
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>and her daughter. Both pairs are essentially
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>alone in the world. The Black woman, Delilah, is
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>hired to run the house by the white woman, Miss
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>B., who has been recently widowed. Delilah car¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>ries with her various recipes, and these prove to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>be the &quot;salvation&quot; of Miss B. and family. In a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>relatively short time, Miss B. is the proprietor of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>a chain of restaurants in which Delilah&apos;s food is
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>the main attraction, and which are recognized by
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>a likeness of Delilah on the sign. When Miss B.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>hits on the idea of photographing Delilah as the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>advertising gimmick for the enterprise, she
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>dresses Delilah as a chef. Delilah, faithful ser¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>vant throughout the book, in this one instance
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>asks her employer not to humiliate her but to al¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>low her to wear her best clothes.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>Miss B., however, prevails. Hurst describes
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>the final result: &quot;Breaking through a white back¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>ground, as through a paper-covered hoop, there
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>burst the chocolate-and-cream effulgence that
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l38' n='N038'/>was Delilah.&quot;2 Here is Aunt Jemima; the female
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l39' n='N039'/>server of Sanka; even Mrs. Butterworth, whose
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l40' n='N040'/>color literally pours forth. Here is an instance of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l41' n='N041'/>the brainchild of a Black woman, her recipe, her
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l42' n='N042'/>art form, passed through generations of Black
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l43' n='N043'/>women, co-opted and sold, with a caricature of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l44' n='N044'/>the artist used to ensure its success.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l45' n='N045'/>In and around the main theme of the novel¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l46' n='N046'/>the &quot;success&quot; of Miss B. as an independent
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l47' n='N047'/>businesswoman&quot;—is the subplot concerning De¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l48' n='N048'/>lilah&apos;s light-skinned daughter, Peola—unable to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l49' n='N049'/>be white, unwilling to be Black, in the course of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l50' n='N050'/>her dilemma denying her mother. Peola moves
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l51' n='N051'/>west, works as a librarian, passes for white, and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l52' n='N052'/>marries a white man. She has herself &quot;steri¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l53' n='N053'/>lized,&quot; eliminating any chance of throwback.&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l54' n='N054'/>Her husband is also mutilated, having lost part of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l55' n='N055'/>a hand. Perhaps he is all she is entitled to. Delilah
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l56' n='N056'/>has the final say: &quot;Black women who pass, pass
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l57' n='N057'/>into damnation.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l58' n='N058'/>Taken together, Delilah and Peola represent
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l59' n='N059'/>what George Frederickson has characterized as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l60' n='N060'/>soft&quot; and hard&quot; stereotypes.10 Bell Hooks also
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l61' n='N061'/>juxtaposes two stereotypes of Black women:
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l62' n='N062'/>Mammy and Sapphire.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l63' n='N063'/>It is not too difficult to imagine how whites came to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l64' n='N064'/>create the black mammy figure.... She was first
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l65' n='N065'/>36
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>and foremost asexual and consequently had to be
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>fat (preferably obese); she also had to give the im¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>pression of not being clean so she was the wearer of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>a greasy dirty headrag; her too tight shoes from
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>which emerged her large feet were further confir¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>mation of her bestial cowlike quality. Her greatest
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>virtue was of course her love for white folk which
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>she willingly and passively served.... In a sense
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>whites created in the mammy figure a black woman
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>who embodied solely those characteristics they as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>colonizers wished to exploit. 11
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>As Sapphires, black women were depicted as evil,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>treacherous, bitchy, stubborn, and hateful, in short
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>all that the mammy was not. White men could justify
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>their de-humanization and sexual exploitation of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l16' n='N016'/>black women by arguing that they possessed inher¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l17' n='N017'/>ent evil demonic qualities.... And white women
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l18' n='N018'/>could use the image of the evil sinful black woman
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l19' n='N019'/>to emphasize their own innocence and purity. 12
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l20' n='N020'/>To talk about the history of Black women in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l21' n='N021'/>America, and of the various images I have men¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l22' n='N022'/>tioned, we must begin with the woman who was a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l23' n='N023'/>slave. Who was she? How did she survive? How
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l24' n='N024'/>many of her did survive? What did she teach her
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l25' n='N025'/>children? What was her relationship to her hus¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l26' n='N026'/>band? What were her options?
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l27' n='N027'/>She could be lynched, beaten, tortured, muti¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l28' n='N028'/>lated, raped. She could have her children sold
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l29' n='N029'/>away from her. She was forbidden education.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l30' n='N030'/>She was considered a beast of burden. She was
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l31' n='N031'/>subject to the white man&apos;s power and the white
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l32' n='N032'/>woman&apos;s powerlessness masking as whim. Her
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l33' n='N033'/>womb was a commodity of the slavemaster, and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l34' n='N034'/>her childlessness, a liability of the slavemaster.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l35' n='N035'/>She was not expected to love—but she did. She
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l36' n='N036'/>was not expected to run away—but she did. She
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l37' n='N037'/>was known to commit infanticide and induce
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l38' n='N038'/>abortion rather than have her child be a slave.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l39' n='N039'/>She was known to commit acts of violence and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l40' n='N040'/>rebellion—with magic, poison, force, even with
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l41' n='N041'/>spit. And she sometimes learned to read and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l42' n='N042'/>write and sustain the art forms she had carried
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l43' n='N043'/>with her.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l44' n='N044'/>In 1960 Lorraine Hansberry was commis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l45' n='N045'/>sioned to write a play about slavery for national
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l46' n='N046'/>television. She wrote The Drinking Gourd, about
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l47' n='N047'/>a Black family and a white family under slavery.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l48' n='N048'/>In it, as in Raisin, Hansberry attempted to con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l49' n='N049'/>tradict the myths about Black people and to re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l50' n='N050'/>capture and recast history. Her play was never
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l51' n='N051'/>performed; it was judged &quot;too controversial&quot; by
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l52' n='N052'/>the network. Hansberry had described Lena
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l53' n='N053'/>Younger, her mother-figure in Raisin, as an af¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l54' n='N054'/>firmation,&quot; as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l55' n='N055'/>the black matriarch incarnate, the bulwark of the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l56' n='N056'/>Negro family since slavery, the embodiment of the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l57' n='N057'/>Negro will to transcendence. It is she, who in the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l58' n='N058'/>mind of the black poet scrubs the floors of a nation
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l59' n='N059'/>in order to create black diplomats and university
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l60' n='N060'/>professors. It is she, while seeming to cling to tradi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l61' n='N061'/>tional restraints, who drives the young on into the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l62' n='N062'/>fire hoses. And one day simply refuses to move to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l63' n='N063'/>the back of the bus in Montgomery. Or goes out and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l64' n='N064'/>buys a house in an all-white neighborhood where
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l65' n='N065'/>her children may possibly be killed by bricks thrown
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l66' n='N066'/>through the windows by a shrieking racist mob. 13
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>With her mother-figure in The Drinking Gourd,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>Hansberry went further. Rissa, the slavemother,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>does what the Black mother-figure in white Amer¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>ican mythology has never done: She, in effect,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>kills a white man (the &quot;good&quot; white man), and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>gives his guns to her children, after her son has
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>been blinded for learning to read. The play ends
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>as Rissa and her band of revolutionaries escape
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>into the woods.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>We know that Black women—mothers and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>nonmothers—have been intrinsic to the activism
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l12' n='N012'/>of Black history. There is the following story, for
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l13' n='N013'/>example, quoted by Angela Davis:
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l14' n='N014'/>She didn’t work in the field. She worked at a loom.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l15' n='N015'/>She worked so long and so often that once she went
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l16' n='N016'/>to sleep at the loom. Her master&apos;s boy saw her and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l17' n='N017'/>told his mother. His mother told him to take a whip
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l18' n='N018'/>and wear her out. He took a stick and went out to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l19' n='N019'/>beat her awake. He beat my mother till she woke
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l20' n='N020'/>up. When she woke up, she took a pole out of the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l21' n='N021'/>loom and beat him nearly to death with it. He hol¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l22' n='N022'/>lered, &quot;Don&apos;t beat me no more, and I won&apos;t let &apos;em
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l23' n='N023'/>whip you.&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l24' n='N024'/>She said, I&apos;m going to kill you. These black titties
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l25' n='N025'/>sucked you, and then you come out here to beat
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l26' n='N026'/>me.&quot; And when she left him, he wasn&apos;t able to walk.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l27' n='N027'/>And that was the last I seen of her until after free¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l28' n='N028'/>dom. She went out and got an old cow that she used
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l29' n='N029'/>to milk—Dolly, she called it. She rode away from
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l30' n='N030'/>the plantation because she knew they would kill her
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l31' n='N031'/>if she stayed. 14
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l1' n='N001'/>This story tells of a Black woman in the act of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l2' n='N002'/>freeing herself. A selfish need for freedom, and a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l3' n='N003'/>recognition that freedom is their right, is some¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l4' n='N004'/>thing usually denied to Black women historically,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l5' n='N005'/>even when they are recognized as liberators of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l6' n='N006'/>their race. But Fannie Lou Hamer, Ida B. Wells,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l7' n='N007'/>Mary McLeod Bethune, Sojourner Truth—and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l8' n='N008'/>the many women whose names we do not know—
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l9' n='N009'/>all felt a personal desire for freedom, which came
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l10' n='N010'/>from a feeling of self-esteem, self-worth, and they
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l11' n='N011'/>translated this into a political commitment that
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l12' n='N012'/>their people also be free. Harriet Tubman said:
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l13' n='N013'/>Ilooked at my hands to see if I was de same person
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l14' n='N014'/>now I was free. Dere was such a glory ober ebery¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l15' n='N015'/>thing, de sun came like gold trou de trees, and ober
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l16' n='N016'/>de fields, and I felt like I was in heaven.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l17' n='N017'/>I had crossed de line of which I had so long been
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l18' n='N018'/>dreaming. I was free; but dere was no one to wel¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l19' n='N019'/>come me to de land of freedom, I was a stranger in a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l20' n='N020'/>strange land, and my home after all was down in de
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l21' n='N021'/>ole cabin quarter, wid de ole folks, and my brudders
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l22' n='N022'/>and sisters. But to dis solemn resolution I came;
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l23' n='N023'/>was free, and dey should be free also; I would make
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l24' n='N024'/>a home for dem in de North, and de Lord helping
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l25' n='N025'/>me, I would bring dem all dere. 15
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l26' n='N026'/>The artist, like the liberator, must begin with
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l27' n='N027'/>herself.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l28' n='N028'/>Edmonia Lewis (1843-1900?) is the first wom¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l29' n='N029'/>an of color we know whose work as a visual artist
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l30' n='N030'/>was recognized by the dominant culture. During
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l31' n='N031'/>her life as a sculptor she was confronted with the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_8_1l32' n='N032'/>objectification of herself as Black and female.
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>While her work was not ignored, it was given a
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>secondary place of importance by most critics.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>Lewis was seen as a &quot;wonder,&quot; a work of art in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>herself—a curiosity. The following excerpt from
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>an abolitionist newspaper describes the artist
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>and her marble group Forever Free (1867):
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>No one... could look upon this piece of sculpture
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>without profound emotion. The noble figure of the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>man, his very muscles seeming to swell with grati¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>tude; the expression of the right now to protect,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>with which he throws his arms around his kneeling
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>wife; the Praise de Lord&quot; hovering on their lips;
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>the broken chain—all so instinct with life, telling
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>in the very poetry of stone the story of the last ten
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>years. And when it is remembered who created this
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>group, an added interest is given to it.... Will any¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>one believe it was the small hand of a girl that
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>wrought the marble and kindled the light within it?
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>—a girl of dusky hue, mixed Indian and African,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>who not more than eight years ago sat down on the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>steps of City Hall to eat the dry crackers with which
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>alone her empty purse allowed her to satisfy her
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>hunger; but as she sat and thought... of her home¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>less state, something caught her eye, the hunger of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>the stomach ceased, but the hunger of the soul
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>began. That quiet statue of the good old Franklin.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>kindled the latent genius which was enshrined with¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>in her, as her own group was in marble, till her
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>chisel brought it out. For weeks she haunted that
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>spot and the State House, where she could see
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>Washington and Webster. She asked questions, and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>found that such things were first made in clay. She
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>got a lump of hard mud, shaped her some sticks,
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l1' n='N001'/>and, her heart divided between art and the terrible
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l2' n='N002'/>need for freedom.. she wrought out... an admir¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l3' n='N003'/>able bust of [Col. Robert Gould Shaw, white Bos¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l4' n='N004'/>tonian commander of a company of Black troops
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l5' n='N005'/>organized due to pressure from Frederick Doug-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l6' n='N006'/>lass). 16
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l7' n='N007'/>When this article was written Lewis was a well¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l8' n='N008'/>known sculptor living in Rome, with a degree in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l9' n='N009'/>liberal arts from Oberlin College. She had studied
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l10' n='N010'/>sculpture with Edward Brackett, a prominent
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l11' n='N011'/>neoclassical artist. She was not particularly in¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l12' n='N012'/>terested in creating likenesses of Franklin, Wash¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l13' n='N013'/>ington, or Webster—her interest in these pieces
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l14' n='N014'/>would have been purely technical, not inspira¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l15' n='N015'/>tional. The only leader&quot; of white America she
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l16' n='N016'/>ever depicted was Abraham Lincoln. All her
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l17' n='N017'/>other subjects were drawn from her history as
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l18' n='N018'/>the daughter of a Black man and a Chippewa
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l19' n='N019'/>woman, and her consciousness of racism.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l20' n='N020'/>Just as the author patronizes the artist, so
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l21' n='N021'/>does he minimize the political statement of her
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l22' n='N022'/>work. For instance, he uses the word &quot;gratitude&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l23' n='N023'/>rather than &quot;pride,&quot; or triumph,&quot; in his com¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l24' n='N024'/>ments on the male figure; he focuses on the arm
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l25' n='N025'/>which embraces the woman, rather than on the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l26' n='N026'/>hand which is raised, the broken chain dangling
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l27' n='N027'/>from the wrist. He cites the struggle of the last
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l28' n='N028'/>ten&quot; years with typical white solipsism. In addi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l29' n='N029'/>tion, his &quot;Praise de Lord&quot; does not allow us
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l30' n='N030'/>knowledge of the politics of Black Americans, to
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l31' n='N031'/>which religion has been historically intrinsic.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l32' n='N032'/>Rather, it can be read in such a way that the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_6_1l33' n='N033'/>triumph is taken from the hands of those who
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>have won it and placed somewhere &quot;out there.&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>It is commonly believed that the slaves were
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>freed by white Northerners. But as W. E. B.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>Du Bois observed: &quot;In proportion to population,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>more Negroes than whites fought in the Civil
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>War. These people, withdrawn from the support
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>of the Confederacy, with the threat of the with¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>drawal of millions more, made the opposition of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>the slaveholder useless, unless they themselves
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>freed and armed their own slaves.&quot; 17 The jour¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>ney out of slavery was one in which Black people
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>played a dominant role. It is this that Lewis is
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>commemorating in her work. She had earlier
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>commemorated the slave-woman in her piece
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>Freedwoman on First Hearing of Her Liberty
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>(which has been lost to us).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>In an interview with the Lorain County News,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>Lewis spoke of her childhood:
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>My mother was a wild Indian and was born in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>Albany, of copper color and with straight black
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>hair. There she made and sold moccasins. My fath¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>er, who was a Negro, and a gentleman&apos;s servant,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>saw her and married her. Mother often left home
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>and wandered with her people, whose habits she
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>could not forget, and thus we were brought up in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>the same wild manner. Until I was twelve years old,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>I led this wandering life, fishing and swimming...
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>and making moccasins. 18
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>Alice Walker speaks about looking &quot;high—and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>low&quot; for the artistic antecedents of Black women;
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>she speaks specifically of her own mother&apos;s gar¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l1' n='N001'/>den—how this was the place of her mother&apos;s cre¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l2' n='N002'/>ative expression, the background against which
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l3' n='N003'/>Walker&apos;s own work proceeded: &quot;Guided by my
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l4' n='N004'/>heritage of a love of beauty and a respect for
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l5' n='N005'/>strength—in search of my mother&apos;s garden I
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l6' n='N006'/>found my own.&quot; This statement makes me think
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l7' n='N007'/>of Lewis&apos;s mother, her independence and her
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l8' n='N008'/>craft. The fact that she trained her daughter in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l9' n='N009'/>her art form. That she taught her strength.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l10' n='N010'/>Lewis&apos;s sculpture, because she chose primari¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l11' n='N011'/>ly to depict subjects directly related to her own
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l12' n='N012'/>and her people&apos;s experience, has a certain pow¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l13' n='N013'/>er. Where her pieces lose power is in the style
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l14' n='N014'/>she adopted and the material she used: the neo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l15' n='N015'/>classical style, with its emphatic focus on Greek
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l16' n='N016'/>idealization, and the pristine whiteness of the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l17' n='N017'/>marble, which supports the narrowness of the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l18' n='N018'/>style—so that a black face must appear white
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l19' n='N019'/>and be carved according to principles of beauty
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l20' n='N020'/>which are white, &quot;fine&quot; features as perfection.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l21' n='N021'/>The 19th century was the century of jubilee, of a
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l22' n='N022'/>women&apos;s movement, and of a revolutionary move¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l23' n='N023'/>ment in Europe. But these moral reactions need
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l24' n='N024'/>to be understood against the immorality which
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l25' n='N025'/>dominated that century: the &quot;white man&apos;s bur¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l26' n='N026'/>den,&quot; the political/religious/economic affirma¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l27' n='N027'/>tion of the supremacy of the white race. The neo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l28' n='N028'/>classical style arose quite naturally from all this,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l29' n='N029'/>based as it was on the imitation of fifth-century
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l30' n='N030'/>Athens, a slave-owning, gynephobic society, but
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l31' n='N031'/>one popularly regarded as high-minded and dem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l32' n='N032'/>ocratic. In Lewis&apos;s Forever Free the limitations
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_7_1l33' n='N033'/>placed on a Black and Indian artist working in
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>this style and with this material are evident: the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>curly hair of the male figure and the broken
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>chain are the only signs that these are people of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>color.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>Of her sculpture Hagar (1875), Lewis said: &quot;I
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>have a strong sympathy for all women who have
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>struggled and suffered.&quot;2 Again, we have to look
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>beyond the actual figure to the story Lewis is
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>illustrating to find the political/historical state¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>ment in her work. Hagar was an Egyptian, a
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>woman of color, the slave of Abraham&apos;s wife,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>Sarah. Hagar was &quot;given&quot; to Abraham by Sarah
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>so that he might have an heir; and she was the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>mother of his first-born son, Ishmael. Then Isaac
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>was born to Abraham and Sarah. The book of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>Genesis continues the story:
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>Sarah saw the son of Hagar the Egyptian, whom she
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>had borne to Abraham, playing with her son Isaac.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>So she said to Abraham, Cast out this slave woman
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>with her son; for the son of this slave woman shall
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>not be heir with my son Isaac.&quot; And the thing was
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>very displeasing to Abraham on account of his son.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>But God said to Abraham, &quot;Be not displeased be¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>cause of the lad and because of your slave woman;
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>whatever Sarah says to you, do as she tells you, for
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>through Isaac shall your descendents be named.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>So Abraham rose early in the morning... and sent
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>[Hagar] away. And she departed, and wandered in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>the wilderness of Beer-sheba.21
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>It is quite impossible to read this story and ne
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>think of the Black woman under slavery, rape¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l1' n='N001'/>by the white master, serving the white master&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l2' n='N002'/>wife, bearing a child by the white master, and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l3' n='N003'/>bearing the responsibility for that child—with no
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l4' n='N004'/>power over her own fate, or that of her child.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l5' n='N005'/>Lewis&apos;s choice of Hagar as a symbol for Black
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l6' n='N006'/>slave-women also fits into the Black tradition in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l7' n='N007'/>America, one immersed in the stories of the Bible
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l8' n='N008'/>(often the Bible was the only access slaves had to
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l9' n='N009'/>the written word), and characterized by the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l10' n='N010'/>translation of these stories according to Black
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l11' n='N011'/>history.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l12' n='N012'/>In reading this account from Genesis, I am
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l13' n='N013'/>also thrown back to Lillian Smith&apos;s description of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l14' n='N014'/>the split between Black and white women. It is
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l15' n='N015'/>Sarah who is made responsible for the banish¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l16' n='N016'/>ment of Hagar. Her husband and his god remain
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l17' n='N017'/>blameless, even noble.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l18' n='N018'/>After approximately ten years of recognition,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l19' n='N019'/>Edmonia Lewis disappeared.&quot; This sort of fall¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l20' n='N020'/>ing out of fame is usually seen as tragic, but I
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l21' n='N021'/>wonder what happened to her? Was her disap¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l22' n='N022'/>pearance by choice? Or did she disappear be¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l23' n='N023'/>cause she was a Black woman artist who was no
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l24' n='N024'/>longer in vogue, because she was no longer seen
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l25' n='N025'/>as &quot;exotic“?
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l26' n='N026'/>In contrast to Lewis&apos;s white marble sculp¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l27' n='N027'/>tures, Elizabeth Catlett&apos;s figures are done in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l28' n='N028'/>brown wood or terra cotta, or another material
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l29' n='N029'/>which suggests the color of her subjects, or at
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l30' n='N030'/>least that her subjects are people of color. No
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l31' n='N031'/>white Western features replace the character¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l32' n='N032'/>istics of Black and other Third World people. But
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l33' n='N033'/>Catlett is a contemporary artist, one who rela¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_8_1l34' n='N034'/>37
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>tively early in her career left this country and
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>moved to a country of colored people—Mexico
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>Yet her piece Homage to My Young Black
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>Sisters (1969), when we make allowances over
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>time and across space, is not that far removed in
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>political intent from Lewis&apos;s Hagar. In form the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>differences are enormous: Hagar&apos;s hands are
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>clasped in front of her, in resignation, in suppli¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>cation—in the wilderness she has to turn to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>Abraham&apos;s god to save the life of her son. The
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>female figure of Homage has one arm raised in a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>powerful and defiant fist. The similarity betweer
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>the two pieces is that both, I think, represent part
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>of the history of Black women, particularly Black
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>motherhood, in America. The midsection of the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>Homage figure is an open space, which I take as
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>Catlett&apos;s statement of the historical white denia
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>of Black women&apos;s right to motherhood in any self¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>defining way, and of the theft of the children of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l16' n='N016'/>Black women, and of what these children repre¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l17' n='N017'/>sent—whether through the laws of the slavocra¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l18' n='N018'/>cy or those of postindustrial America.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l19' n='N019'/>Catlett uses the theme of Black women and
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l20' n='N020'/>children often in her work, depicting over anc
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_4_1l21' n='N021'/>again the heroism required of Black women sim¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>ply to survive. In her lithographs, engravings
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>and linocuts, Catlett seeks to tell the history of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>Black women, breaking away from the objectifi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>cation of the dominant culture. We might, for ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>ample, look at her wood engraving of Harriet
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>Tubman (1975), in contrast to Judy Chicago&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>Sojourner Truth plate in the Dinner Party.22 Cat¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>lett&apos;s Harriet dominates the foreground; one pow¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>erful arm points forward, the other holds a rifle
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>She is tall and she is strong and she is Black. In
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>the background are the men and women she
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l12' n='N012'/>leads. What is interesting to me is the expression
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l13' n='N013'/>on Tubman&apos;s face—she is fiercely determined.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l14' n='N014'/>This expression is repeated in the group she
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l15' n='N015'/>leads. There is no passivity here, no resignation,
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l16' n='N016'/>no impotent tears, no humming. Rather, this is
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l17' n='N017'/>a portrait of the activity of a people in conflict
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l18' n='N018'/>with their oppression.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l19' n='N019'/>Catlett has stated that art should be obviously
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l20' n='N020'/>political, available to the people who are its sub¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l21' n='N021'/>ject. We have no such clear statement from
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l22' n='N022'/>Lewis, but we must wonder for whom her work
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l23' n='N023'/>was done, finally; and whether she stopped work¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l24' n='N024'/>ing as she did because of a distance between her
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l25' n='N025'/>art and her subjects.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l26' n='N026'/>Harriet Powers (1837-1911) was a quilt-maker
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l27' n='N027'/>(only two of her quilts are known to survive). She
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l28' n='N028'/>worked in appliqué, a method of needlework de¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l29' n='N029'/>vised by the Fon of Dahomey, brought to this
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l30' n='N030'/>country on slave ships.23 Betye Saar is a collec¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l31' n='N031'/>tor; an artist who constructs images with various
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l32' n='N032'/>objects, mementos, photographs, bits and pieces
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l33' n='N033'/>picked up here and there and saved; things used
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l34' n='N034'/>in another context, by other hands. Both Powers
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l35' n='N035'/>and Saar endow their work with a belief in the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l36' n='N036'/>spiritual nature of the ordinary. Powers&apos;s quilts,
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l37' n='N037'/>constructed from the scraps saved by a poor
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l38' n='N038'/>Black woman, convey a real portrait of one Black
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l39' n='N039'/>woman&apos;s religion and politics. Marie Jeane
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l40' n='N040'/>Adams states: The more one examines the style
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l41' n='N041'/>and content of Harriet Powers&apos;s work, the more
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l42' n='N042'/>one sees that it projects a grand spiritual vision
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l43' n='N043'/>24
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l44' n='N044'/>that breaks out of the confines of folk art.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l45' n='N045'/>The employment of once-used objects by these
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l46' n='N046'/>artists is one aspect of their work which needs
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l47' n='N047'/>further thought. In the history of white Western
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l48' n='N048'/>art there is an obsession with the purity of mater
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l49' n='N049'/>ials. And also with their value. For one exam¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l50' n='N050'/>ple: In the art of 15th-century Italy, and even
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l51' n='N051'/>earlier, the color ultramarine was often used to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l52' n='N052'/>depict the most important figure or feature in a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l53' n='N053'/>painting or fresco. This choice was made with
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l54' n='N054'/>the knowledge that the color was created by
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l55' n='N055'/>crushing lapis lazuli, the most expensive source
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l56' n='N056'/>of pigment after gold.2 And this choice extended
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l57' n='N057'/>to the very meaning of the work produced. In the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l58' n='N058'/>art of Powers and Saar, the sources of the artist&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l59' n='N059'/>materials are also important, but the choice is
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l60' n='N060'/>more deeply personal. We might ask: How much
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l61' n='N061'/>does the power of a work of art consist in the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l62' n='N062'/>material which makes up that work? What is the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l63' n='N063'/>difference between a work of art made with
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l64' n='N064'/>things specifically employed in that work and
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l65' n='N065'/>never before, and one which uses only things
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l66' n='N066'/>used before? Is one more useful than the other?
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l67' n='N067'/>More magical than the other?
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l68' n='N068'/>We know of Harriet Powers&apos;s work partly be¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l69' n='N069'/>cause of a white woman—Jennie Smith, herself
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l70' n='N070'/>an artist—who left an 18-page monograph on the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l71' n='N071'/>artist. She recorded the following in 1891, when
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l72' n='N072'/>Powers finally agreed to sell her a quilt:
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l73' n='N073'/>I found the owner, a negro woman, who lived in the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l74' n='N074'/>country on a little farm whereon she and her hus¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l75' n='N075'/>band made a respectable living.... Last year I sent
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l76' n='N076'/>word that I would buy it if she still wanted to dis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l77' n='N077'/>pose of it. She arrived one afternoon in front of my
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l78' n='N078'/>door...with the precious burden...encased in a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l79' n='N079'/>clean crocus sack.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_5_1l80' n='N080'/>She offered it for ten dollars, but I told her I only
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l1' n='N001'/>had five to give. After going out consulting with her
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l2' n='N002'/>husband she returned and said, &quot;Owin&apos; to de hard¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l3' n='N003'/>ness of de times, my old man lows I&apos;d better teck
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l4' n='N004'/>hit. Not being a new woman she obeyed.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l5' n='N005'/>After giving me a full description of each scene with
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l6' n='N006'/>great earnestness, she departed but has been back
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l7' n='N007'/>several times to visit the darling offspring of her
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l8' n='N008'/>brain. 26
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l9' n='N009'/>Powers&apos;s second quilt—now in the Boston
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l10' n='N010'/>Museum of Fine Arts—was commissioned in 1898
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l11' n='N011'/>by the wives of professors at Atlanta University.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l12' n='N012'/>This quilt, known as the second Bible quilt, con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l13' n='N013'/>sists of five columns, each divided into three
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l14' n='N014'/>frames. All the frames deal with the theme of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l15' n='N015'/>God&apos;s vengeance and redemption, illustrated
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l16' n='N016'/>through Biblical images and representations of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l17' n='N017'/>cataclysmic events in 18th- and 19th-century
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l18' n='N018'/>America.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l19' n='N019'/>This. much-exhibited quilt portrays fifteen scenes.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l20' n='N020'/>Ten are drawn from familiar Bible stories which
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l21' n='N021'/>concern the threat of God&apos;s judgment inextricably
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l22' n='N022'/>fused with His mercy and man&apos;s redemption, among
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l23' n='N023'/>which are the Fall, Moses in the wilderness, Job&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l24' n='N024'/>trials, Jonah and the whale, the Baptism of Christ
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l25' n='N025'/>and the Crucifixion....Four others depict astro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l26' n='N026'/>nomical or meteorological events, only one of which,
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l27' n='N027'/>an extremely cold spell in 1895 in the eastern United
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l28' n='N028'/>States, occurred in Mrs. Powers&apos; adult life. Given
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l29' n='N029'/>Mrs. Powers&apos; intensely religious outlook, she inter¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l30' n='N030'/>preted these events in the celestial atmosphere as
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l31' n='N031'/>messages from God to mankind about punishment,
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l32' n='N032'/>apocalypse, and salvation. 27
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l33' n='N033'/>The one frame which does not fit into this cate¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l34' n='N034'/>gorization is the one which, as Marie Jeane
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l35' n='N035'/>Adams observes, is the key to the quilt. Powers
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l36' n='N036'/>left a description in her own words of all the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l37' n='N037'/>scenes in the quilt; of this particular frame, she
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l38' n='N038'/>said:
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l39' n='N039'/>Rich people who were taught nothing of God. Bob
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l40' n='N040'/>Johnson and Kate Bell of Virginia. They told their
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l41' n='N041'/>parents to stop the clock at one and tomorrow it
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l42' n='N042'/>would strike one and so it did. This was the signal
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l43' n='N043'/>that they had entered everlasting punishment. The
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l44' n='N044'/>independent hog which ran 500 miles from Ga. to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l45' n='N045'/>Va. Her name was Betts. 28
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l46' n='N046'/>The frame has a clock in the center, stars and a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l47' n='N047'/>moon scattered around, two human figures. At
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l48' n='N048'/>the bottom is the independent hog named Betts,
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l49' n='N049'/>the largest figure of the quilt. Metallic thread
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l50' n='N050'/>outlines the clockface and creates a tiara around
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l51' n='N051'/>the head of the white woman Kate Bell. Betts is
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r_6_1l52' n='N052'/>made from gray cloth, but she is placed over a
			</p>
			<pb n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>swatch of orange so that her figure unmistakably
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>stands out.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>This quilt represents a great spiritual vision,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>but it also represents a great political vision: as
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>well as hope, it represents rage. It is a safe guess
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>that Bob Johnson and Kate Bell of Virginia were a
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>son and daughter of the slavocracy. They stand
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>surounded by scenes representing the punish¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>ment meted out to those who are arrogant and
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>self-serving, and the redemption promised those
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>who are righteous. In this particular frame it is
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>their sin of pride which has damned them; and
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>Powers is clear in her belief that their damnation
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>is well-earned. In contrast is the dominating fig¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>ure of Betts, who in an act of self-liberation goes
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>free. Her 500-mile flight from Georgia to Virginia
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>is, as Adams points out, a reference to one route
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>traveled by runaway slaves. And Betts is undeni¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>ably female—her teats hang down from her gray¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>cloth body. I think of Dolly—the cow in the anec¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>dote cited above—being ridden away by a Black
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>woman. And I think of the white idea of Black
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>women as beasts of burden, mules,&quot; farm ani¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>mals; of the image of Harriet Tubman being
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>forced to draw a wagon for the entertainment of
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>white folks. I take Betts to be a metaphor for this
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>experience. Angela Davis has quoted Frederick
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>Law Olmstead&apos;s description of a slave crew in
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>Mississippi returning from the fields:
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>[I saw] forty of the largest and strongest women I
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>ever saw together; they were all in a simple uniform
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>dress of a bluish check stuff; their legs and feet
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>were bare; they carried themselves loftily, each
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>having a hoe over the shoulder, and walking with a
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>free, powerful swing like chausseurs on the march. 29
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>It would be very simple to romanticize this
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>group of women. But, as Davis says, it is not slav¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>ery and the slave system that have made them
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>strong; it is the experience of their labor and
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>their knowledge of themselves as producers and
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>creators. She quotes Marx: &quot;labor is the living,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>shaping fire; it represents the impermanence of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>things, their temporality. Davis makes a brilli
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>ant connection here:
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l16' n='N016'/>perhaps these women had learned to extract
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l17' n='N017'/>from the oppressive circumstances of their lives the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l18' n='N018'/>strength they needed to resist the daily dehumani¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l19' n='N019'/>zation of slavery. Their awareness of their endless
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_4_1l20' n='N020'/>capacity for hard work may have imparted to them
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>a confidence in their ability to struggle for them¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>selves, their families and their people. 30
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>Black women were not dehumanized under slav¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>ery; they were dehumanized in white minds. I re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>turn again and again in my own mind to the ad¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>jective &quot;independent,&quot; which Powers uses to de¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>scribe Betts, a &quot;chasseur on the march.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>It is not that far a distance from Lewis&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>Hagar, to Catlett&apos;s Homage, to Powers&apos;s Betts, to
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>Betye Saar&apos;s Aunt Jemima. Saar&apos;s construction,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>entitled The Liberation of Aunt Jemima, is per¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l12' n='N012'/>haps the most obvious illustration of what I mean
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l13' n='N013'/>by the title of this essay: &quot;Object into Subject.&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l14' n='N014'/>Here is the most popularized image of the Mammy
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l15' n='N015'/>— in the center of the piece she is a cookie jar,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l16' n='N016'/>the source of nourishment for others; behind her
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l17' n='N017'/>are faces cut from the pancake mix. In front of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l18' n='N018'/>the central figure is another image of Mammy,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l19' n='N019'/>holding a white baby. And there is a broom along¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l20' n='N020'/>side the central figure. But she also holds a pistol
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l21' n='N021'/>and a rifle; and the skirt of Mammy with the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l22' n='N022'/>white baby forms an unmistakable Black fist.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l23' n='N023'/>Saar&apos;s message is clear: Aunt Jemima will free
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l24' n='N024'/>herself.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l25' n='N025'/>In an interview in Black Art, Saar described
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l26' n='N026'/>the components she uses in her work:
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l27' n='N027'/>They are all found objects or discarded objects, so
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l28' n='N028'/>they have to be remnants. They are connected with
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l29' n='N029'/>another sensitivity so it has to be a memory of be¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l30' n='N030'/>longing to another object, or at least having another
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l31' n='N031'/>function. 31
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l32' n='N032'/>Aunt Jemima has been created by another sensi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l33' n='N033'/>tivity than that of the artist who has made this
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l34' n='N034'/>portrait. Aunt Jemima has a memory of belonging
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l35' n='N035'/>to someone else, of being at the service of some¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l36' n='N036'/>one else. She exists against an image, which
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l37' n='N037'/>exists in another mind. The cookie jar is a rem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l38' n='N038'/>nant of another life: most likely she &quot;lived&apos; on the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l39' n='N039'/>kitchen counter of a white family, maybe Saar
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l40' n='N040'/>found her discarded on a white elephant table, or
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l41' n='N041'/>at a garage sale. She has appeared to me in my
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l42' n='N042'/>travels, usually turning up in rural antique stores
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l43' n='N043'/>or church basements, labeled &quot;collectible. The
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l44' n='N044'/>picture of Mammy with the white baby reminds
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l45' n='N045'/>me first of old magazine advertisements, usually,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l46' n='N046'/>as Irecall, for soap or cereal or other necessities
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l47' n='N047'/>of the servant role. And I additionally recall the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l48' n='N048'/>many films of the &apos;40s and &apos;50s about white middle¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l49' n='N049'/>class America, in which a large Black woman
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l50' n='N050'/>who worked in the kitchen was always present
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l51' n='N051'/>but only occasionally given a line to speak. She
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l52' n='N052'/>was played by Louise Beavers, Hattie McDaniel,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l53' n='N053'/>or Ethel Waters—and she was usually charac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l54' n='N054'/>terized by her loyalty to the white family for
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l55' n='N055'/>whom she worked. She also appeared on televi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l56' n='N056'/>sion: &quot;Beulah&quot; was a program in which she was
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l57' n='N057'/>featured. She was kind, honest, a good cook,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l58' n='N058'/>always with a song to hum her troubles away;
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l59' n='N059'/>and as usual, devoted to those white folks.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l60' n='N060'/>All but three of the elements in Saar&apos;s con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l61' n='N061'/>struction are traditional to Aunt Jemima; the two
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l62' n='N062'/>guns and the fist are not. Saar, by including these
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l63' n='N063'/>unfamiliar aspects has changed the function of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l64' n='N064'/>the figure she is representing. She has combined
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l65' n='N065'/>the myth with the reality of Black women&apos;s his¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l66' n='N066'/>toric opposition to their oppression.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l67' n='N067'/>This representation of Aunt Jemima is star¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l68' n='N068'/>tling. All of us who have grown up with the mythi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l69' n='N069'/>cal figure of Aunt Jemima and her equally mythi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l70' n='N070'/>cal attributes—whether or not we recognized
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l71' n='N071'/>they were mythic—have been affected. We may
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l72' n='N072'/>not have known her, but aren&apos;t we somehow con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l73' n='N073'/>vinced that somewhere she exists, or at least has
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l74' n='N074'/>existed? The last thing we would expect would be
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l75' n='N075'/>that she would carry a gun, or raise a hand. As a
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l76' n='N076'/>child in Jamaica I was taught that the women
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r_5_1l77' n='N077'/>who worked for us were to be respected and
			</p>
			<pb n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>obeyed, and yet I remember my 12-year-old light¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>skinned self exercising what I felt was my au¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>thority over these women, and being quite taken
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>aback when one of the women threatened to beat
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>me—and my mother backed her up. Just as I was
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>shocked to find that another houseworker had
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>tied up my cousins and shut them on the veran¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>dah because they were interfering with her work.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>So while we may know the image is an image,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>the expectations of Black women behaving ac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>cording to this image persist. As far as I can tell,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>Harriet Tubman carried both a carbine and a
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>pistol. And she threatened to shoot any slave who
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>decided to turn back on the journey north. Just as
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>Lorraine Hansberry&apos;s slavemother armed her
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>children and set out with them—after leaving a
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>white man to die.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>1. For Lillian Smith&apos;s definition of racism, see &quot;The
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>Mob and the Ghost“ and &quot;Words That Chain Us
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>and Words That Set Us Free,&quot; in The Winner
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>Names the Age, ed. Michelle Cliff (New York:
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>Norton, 1978)
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>2. Erlene Stetson, &quot;Studying Slavery,&quot; in But Some of
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>Us Are Brave, ed. Gloria T. Hull, Patricia Bell Scott,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>&amp; Barbara Smith (Old Westbury, N.Y.: Feminist
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>Press, 1981)
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>3. Lorraine Hansberry, quoted in Les Blancs: The Col¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>lected Last Plays of Lorraine Hansberry, ed. Robert
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>Nemiroff (New York: Vintage, 1973), p. 206.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>4. Lillian Smith, Killers of the Dream (New York: Nor-
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>ton, 1949), p. 31
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>5. Smith, Winner, p. 204.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>6. Alice Walker, &quot;In Search of Our Mothers&apos; Gar¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>dens,&quot; in Working It Out, ed. Sara Ruddick &amp; Pam¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>ela Daniels (New York: Pantheon, 1977), p. 94.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>7. Toni Morrison, Sula (New York: Bantam, 1975),
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>p. 105.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>8. Quoted by Robert Hemenway, Zora Neale Hurston
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>(Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1977), p. 24.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>9. Fannie Hurst, Imitation of Life (New York: Harper
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>&amp; Bros., 1933), p. 105.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>10. Although Frederickson&apos;s The Black Image in the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>White Mind deals primarily with stereotypes of
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>Black men, with some alterations his categories
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>apply to stereotypes of Black women.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>11. Bell Hooks, Ain’t I a Woman (Boston: South End,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>1981), p. 84.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>12. Ibid., p. 85.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>13. Hansberry, Winner, p. 210.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>14. Angela Davis, &quot;The Black Woman&apos;s Role in the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>Community of Slaves,&quot; Black Scholar (1971), p. 13.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>15. Quoted by Sarah Bradford, Harriet Tubman: Moses
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>of Her People (Secaucus, N.J.: Citadel, 1974, rpt.),
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>pp. 30-32.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>16. Quoted by Phebe A. Hanaford, Daughters of Ameri¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>ca (Augusta, Me: True, n.d.), pp. 296-97.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>17. Quoted by Sara Bennett &amp; Joan Gibbs, &quot;Racism and
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>Classism in the Lesbian Community,&quot; in Top Rank¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>ing, ed. Bennett &amp; Gibbs (Brooklyn: February 3rd
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>Press, 1980), pp. 14-15.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>18. Quoted by Eleanor Tufts, Our Hidden Heritage
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>(New York: Paddington, 1974), p. 159.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>19. Walker, &quot;Gardens.&quot; p. 101.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>20. Tufts, Heritage, p. 163.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>21. Genesis, 21: 9-14.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>22. For a brilliant analysis of the Sojourner Truth plate
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>in Chicago&apos;s Dinner Party, see Alice Walker, &quot;One
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>Child of One&apos;s Own,&quot; in But Some of Us are Brave.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>23. This detail, and most of the information about
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l53' n='N053'/>Powers and her quilt, comes from Marie Jeane
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l54' n='N054'/>Adams, &quot;The Harriet Powers Pictorial Quilts,&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l55' n='N055'/>Black Art, vol. 3, no. 4, pp. 12-28.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l56' n='N056'/>24. Ibid., p. 16.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l57' n='N057'/>25. Michael Baxandall, Painting and Experience in
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l58' n='N058'/>Fifteenth-Century Italy (London: Oxford University
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l59' n='N059'/>Press, 1972), p. 9 ff.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l60' n='N060'/>26. Quoted by Mirra Bank, Anonymous Was a Woman
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l61' n='N061'/>(New York: St. Martin&apos;s, 1979), p. 118.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l62' n='N062'/>27. Adams, &quot;Powers,&quot; p. 14.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l63' n='N063'/>28. Mrs. Powers&apos;s description of the quilt appears in
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l64' n='N064'/>both Adams and Bank.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l65' n='N065'/>29. Davis, &quot;Black Woman&apos;s Role,&quot; p. 11.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l66' n='N066'/>30. Ibid.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l67' n='N067'/>31. Betye Saar, &quot;Interview with Houston Conwill,&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r_2_1l68' n='N068'/>Black Art, vol. 3, no. 1, p. 9.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
