<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='55'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_1' n='N001'/>...the common world is what we enter when we are
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_2' n='N002'/>born and what we leave behind when we die. It tran¬
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_3' n='N003'/>scends our life-span into past and future alike; it was
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_4' n='N004'/>there before we came and will outlast our brief sojourn
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_5' n='N005'/>into it. It is what we have in common not only with those
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_6' n='N006'/>who live with us, but also with those who were here be-
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_7' n='N007'/>fore and with those who will come after us. But such a
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_8' n='N008'/>common world can survive the coming and going of the
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_9' n='N009'/>generations only to the extent that it appears in public. It
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_10' n='N010'/>is the publicity of the public realm which can absorb and
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_11' n='N011'/>make shine through the centuries whatever men (sic may
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_2_tl_12' n='N012'/>want to save from the natural ruin of time.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_13_tl_1' n='N001'/>Women both have and have not a common world.
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_13_tl_2' n='N002'/>The mere sharing of oppression does not constitute a
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_13_tl_3' n='N003'/>common world. Our thought and action, insofar as it
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_13_tl_4' n='N004'/>has taken the form of difference, assertion, or rebellion,
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_13_tl_5' n='N005'/>has repeatedly been obliterated, or subsumed under &quot;hu-
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_13_tl_6' n='N006'/>man history, which means the “publicity of the public
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_13_tl_7' n='N007'/>realm&quot; created and controlled by men. Our history is
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_6_tl_1' n='N001'/>the history of a majority of the species, yet the struggles
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_6_tl_2' n='N002'/>of women for a &quot;human” status have been relegated to
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_6_tl_3' n='N003'/>footnotes, to the sidelines. Above all, women’s relation¬
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_6_tl_4' n='N004'/>ships with women have been denied or neglected as a
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_6_tl_5' n='N005'/>force in history.
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_6_tl_6' n='N006'/>The essays in this book are parts of a much larger
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_6_tl_7' n='N007'/>work, which we are still struggling to possess: the long
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_6_tl_8' n='N008'/>process of making visible the experience of women. The
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_6_tl_9' n='N009'/>tentativeness, the anxiety, sometimes approaching
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_1' n='N001'/>paralysis, the confusions, described in many of these
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_2' n='N002'/>essays by intelligent, educated, &quot;privileged” women, are
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_3' n='N003'/>themselves evidence of the damage that can be done to
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_4' n='N004'/>creative energy by the lack of a sense of continuity, his¬
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_5' n='N005'/>torical validation, community. Most women, it seems,
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_6' n='N006'/>have gone through their travails in a kind of spiritual
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_7' n='N007'/>isolation, alone both in the present and in ignorance of
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_8' n='N008'/>their place in any female tradition. The support of
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_9' n='N009'/>friends, of a women’s group, may make survival possi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_10' n='N010'/>ble; but it is not enough.
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_11' n='N011'/>It is quite clear that the universities and the intellectual
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_12' n='N012'/>establishment intend to keep women’s experiences as far
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_3_tl_13' n='N013'/>as possible invisible; and women’s studies a barely sub¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_9_tl_1' n='N001'/>sidized, condescendingly tolerated ghetto. The majority
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_9_tl_2' n='N002'/>of women who go through undergraduate and graduate
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_9_tl_3' n='N003'/>school suffer an intellectual coercion of which they are
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_9_tl_4' n='N004'/>not even consciously aware. In a world where language
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_9_tl_5' n='N005'/>and naming are power, silence is oppression, is violence.
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_9_tl_6' n='N006'/>This article appears as the foreword to Working It Out,
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_9_tl_7' n='N007'/>edited by Pamela Daniels and Sally Ruddick, published
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_9_tl_8' n='N008'/>by Pantheon.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_4_tl_1' n='N001'/>CONDITIONS FOR WORK:
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_4_tl_2' n='N002'/>The Common World Of Women
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_4_tl_3' n='N003'/>ADRIENNERICII
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_7_tl_1' n='N001'/>This content downloaded from
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_7_tl_2' n='N002'/>134.82.70.63 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:12:29 UT(
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_7_tl_3' n='N003'/>All use subject to https://abou
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_7_tl_4' n='N004'/>stor.org/terms
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_11_tl_1' n='N001'/>Writing of the destruction of the civilization of Langue¬
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_11_tl_2' n='N002'/>doc by the forces of the Church under Simon de Mont-
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_11_tl_3' n='N003'/>fort, Simone Weil reminds us: &quot;Nothing is more cruel to
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_11_tl_4' n='N004'/>the past than the commonplace which asserts that spirit¬
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_11_tl_5' n='N005'/>ual values cannot be destroyed by force; on the strength
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_11_tl_6' n='N006'/>of this belief, civilizations that have been destroyed by
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_11_tl_7' n='N007'/>force of arms are denied the name of civilization; and
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_5_tl_1' n='N001'/>there is no risk of our being refuted by the dead.&quot;3 For
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_5_tl_2' n='N002'/>spiritual values and a creative tradition to continue
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_5_tl_3' n='N003'/>unbroken we need concrete artifacts, the work of hands,
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_5_tl_4' n='N004'/>written words to read, images to look at, a dialogue
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_5_tl_5' n='N005'/>with brave and imaginative women who came before
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_5_tl_6' n='N006'/>us. In the false names of love, motherhood, natural
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_5_tl_7' n='N007'/>law—false because they have not been defined by us to
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_5_tl_8' n='N008'/>whom they are applied—women in patriarchy have
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_5_tl_9' n='N009'/>been withheld from building a common world, except in
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_5_tl_10' n='N010'/>enclaves, or through coded messages.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>The protection and preservation of the world against
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>natural processes are among the toils which need the
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>monotonous performance of daily repeated chores.... In
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>old tales and mythological stories it has often assumed
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>the grandeur of heroic fights against overwhelming odds,
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>as in the account of Hercules, whose cleansing of the
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>Augean stables is among the twelve heroic “labors.&quot; A
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>similar connotation of heroic deeds requiring great
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>strength and courage and performed in a fighting spirit is
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>manifest in the mediaeval use of the word: labor, travail,
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>arbeit. However, the daily fight in which the human
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>body is engaged to keep the world clean and prevent its
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>decay bears little resemblance to heroic deeds; the endur
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>ance it needs to repair every day anew the waste of yes¬
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>terday is not courage, and what makes the effort painful
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>is not danger but its relentless repetition.“
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_8_tl_1' n='N001'/>Hannah Arendt does not call this “woman’s work.
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_8_tl_2' n='N002'/>Yet it is this activity of world-protection, world-preser¬
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_8_tl_3' n='N003'/>vation, world-repair, the million tiny stitches, the fric¬
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_8_tl_4' n='N004'/>tion of the scrubbing brush, the scouring-cloth, the iron
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_8_tl_5' n='N005'/>across the shirt, the rubbing of cloth against itself to
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_8_tl_6' n='N006'/>exorcise the stain, the renewal of the scorched pot, the
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_8_tl_7' n='N007'/>rusted knife-blade, the invisible weaving of a frayed and
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_8_tl_8' n='N008'/>threadbare family life, the cleaning-up of soil and waste
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_12_tl_1' n='N001'/>left behind by men and children—that we have been
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_12_tl_2' n='N002'/>charged to do &quot;for love”—not merely unpaid, but unac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_12_tl_3' n='N003'/>knowledged by the political philosophers. Women are
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_12_tl_4' n='N004'/>not described as “working&quot; when we create the essential
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_12_tl_5' n='N005'/>conditions for the work of men; we are supposed to be
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_12_tl_6' n='N006'/>acting out of love, instinct, or devotion to some higher
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_12_tl_7' n='N007'/>cause than self.
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_12_tl_8' n='N008'/>Arendt tells us that the Greeks despised all labor of
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_55_tr_10_tl_1' n='N001'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='56'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_1' n='N001'/>Communal kitchen of the Oneida Community. from Frank
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_2' n='N002'/>Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper, April 9, 1870.
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_3' n='N003'/>the body necessitated by biological needs. It was to
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_4' n='N004'/>spare themselves such labor that men kept slaves—not
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_5' n='N005'/>as a means to cheaper production. “Contempt for labor¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_6' n='N006'/>ing, originally arising out of a passionate striving for
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_7' n='N007'/>freedom from necessity and a no less passionate impa¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_8' n='N008'/>tience with every effort that left no trace, no monument,
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_9' n='N009'/>no great work worthy of remembrance, spread with the
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_10' n='N010'/>increasing demands of polis life upon the time of the citi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_11' n='N011'/>zens (i.e., males) and its insistence on their abstention
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_12' n='N012'/>from all but political activities.&quot;5
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_3_tl_13' n='N013'/>And, in the aside of a footnote: “Women and slaves
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_5_tl_1' n='N001'/>belonged and lived together...no woman, not even the
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_5_tl_2' n='N002'/>wife of the household head, lived among her equals—
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_5_tl_3' n='N003'/>other free women—so that rank depended much less on
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_5_tl_4' n='N004'/>birth than on ’occupation’ or function.... According
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_5_tl_5' n='N005'/>to the index, this footnote is the last reference to women,
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_5_tl_6' n='N006'/>on page 73 of a volume of 325 pages on The Human
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_5_tl_7' n='N007'/>Condition, written by a woman.
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_5_tl_8' n='N008'/>Every effort that left no trace.... The efforts of
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_5_tl_9' n='N009'/>women in labor, giving birth to stillborn children, chil¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_5_tl_10' n='N010'/>dren who must die of plague or by infanticide; the
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_10_tl_1' n='N001'/>efforts of women to keep filth and decay at bay, children
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_10_tl_2' n='N002'/>decently clothed, to produce the clean shirt in which the
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_10_tl_3' n='N003'/>man walks out daily into the common world of men, the
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_10_tl_4' n='N004'/>efforts to raise children against the attritions of racist
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_10_tl_5' n='N005'/>and sexist schooling, drugs, sexual exploitation, the bru¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_10_tl_6' n='N006'/>talization and killing of barely grown boys in war.
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_10_tl_7' n='N007'/>There is still little but contempt and indifference for this
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_10_tl_8' n='N008'/>kind of work, these efforts. (The phrase “wages for
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_10_tl_9' n='N009'/>housework&quot; has the power to shock today that the
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_10_tl_10' n='N010'/>phrase &quot;free love&quot; possessed a century ago.)
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_9_tl_1' n='N001'/>There is a natural temptation to escape if we can, to
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_9_tl_2' n='N002'/>close the door behind us on this despised realm which
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_9_tl_3' n='N003'/>threatens to engulf all women, whether as mothers, or
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_9_tl_4' n='N004'/>in marriage, or as the invisible, ill-paid sustainers of the
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_9_tl_5' n='N005'/>professions and social institutions. There is a natural
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_9_tl_6' n='N006'/>fear that if we do not enter the common world of men,
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_9_tl_7' n='N007'/>as asexual beings or as exceptional&quot; women, do not
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_9_tl_8' n='N008'/>enter it on its terms and obey its rules, we will be sucked
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_9_tl_9' n='N009'/>back into the realm of servitude, whatever our tempo¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_11_tl_1' n='N001'/>rary class status or privileges. This temptation and this
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_11_tl_2' n='N002'/>fear compromise our powers, divert our energies, form
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_11_tl_3' n='N003'/>a potent source of “blocks&quot; and of acute anxiety about
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_11_tl_4' n='N004'/>work.
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_11_tl_5' n='N005'/>For if, in trying to join the common world of men, the
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_11_tl_6' n='N006'/>professions moulded by a primarily masculine con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_11_tl_7' n='N007'/>sciousness, we split ourselves off from the common life
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_4_tl_1' n='N001'/>This content downloaded from
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_4_tl_2' n='N002'/>34.82.
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_4_tl_3' n='N003'/>3 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:12:29 UTC
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_4_tl_4' n='N004'/>s:/ab
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_4_tl_5' n='N005'/>terms
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_7_tl_1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_7_tl_2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_7_tl_3' n='N003'/>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_2' n='N002'/>of women and deny our female heritage and identity in
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_3' n='N003'/>our work, we lose touch with our real powers, and with
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_4' n='N004'/>the essential condition for all fully realized work:
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_5' n='N005'/>community.
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_6' n='N006'/>Feminism begins, but cannot end, with the discovery
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_7' n='N007'/>by an individual of her self-consciousness as a woman.
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_8' n='N008'/>It is not, finally, even the recognition of her reasons for
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_9' n='N009'/>anger, or the decision to change her life, go back to
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_10' n='N010'/>school, leave a marriage (though in any individual life
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_11' n='N011'/>such decisions can be momentous and require great cour¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_12' n='N012'/>age). Feminism means finally that we renounce our obe¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_2_tl_13' n='N013'/>dience to the fathers, and recognize that the world they
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_8_tl_1' n='N001'/>have described is not the whole world. Masculine ideol¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_8_tl_2' n='N002'/>ogies are the creation of masculine subjectivity; they are
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_8_tl_3' n='N003'/>neither objective, nor value-free, nor inclusively “hu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_8_tl_4' n='N004'/>man. Feminism implies that we recognize fully the
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_8_tl_5' n='N005'/>inadequacy for us, the distortion, of male-created ideol¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_8_tl_6' n='N006'/>ogies; and that we proceed to think, and act, out of that
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_8_tl_7' n='N007'/>recognition.
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_8_tl_8' n='N008'/>In the common world of men, in the professions
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_8_tl_9' n='N009'/>which the writers of these essays have come to grips
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_8_tl_10' n='N010'/>with, it takes more than our individual talent and intel¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>ligence to think and act further. In denying the validity
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>of women’s experience, in pretending to stand for “the
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>human, masculine subjectivity tries to force us to name
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>our truths in an alien language; to dilute them; we are
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>constantly told that the “real” problems, the ones worth
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>working on, are those men have defined, that the prob¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>lems we need to examine are trivial, unscholarly, non¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>existent. We are urged to separate the “personal&quot; (our
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>entire existence as women) from the scholarly” or “pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>fessional.&quot; Several of the women who contribute to this
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>book have described the outright insults and intellectual
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>sabotage they encountered as women in graduate school.
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>But more insidious may be the sabotage which appears
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>as paternal encouragement, approval granted for inter¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>nalizing a masculine subjectivity. As Tillie Olsen puts it,
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_1' n='N001'/>&quot;Not to be able to come to one’s own truth or not to use
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_2' n='N002'/>it in one’s writing, even in telling the truth to have to
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_3' n='N003'/>tell it slant, robs one of drive, of conviction, limits
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_4' n='N004'/>potential stature. Everywhere, women working in the
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_5' n='N005'/>common world of men are denied that integrity of work
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_6' n='N006'/>and life which we can only find in an emotional and
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_7' n='N007'/>intellectual connectedness with ourselves and other
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_8' n='N008'/>women.
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_9' n='N009'/>More and more, however, women are creating com¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_10' n='N010'/>munity, sharing work, and discovering that in the shar¬
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_11' n='N011'/>ing of work our relationships with each other become
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_12' n='N012'/>larger and more serious. In organizing a women’s self-
				<lb facs='#facs_56_tr_6_tl_13' n='N013'/>help clinic or law collective, a writing workshop, in
			</p>
			<pb n='57'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>editing a magazine, creating a center for women’s work
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>like the Women’s Building in Los Angeles, in running a
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>press that publishes “lost&quot; books by women, or contem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>porary work that may be threatening or incomprehensi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>ble to male editors, in participating in a women’s prison
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>project or a crisis center, we come to understand at first¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>hand not only our unmet needs, but the resources we
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>can draw on for meeting them even in the face of female
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>poverty, the hostility of institutions, the lack of docu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>mentation of our shared past. Susan Griffin has said
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>that, for a feminist, writing may be solitary but thinking
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>is collective. Any woman who has moved from the
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>playing-fields of male discourse into the realm where
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>women are developing our own descriptions of the
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>world, knows the extraordinary sense of shedding, as it
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>were, the encumbrance of someone else’s baggage, of
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_9_tl_1' n='N001'/>ceasing to translate. It is not that thinking becomes easy.
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_9_tl_2' n='N002'/>but that the difficulties are intrinsic to the work itself
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_9_tl_3' n='N003'/>rather than to the environment. In the common world
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_9_tl_4' n='N004'/>of men, the struggle to make female experience visible¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_9_tl_5' n='N005'/>will they take seriously a thesis on women? Will they let
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_9_tl_6' n='N006'/>me teach a course on women? Can 1 speak bluntly of
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_9_tl_7' n='N007'/>female experience without shattering the male egos
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_9_tl_8' n='N008'/>around me, or being labeled hysterical, castrating?-
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_9_tl_9' n='N009'/>such struggles assume the status of an intellectual prob¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_1' n='N001'/>lem, and the real intellectual problems may not be
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_2' n='N002'/>probed at all.
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_3' n='N003'/>Working together as women, consciously creating
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_4' n='N004'/>our networks even where patriarchal institutions are the
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_5' n='N005'/>ones in which we have to survive, we can confront the
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_6' n='N006'/>problems of women’s relationships, the mothers we
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_7' n='N007'/>came from, the sisters with whom we were forced to
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_8' n='N008'/>divide the world, the daughters we love and fear. We
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_9' n='N009'/>can challenge and inspirit each other, throw light on one
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_10' n='N010'/>another’s blind spots, stand by and give courage at the
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_11' n='N011'/>birth-throes of one another’s insights. I think of the poet
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_12' n='N012'/>H.D. s account of the vision she had on the island of
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_2_tl_13' n='N013'/>Corfu, in the Tribute to Freud:
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_8_tl_1' n='N001'/>And there I sat and there is my friend Bryher who has
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_8_tl_2' n='N002'/>brought me to Greece. I can turn now to her, though I do
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_8_tl_3' n='N003'/>not budge an inch or break the sustained crystal-gazing
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_8_tl_4' n='N004'/>at the wall before me. I say to Bryher, “There have been
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_8_tl_5' n='N005'/>pictures here—I thought they were shadows at first, but
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_8_tl_6' n='N006'/>they are light, not shadow. They are quite simple objects
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_8_tl_7' n='N007'/>—but of course it’s very strange. I can break away from
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_8_tl_8' n='N008'/>them now, if I want—it’s just a matter of concentrating
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_8_tl_9' n='N009'/>what do you think? Shall I stop? Shall I go on?&quot; Bryher
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_8_tl_10' n='N010'/>says without hesitation, &quot;Go on.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_12_tl_1' n='N001'/>...I had known such extraordinarily gifted and charm¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_12_tl_2' n='N002'/>ing people. They had made much of me or they had
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_12_tl_3' n='N003'/>slighted me and yet neither praise nor neglect mattered in
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_12_tl_4' n='N004'/>the face of the gravest issues—life, death.... And yet, so
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_12_tl_5' n='N005'/>oddly, I knew that this experience, this writing-on-the-
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_12_tl_6' n='N006'/>wall before me, could not be shared with anyone except
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_12_tl_7' n='N007'/>the girl who stood so bravely there beside me. This girl
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_5_tl_1' n='N001'/>had said without hesitation, “Go on.&quot; It was she really
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_5_tl_2' n='N002'/>who had the detachment and integrity of the Pythoness
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_5_tl_3' n='N003'/>of Delphi. But it was I, battered and disassociated...who
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_5_tl_4' n='N004'/>was seeing the pictures, and who was reading the writing
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_5_tl_5' n='N005'/>or granted the inner vision. Or perhaps, in some sense,
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_5_tl_6' n='N006'/>we were &quot;seeing&quot; it together, for without her, admittedly,
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_5_tl_7' n='N007'/>I could not have gone on.6
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_5_tl_8' n='N008'/>Even for those who would mistrust visionary experience,
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_5_tl_9' n='N009'/>the episode is revealing as metaphor. The personal rela¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_5_tl_10' n='N010'/>tionship helps create the conditions for work (out of her
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_11_tl_1' n='N001'/>This content downloaded from
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_11_tl_2' n='N002'/>134.82.70.63 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:12:29 UTC
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_11_tl_3' n='N003'/>All use subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_1' n='N001'/>vision H.D. went on to create her great, late, long poems
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_2' n='N002'/>celebrating a matriarchal world and the quest of female
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_3' n='N003'/>heroes); no less does the fact of working together deepen
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_4' n='N004'/>and sustain a personal relationship. &quot;If Chloe likes Oliv¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_5' n='N005'/>ia and they share a laboratory...this of itself will make
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_6' n='N006'/>their friendship more varied and lasting because it will
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_7' n='N007'/>be less personal.&quot; By “like” I believe Virginia Woolf
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_8' n='N008'/>(still, in that book, writing more cautiously than later in
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_9' n='N009'/>Three Guineas) also meant “love&quot;; for a laboratory
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_10' n='N010'/>we can read &quot;the creation of a common world.
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_11' n='N011'/>Many women have known the figure of the male
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_12' n='N012'/>mentor&quot; who guides and protects his female student or
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_13' n='N013'/>colleague, tenderly opening doors for her into the com¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_3_tl_14' n='N014'/>mon world of men. He seems willing to share his power,
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_13_tl_1' n='N001'/>to conspire with her in stealing what Celia Gilbert names
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_13_tl_2' n='N002'/>in this book “the sacred fire” of work. Yet what can he
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_13_tl_3' n='N003'/>really bestow but the illusion of power, a power stolen,
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_13_tl_4' n='N004'/>in any case, from the mass of women, over centuries, by
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_13_tl_5' n='N005'/>men? He can teach her to name her experience in lan¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_13_tl_6' n='N006'/>guage that may allow her to live, work, perhaps succeed
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_13_tl_7' n='N007'/>in the common world of men. But he has no key to the
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_7_tl_1' n='N001'/>powers she might share with other women.
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_7_tl_2' n='N002'/>There is also the illusion that if you make your emo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_7_tl_3' n='N003'/>tional and erotic life with women, it does not matter
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_7_tl_4' n='N004'/>that your intellectual work is a collaboration with
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_7_tl_5' n='N005'/>silence and lying about female experience. At a panel of
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_7_tl_6' n='N006'/>lesbian writers at the Modern Language Association in
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_7_tl_7' n='N007'/>San Francisco in December 1975, Susan Griffin spoke of
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_7_tl_8' n='N008'/>the damages we do to ourselves and our work in censor¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_7_tl_9' n='N009'/>ing our own truths:
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_1' n='N001'/>I feel that this whole idea of the Muse, of inspiration, is a
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_2' n='N002'/>kind of cop-out. There is something very fascinating go¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_3' n='N003'/>ing on with a writer’s psyche when you are undergoing a
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_4' n='N004'/>silence, an inability to write. Each silence and each erup¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_5' n='N005'/>tion into speech constitute a kind of struggle in the life of
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_6' n='N006'/>a writer.... The largest struggle around silence in my life
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_7' n='N007'/>has had to do with the fact that I am a woman and a
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_8' n='N008'/>lesbian. When I recognized my feelings as a woman,
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_9' n='N009'/>when 1 recognized my anger as a woman, suddenly my
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_10' n='N010'/>writing was transformed—suddenly I had a material, a
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_11' n='N011'/>subject-matter... And then a few years later I found my-
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_12' n='N012'/>self unhappy with my writing, unhappy with the way 1
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_13' n='N013'/>expressed myself, unable to speak; 1 wrote in a poem,
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_4_tl_14' n='N014'/>Words do not come to my mouth any more. And I hap-
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_10_tl_1' n='N001'/>pened also...to be censoring the fact that I was a lesbian.
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_10_tl_2' n='N002'/>I thought that I was doing this because of the issue of
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_10_tl_3' n='N003'/>child custody, and that was and still is a serious issue.
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_10_tl_4' n='N004'/>But I wasn’t acknowledging how important it was to me,
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_10_tl_5' n='N005'/>both as a writer and as a human being, to be able to...
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_10_tl_6' n='N006'/>write about my feelings as a lesbian.
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_10_tl_7' n='N007'/>In fact, I think that writers are always dealing with taboos
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_10_tl_8' n='N008'/>of one sort or another; if they are not taboos general in
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_10_tl_9' n='N009'/>society, you may just have a fear in your private life of
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_1' n='N001'/>perceiving some truth because of its implications, and
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_2' n='N002'/>that will stop you from writing.... But when we come to
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_3' n='N003'/>the taboo of lesbianism, this is one which is most loaded
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_4' n='N004'/>for everyone, even those who are not lesbians. Because
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_5' n='N005'/>the fact of love between women...is one which affects
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_6' n='N006'/>every event in this society, psychic and political and
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_7' n='N007'/>sociological. And for a writer, the most savage center is
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_8' n='N008'/>oneself. 8
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_9' n='N009'/>The whole question of what it means, or might mean, to
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_10' n='N010'/>work as a lesbian might have occupied an entire essay in
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_11' n='N011'/>this book. Of past women whose thought and work
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_12' n='N012'/>have remained visible in history, an enormous num¬
				<lb facs='#facs_57_tr_6_tl_13' n='N013'/>ber have been lesbians, yet because of the silence and
			</p>
			<pb n='58'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>denial that has enveloped lesbianism, we learn little
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>from women’s biographies about the relation of thein
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>work to their relationships with women or to the social
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>taboos they lived among. One writer in this book
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>mourns that &quot;there was only one Alice B. Toklas. But
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>in fact women’s support to women has been there all
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>along, lifetime or long-term comradeships. For many
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>women, struggling for economic survival in the com¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>mon world of men, these relationships have had to be
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>dissimulated, at what cost to the work (let alone the
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>relationships) we cannot begin to know. Every lesbian
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>has been forced to walk past the distorting mirrors of
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>homophobia before she could get down to the real
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_1' n='N001'/>problems of her work. Every lesbian artist knows that
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_2' n='N002'/>when she attempts to embody lesbian sexuality in her
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_3' n='N003'/>work she runs the risk of having it perceived porno¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_4' n='N004'/>graphically, if it is not simply denied visibility. When
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_5' n='N005'/>a lesbian feels she may have to choose between writing
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_6' n='N006'/>or painting her truths and keeping her child, she is
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_7' n='N007'/>flung back on the most oppressive ground of maternal
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_8' n='N008'/>guilt in conflict with creative work. The question of eco¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_9' n='N009'/>nomic survival, of keeping one’s job, is terribly real, but
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_10' n='N010'/>the more terrible questions lie deeper where a woman is
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_4_tl_11' n='N011'/>forced, or permits herself, to lead a censored life.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_10_tl_1' n='N001'/>In thinking about the issues of women and work
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_10_tl_2' n='N002'/>raised in this book, I turned to Hannah Arendt&apos;s The
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_10_tl_3' n='N003'/>Human Condition to see how a major political philoso¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_10_tl_4' n='N004'/>pher of our time, a woman, greatly respected in the
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_10_tl_5' n='N005'/>intellectual establishment, had spoken to the theme. I
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_10_tl_6' n='N006'/>found her essay illuminating, not so much for what it
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_10_tl_7' n='N007'/>says, but for what it is. The issue of women as the labor
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_10_tl_8' n='N008'/>ers in reproduction, of women as workers in production,
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_10_tl_9' n='N009'/>of the relationship of women’s unpaid labor in the home
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_1' n='N001'/>to the separation between “private” and public
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_2' n='N002'/>spheres, of the woman’s body as commodity—these
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_3' n='N003'/>questions were not raised for the first time in the 1960&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_4' n='N004'/>and 1970’s; they had already been documented in the
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_5' n='N005'/>1950’s when The Human Condition was being written.
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_6' n='N006'/>Arendt barely alludes, usually in a footnote, to Marx
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_7' n='N007'/>and Engels’ engagement with these questions; and she
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_8' n='N008'/>writes as if the work of Olive Schreiner, Charlotte Per¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_9' n='N009'/>inds Gilman, Emma Goldman, Jane Addams, to name
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_10' n='N010'/>only a few writers, had never existed. The withholding
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_11' n='N011'/>of women from participation in the vita activa, the
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_2_tl_12' n='N012'/>&quot;common world,&quot; and the connection of this with repro¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_8_tl_1' n='N001'/>ductivity, is something from which she does not so
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_8_tl_2' n='N002'/>much turn her eyes as stare straight through unseeing.
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_8_tl_3' n='N003'/>This &quot;great work&quot; is thus a kind of failure for which
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_8_tl_4' n='N004'/>masculine ideology has no name, precisely because in
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_8_tl_5' n='N005'/>terms of that ideology it is successful, at the expense of
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_8_tl_6' n='N006'/>truths the ideology considers irrelevant. To read such a
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_8_tl_7' n='N007'/>book, by a woman of large spirit and great erudition,
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_8_tl_8' n='N008'/>can be painful, because it embodies the tragedy of the
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_8_tl_9' n='N009'/>female mind nourished on male ideologies. In fact, the
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_8_tl_10' n='N010'/>loss is ours, because Arendt’s desire to grasp deep moral
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_13_tl_1' n='N001'/>issues is the kind of concern we need to build a common
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_13_tl_2' n='N002'/>world which will amount to more than &quot;life-styles.&quot; The
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_13_tl_3' n='N003'/>power of male ideology to possess such a female mind,
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_13_tl_4' n='N004'/>to disconnect it as it were from the female body which
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_13_tl_5' n='N005'/>encloses it and which it encloses, is nowhere more strik¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_13_tl_6' n='N006'/>ing than in Arendt’s lofty and crippled book.
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_13_tl_7' n='N007'/>Women’s minds cannot grow to full stature, or touch
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_9_tl_1' n='N001'/>This content downloaded from
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_9_tl_2' n='N002'/>134.82.70.63 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:12:29 UT(
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_9_tl_3' n='N003'/>Allu
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_9_tl_4' n='N004'/>subject to https://about.jstor.org/term
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_12_tl_1' n='N001'/>the real springs of our power to alter reality, on a diet of
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_12_tl_2' n='N002'/>masculine ideology. This is not the same thing as saying
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_12_tl_3' n='N003'/>that we can use nothing of these ideologies, or their
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_12_tl_4' n='N004'/>methods; or that we need not understand them. But the
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_12_tl_5' n='N005'/>common world of men cannot give us what we need,
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_12_tl_6' n='N006'/>and parts of it are poisoning us. Miriam Schapiro, in
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_12_tl_7' n='N007'/>this book, describes the process through which she
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_12_tl_8' n='N008'/>begins to work: filling sheets of paper with smeared
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_6_tl_1' n='N001'/>paint, images created &quot;freely, mindlessly, going back
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_6_tl_2' n='N002'/>to that place in childhood where she simply painted and
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_6_tl_3' n='N003'/>was happy. To her husband, this appeared as “de-pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_6_tl_4' n='N004'/>fessionalizing&quot; herself. Yet the very concept of “profes¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_6_tl_5' n='N005'/>sionalism,&quot; tainted as it is with the separation between
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_6_tl_6' n='N006'/>personal life and work, with a win-or-lose mentalilty
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_6_tl_7' n='N007'/>and the gauging of success by public honors and market
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_6_tl_8' n='N008'/>prices, needs a thorough revaluation by women. Forty
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_6_tl_9' n='N009'/>years back Virginia Woolf was asking
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_1' n='N001'/>What is this “civilization&quot; in which we find ourselves?
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_2' n='N002'/>What are these ceremonies and why should we make
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_3' n='N003'/>money out of them? Where in short is it leading, the pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_4' n='N004'/>cession of the sons of educated men?
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_5' n='N005'/>Her answer was that it is leading to war, to elitism, to
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_6' n='N006'/>exploitation and the greed for power; in our own time
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_7' n='N007'/>we can also add that it has clearly been leading to the
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_8' n='N008'/>ravagement of the non-human living world. Instead of
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_9' n='N009'/>the concept of “professionalism, we need, perhaps, a
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_10' n='N010'/>vision of work akin to that described by Simone Weil in
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_3_tl_11' n='N011'/>her “Theoretical Picture of a Free Society”:
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_5_tl_1' n='N001'/>A clear view of what is possible and what impossible,
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_5_tl_2' n='N002'/>what is easy and what difficult, of the labors that sepa¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_5_tl_3' n='N003'/>rate the project from its accomplishment—this alone does
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_5_tl_4' n='N004'/>away with insatiable desires and vain fears; from this
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_5_tl_5' n='N005'/>and not from anything else proceed moderation and
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_5_tl_6' n='N006'/>courage, virtues without which life is nothing but a dis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_5_tl_7' n='N007'/>graceful frenzy. Besides, the source of any kind of virtue
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_5_tl_8' n='N008'/>lies in the shock produced by the human intelligence
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_5_tl_9' n='N009'/>being brought up against a matter devoid of lenience and
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_5_tl_10' n='N010'/>of falsity.10
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_11_tl_1' n='N001'/>If we conceive of feminism as more than a frivolous
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_11_tl_2' n='N002'/>label, if we conceive of it as an ethics, a methodology, a
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_11_tl_3' n='N003'/>more complex way of thinking about, thus more
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_11_tl_4' n='N004'/>responsibly acting upon, the conditions of human life,
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_11_tl_5' n='N005'/>we need a self-knowledge which can only develop
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_11_tl_6' n='N006'/>through a steady, passionate attention to all female
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_11_tl_7' n='N007'/>experience. I cannot imagine a feminist evolution lead¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_11_tl_8' n='N008'/>ing to radical change in the private/political realm of
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_11_tl_9' n='N009'/>gender, that is not rooted in the conviction that all
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_7_tl_1' n='N001'/>women’s lives are important, that the lives of men can¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_7_tl_2' n='N002'/>not be understood by burying the lives of women; and
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_7_tl_3' n='N003'/>that to make visible the full meaning of women’s experi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_7_tl_4' n='N004'/>ence, to re-interpret knowledge in terms of that experi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_7_tl_5' n='N005'/>ence, is now the most important task of thinking
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_7_tl_6' n='N006'/>If this is so, we cannot work alone. We had better face
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_7_tl_7' n='N007'/>the fact that our hope of thinking at all, against the force
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_7_tl_8' n='N008'/>of a maimed and maiming world-view, depends on
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_7_tl_9' n='N009'/>seeking and giving our allegiance to a community of
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_7_tl_10' n='N010'/>women co-workers. And, beyond the exchange and cri¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_14_tl_1' n='N001'/>ticism of work, we have to ask ourselves how we can
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_14_tl_2' n='N002'/>make the conditions for work more possible, not just for
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_14_tl_3' n='N003'/>ourselves but for each other. This is not a question of
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_14_tl_4' n='N004'/>generosity. It is not generosity that makes women in
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_14_tl_5' n='N005'/>community support and nourish each other. It is rather
				<lb facs='#facs_58_tr_14_tl_6' n='N006'/>what Whitman called the “hunger for equals&quot;—the
			</p>
			<pb n='59'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_1' n='N001'/>desire for a context in which our own strivings will be
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_2' n='N002'/>amplified, quickened, lucidified, through those of our
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_3' n='N003'/>peers.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_4' n='N004'/>We also, of course, need community with our past.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_5' n='N005'/>Women’s art and thought and action will continue to be
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_6' n='N006'/>seen as deviant, its true meaning distorted or buried, as
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_7' n='N007'/>long as women’s work can be dismissed as exceptional,
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_8' n='N008'/>an interesting footnote to the major texts. Or, it will be
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_9' n='N009'/>encouraged for its timidities and punished for its daring.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_10' n='N010'/>This is obvious to women who have tried to work along
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_6_tl_11' n='N011'/>seriously feminist lines in the established professions.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_1' n='N001'/>But even before the work exists, long before praise or
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_2' n='N002'/>attack, the very form it will assume, the courage on
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_3' n='N003'/>which it can draw, the sense of potential direction it
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_4' n='N004'/>may take, require—given the politics of our lives and of
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_5' n='N005'/>creation itself—more than the gifts of the individual
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_6' n='N006'/>woman, or her immediate contemporaries. We need
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_7' n='N007'/>access to the female past.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_8' n='N008'/>The problem, finally, is not that of who does house¬
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_9' n='N009'/>work and child-care, whether or not one can find a life¬
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_10' n='N010'/>companion who will share in the sustenance and repair
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_11' n='N011'/>of daily life—crucial as these may be in the short run. It
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_12' n='N012'/>is a question of the community we are reaching for in
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_5_tl_13' n='N013'/>our work, and on which we can draw; who we envision
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>as our hearers, our co-creators, our challengers; who
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>will urge us to take our work further, more seriously,
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>than we had dared; on whose work we can build.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>Women have done these things for each other, sought
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>each other in community, even if only in enclaves, often
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>through correspondence, for centuries. Denied space in
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>the universities, the scientific laboratories, the profes¬
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>sions, we have devised our networks. We must not be
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>tempted to trade the possibility of enlarging and
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>strengthening those networks, and of extending them to
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>more and more women, for the illusion of power and
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>success as exceptional&quot; or “privileged&quot; women in the
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>professions.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_7_tl_1' n='N001'/>This content downloaded from
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_7_tl_2' n='N002'/>134.82.70.63 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:12:29 UT(
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_7_tl_3' n='N003'/>ise subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_4_tl_1' n='N001'/>1. Hannah Arendt, The Human Condition. University of
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_4_tl_2' n='N002'/>Chicago Press, 1958, p. 55.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_4_tl_3' n='N003'/>2. The historian Joan Kelly-Gadol suggests that a feminist
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_4_tl_4' n='N004'/>view of history is not merely compensatory history, a
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_4_tl_5' n='N005'/>parallel to the accepted views of history as male. It means
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_4_tl_6' n='N006'/>’to look at ages or movements of great social change in
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_4_tl_7' n='N007'/>terms of their liberation or repression of woman’s poten¬
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_4_tl_8' n='N008'/>tial, their import for the advancement of her humanity as
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_4_tl_9' n='N009'/>well as his. The moment this is done—the moment one as¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_9_tl_1' n='N001'/>sumes that women are a part of humanity in the fullest
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_9_tl_2' n='N002'/>sense—the period or set of events with which we deal takes
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_9_tl_3' n='N003'/>on a wholly different character or meaning from the nor¬
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_9_tl_4' n='N004'/>mally accepted one. Indeed, what emerges is a fairly regu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_9_tl_5' n='N005'/>lar pattern of relative loss of status for women in those
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_9_tl_6' n='N006'/>periods of so-called progressive change.&quot; (“The Social Re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_9_tl_7' n='N007'/>lation of the Sexes: Methodological Implications of Wom¬
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_9_tl_8' n='N008'/>en’s History,&quot; in SIGNS, Vol. 1, 14, Summer 1976.)
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_1' n='N001'/>3. Simone Weil, Selected Essays 1934-1943. Oxford Univer¬
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_2' n='N002'/>sity Press, 1962, p. 43.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_3' n='N003'/>4. Arendt, p. 55.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_4' n='N004'/>5. Arendt, pp. 81-83.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_5' n='N005'/>6. H.D., Tribute to Freud. Carcanet Press, Oxford, 1971,
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_6' n='N006'/>pp. 50-54.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_7' n='N007'/>7. Virginia Woolf, A Room of One’s Own. Hogarth Press,
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_8' n='N008'/>London, 1929, p. 126.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_9' n='N009'/>8. Sinister Wisdom, Vol. I, f2, Fall 1976.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_10' n='N010'/>9. Virginia Woolf, Three Guineas (1938). Harbinger Book,
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_11' n='N011'/>New York, 1966, p. 63.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_12' n='N012'/>10. Simone Weil, Oppression and Liberty. Translated by
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_13' n='N013'/>Arthur Wills and John Petrie. University of Massachusetts
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_2_tl_14' n='N014'/>Press, Amherst, Mass., 1973, p. 87.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_8_tl_1' n='N001'/>Adrienne Rich’s most recent books are Poems Selected and
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_8_tl_2' n='N002'/>New: 1950-1974 and Of Woman Born: Motherhood as Exper¬
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_8_tl_3' n='N003'/>ience and Institution, both published by W.W. Norton, and
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_8_tl_4' n='N004'/>Twenty-One Love Poems, published by Effie’s Press, Emery-
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_8_tl_5' n='N005'/>ville California.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_1' n='N001'/>Sarah Ponsonby (1755-1831) and Eleanor Butler
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_2' n='N002'/>(1739-1829), known as the Ladies of Llangollen, were
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_3' n='N003'/>born in Ireland but left their homes at an early age,
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_4' n='N004'/>to spend the rest of their lives together in the small
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_5' n='N005'/>Welsh village of Llangollen. They were a curiosity of
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_6' n='N006'/>their day; several articles about their “romantic
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_7' n='N007'/>friendship&quot; were written and their farmhouse became
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_8' n='N008'/>something of an intellectual center in Great Britain.
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_9' n='N009'/>Louisa Gordon wrote a novel, The Chase of the Wild
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_10' n='N010'/>Goose, based on their lives, which was originally
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_11' n='N011'/>published by Virginia Woolf’s Hogarth Press. In
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_12' n='N012'/>1971 Elizabeth Mavor published a biography entitled
				<lb facs='#facs_59_tr_3_tl_13' n='N013'/>The Ladies of Llangollen.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
