<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1"/>
         <p>
				ELIZABETH
				WEATHERFORD
				Kickapoo woman in front of her wigwam.
			</p>
         <p>
				WOMEN'S TRADITIONAL ARCHITECTURE
			</p>
         <p>
				Human culture has been viewed by his¬
				tory as the product of "mankind's" efforts.
				Most of the events and achievements
				chosen for posterity as significant have
				been dominated and determined by males.
				However, there are histories other than
				those of modern post-industrial nation/
				states. In traditional societies, located in
				what is often called the Third World,
				women have played a crucial role in the
				formation of cultural features vital to
				human existence. One such area, not usu¬
				ally credited to women, is architecture. In
				traditional cultures, women are often the
				builders and owners of structures, pro¬
				viding shelter and creating the conditions
				for social interaction.
				Although I will use the "ethnographic
				present" in most of this article, many of
				the traditional non-state societies in North
				America and Africa on which I focus here
				no longer exist, or no longer exist in their
				original forms. Their structures differ
				vastly from those of modern states. Some
				of these societies are small bands of
				gatherers and hunters, some are semi¬
				nomadic peoples who seasonally follow
				herds, and others pursue a form of farm¬
				ing called horticulture, where the local
				économy is self-sufficient and women are
				frequently the farmers.
				Initially victimized by colonization,
				virtually all those societies that remain are
				now undergoing "modernization.“ If we
				lose the histories of these cultures, we will
			</p>
         <p>
				also lose an important part of the history
				of women's roles in world culture, for in
				societies whose traditions remain intact,
				the roles women play are central to their
				cultures—not on the sidelines, where our
				culture seems to wish us to be. In light of
				this, contemporary feminists' identifica¬
				tion and re-creation of "women's culture“
				can be seen not just as a protest against
				oppression, but as a recognition of the ar¬
				bitrary denigration of the history of
				women's activities. The discovery that
				architecture is a traditional woman's art
				opens up the possibility for a new under¬
				standing of our role in the formation of
				human culture.
				Grass Houses
				Societies of gatherers and hunters lived
				in small bands, constantly moving within
				a relatively large territory from which
				they foraged for plants and animals. These
				groups, which include the (Kung of the
				Kalahari Desert in Namibia and the
				BaMbuti (Pygmies) of central Africa's
				Ituri Forest, bands in the Sahara Desert,
				Algonkian and Athabascan groups in
				North America, are intriguing in their so¬
				cial harmony and their knowledgeable,
				non-exploitative interaction with their en¬
				vironments. Women and men regard each
				other as equals. Among the BaMbuti,
				hunting is a joint effort, men care for
				babies and women enter public discus¬
				sions.!
				In gathering societies women may pro¬
			</p>
         <p>
				vide up to eighty percent of the food and
				as an extension of their expertise in plants
				and fibers (with which they make nets),
				they are also the builders. The dwelling
				the women construct usually consists of a
				framework woven like an inverted loose
				basket, covered or thatched with avail¬
				able materials such as large leaves, bun¬
				dles of grass or woven mats. These shel¬
				ters share significant characteristics across
				cultures. They are flexible, often flooded
				with translucent light, and scented with
				the smoke of fires and fragrant floor cov¬
				erings. They are round, ovoid or conical,
				with no edges or planes to interrupt the
				flow of space. Their size and shape maxi¬
				mizes physical and psychological contact
				among the dwellers. Anthropologists sug¬
				gest that such human proximity is particu¬
				larly conducive to intuitive and non¬
				verbal communication, to the develop¬
				ment of internalized cultural rhythms.“
				In our Western cultures, such tacit syn¬
				chrony is usually found only in mother¬
				infant relationships, a vestige of what was
				once the nature of communication be¬
				tween both sexes and all ages.
				A freudian theorist might suggest that
				the organic nature of gatherers' dwellings
				is a cultural extension of the biophysical
				environment of the womb. But in fact,
				these shelters can be extremely open and
				unwomblike. They include unsheltered
				areas where the work of the household,
				such as plaiting mats and scraping skins,
			</p>
         <p>
				35
			</p>
         <pb n="2"/>
         <p>
				takes place. The house life overflows into
				outdoor space, allowing the activities of
				its inhabitants to expand. Many gatherers
				dwellings are easily adaptable, and when
				not easily expanded (as in the hemispheri¬
				cal scherms of the IKung) there is flexibil¬
				ity as to who inhabits them. Children do
				not have to sleep with their parents, and
				can either stay with their grandparents or
				make camp with other children of the
				same sex at either end of the settlement.
				Thus the gatherers' house is not a struc¬
				ture enforcing family isolation, but serves
				as a shelter of great social fluidity.
			</p>
         <p>
				Kung gatherers and scherms.
				In these mobile cultures land is not in¬
				dividually owned and no dwelling is per-
				manent. Women possess the building
				know-how rather than the actual struc¬
				tures, which they may erect collectively.
				The building activity may be almost ritu¬
				alized, as the "performer“ sets into mo¬
				tion a body of traditional knowledge
				shared with other women:
				Now she squatted down making her
				own home, driving the saplings into
				the ground with sharp thrusts, each
				time in exactly the same place, so
				that they went deeper and deeper.
				When she had completed a circle she
				stood up and deftly bent the fito over
				her head, twisting them together and
				twining smaller saplings across form-
				ing a lattice framework. Then she
				took the leaves we had collected and
				slit the stalks toward the end, like
				clothespins, hooking two or three of
				them together. When she had enough
				she started hanging them on the
				framework like tiles, overlapping
				each other and forming a waterproof
				covering. There were leaves left over
				when she had finished, so she let
				other women take them for their
				houses.“
				The dwelling in the gathering culture is
			</p>
         <p>
				the focal point of women's creative activi¬
				ties. Since it is usually constructed from
				materials that can be replaced from avail¬
				able natural sources, it also binds society
				to its natural environment.
				Desert Dwellings, Wigwams and Tipis
				Semi-nomadic peoples live some part of
				the year in relatively permanent camps
				when an adequate food supply is avail¬
				able — wild plants, such as the wild rice of
				the Great Lakes region, or those provided
				by temporary cultivation. Some semi¬
				nomadic peoples follow herds of wild or
			</p>
         <p>
				of the grass house remained essential. For
				semi-nomadic desert dwellers, such as the
				Pima and Papago of the American South¬
				west, the convenient raw materials for
				building might still be plant fibers, par¬
				ticularly where the women were highly
				skilled basketweavers and had developed
				ways of weaving fibers into other forms,
				such as cotton cloth or yucca-fiber san¬
				dals. Up until the twentieth century the
				Pima were dispersed in the winter and set¬
				tlements were occupied only for a few
				months during a short growing season.
				The women built structures that mingled
				the style of mobile peoples with that of
				the ancient Southwest Pueblos. Their
				houses were grass but the interiors were
				slightly below ground. Sometimes earth
				was used to anchor the lower portion of
				the exterior wall, a feature which perhaps
				explains the evolution of the earth lodges
				built by the Navaho and by the Mandan
				further north.
				Another feature of grass houses is the
				tensile flexibility of the structure, which
				was later developed into the tent form. In
				the desert or plains it might be adjusted or
				even formed in relationship to wind pat¬
				terns; the walls might be opened, or
				closed tightly, to adapt to the wide range
				of temperatures characteristic of these
				environments. The tent consists of a
				framework over which a tight covering is
				stretched; it may be low and rounded or
			</p>
         <p>
				Pima women and house. (Museum of the American Indian, Heye Foundation.)
			</p>
         <p>
				domestic animals part of the year and
				spend the rest gathering and hunting, or
				trading. These societies are not sedentary
				because they or their animals must range
				for some proportion of their food and the
				basics for making material goods. Gen¬
				erally they inhabit arid desert lands or
				plains choked with grasses, where farm¬
				ing is difficult.
				The architecture of such semi-nomads
				grew out of forms developed within gath¬
				ering societies. Certain structural features
			</p>
         <p>
				tall and conical, but either shape, with its
				flexible covering, is perfectly adaptable.
				Tents also differ from grass houses in that
				the coverings, and sometimes the frames,
				are carried with the band as it moves. All
				the components of such tents, including
				those of the Tuareg, Algonkian wigwams
				and Plains tribes' tipis, are made by wom¬
				en — exterior and interior walls, floor
				coverings and frames. There is a tradi¬
				tional basic form, but the tent is by no
				means standardized. In each society wom¬
			</p>
         <p>
				36
			</p>
         <pb n="3"/>
         <p>
				en have created subtle variations on the
				frame or the arrangement of tent flaps for
				ventilation. In the arid Atlas Mountains
				of North Africa, Tuareg women weave
				and embroider wool coverings for their
				tents. The frame has a number of possible
				shapes, demonstrating the interplay be¬
				tween individual choice and cultural
				tradition.
			</p>
         <p>
				Tuareg tent and structural variations. (From
				Nicolaisen.)
			</p>
         <p>
				Algonkian-speaking groups, originally
				inhabiting much of the Eastern United
				States, were pushed west to the Great
				Lakes region after the white invasion.
				They hunted, gathered, fished, collected
				maple sugar, gathered wild rice, and had
				gardens. Some, like the Kickapoo, con¬
				structed wigwams of frames covered by
				mats. Others, including the Ojibwa, con¬
				structed conical tents covered with thin
				sheets of birch bark sewed together with
				small roots until long enough to cover the
				sides. Ojibwa women cut the poles for the
				frames and made colorful mats from reeds
				to cover the walls, and to serve as carpets,
				beds and sofas. Softening, bleaching and
				dyeing these reeds was a complicated
				process. The completed mats were carried
				from site to site. Early white observers
				were greatly impressed with the women's
				strength, as shown by this comment from
				1855:
				It may be easily supposed that these
				squaws, owing to their performing
				all the work of joiners, carpenters
				and masons have blistered hands. In
				fact, their hands are much harder to
			</p>
         <p>
				the touch than those of the men; and
				indeed their entire muscular system is
				far more developed and they are pro¬
				portionately stronger in the arm.5
				Similarly, the tipi-builders of the Great
				Plains were responsible for all aspects of
				the construction of their dwellings. They
				developed one of the most striking forms
				in women's vernacular architecture. The
				Plains societies were mobile; they moved
				from winter hunting camps to large sum¬
				mer ceremonial villages and the women
				carried not only the skin coverings and
				interior liners, but the poles with which
				the tipi was erected as well. These were
				hard to find on the Plains, and made a
				useful sled (travois) for carrying house¬
				hold property and people over long dis-
				tances.
				When more permanent materials were
				used for making dwellings, women often
				cooperated in their manufacture. In mak¬
				ing an ordinary tipi, the owner scraped
				and tanned the hides from which the
				cover would be made, frequently using
				treasured tools which she had inherited
				from the women of her family. Then a
				female specialist was called in to cut and
				fit the skins, and neighbors gathered to
			</p>
         <p>
				but the traditional sacred designs and high
				standards of work are still rigorously
				adhered to.
				The Quillers' Society met when a wom¬
				an of the community had vowed to under¬
				take a project. An older woman held the
				society's medicine bundle, filled with
				objects of spiritual power, and with the
				vower, performed the rituals necessary
				for the work to begin and end. She would
				instruct the younger woman in needle¬
				work and the society's ceremonies; then
				the entire group started work together.
				Afterwards the woman who had vowed
				the task continued alone, although she
				could consult with society members
				whenever a problem arose.
				Men and children were not allowed to
				touch or see the work until it was com¬
				pleted, when members of the society dis¬
				played the piece to the public. Following a
				feast, the women whose work was on
				view became a member of the society, one
				of the most respected institutions of her
				world. Among the Cheyenne a woman's
				achievements in decorative craft were
				valued as highly as a man's deeds in war.
				Moreover, the Quillers' Society:
				was spoken of as being similar in
			</p>
         <p>
				Southern Cheyenne woman erecting a tipi. (Museum of the American Indian, Heye Foundation.)
			</p>
         <p>
				help stitch them together with sinew.
				Making a tipi could also fulfill a sa¬
				cred function. Plains women formed spe¬
				cial associations, notably the Cheyenne
				Quillers' Society, for the ceremonial deco¬
				ration of tipis and their interior walls with
				dyed porcupine or bird quills. More re¬
				cently these tipis have been made from
				canvas and decorated with glass beads,
			</p>
         <p>
				conception and attitudes to the
				Sacred Arrows [most sacred Chey¬
				enne men's society), one very impor¬
				tant difference in behavior may be
				noted. During the four-day arrow cer¬
				emony no talking, joking, or laugh-
				ing was allowed in camp. The mak¬
				ing of the sacred beading was at¬
				tended by a good deal of joking,
				teasing, and fun. While the cere¬
			</p>
         <p>
				37
			</p>
         <pb n="4"/>
         <p>
				monial character of the work was
				recognized, it interfered in no way
				with the social pleasure of the occa¬
				sion.6
				Female Farmers
				When societies obtain their food pre¬
				dominantly from horticulture, it is practi¬
				cal for the people to settle in more per¬
				manent villages close to their fields. Jobs
				are traditionally assigned to one sex or an
				other. Sometimes men and women culti¬
				vate different crops and even speak differ-
				ent languages.
				Even space within the village might alsco
				be divided along sex lines, and the archi¬
				tecture reflects and affects sex-specialized
				tasks. Women generally dominate culti-
				vation but building tasks are specified and
				divided according to sex. In much of
				Africa the characteristic building form is
				round, with a gabled and thatched roof
				and walls made of wattle and daub. Each
				component is made separately by men
				or women. Male and female tasks vary
				from society to society. Among the Kiku¬
				yu of Kenya, men construct the walls and
				women the roof. After the men finish their
				work, they go to the feast celebrating the
				house building. They goad the women,
				calling them "slow chameleons“ who will
				miss the feast if they don't hurry. The
				women, who are working on the thatch¬
				ing, typically respond in chorus:
				You men, you lack the most impor¬
				tant art in building, namely thatch¬
				ing. A wall and an empty roof cannot
				protect you from heavy rain nor
				from the burning sun. It is our careful
				thatching that makes the hut worth
				living. We are not chameleons but
			</p>
         <p>
				nyoni ya nyagathanga ssmall song-
				birds known for their beautiful
				nests).
				Separation of the sexes does not neces¬
				sarily serve as a foundation for male
				domination. Cultural practices that en¬
				courage one sex to feel communal soli¬
				darity and to express itself in opposition
				to the other seem to yield much autonomy
				to both men and women as groups, indi¬
				cated by the development of separate eco¬
				nomic, social or ritual spheres outside of
				the activities that demand the involve¬
				ment of both sexes. The position of wom¬
				en is particularly strong in matrilineal
				societies, where they are leaders of clans
				and owners of the fields, of harvest, food
				storage and dwellings. The longhouse of
				the Iroquois-speaking tribes of North
				America, built until the mid-nineteenth
				century, was controlled by women, and
				was a remarkable example of communal
				living. The longhouse served as the center
				of Iroquois social life. Ritual perfor¬
			</p>
         <p>
				mances took place there and it was both
				dwelling and workplace for the many
				families of the clan to whom it belonged.
				By controlling the longhouse and the food
				stores, women played a vital part in the
				political affairs of the tribes.8 Through
				manipulation of supplies they could en¬
				courage or prevent war parties. The
				senior women, who controlled the long¬
				house, also played an important role in
				social policy decisions. They appointed
				spokesmen for the clan in village and
				tribal councils, and they could also "re¬
				move the horns," that is, remove those
				spokesmen from office if they did not do
				their job according to the women's inter¬
				ests. The longhouse stood as a symbol of
				the society at large; the confederation of
				the Iroquois tribes recognized the signifi¬
				cance of this woman-owned institution by
				naming themselves The League of the
				Longhouse.
				There are few matrilineal cultivating
				societies remaining in the world. One of
				their striking characteristics was that they
				were subsistence societies —that is, no
				wealth was accumulated from year to
				year. Although the source of food and the
				type of settlement differed, they shared
				this feature with the gathering peoples
				mentioned earlier. The change from sub¬
				sistence society to one in which it is pos¬
				sible to accumulate wealth frequently
				comes with the addition of livestock or
				herd animals to horticultural life. Such a
				change in process was observed in the
				early nineteenth century among the Man¬
				dan, a cultivating society living on the
				North American Plains. Basically, the
				Mandan lived two life styles. The matri¬
				lineal one dominated the life of the vil¬
				age, where women were the farmers and
				owned and built the houses; the second
				was patrilineal, occurring during the sum-
				mer months, when some of the women
				tended the fields, while most of the men
				and a few women went into the Plains to
				hunt buffalo. This resulted in an impor¬
				tant division of economic tasks and calen¬
				dars —the women living by an older agri¬
				cultural calendar, and the men by the sea¬
				sonal migration of the buffalo herds.
				In the Mandan village, the lodges the
				women constructed were admirably
				suited to the climate of the Great Plains.
				They may have originated as structures
				like those of the Pima. Walls of willow
				saplings and brush and a final layer of
				earth were erected over a wooden frame.
				The walls were built quite thick and the
				lodges were cool in summer and warm in
				winter. Quite possibly these were the
				prototypes for the sod houses built by
				pioneers settling in the Plains in the nine¬
				teenth century.
			</p>
         <p>
				38
			</p>
         <pb n="5"/>
         <p>
				If the Mandan had survived the epi¬
				demic of smallpox which destroyed the
				tribe in 1840, it is possible that they would
				have become patrilineal, giving up culti¬
				vation altogether to pursue the buffalo as
				other Plains tribes did. In patrilineal soci¬
				eties, as we have seen with the Cheyenne,
				the woman's position is secure when she
				continues to control important cultural or
				economic features. Frequently these two
				spheres are connected, as in societies
				where women have a specialized architec¬
				ture for their own activities. The Igbo
				society in Nigeria is patrilineal, but with
				the exception of the yam, all produce is
				considered women's property; they sell
				anything left over from feeding their fami¬
				lies, becoming successful traders. A cen¬
				tury ago when this marketing activity
				was increasing, the women also began to
				construct ritual sanctuaries in groves out¬
				side the villages. Called mbayo houses,
				these were maintained by a cult of the
				earth goddess Ala, and were decorated
				with male and female symbols and erotic
				figures.
				In patrilineal societies women may
				have certain economic powers; if so, they
				usually own their own houses within the
				compounds of their husbands' families.
				But when men control agriculture and
				herding, or have access to a modern cash
				market, the domicile and all public build¬
				ings fall totally under male control. Men
				erect the structures; if they are dwellings,
				women may decorate the walls. In Medi¬
				terranean villages in Spain, Greece and
				the Balkans, and in Islamic villages of the
			</p>
         <p>
				Near East and Africa, woman is associ¬
				ated with the domicile as its caretaker, not
				as its owner. The isolation of women in
				the home is, of course, a function of
				wealth. In poorer cultures the woman
				may be forced to work for the family's
				survival, but in most places, she is sup¬
				posed to remain in the home. In Spain,
				she decorates her house with whitewash
				as a symbol of purity —both of the domi¬
				cile and of its keeper. When a woman's
				life is relegated to the private sphere of
				society, her significance in the culture ap¬
				pears merely symbolic. She is a posses¬
				sion to be protected. In Berber villages,
				she weaves inside her husband's house;
				the loom is not considered her tool, but a
				symbol of male protection. Sitting behind
				it, she is shielded from the door and from
				the street life that lies beyond it.? Thus
				women are isolated from the world of
				confrontation, conversation and public
				interaction.
				With the advent of industrialism and
				the wage economy in any society, separa¬
				tion of home life from public work be¬
				comes firmly entrenched. The many roles
				of women are reduced to motherhood and
				housekeeping. The number of craftswom¬
				en, artists, businesswomen and builders
				decrease. Separation of home from busi¬
				ness premises makes it more difficult for
				women to share in a work world domi¬
				nated by men. Machine-made products
				limit the type of paid work that can be
				done in the household. Control over the
				design and construction of buildings
				passes into the hands of "professionals.
				Women's creativity is confined to plan¬
				ning interiors and obtaining or making in¬
				terior decorations according to mass-pro¬
				duced guides like women's magazines.
				Ironically, this vestige of woman's im¬
				portance as architect and builder is used
				against her when psychology and popular
				belief insist that women are by nature'
			</p>
         <p>
				oriented to interiors, and interiors alone.
				The home, as the exclusive province of
				women, has become a significant cultural
				image on many levels — almost an arche¬
				typal reflection of the privatization of
				women's lives and the resulting obsession
				with house/home. So now we paint,
				write, sculpt our houses; so far, too few
				of us are creating architecture.10 In learn¬
				ing more about the options available to
				women in other cultures, we become
				more conscious of our own untapped
				potential.
				1. Colin Turnbull, The Forest People (New
				York: Natural History Library, 1962),
				pp. 156-157.
				2. Edward T. Hall, Beyond Culture (Garden
				City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1976), Chap. 5,
				passim.
				3. Patricia Draper, "IKung Women," in To¬
				ward an Anthropology of Women, ed. Rayna
				Reiter (New York: Monthly Review Press,
				1975), p. 94.
				4. Turnbull, pp. 59-60.
				5. J.G. Kohl, Kitchi-Gami: Wandering Round
				Lake Superior (London, 1860), p. 4.
				6. Alice Marriott, The Trade Guild of South¬
				ern Cheyenne Women," Bulletin of Okla-
				homa Anthropological Society (April 1956),
				p. 24.
				7. Jomo Kenyatta, Facing Mount Kenya, Re-
				print of original 1938 edition (New York:
				AMS Press, 1976), pp. 80-81.
				8. Judith K. Brown, "Iroquois Women: An
				Ethnographic Note, in Toward an Anthro¬
				pology of Women, pp. 235-251
				9. Pierre Bourdieu, "The Berber House, or the
				World Reversed," excerpted in Rules and
				Meanings, ed. Mary Douglas (Baltimore:
				Penguin, 1973), p. 100.
				10. Two recently published books have begun
				the documentation of women in architec¬
				ture: Doris Cole, From Tipi to Skyscraper:
				A History of Women in Architecture (Boston:
				press, 1973) and Susana Torre, ed., Women
				in American Architecture: A Historic and
				Contemporary Perspective (New York: Wat-
				son-Guptill, 1977).
				A native of Tennessee, Elizabeth Weatherford is
				an anthropologist on the faculty of the School of
				Visual Arts.
			</p>
         <p>
				39
			</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
