<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='100'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>a newborn conch</l>
					<l>sparkles on wet sand</l>
					<l>no bigger than a grain of rice</l>
					<l>already</l>
					<l>she knows how to secrete</l>
					<l>her own house</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>III.</l>
					<l>concerned we are concerned</l>
					<l>we have always been alone together</l>
					<l>we have always confided in one another</l>
					<l>we have always found time to whisper</l>
					<l>amongst ourselves concerning our concerns</l>
					<l>long ago we learned to speak to each other</l>
					<l>with borrowed cups of sugar</l>
					<l>singing together as we washed our blood</l>
					<l>from endless sheets and towels</l>
					<l>nourishing each other with perpetual</l>
					<l>soup concerned we have</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Design for the City of Women</l>
					<l>Jacqueline Lapidus</l>
					<l>to Catherine Blake</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Walking along the shore at low tide, I came to a place where the cliffs were white with salt, as if the</l>
					<l>tears of an entire continent had dried in an instant on the rock’s flushed face. Above the high water mark</l>
					<l>was a row of irregularly shaped holes in which birds nested; above these, the earth was brick-red, and at</l>
					<l>the summit tufts of wild rosemary, thyme and fern thrust their heads into a hazy sky. As I stood admiring</l>
					<l>the wheeling flight of the gulls, I heard music coming from the next beach. I climbed over a shelf of mossy</l>
					<l>rocks, following the sound, and stumbled into the entrance of a grotto worn away in the cliff. The sun had</l>
					<l>not yet set. A shaft of late afternoon light slipped violet into the grotto and fell upon a circle of women</l>
					<l>sitting around a slab of rock that jutted out from the cavern wall like a table.</l>
					<l>The women were not surprised to see me. They moved over to make room for me at the table. In the</l>
					<l>center of the table was a tide pool filled with mussels and clams. One of the women dipped her hand into</l>
					<l>the pool and scooped up several fresh clams with fluted shells which she offered to me. I pulled one from</l>
					<l>its shell with my teeth and swallowed it live; it slipped easily down my gullet, and in a few seconds I felt a</l>
					<l>warm, insistent throbbing between my legs as my clitoris emerged from its bed of wet moss. The women</l>
					<l>smiled at me and began to sing, in a language strangely familiar. I lay down naked on the rock ledge with</l>
					<l>my buttocks in the tide-pool, my arms and legs outstretched. The women leaned over me. Their cool</l>
					<l>fingers stroked my hands and feet, then my nipples and my clitoris. One woman slid her tongue deep into</l>
					<l>my cunt, and 1 felt a great wave surge through my entire body.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='101'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>always been concerned</l>
					<l>for centuries our cheeks have brushed</l>
					<l>each other’s cheeks at weddings</l>
					<l>funerals, fairs and church bazaars</l>
					<l>we have tasted each other’s tears</l>
					<l>laying out corpses</l>
					<l>we have stroked our sisters’ bellies</l>
					<l>and held our daughters’ hands</l>
					<l>and sung to their screams, and drawn</l>
					<l>babies gasping from their wombs</l>
					<l>concerned we are always concerned,</l>
					<l>oh yes we are used to one another</l>
					<l>bearing our burden together, struggling</l>
					<l>for a common cause: our own survival</l>
					<l>and now we are doing it</l>
					<l>openly and for ourselves</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>IV.</l>
					<l>The women live in the grotto. They gather seaweed, moss and wild flowers which they eat raw, or</l>
					<l>pound into paste to form little cakes baked in the sun. Mussels, clams, shellfish and tiny crabs caught in the</l>
					<l>cracks of the rocks at low tide also nourish the women. Their bodies are strong, tanned and healthy. They</l>
					<l>have learned to conceive their babies parthenogenetically. Any woman, by concentrating her energy and</l>
					<l>projecting it into her lover’s fertile womb, can get her with child. During pregnancy, the women caress</l>
					<l>each other’s bellies to prepare the child for community. They give birth squatting: friends support the</l>
					<l>mother as she breathes, blows and grunts in rhythm with the others, who also sing to encourage her and</l>
					<l>maintain the breathing pattern. When the baby has emerged from the womb, they bathe it in sun-warmed</l>
					<l>sea water, lay it on the mother’s belly, and massage it gently until it begins to smile. When a mother lacks</l>
					<l>milk for her child, another nursing mother offers the baby her breast. The women delight in the taste of</l>
					<l>one another’s nipples, and send shivers of pleasure through their entire bodies by drinking one another’s</l>
					<l>milk.</l>
					<l>The women have lived together for so long that nearly all menstruate at the same time. During the</l>
					<l>menstrual period they feel particularly strong and exuberant. The power of their blood surges through</l>
					<l>them. Squatting on the beach, they study the patterns made by their blood on the sand, acquiring an</l>
					<l>intimate knowledge of the inner self. At night they perform the following ritual: The women reach into</l>
					<l>each other’s cunts, extracting the blood with loving fingers, then paint each other’s bodies with it. Images</l>
					<l>of pleasure flow from each woman onto her partner’s face, breasts, belly and buttocks. Then they dance</l>
					<l>in spiral formation, singing of their lives, their loves. When a young girl menstruates for the first time, her</l>
					<l>mother or wet-nurse initiates her into the blood-painting ritual. Older women who no longer menstruate,</l>
					<l>excited by the younger women’s caresses, secrete enough cyprine to paint their bodies. Although the</l>
					<l>symbols are colorless on their wrinkled skin, everyone can see them clearly.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Dear Catherine, the message</l>
					<l>you could not then transmit to us</l>
					<l>has nonetheless arrived</l>
					<l>as surely as if etched with acid</l>
					<l>on the moon’s dark side</l>
					<l>spreading like bacteria</l>
					<l>nourishing as bread</l>
					<l>decoded in our guts</l>
					<l>absorbed into the very tissues of our being</l>
					<l>and suddenly appearing</l>
					<l>as sweat, saliva, blood, cyprine</l>
					<l>women’s language of love</l>
					<l>the words of the poems dance across the page,</l>
					<l>the birds in the air dance above the clouds,</l>
					<l>the fish in the water dance among the waves</l>
					<l>let us leave the drones to build cities</l>
					<l>let us play with each other like ribbons of light</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<pb n='102'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>The women are developing a new language, fully aware that although they have become a people</l>
					<l>capable of reproducing themselves, they can not consider themselves a nation unless they share a mother</l>
					<l>tongue. They expect this to take several centuries.</l>
					<l>&quot;We live,” says Catherine, &quot;in the crevices, the hollows, the spaces, the secret places, we live on the</l>
					<l>edge of the wave. The tide never goes out exactly as she came in—she always leaves us something we can</l>
					<l>use.</l>
					<l>She reminds me that the little mermaid’s fatal error was not that she longed for feet, but that she paid</l>
					<l>for them with her voice.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>VII.</l>
					<l>Point.</l>
					<l>Pirouette.</l>
					<l>Spiral.</l>
					<l>Each dwelling shall begin with the self</l>
					<l>firmly planted on her own spot</l>
					<l>concentrating energy.</l>
					<l>Clitoris.</l>
					<l>Navel.</l>
					<l>Plexus.</l>
					<l>Psyche.</l>
					<l>Stretching, unfolding, expanding,</l>
					<l>turning, whirling</l>
					<l>outward upon her axis.</l>
					<l>Ears.</l>
					<l>Nostrils.</l>
					<l>Mouth.</l>
					<l>Vagina.</l>
					<l>Anus.</l>
					<l>Each orifice dilates, opening</l>
					<l>like windows, the air</l>
					<l>dances through the body.</l>
					<l>Cell.</l>
					<l>Chromosome.</l>
					<l>Molecule.</l>
					<l>Atom</l>
					<l>Particle.</l>
					<l>Elements in orbit, exchanging</l>
					<l>surplus for need in perpetual motion,</l>
					<l>pleasurebound</l>
					<l>syntax, uniqueness</l>
					<l>incorporate.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Jacqueline Lapidus is a radical lesbian feminist who lives in Paris. Her latest book of poems is Starting Over, published</l>
					<l>by Out and Out Press.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
