<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1"/>
         <p>
				Criticism/or/Between the Lines
			</p>
         <p>
				Howardena Pindell
				O 1979
			</p>
         <p>
				February 1979
				The following notes were prepared for publi¬
				cation after ! participated in a symposium on
				art criticism organized by John Goodyear and
				held at Douglass College, Rutgers University
				New Brunswick, New Jersey, April 20, 1978.
				The panelists were Joseph Kosuth, Rosalind
				Krauss, Morse Peckham, Alan Coleman, Leon
				Golub and Howardena Pindell, with Donald
				Kuspit as moderator The following questions
				were addressed to the panelists by Kuspit prior
				to the symposium:
				Is the critic a legitimator of values? The art¬
				ist carries the burden of his/her own jus¬
				tification, but what is the role of the critic in
				this? Is it possible to eliminate any hierarchical
				relationship between artists and critics—to
				eliminate any residue of feeling that the one is
				better than the other? The working relationship
				between the artist and the critic: how does one
				deal with the possible promotional value of
				criticism, both bad and good, favorable and
				unfavorable to the artist? Does criticism exist
				as a thing in itself, can it exist as such, or does
				it only function along with the works with
				which it deals?
				The effects of criticism on the art work are
				rarely confronted. Somehow the examination of
				any activity in the art community, criticism be¬
				ing only one, is taboo, "tasteless and crude.
				decided to tackle the subject despite the antici¬
				pated disapproval, motivated partly by some of
				my riper experiences in the art world (during
				my exhibition at A.I.R. Gallery in 1973 a young
				white male critic confided to me that he hesi¬
				tated to review my exhibition because he heard
				that 1 was black—and told me how relieved he
				was to find that the work was good). In spite of
				some experiences to the contrary, 1 recognize
				that a few critics, and even a few dealers, those
				who pioneer in showing work considered “dif-
				ficult"' by the "art world,"' do attempt to be
				open and fair and aware of their own motiva¬
				tions. It is to the remainder that 1 direct the
				following.
				have decided to take a rather subjective ap¬
				proach to the questions presented. When 1 read
				through the topics to be discussed, my first
				response was a feeling of negativity towards
			</p>
         <p>
				criticism and the institution of art writing as it
				is manifested in art periodicals, mass-produced
				art books, and newspapers. From my vantage
				point as an artist, 1 find that critics usually
				view an artist’s work while it is on exhibition in
				a gallery and, occasionally, while it is on view
				in a public institution. A number of critics do
				not as a rule go to the studio independent of an
				exhibition. More often than not the gallery
				exhibition brings them forth, prodded by the
				dealer or the artist, or coaxed by financial
				necessity...the need to earn money or “brown¬
				ie points"' by having reviews or articles pub¬
				lished. The critic is therefore viewing work
				which has been preselected by the dealer. A
				gallery is a business. Making money is its
				primary objective. The critic is used by the
				dealer as a means of endorsing the "product'i
				work of art), ripening it for sale. (If a repro¬
				duction of a work appears in a review or an
				article, it is often sold as a result of the en¬
				dorsement.) Criticism is contaminated by the
				fact that it is used to market a “product. A
				parallel in the non-art world can be seen in the
				subtle manipulations utilized by advertising to
				create a need for a particular product in order
				to increase profits. The critic is therefore used
				as a means of "hyping" an artist's work.
				A number of unconscious factors determine
				what is marketable and what is not, who is
				written about and who is not. These un¬
				conscious factors include learned attitudes re¬
				flecting the negative and positive fantasies and
				taboos of a culture. In this culture work by
				white males is more marketable than work by
				non-white males or females. (Occasionally
				honorary status"' is given to a non-white if a
				market is temporarily created for the work.)
				The needs of the buyer are based on class,
				caste, fashion, and personal preference, guided
				by unconscious factors. The buyer will tend to
				select that which appears to enhance self-image
				and improve status. The dealer is influenced by
				the needs of the buyer The critic is used to
				blessing" this interchange and making it appear
				on the surface to be something other than what
				it is... a form of barter with hidden incen¬
				tives. The critic is often a pawn, although he/
			</p>
         <p>
				2
			</p>
         <p>
				This content downloaded from
				134.82.70.63 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:19:44 UTC
				All use subject to https: //about, jstor.org/terms
			</p>
         <pb n="2"/>
         <p>
				she attempts to cloak the transaction in elabor¬
				ate syntax in an effort to fabricate an artificial
				"moral"' detachment. Critics rarely examine
				their own unconscious needs and goals for
				status or power, needs which seem to keep
				them locked into writing about what has al¬
				ready been approved and sifted by the dealers,
				avoiding controversy or controversial artists.
				A simplistic allegory about the system could
				be set forth: Some critics are gourmets (others,
				gourmands) who prefer to eat at the best res¬
				taurants (i.e., galleries). The maître d' (i.e.,
				dealer) knows the critic by name. Flattered by
				this recognition the critic accepts the menu
				(gallery staple) which lists the special of the
				day (current exhibition). The critic may praise
				or damn the cooking but returns for more. The
				critic rarely cooks at home (goes outside the
				established system to see work).
			</p>
         <p>
				The "mongrel"' hordes represent the taboos
				and negative fantasies of the tribe. The “mon¬
				grel"' hordes, or alternate clans, are made up
				of men and women, shamans and bards who
				are non-white or whites who have been out¬
				lawed by the main clan. Honorary status in the
				main clan may be achieved through death or a
				temporary economic demand.
				would like to address a few of the topics
				suggested by our moderator. "The working re¬
				lationship between the artist and the critic: how
				does one deal with its promotional aspects?'
				How is the critic influenced to select work to
				write about? It would be enlightening if a test
				could be devised to study how critics are influ¬
				enced on a subconscious level by setting up a
				method for reviewing the same work in differ¬
				ent settings. What would the critic say about
				the same artist who exhibits his/her work in a
			</p>
         <p>
				Howardena Pindell. Yes—No. Pen and ink on acetate. Photo credit: Amy Stromstem.
			</p>
         <p>
				One could see the art world and the critic's
				place within that world through the following:
				The art world is a neolithic, loose association of
				clans within a larger tribe. The clan chiefs are
				the dealers. The critics are the bards who sing
				the praises of the clan and its leaders. Artists
				are the shamans whose talents are sold through
				the chief. Rituals, reinforcement of the tribal
				structure, are performed in huts or compounds
				designated for this purpose (private and public
				institutions, auction houses).
				Advancement within the clan to higher rank
				is predominantly achieved through strategies
				dependent on the buddy system and nepotism.
				White males hold most of the prominent posi¬
				tions as shamans, bards and chiefs; however
				white females may be elevated to a position of
				prominence through personal financial status,
				ties of kinship or temporary bonds of affection.
			</p>
         <p>
				museum space, an alternate space, or in the
				studio; in a blue-chip gallery or one not-so¬
				blue-chip; in New York or out of New York?
				The variables are infinite. It would be addition¬
				ally enlightening to see how the same work
				would be reviewed where the gender and race
				of the artist are known, and not known, as well
				as the artist's financial status (i.e., whether the
				work sells or doesn’t sell). A fascinating study
				is discussed in Vance Packard's Hidden Per¬
				suaders. A study of behavior and motivation
				revealed that the same product wrapped in dif¬
				ferent packages elicited responses such as “too
				strong"' in a package of one color and shape,
				inadequate"' in another package, and "won¬
				derful" in yet another. Racial types used to
				display products were found to cause the
				viewer to project onto the product his/her posi¬
				tive or negative fantasies and expectations. A
			</p>
         <p>
				3
			</p>
         <p>
				This content downloaded from
				134.82.70.63 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:19:44 UTC
				luse subject to https: //about, jstor.org/terms
			</p>
         <pb n="3"/>
         <p>
				brown or black model elicited in Americans
				suspicion and a generally negative response to
				the product. The same product displayed with a
				blond Germanic type elicited in Americans a
				positive, warm, supportive response. How does
				the positive or negative halo effect distort a
				critic's judgment? (One wonders why there has
				never been a scientific objective study of the
				hidden aspects of the art world.) Who is the
				critic writing for and how is the critic affected
				and infected by the prejudices of his/her
				unconscious?
				Is it possible to eliminate any hierarchical
				relationship between artists and critics...?" As
				long as critics allow themselves to be used to
				promote "products"' and the "real estate
				value"' of art, and as long as the major part of
				this dialogue takes place in magazines depen¬
				dent on dealer advertising, a hierarchical rela¬
				tionship will continue. Artist is pitted against
				artist, thus creating an artificial need for the
				critic. The IRS, ironically, continues to promote
				this system by defining the artist as a “profes¬
			</p>
         <p>
				sional" or "hobbyist"' depending on how much
				work is sold. A number of "great"' artists sold
				few works in their lifetimes.
				A possible solution would be the placing of
				critical writing in publications which are not
				controlled by advertising. The alternate period¬
				ical would allow the critic to go directly to the
				public. A new generation of critics would
				emerge, a group less given to nepotism, less
				meshed with the cocktail circuit or bedtime
				grapevine, more conscious of their own limita¬
				tions and prejudices. The system, itself, could
				be influenced by the emergence of a new buy¬
				ing public as increasing amounts of money,
				through greater employment opportunities, are
				made available to non-whites and women. New
				demands could be made on the dealer, which
				would force the critic, locked into the system,
				to be influenced by default. Artists could
				change the structure by working and showing
				in a manner which circumvents the gallery,
				leaving it with less power over the artist or the
				critic.
			</p>
         <p>
				Gloria Rayl. Untitled. Clay masks pulled from manikin heads, suggests the tagging and discarding of Third World people.
			</p>
         <p>
				This content downloaded from
				34.82.
				2022 19:19:44 UTC
				n Sat, 2
				to h
				bout jst
				erms
			</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
