<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Jennings_Issue1_97</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: rmh036@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>Moratorium: Front Lawn: 1970
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>Kate Jennings
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>watch out! you may meet a real
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>castrating female
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>or
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>you&apos;Il say I&apos;m a manhating braburning
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>lesbian member of the castration
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>penisenvy brigade, which I am
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>I would like to speak.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>I would like to give a tubthumpingtablebanging
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>emotional rap AND be listened to, not laughed at.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>You don’t laugh at what your comrade brothers
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>say, you wouldn’t laugh at the negroes, the black
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>panthers. Many women are beginning to feel the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>necessity to speak for themselves, for their sisters.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>I feel the necessity now.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>It&apos;s the moratorium. l would say, oh yes, the war is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>bad a pig bosses war may the nlf win, I also say
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>VICTORY TO THE VIETNAMESE WOMEN. Now
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>our brothers on the left in the peace movement
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>will think that what I am about to say is not justi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>fied, this is a moratorium. It&apos;s justified anywhere.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>We&apos;ve heard you loud and clear before, brother¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>shits, we know we have to work towards the Revo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>lution and then join the ladies liberation auxiliary
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>if we have any time left over. l&apos;ve worked my
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>priorities out, I will work towards what I know
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>about, what I feel, and I feel because l&apos;m told ad
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>infinitum that l&apos;m a woman, l&apos;m a second-class
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>citizen, and l should shutup right now because my
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>mind&apos;s between my legs. I say you think with your
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>pricks. We should all get our priorities straight and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>organise around our own injustices, our own con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>dition. There are a lot of people here who feel
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>strongly about the Vietnam war. But how many of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>you, who can see so clearly the suffering and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>misery in Vietnam, how many of you can see at
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>the end of your piggy noses the women who can&apos;t
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>get abortions, how many of you would get off your
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>fat piggy asses and protest against the killing and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>victimisation of women in your own country. Go
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>check the figures, how many Australian men have
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>died in Vietnam, and how many women have died
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>from backyard abortions. Yes, that&apos;s cool, they&apos;re
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>only women, and you&apos;Il perhaps worry if your own
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>chickie gets pregnant. Can you think about all the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>unwanted children, or the discrimination against
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>unmarried mothers. Illegal dangerous abortions
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>are going to be performed regardless. So make
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>them legal. And to these women who think an
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>abortion campaign, or women&apos;s lib for that matter,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>is reformist, I quote &quot;in fighting for our liberation
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>we will not ask what is revolutionary or reformist,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>only what is good for women&quot; some of us are rev¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l53' n='N053'/>olutionaries, some of us are manhunting crazies,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l54' n='N054'/>but we are all working toward one thing, the lib¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l55' n='N055'/>eration of women, and most of us will recognise
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l56' n='N056'/>that this will only happen in a socialist society.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l57' n='N057'/>We all feel very strongly about conscription and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l58' n='N058'/>freedom of the individual, some go to great lengths
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l59' n='N059'/>to martyr themselves on the issue of the draft. I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l60' n='N060'/>don’t feel very strongly anymore about the ego
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l61' n='N061'/>scenes of the mike jones&apos;s around me. I do feel
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l62' n='N062'/>strongly about my freedom and my sisters&apos; free¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l63' n='N063'/>dom. Women are conscripted every day into their
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l64' n='N064'/>personalised slave kitchens, can you, with your
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l65' n='N065'/>mind filled with the moratorium, spare a thought
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l66' n='N066'/>for their freedom, identity, minds and emotions,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l67' n='N067'/>they&apos;re women, and your stomach is full. It suits
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l68' n='N068'/>you to keep women in the kitchens, and underpaid
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l69' n='N069'/>menial jobs, and with the children. You, by your
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>silence, apathy and laughter sanction the legis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>lators, the pig parliamentarians, the same men
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>who sanction the war in Vietnam. You won’t make
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>an issue of abortion, equal pay, and child minding
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>centres, because they&apos;re women&apos;s matters, and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>under your veneer you are brothers to the pig
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>politicians. And I say to all you highminded
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>intellectual women who say you&apos;re liberated with
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>such force and conviction, I say you make me
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>sick. So women&apos;s lib doesn’t concern you. Ask your
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>companion what he would prefer—to talk to you
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>or fuck you? (and if you say you&apos;d prefer to be
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>fucked, you&apos;ve absorbed your conditioning well).
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>And the women in the suburbs are no concern of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>yours? Your mother is no concern of yours? so long
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>as you think you&apos;re liberated, all&apos;s well. You and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>your sisters and the silent suburban women are all
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>part of a capitalist PATRIARCHAL society which
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>you cannot ignore.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>And don’t start to trust the sympathetic men who
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>want a socialist society. Where will the women be
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>after the revolution? Go, ask them, the men on the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>left stink—they stink from their motherfucking
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>socks to their long hair, from their jock straps to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>their mao and moratorium badges. The ones who
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>pretend to espouse our aims are far worse than
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>those who at least wear their true colors on their
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>sleeves. And to my brothers on the drug scene.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>Grass is good. Oh yes, but instead of becoming
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>happy and peaceful and oh so motherfucking lov¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>ing all I can see is you sitting there, asserting, even
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>grooving on your maleness, dominating every joint
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>every puff. Chickies aren’t very good at rapping,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>aren’t clever or subtle enough. I mean, it&apos;s a male
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>scene, isn’t it, you fat arrogant farts.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>Okay, I&apos;ve stopped trying to love and understand
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>my oppressors.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l38' n='N038'/>I know who my enemy is.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l39' n='N039'/>I will tell you what I feel, as an individual, as a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l40' n='N040'/>woman.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l41' n='N041'/>I feel that there can be no love between men and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l42' n='N042'/>women.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l43' n='N043'/>Maybe after the revolution people will be able to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l44' n='N044'/>love each other regardless of skin color, ethnic
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l45' n='N045'/>origin, occupation or type of genitals. But if that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l46' n='N046'/>happens it will only happen if we make it happen.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l47' n='N047'/>Starting right now.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l48' n='N048'/>I feel hatred.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l49' n='N049'/>I feel anger.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l50' n='N050'/>Without indulging in an equality or marxist argu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l51' n='N051'/>ment I say all power to women because that&apos;s what
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l52' n='N052'/>I feel.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l53' n='N053'/>ALL POWER.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l54' n='N054'/>And I say to every woman that every time you&apos;re
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l55' n='N055'/>put down or fucked over, every time they kick you
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l56' n='N056'/>cunningly in the teeth, go stand on the street
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l57' n='N057'/>corner and tell every man that walks by, every one
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l58' n='N058'/>of them a male chauvinist by virtue of HIS birth¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l59' n='N059'/>right, tell them all to go suck their own cocks. And
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l60' n='N060'/>when they laugh, tell them that they&apos;re getting
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l61' n='N061'/>bloody defensive, and that you know what size
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l62' n='N062'/>weapon to buy to kill the bodies that you&apos;ve un¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l63' n='N063'/>fortunately laid under often enough.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l64' n='N064'/>ALL POWER TO WOMEN.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l65' n='N065'/>&quot;Kate Jennings is a feminist. She believes in what Jane
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l66' n='N066'/>Austen recommended at fifteen: Run mad as often as you
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l67' n='N067'/>chuse; but do not faint.&apos;&quot; This &quot;biography&quot; appears on the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l68' n='N068'/>jacket of Jennings&apos; book of poems (from which &quot;Moratori¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l69' n='N069'/>um&quot; is reprinted)—Come to Me My Melancholy Baby.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l70' n='N070'/>published in 1975 by Outback Press, Fitzroy (Victoria), in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l71' n='N071'/>her native Australia.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
