<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>If the Present Looks Like the Past, What Does the Future Look Like?</title>
            <author>Alice Walker</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>Issue 15: Race is the Issue</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="56"/>
				<head><title>IF THE PRESENT LOOKS LIKE THE PAST, WHAI DOES THE FUTURE LOOK LIKE?</title></head>
      	<byline>by Alice Walker</byline>			
         <p>
				Equally important, however, [to "What it is,
				brother?] is Whot it is, sister? No one dares to
				utter the plight of her reality, not evenemy black sisters themselves. But what it is, is the great cannon
				of cruel racism directed toward the black black
				woman by the black middle class. The black middle
				class has for generations excluded the black black
				woman from the mainstream of black middle-class
				society, and it has by its discrimination against her,
				induced in itself a divisive cancer that has chopped
				the black race in this country into polarized sections; consequentiy the block middle class has devoured its own soul and is doomed, a large number
				of black working-class people believe, to extinction.</p>
				<p>What it is is an insanity that has helped whites
				turn blacks on themselves and that has caused the
				black middle class to claw itself into a form of psychic annihilation.</p>
				<p>Thus the black working class is beginning to ask
				itself the questions: "What is a people that props
				itself up on the color of its skin? And what is a people that excludes the womb-source of its own genetic
				heritage?" For certainly every Afro-American is
				descended from a black black woman. What then
				can be the destiny of a people that pampers and
				cherishes the blood of the white slaveholder who
				maimed and degraded their female ancestor? What
				can be the future of a class of descendants of slaves
				that implicitly gives slaveholders greater honor
				than the African women they enslaved? What can
				be the end of a class that pretends to honor blackness while secretly it despises working class black
				skinned women whose faces reveal no trace of
				white blood?</p>
				<bibl>—Trellie Jeffers. "The Black Black Woman and the Black Middle Class: A Personal Viewpoint." The Black Scholar (March-April 1973).</bibl>
				
				<p>For many years I pondered Jeffers' statement,
				then turned to black literature because it is so
				very instructive, to see whether it had support. I
				began with three l9th-century novels by black
				women, as background and this is what l found.
				In the first novel one character savs to another:</p>
				<quote>"But if you d'seed them putty white hands of hern
				you'd never think she kept her own house, let 'lone
				anybody else's.<lb/>
				"My! but she's putty. Beautiful long hair comes
				way down her back: putty blue eyes, an jez ez white
				as anybody in dis place..."</quote>
				<p>In the second novel, it goes like this:</p>
				
				<quote>Meg Randal opened wide a pair of lovely dark
				eyes and raised two small, white hands in surprise.
				Ethel sat down and took one of Meg's perfect little
				hands in her own. Meg's hand was her one source
				of pride, and it would almost seem as if she were
				justified in this pride. Such a delicate white slender, dimpled hand it was!</quote>
				<p>In the third novel.</p>
				<quote>"Her dress was plain black, with white chiffon at the
				neck and wrists, and on her breast a large bunch of
				"Jack" roses was fastened .... Tall and fair with
				hair of a golden cast, aquiline nose, rosebud mouth,
				soft brown eyes veiled by long dark lashes which
				swept her cheek, just now covered with a delicate
				rose flush she burst upon them - a combination of
				queen rose and lily in one."</quote>
				<p>The novels quoted fram are <title>Lola LeBoy. Or Shadows Uplifted</title> (published in 1895) by Frances
				Ellen Watkins Harper; <title>Megda</title> (1891) by Emma
				Dunham Kellv, and <title>Contending Forces</title> (1899) by
				Pauline E. Hopkins.</p>
				<p>Photographs of the novelists show them to be
				identifiably "colored" if not literally black. Why
				are their black heroines depicted as white — and
				non-working-class? After all, Frances Watkins
				Harper — the most notable of these writers - did
				not spend mest of her time with white-skinned,
				middle-class black women, but, following the Civil
				War, she worked as a lecturer and teacher
				among the black- and brown-skinned freed people during Reconstruction in the briefiy "liberated" South. She wrote of the women:</p>
				<quote>I know of girls from sixteen to twenty-two who iron
				till midnight that they may come te sehool in the day.
				Some of our scholars, aged about nineteen, living
				about thirty miles off, rented land, ploughed, planted, and then sold their cotton in order to come to
				us. A woman near me urged her hushand to go in
				debt five hundred dollars for a home as titles to the
				land they had built on were insecure, and she said
				to me, "We have five years to pay it in, and I shall
				begin today to do it if life be spared. I will make a
				hundred dollars at washing, for I have done it." Yet
				they have seven little children to feed, clothe, and
				educate. In the field the women receive the same
				wages as the men, and are often preferred, clearing
				the land, hoeing, or picking cotton with equal
				ability.</quote>
				
				<p>No "queen rose and lily in one her." No
				"<emph>delicate</emph> white hands." Brown hands and black
				hands all - if not because of genetics then because of the work. Yet no 19th-century black novelist, female or male, wrote novels about these
				women.</p>
				Indeed, ine verv orst novel by an Mrican¬
				American te be published cistelle Or Ee Col-
				ored Heroine (185) by William Wells Brown, in
				the very first paragraph of the 1867 edition not
				only offers black womanhood as indistinguish-
				able, physically from white but slanders, gen-
				erally, the black womanis character
				For many years the South has been noted for its
				beautiful Quadroon fone fourth black and capable
				of passing as white women Botties of ink, and
				reams of paper have been used te portray the
				finely-cuf and well-mouided featuree the silken
				curls. the dark and brilliant eves the splen-
				did forms ihe fascinatine smies and faccom-
				plished manners of these impassioned and volup-
				tuous daughters of the two racesthe unlawful
				product of the crime of human bondage. When we
				take into consideration the fact that no safeguard
				was ever thrown areund virtue and no inducement
				held out to slave-Women to be pure and chaete we
				will not be surprised when fold thataimmorality per¬
				vades the domestic cirele in the cities and towns of
				the South to an extent unknown in the Northern
				States Many a planters wife has dragsed-out a
				miserable existence with an aching heart arsseing
				her place in her husband's affections usurped by
				the unadorned heautwand cantivatine smiles of her
				waitins maid Indeed the greater portion of the
				coiored iomen in the days o slavery had no great
				er aspiration thon thet or becoming the inely
				dressed mistress oi some ichite man ny eiphasis!
				Notice how adroitiy Brovn places the respon-
				sibility for rape child abuse incest and other
				immoralities squarely on the shoulders of the
				persons least responsible for them, being en-
				slaved and powerless—black women—whom he
			</p>
         <p>
				sets up for this calumny by describing them as
				voluptuous" and impassionsc
				It is unlikelv that a raped enslaved servant to
				a planter's wifé assumed, because oithis rape.
				that she had usurpenthe witeaplace in the
				rapist's affeetiens Braien obieusi intended
				blacks to feelprond of the insuliine aitentions"
				of the rapisgand ererioia because ofdie suffer¬
				ing of the e set Erein wond have us
				believe the enslauee womanugs ds neterful as
				the enslaven eince with her eme She Sapti-
				vatesd), " 1icantured himjust aahecaptured
				her with his gun and his lawe.
				Nor does Brotn oneider te millions of
				raped, enslavenAfueen women hohad no like-
				lihood whatsoeyer orbesgmnenedressed
				or ever attainines
				Bottles of ink, reams dpanehe says.
				But who were these writer were in the
				17th, 18th, and 19th centuriesn fe excep-
				tions, white men, writing oftthei ven sadistic
				fantasies about black women and describing—
				in lurid detail—their own perverse sexual prefeee
				ences, where enslaved women were concernee
				These feverishly imaginedquadroon omen
				were not real, and ad more to de muith ihe
				white men chose to perceive biae women n
				the way blackinen perceited themorblach 
				
				en perceivec themselves
				And 18s Brotn auehsrbeeren
				this, ouptret black notei pues ue geens aler
				scene anderieis ttener eis nnchnaie rseile
				blondes aid henelesburdenen unerrhe
				weighturthelalgse eien grapnle withthe
				tedium of slateaae involued i some
				faithless white manerether nd rareh nbing
				anything reseiblieserdi 
				The threg seemen navele o 19th
				century turnedaom ie nes in
				depicting fblact Momanhead and follaed a
				black man dinterpreian d sehite leiters
				fantasies Sonsequenids aie ait was
				unheard dire darennee weman to
				appear in a norelunesas clear ahewas to
				be recognized as aprobem or a jokes in the
				case of Emma Eanin Wallace Thurman's The
				Blacker the 1929) schich axplored the
				very real tuiaisotablackbiack womanin a white
				and a coloisisuek blaclesoeist
				She shouie hste been a bor ihen eojen of skin
				wouldn t ave matieredse mueh ier waenit her
				mother altays sarinenat a black hor wouid get
				along but these black girl would neven knou any-
				thing but sonree and disappeintment
				The heroine of fhis novel-chinis et her biacl
				color as somethine unnaturai even demone Yet
				for millions of quite coniented wemen here and
				in Africa black sein issthe most nafural, un¬
				
				demonie thing in the world
				1 aaneresting to note the changes wrought
				in the maie hero of William Welis Brotens hovel.
				over the counee ofits sevaraiversions inthe first
				version he is wvhite skinned eren as Broun was
				himseihis father was white his mother mulat
				tal and capable of passing In the final version
				he is blaekskinned, thouch with eiraighe black
				hair he heroine, however remais fain and
				neber becemes darker thana der Burepean.
				Thege was mothingen ihe annear anee et Giofelle to
				indieBlood coursed
				through her veins, except, perhaps, the slight wave
				O1982 Alice Walker

         <pb n="57"/>

				of her hair, and the scarcely perceptible brunettish
				tinge upon the countenance. She passed as a rebel
				lady.
				One reason the nèvels of leth-century black
				authors abound with white-skinned wemen char¬
				acters is thatmost readers oi notels in the 19th
				century were white pecple shite Deaple who
				then, as more oifenthan nernou Coulconly iden-
				tify human feeling humaness i i Came in a
				white or near white bedy andbesause alhough
				black men couid be depietedashteralv bisekand
				still be considered men (sinée dark ie masculine
				to the Euro-American mind) the blaek-skinned
				woman, being dark andfemale mist perforce be
				whitened, sines fairnass ne andeis the stand-
				ard of Euro-Ameriean femimin
				Of course in the Tothcente of the
				former slaves could read at al having been
				denied literacy under penaltol law and cer-
				tainly could not hope to struggle threngh  novel,
				however true it might havesbeen te iheir experi-
				ence. It is understandable thatvriters wrote to
				the capacities of the audience at hand Yet their
			</p>
         <p>
				depictions of themselves and black peore
				whiter than we are has led to a crippling ot te
				imagination andéer truti itself fer whiche pa
				dearly-in anget hurt, enve andimisunderstane
				ing—to this dai
				Portunately for us thare aneg black em¬
				an writer Zora Nesle Hursien whe did nst
				view her black wamen charsgiers ihrouch ihe
				eyes ofmen hlack ar ehitesand it is in her Work
				—coming aiten Bnoren atkins Kelly andeHop-
				kins in the logentunandafter jesse Fauset,
				Nella Larsen andeanloemer in the 1920 orit-
				ers who stilledenisted black women as fair-
				skinned, if nor aemally rhie skinned and in
				other ways alvpical that hiael emen begin to
				emerge nafiralle in allihe eolors thatthe exist,
				predominantiebrotn skin and blac and cul-
				turally African-Ameriean dhoneh lanie Craw¬
				ford, Hurstensbeskndtnhereine is deseribed
				as being ligntatskin and feaierv of haias soon
				as she opens her meuth e know whe and what
				she is—and herhands iheugh genetically light"
				are brown fremthe labor she chares with other
				blacks, fromschem she is not in faat separate:
				though al thrse ether husbands atempt le con-
				vince her thatshe is
				Many darieskinned bisciomen fndit hard
				to identify with Janie Grawrord and speak dispar¬
				agingly of her mulatta privileges Privileges
				that stem from being worshipped for her color
				and hair, and being piaced by her color-stauck
				husbandsahove othar black women hle not
				being permittad to spsale in pilie besause her
				looks are supposed fossaval
				And fer ihe black man based on our litera¬
				ture and too often unfortunaiel an reality, the
				white lasking woman s locks do saveit al But
				what dothese locks in factsa For ihe dark
				skinned black woman i cemesas a geries of dis-
				appeimimente and embarrassments that ine
				wives et virinally al black leaders (includins
				Mareus Garveyl appear to have been chesen for
				the neaeness oftheir commierions to schite alone
				It is tue that Prederick Douglass hrst uie was
				black skinned, but he managedtaidemastofher
				actinity in his life Aegording oresearch done by
				Sylviä Evore pendernnie Murray Douglass
				sewed the very sailor suit Douglass escaped from
			</p>
         <p>
				slavery wearing, yet nowvhère does he give her
				credit for her help. His second wife the wife he
				chose in Freedom, was white; this marriage con-
				tinued a pattern that besanin the davaofslavery,
				when white was right and the oetoroon or quad-
				roon offspringota rapediacker mulattomnother
				was the nex bestthing lewhite A lock at the
				photographs ofthe wemen chosen by our male
				leaders is, in man avs ehillineyoil are a
				black-skinned woman Andthis ehin ex¬
				perience is one tiich thedarlne Hack
				woman can hardly escape having in these fiies
				of black pictorial historv Because itis apparent
				that though ihe manhave eenscibusly affirmed
				blackness in the abstsetand ten others, for
				themselves, lighiremainednient onle Maicolm X.
				among our recentmaie leaders chase toaffirm.
				by publicly loving and marivine hen black
				black woman. And it is thisneleshan his
				public" politics that acconnte for the respect
				black people, and especiallywemen had for him,
				and this that makes him radeal and revolution-
				ary in a way few of our other black male les
				are.
				
				Black black womenare not suppesed to
				these things. Bil to tell the truihand
				shouldn't we?e may be living our last monihs
				on earth), this soften dil wenohiee We are oid
				such things arenot serians and net poliieal
				and mean eiling to the blaet libenatien taus
				gle. Andeseme of usafter all marru sehiemen.
				who ape ssto cemplain  But no bladk woman
				pursues and propesegi sotorcem and auadison
				or white men as a malter ei female preregative:
				the patriarchal seeiei in which ve live does not
				permit it. The man chooges frequent ih the
				same perceptivit with which he choosesa toy.
				Every bläckman inTheir bves Wes Watch-
				ing Cod lusis atier jarie Grauford They lust
				after her colerandher lenghair neveronee con¬
				sideringhe pain her mother and grandmother
				(one rapécbua sehie manone va baek) must
				have enduredte pass alenihése qualities to
				her. Never ondsmineng ei länie s isolation be-
				cause of looks che cd nechoose norob her con-
				fusion whenshe ealsed thatthe ame men who
				idolize her jocks ane capable antotal separating
				her looks fremher self Phese were allbaekcoun-
				try folk, andsthey woulen tehate haucht of it in
				these terms Butthei irue mnferest n fanie is
				sadistic and pornoeraphie jus as that of the
				white men ot the time Would have been And I
				think this is one ofthe reasens Hurston (with her
				usual attention to the cfference hetween chat
				black folks saikand vehat they meantl mädle her
				character solaPomoint thisute ue
				The first tew Umes resd inen Eyes lman-
				ased to block theimplcations of the scene in
				Chanter in which lea Cake beats lanie Femi-
				nists have often ilagged mny aiention to i but I
				alwaye explained it as simi a mistake on
				Hurstens part Intruth Amissedhe peit entire¬
				Dotket happensd andcha happenedeis dne
				ef themestimportant insichts in the book
				Aste Hurston reader wilrecali les Gakeis
				vergsaleus efjanie, where Mre Furnar s broih
				ershe of icht skin and flvaway hainsig scou
				cerned There is noreasen forihis as jama time
				andagaininsists enereason Ten eake is jealous
				is because so unusual for a woman as light
				and well-to-do as Janie to be with a man as poor
			</p>
         <p>
				Dogon kneeling female figure. Mali. Wood. 23½".
			</p>
         <pb n="3"/>
         <p>
				and black as he is. Not because all the light¬
				skinned women chase after and propose to light¬
				skinned men, but because both light- and dark¬
				skinned men chase after and propose to light¬
				skinned women. Since the light-skinned men gen¬
				erally have more education than the blacker men,
				and better jobs (morticians to this day in the
				South are generally light-skinned blacks, as are
				the colored doctors and insurance men), they
				have the advantage of color, class and gainful
				employment, and so secure the "prizes" light¬
				skinned women represent to them. Like all
				prizes," the women are put on display and
				warned not to get themselves dirty (other black
				black people often being this "dirt“). Their resem¬
				blance to the white man's "prize, i.e., the white
				woman—whom they resemble largely because of
				rape (and I submit that any sexual intercourse
				between a free man and a human being he owns
				or controls is rape)—must be maintained at all
				times.
				Unlike Janie's first two husbands, Tea Cake
				has discovered that his "prize" is as attractive
				dirty as she is clean and supports her in her de¬
				termination to dress, speak and act as she likes.
				But he must still show his male friends, and the
				ubiquitous Mrs. Turner, who wishes to bring
				Janie and her brother together (light belongs to
				light, in her mind), that his ownership is intact.
				When Mrs. Turner brings her brother over and
				introduces him, Tea Cake has a "brainstorm.
				Before the week is over, he has "whipped" Janie.
				He whips her not, Hurston writes, "because
				her behavior justified his jealousy, but it relievec
				that awful fear inside him. Being able to whip her
				reassured him in possession. No brutal beating at
				all. He just slapped her around a bit to show he
				was boss. Everybody talked about it next day in
				the fields. It aroused a sort of envy in both men
				and women. The way he petted and pampered
				her as if those two or three face slaps had nearly
				killed her made the women see visions and the
				helpless way she hung on him made men dream
				dreams.
				An astute reader would realize that this is the
				real reason Tea Cake is killed by Janie in the end.
				Or, rather, this is the reason Hurston permits
				Janie to kill Tea Cake in the end. For all her  help¬
				less" hanging on to him, Janie knows she has
				been publicly humiliated, and though she acts the
				role of battered wife (from what I read, coming
				out of battered women's shelters, the majority of
				such batterings end in sex and the total submis¬
				sion—hanging on helplessly"—of the wife), her
				developing consciousness of self does not stop at
				that point. She could hardly enjoy knowing her
				beating becomes visions" for other women¬
				who would have to imagine themselves light
				and long-haired, like Janie, to 'enjoy“ them—or
				dreams, i.e., sexual fantasies, for Tea Cake's
				male friends.
				"Tea Cake, you sho is a lucky man," Sop-de¬
				Bottom told him. "Uh person can see every place
				you hit her. Ah bet she never raised her hand tuh
				hit yuh back, neither. Take some uh dese ol' rusty
				black women and dey would fight yuh all night long
				and next day nobody couldn't tell you ever hit 'em.
				Dat's de reason Ah done quit beating mah women.
				You can't make no mark on 'em at all. Lawd!
				would'nt Ah love tuh whip uh tender woman lak
				Janie! Ah bet she don’t even holler. She jus' cries,
				eh Tea Cake?" (my emphasis).
				Dat's right.'
				See dat! Mah woman would spread her lungs all
				over Palm Beach County, let alone knock out mah
				jaw teeth. You don’t know dat woman uh mine. She
				got ninety-nine rows uh jaw teeth and git her good
				and mad, she'll wade through solid rock up to her
				hip pockets.
			</p>
         <p>
				[To which Tea Cake replies:
				Mah Janie is uh high time woman and useter
				things. Ah didn't get her outa de middle uh de road.
				What is really being said here?
				What is being said is this: that in choosing the
				fair," white-looking woman, the black man as¬
				sumes he is choosing a weak woman. A woman
				he can own, a woman he can beat, can enjoy
				beating, can exhibit as a woman beaten; in short,
				a conquered" woman who will not cry out, and
				will certainly not fight back. And why? Because
				she is a lady, like the white man's wife, who is
				also beaten (the slaves knew, the servants knew
				the maid always knew because she doctored the
				bruises) but who has been trained to suffer in
				silence. Even to pretend sex is better afterward,
				that she enjoys it because her husband obviously
				does. A masochist.
				And who is being rejected? Those women
				out of the middle of the road"? Well, Harriet
				Tubman, for one, Sojourner Truth, Mary McCleod
				Bethune, Shirley Chisholm, Ruby McCullom, As¬
				sata Shakur, Joan Little and Dessie "Rashida
				Woods. You who are black-skinned and fighting
				and screaming through the solid rock of America
				up to your hip pockets every day since you ar¬
				rived, and me, who treasures every 99 rows of
				my jaw teeth, because they are all I have to chew
				my way through this world.
				That black men choose light and white women
				is not the women's fault, any more than it was
				their fault they were chosen as concubines to
				rich plantation owners during slavery. Nobody
				seems to choose big, strong, fighting light or white
				women (and these have existed right along with
				those who could be beaten). Though there used to
				be a saying among black men that fat white wom¬
				en are best because the bigger they are the more
				whiteness there is to love, this is still in the realm
				of ownership, of "prize. And any woman who
				settles for being owned, for being a "prize, is
				more to be pitied than blamed
				We are sisters of the same mother, but we
				have been separated—though put to much the
				same use—by different fathers. In the novels of
				Frank Yerby, a wildly successful black writer,
				you see us: the whiter-skinned black woman
			</p>
         <p>
				placed above the blacker as the white man's mis¬
				tress or the black man's "love. The blacker
				woman, when not preparing the whiter woman
				for sex, marriage or romance, simply raped. Put
				to work in the fields. Stuck in the kitchen. Raising
				everybody's white and yellow and brown and
				black kids. Or knocking the overseer down, or
				cutting the master's throat. But never desired or
				romantically loved, because she does not care for
				aesthetic' suffering. Sexual titillation is out, be¬
				cause when you rape her the bruises don't show
				so readily, and besides, she lets you know she
				hates your guts, goes for your balls with her
				knees, and calls you the motherfucker (in the
				original sense) you are until you knock her out.
				Perhaps one problem has been that so many
				of our leaders (and writers) have not been black¬
				skinned themselves. Think of William Wells
				Brown, who could pass; Charles W. Chesnutt,
				who could and did pass; Jean Toomer, who passed
				with a vengeance; Langston Hughes, who could
				pass (when young) as a Mexican; Booker T. Wash¬
				ington, John Hope Franklin, James Weldon John-
				son, Frederick Douglass, W.E.B. Du Bois, Arna
				Bontemps, Nella Larsen, Richard Wright, Chester
				Himes, Frank Yerby—all very different in ap¬
				pearance from, say, Wallace Thurman, who was
				drawn to write about a black black woman be¬
				cause he was so black himself, and blackness
				was a problem for him among other blacks lighter
				than himself, as it was among whites. We can
				continue to respect and love many of these writ¬
				ers, and treasure what they wrote because we
				understand America; but we must be wary of
				their depictions of black women because we
				understand ourselves.
				In his landmark essay "Of the Dawn of Free¬
				dom" (1903), W.E.B. Du Bois wrote:The problem
				of the twentieth century is the problem of the
				color-line—the relation of the darker to the light¬
				er races of men in Asia and Africa, in America
				and the islands of the sea. It was a phase of this
				problem that caused the Civil War. This is a
				true statement, but it is a man's vision. That is to
				say, it sees clearer across seas than across the
				table or the street. Particularly it omits what is
				happening within the family, "the race" at home;
				a family also capable of civil war.
			</p>
         <pb n="4"/>
         <p>
				In paraphrase of this statement I would say
				that the problem of the 21st century will still be
				the problem of the color-line, not only "of the
				relation of the darker races of men [sic) in Asia
				and Africa, in America and the islands of the
				sea," but of the relations between the darker and
				the lighter people of the same races, and of the
				women who represent both dark and light within
				each race. It is our familial" relations with each
				other in America that we need to scrutinize. And
				it is the whole family, rather than the dark or the
				light, that must be affirmed.
				Light- and white-skinned black women will
				lose their only link to rebellion against white
				America if they cut themselves off from the black
				black woman. Their children will have no hip
				pockets in which to keep their weapons, no teeth
				with which to chew up racist laws. And black
				black women will lose the full meaning of their
				history in America (as well as the humor, love
				and support of good sisters) if they see light and
				white black women only as extensions of white
				and black male oppression, while allowing them¬
				selves to be made ashamed of their own strength
				and fighting spirit: that fighting spirit that is our
				birthright, and, for some of us, our "rusty black'
				joy.
				As black women, we have been poorly pre¬
				pared to cherish what should matter most to us.
				Our models in literature and life have been, for
				the most part, devastating. Even when we wish it,
				we are not always able to save ourselves for
				future generations: not our spiritual selves, not
				our physical characteristics. (In the past, in our
				literature—and in life too—the birth of a "gold¬
				en" child to a dark mother has been perceived as
				a cause for special celebration. But was it? So
				much of the mother was obliterated, so much
				changed in the child, whose birth as often as not
				was by her unplanned.) But perhaps we can
				learn something, even from the discouraging
				models of earlier centuries and our own time.
				Perhaps black women who are writers in tle 21st
				century will present a fuller picture of the multi¬
				plicity of oppression—and of struggle. Racism,
				Sexism, Classism and Colorism will be very much
				a part of their consciousness. They will have the
				wonderful novels of black African women to read
				—Buchi Emecheta, Ama Ata Aidoo, Bessie Head
				and others—as 19th-century black women did
				not. They will have a record of the struggles of
				our own times. They will not think of other wom¬
				en with envy, hatred or adulation because they
				are "prizes. They will not wish to be prizes
				themselves. How men want them to look, act,
				speak, dress, acquiesce in beatings and rape will
				mean nothing whatsoever to them. They will, in
				fact, spend a lot of time talking to each other, and
				smiling. Women of all colors will be able to turn
				their full energies on the restoration of the planet,
				as they can't now because they're tied up with all
				this other stuff: divisions, resentments, old hurts,
				charge and countercharge! And talk about the
				need for teeth and hip pockets then! Women who
				are writers in the 21st century will undoubtedly
				praise everyone.
				In any case, the duty of the writer is not to be
				tricked, seduced or goaded into verifying by imi¬
				tation, or even rebuttal, other people's fantasies.
				In an oppressive society it may well be that all
				fantasies indulged in by the oppressor are de¬
				structive to the oppressed. To become involved in
				them in any way at all is, at the very least, to lose
				time defining yourself.
				To isolate the fantasy we must cleave to reali¬
				ty, to what we know, we feel, we think of life.
				Trusting our own experience and our own lives;
				embracing both the dark self and the light.
			</p>
         <p>
				FOR THE WHITE PERSON WHO WANTS
				TO KNOW HOW TO BE MY FRIEND
				BY PAT PARKER
			</p>
         <p>
				The first thing you do is to forget that i'm Black.
				Second, you must never forget that i'm Black.
			</p>
         <p>
				You should be able to dig Aretha, but don't play her every time
				i come over. And if you decide to play Beethoven—don't tell me
				his life story. They made us take music appreciation too.
				Eat soul food if you like it, but don't expect me to locate
				your restaurants or cook it for you.
				And if some Black person insults you, mugs you, rapes your sister,
				rapes you, rips your house or is just being an ass—please, do
				not apologize to me for wanting to do them bodily harm. It makes
				me wonder if you're foolish.
			</p>
         <p>
				And even if you really believe Blacks are better lovers than whites¬
				don’t tell me. I start thinking of charging stud fees.
				In other words—if you really want to be my friend—don't
				make a labor of it. I'm lazy. Remember.
			</p>
         <p>
				THE SUBURB DREAMS OF EVIL IN NEWARK, NJ
			</p>
         <p>
				BY HILDY YORK
			</p>
         <p>
				Small groups of teachers huddle like prisoners within circles of students,
				mostly Black;
				all the department stores are filled with sleazy rayon blouses and the
				signs are in Spanish;
				they have stolen the horses of the mounted police
				and canter arrogantly through the parks, not even stopping
				several rapes and muggings, even laughing and shouting obscenities;
				the city is completely locked, barred, gated, burned, or looted;
				the people are all thieves, rapists, murderers, or shiftless;
				all they do is drink, laugh, dope, pimp, collect welfare and stand around
				on corners;
				someday they will screech toward the suburbs in Cadillacs with fins or
				old jalopies with missing fenders,
				and we will have to give up our maids and hide in our split-level closets.
			</p>
         <p>
				Pat Parker lives and works in Oakland. Her most recent book is Movement in Black.
				Hildreth York, an art historian and artist, is an Associate Professor and currently
				Chair of the Art Department of Rutgers University, Newark College of Arts and
				Sciences.
				Linoleum prints by Michele Godwin, who studies at the School of Visual Arts, NYC.
			</p>
      </body>
   	<back><p>Alice Walker grew up a "definite brown" in Eatonton,
   		Ga. Her most recent novel is The Color Purple.</p></back>
   </text>
</TEI>
