<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Russ_Joanna-issue4</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>Women Talking, Women Thinking
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>Joanna Russ
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>What did we talk about?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>I don&apos;t remember. We talked so hard and sat so still that I got cramps in my knees. We had too many cups of tea and then
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>didn&apos;t want to leave the table to go to the bathroom because we didn’t want to stop talking. You will think we talked of revolu-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>tion but we didn&apos;t. Nor did we talk of our own souls. Nor of sewing. Nor of babies. Nor of departmental intrigue. It was politics
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>if by politics you mean the laboratory talk that characters in bad movies are perpetually trving to convey (unsuccessfully) when
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>they Wrinkle Their Wee Brows and say (valiantly—dutifully—after all, they didn’t write it) &quot;But, Doctor, doesn’t that violate
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>Finagle&apos;s Constant?&quot; I staggered to the bathroom, released floods of tea, and returned to the kitchen to talk. It was professional
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>talk. It left me grey-faced and with such concentration that I began to develop a headache. We talked about Mary Ann Evans&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>loss of faith, about Emily Bronté&apos;s isolation, about Charlotte Bronté&apos;s blinding cloud, about the split in Virginia Woolf&apos;s head
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>and the split in her economic situation. We talked about Lady Murasaki, who wrote in a form that no respectable man would
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>touch, Hroswit, a little name whose plays may perhaps amuse myself,&quot; Miss Austen who had no more expression in society
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>than a firescreen or a poker. They did not all write letters, write memoirs, or go on the stage. Sappho—only an ambiguous,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>somewhat disagreeable name. Corinna? The teacher of Pindar. Olive Schreiner, growing up on the veldt, wrote one book, mar-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>ried happily, and never wrote another. Kate Chopin wrote a scandalous book and never wrote another. (Jean has written
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>nothing.) There was M-ry Sh-Il-y who wrote you know what and Ch-rl-tt- P-rk-ns G-Im-n, who wrote one superb horror story
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>and lots of sludge (was it sludge?), and Ph-Il-s Wh--tl-y who was black and wrote eighteenth-century odes (but it was the eight¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>eenth century) and Mrs. -nn R-del-ff- who wrote silly novels and M-rg-r-t C-v-nd-sh and Mrs.-d-n S-thw-rth and Mrs. G--rg-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>Sh-Id-n and (Miss?) G-rg-tt- H-y-r and B-rb-r- C-rtl-nd and the legion of those who, writing, write not, like the dead Miss B--l-y
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>of the poem who was seduced into bad practices (fudging her endings) and hanged herself in her garter. The sun was going
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>down. I was blind and stiff.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>***
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>Twenty years ago I went to college and began to recognize the roof; having dressed for a date (dates were absolutely crucial
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>then) in my low heels, my nylons, my garter belt, my horsehair petticoat, my cotton petticoat, my taffeta skirt, my knit jersey
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>blouse, my circle pin, my gold earrings, my charm bracelet, my waist-cincher, my lipstick, my little bit of eye shadow, my heavy
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>faille coat, my nail polish, my mohair scarf, and my gloves, I went into the dormitory garden to wait. The garden was full of late
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>spring flowers. I had already admired myself in the full-length mirror on the back of my closet door, but standing between the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>stone walls on the stone-flagged walk, watching the flowers grow ever lighter and more disembodied in the blue twilight—and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>sitting on the stone bench under the Gothic arches and all that ivy—and we were supposed to get A’s and use the library—we
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>were supposed to write papers—we were supposed to be scholars—I felt invisible. I felt awful, I wanted to take off all my
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>clothes and step out of my underwear. And then take off my hair and fingernails and my face and my flesh and finally my very
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>bones. Just to step out of it. All the way out of it.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>My date said,  There you are!&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>*Various excerpts from the forthcoming novel, On Strike Against God, to be published in the spring of 1978 by Out and Out Books.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>14
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>I&apos;ve spent a lot of my time in the library here, picking out obscure references to memoirs written by bad ladies two hundred
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>vears ago and novels by worse ladies who, although personally blameless, wrote wicked books: A Romance of the Pyrenees.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>Marianna or The Puritan&apos;s Daughter. Weird, ghastly stuff. Five romances under the pseudonym By a Lady. Domestic senti¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>ment. Gothic castles. Purity. If only I can reduce this pulp to pulp and spread it out into some kind of shape. Dead voices,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>haunting and terrible: I want, I need, I hope, I believe. What sort of homes did they have? Did they do their own cooking? Did
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>they expect to get pregnant every year? (See Mrs. Defoe&apos;s journal.) The awful constriction, the huge skirts. Mrs. Pepys&apos; dress
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>allowance (&apos;&apos;the poor wretch,&quot; her husband called her).How are we fall&apos;n, fall&apos;n by mistaken rules!&quot; Women live like Bats or
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>Owls, labour like Beasts, and die like Worms.&quot; Anyone may blame me who likes.&quot; &quot;How good it must be to be a man when
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>you want to travel.&quot;John laughs at me, but one expects that in marriage.&quot;It had all been a therapeutic lie. The mind was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>powerless to save her. Only a man . . .&quot; &quot;I / Revolve in my / Sheath of impossibles—
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>Scholars don’t usually sit gasping and sobbing in corners of the library stacks.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>But they should. They should.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>* * *
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>Conversations with the Tooth Fairy:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>When I was five she stood at the foot of my bed in a dream, wearing an airy, blue, nylon-net gown and glittering rhinestone
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>jewelry, with a little rhinestone coronet on her head. Her magic wand was star-topped and she looked just like a Tooth Fairy
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>should.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>She was going to give me three wishes.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>But I woke up.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>And much later:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>Last night she came again and sat down on the end of my bed, looking very benevolent, spreading out her blue nylon-net
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>skirts, and recalling to me (even though I was asleep) where I had seen her before—she was somebody I saw in a live stage show
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>when I was four and I’d swear it was the Ice Follies because I remember her in ice skates.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>The Tooth Fairy: Good evening, dear child. I am here to help you.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>Me: Look here, I&apos;m almost forty. This is ridiculous.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>The Fairy: Never mind. To me you will always be a child. Tell me what you want and I shall get it for you.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>Me: Thanks but no thanks ha ha. (My standards of wit are pretty lousy in dreams.)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>The Fairy: Shall I restore to you your lost heterosexuality so that you may once again on the Late Late Show have strange and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>brilliant adventures in foreign climes with handsome actors such as Buster Crabbe, Dirk Bogarde, James Mason, and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>Christopher Lee?—leaving it to you to determine what common characteristics (if any) unites this rather peculiar list because,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>my dear (to be perfectly frank), you have the damnedest tastes I ever saw.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>Me: (sitting bolt upright in terror): No, no, no, no, no, no!
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>The Fairy (crossing one leg over another, thus revealing she is indeed wearing ice skates, great big clumpy white ones): Well,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>what do you want, for goodness&apos; sakes! Don&apos;t be so difficult. (She then mutters under her breath, What do women want? Dear
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>God, what do they want?&apos;)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>Me: That lousy imitation of Freud—
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>But here I must break off. The Tooth Fairy cometh not. Messias ist nicht gekommen. It&apos;s all ours to get, with Mrs. Anne
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>Radcliffe in one hand and a jackhammer (or jennyhammer) in the other, with books and bricks, pride and perseverance, et
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>cetera. Here endeth the first sermon. (Are ninety-nine.) Suppose you woke up and saw her...
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>5.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>Joanna Russ is the author of a novel published by Dell Books, We Who Are About To, and of the science fiction novel, The Two of Them, to be published by Putnam&apos;s. This spring
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>Daughters, Inc. will present her fantasy novel, Kit&apos;a Story: A Tale of Magic. She lives in Bellevue, Washington.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
