<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Issue15_Lorde15-16</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_line_1666300599177_190' n='N001'/>SISTER OUTSIDERS
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>BY AUDRE LORDE
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>I walked down those three little steps into the Bagatelle on a weekend
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>night in 1956. There was an inner door, guarded by a male bouncer, osten¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>sibly to keep out the straight male intruders come to gawk at the &quot;lezzies,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>but in reality to keep out those women deemed &quot;undesirable.&quot; All too
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>frequently, undesirable meant Black.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>Women stood three-deep around the bar and between the tables, and in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>the doorway to the postage-stamp-sized dance floor. By 9:00 p.m. the floor
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>was packed solid with women&apos;s bodies moving slowly to the jukebox beat of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>Ruth Brown&apos;s When your friends have left you all alone / and you have no
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>one to call your own... or Frank Sinatra&apos;s &quot;Set &apos;em up, Joe / I got a little
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>story.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>When I moved through the bunches of women cruising each other in the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>front room, or doing a slow fish on the dance floor in the back, with the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>smells of cigarette smoke and the music and the hair pomade whirling
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>together like incense through charged air, it was hard for me to believe that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>my being an outsider had anything to do with being a lesbian.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>But when I, a Black woman, saw no reflection in any of the faces there
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>week after week, I knew perfectly well that being an outsider in the Baga¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>telle had everything to do with being Black.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>The society within the confines of the Bagatelle reflected the ripples
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>and eddies of the larger society that had spawned it, and which allowed the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>Bagatelle to survive as long as it did, selling watered-down drinks at
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>inflated prices to lonely dykes who had no other social outlet or community
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>gathering place.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>Rather than the idyllic picture created by false nostalgia, the fifties
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>were really straight white america&apos;s cooling-off period of &quot;let&apos;s pretend
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>we&apos;re happy and that this is the best of all possible worlds and we&apos;ll blow
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>those nasty commies to hell if they dare to say otherwise.&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>The Rosenbergs had been executed, the transistor radio had been
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>invented, and frontal lobotomy was the standard solution for persistent
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>deviation. For some, Elvis Presley and his stolen Black rhythms became
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>arch-symbols of the antichrist.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>Young america&apos;s growing pains, within the Bagatelle, were represented
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>by the fashion conflicts between the blue-jeans set and the Bermuda-shorts
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>set. Then, of course, there were those who fell in between, both by virtue of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>our art or our craziness or our color.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>The breakdown into the mommies and daddies was an important part of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l38' n='N038'/>lesbian relationships in the Bagatelle. If you asked the wrong woman to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l39' n='N039'/>dance, you could get your nose broken in the alley down the street by her
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l40' n='N040'/>butch, who had followed you out of the Bag for exactly that purpose. It was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l41' n='N041'/>safer to keep to yourself. And you were never supposed to ask who was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l42' n='N042'/>who, which is why there was such heavy emphasis on corréct garb. The
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l43' n='N043'/>well-dressed gay-girl was supposed to give you enough clues for you to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l44' n='N044'/>know.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l45' n='N045'/>For some of us, however, the role-playing reflected all the depreciating
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l46' n='N046'/>attitudes toward women which we loathed in straight society. It was a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l47' n='N047'/>rejection of these roles that had drawn us to the life&quot; in the first place.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l48' n='N048'/>Instinctively, without particular theory or political position or dialectic, we
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l49' n='N049'/>recognized oppression as oppression, no matter where it came from.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l50' n='N050'/>But those lesbians who had carved some niche in the pretend world of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l51' n='N051'/>dominance/subordination rejected what they called our &quot;confused&quot; life
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l52' n='N052'/>style, and they were in the majority.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l53' n='N053'/>Felicia was so late one Sunday afternoon for our photography lesson
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l54' n='N054'/>that Muriel and I went off to Laurel&apos;s without her, because you had to be
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l55' n='N055'/>early on Sundays to get something to eat. The Swing Rendezvous had closed
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l56' n='N056'/>its table, but at Laurel&apos;s on Sunday afternoon there was free brunch with
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l57' n='N057'/>any drink, and that meant all you could eat. Many of the gay bars used this
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l58' n='N058'/>to get Sunday afternoon business at a traditionally slow time, but Laurel&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l59' n='N059'/>had the best food. There was a Chinese cook there of no mean talent. He
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l60' n='N060'/>cooked back and kept it coming. After the word got around, every Sunday
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l61' n='N061'/>afternoon at four o&apos;clock there would be a line of gay-girls in front of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l62' n='N062'/>Laurel&apos;s, smoking and talking and trying to pretend we had all arrived
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l63' n='N063'/>there at that time by accident.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l64' n='N064'/>When the doors opened, there was a discreet but determined stampede,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l65' n='N065'/>first to the bar and then to the food table, set up in the rear of the lounge.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l66' n='N066'/>We tried to keep our cool, pretending that we couldn’t care less for barbe¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l67' n='N067'/>cued spare ribs with peach and apricot sweet sauce, or succulent pink
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l68' n='N068'/>shrimp swimming in thick golden lobster sauce, dotted with bits of green
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l69' n='N069'/>scallion and bright yellow egg drops, tiny pieces of pork and onion afloat on
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l70' n='N070'/>Ihis plece isescerptedfrom Audre Lorde snew workof fiction, Zam. A New Spel-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l71' n='N071'/>ing of My Name (Persephone Press). Audre Lorde teaches poetry at Hunter College.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l72' n='N072'/>Her other recent book is Chosen Poems —Old and New (Norton).
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l73' n='N073'/>O 1982 Audre Lorde
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>top. There were stacked piles of crispy brown egg rolls filled with shredded
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>ham and chicken and celery, rolled together and fried with a touch of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>sesame paste. There were fried chicken bits, and every once in a great
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>while, a special delicacy such as lobster or fresh crab. Only the first lucky
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>few got to taste those special dishes, so it was worthwhile being first on line
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>and pushing your cool image a little bit askew.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>We were healthy young female animals mercifully more alive than most
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>of our peers, robust and active women, and our blood was always high and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>our pockets empty and a free meal in convivial surroundings—meaning
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>around other lesbians—was a big treat for most of us, even if purchased at
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>the price of a bottle of beer, which was fifty cents, with many complaints.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>Dancing wasn&apos;t allowed at Laurel&apos;s so it never got to be as popular as
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>the Bag, except on Sunday afternoons. Muriel preferred it because it was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>always quieter. Trix ran the place, and always had a hand for &apos;her girls.&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>Tiny and tough, with a permanent Florida tan and a Bronx accent, she took
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l16' n='N016'/>a shine to Muriel and me, and sometimes she would buy us a beer, and sit
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l17' n='N017'/>down and talk with us if the place wasn&apos;t too crowded.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l18' n='N018'/>We all knew the situation with gay bars, how they came in and out of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l19' n='N019'/>existence with such regularity and who really profited from them. But Trix
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l20' n='N020'/>was pretty and bright and hard and kind all at the same time, and her per¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l21' n='N021'/>manent tan particularly endeared her to me. She looked like one of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l22' n='N022'/>nicer of the hickory-skinned devils who used to people my dreams of that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l23' n='N023'/>period.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l24' n='N024'/>Actually, the lifespan of most gay bars was under a year, with the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l25' n='N025'/>notable exception of a few like the Bag. Laurel&apos;s went the way of all the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l26' n='N026'/>other gay bars—like the Swing and Snooky&apos;s and the Grapevine, the Sea
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l27' n='N027'/>Colony and the Pony Stable Inn. Each closed after a year or so, while
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l28' n='N028'/>another opened and caught on somewhere else. But for that year, Laurel&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l29' n='N029'/>served as an important place for those of us who met and made some brief
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l30' n='N030'/>space for ourselves there. It had a feeling of family.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l31' n='N031'/>On summer Sunday afternoons, Muriel and I would split from the gay
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l32' n='N032'/>beach at Coney Island or Riis Park early, take the subway back home in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l33' n='N033'/>time to wash up and dress and saunter over to Laurel&apos;s in time for the food
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l34' n='N034'/>at 4:00. I had my first open color confrontation with a gay-girl one Sunday
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l35' n='N035'/>afternoon in Laurel&apos;s.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l36' n='N036'/>Muriel and I had come back that day from Riis Park, full of sun and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l37' n='N037'/>sand. We loved with the salt still on our skins, then bathed, washed our
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l38' n='N038'/>hair, and got ready to go out. I put on my faded cord riding britches with
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l39' n='N039'/>the suede crotch, and a pale blue short-sleeved sweatshirt bought earlier
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l40' n='N040'/>that week at John&apos;s on Avenue C for sixty-nine cents. My skin was tanned
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l41' n='N041'/>from the sun and burnished ruddy with the heat and much loving. My hair
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l42' n='N042'/>was newly trimmed and freshly washed, with the particular crispiness that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l43' n='N043'/>it always develops in sustained summer heat. I felt raunchy and restless.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l44' n='N044'/>We walked out of the hot August afternoon sun into the suddenly dark
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l45' n='N045'/>coolness of Laurel&apos;s downstairs. There was Muriel, in her black Bermuda
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l46' n='N046'/>shorts and shirt, ghost pale, her eternal cigarette in hand. And I was beside
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l47' n='N047'/>her, full of myself, knowing I was fat and Black and very fine. We were
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l48' n='N048'/>without peer or category, and on that day I was conscious of being very
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l49' n='N049'/>proud of it, no matter who looked down her nose at us.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l50' n='N050'/>After Muriel and I had gotten our food and beer and copped one of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l51' n='N051'/>tables, Dottie and Pauli came over. We saw them a lot at the Bag and in the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l52' n='N052'/>supermarket over on Avenue D, but we&apos;d never been to their house nor they
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l53' n='N053'/>to ours, except for New Year&apos;s food, when everyone came.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l54' n='N054'/>Where you guys been?&quot; Pauli had an ingenuous smile, her blonde hair
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l55' n='N055'/>and blue eyes incandescent against the turquoise mandarin shirt she wore.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l56' n='N056'/>Riis. Gay Beach.&quot; Muriel&apos;s finger crooked over the bottle as she took a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l57' n='N057'/>slug. All of us eschewed glasses as faggy, although I sometimes longed for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l58' n='N058'/>one because the cold beer hurt my teeth.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l59' n='N059'/>Pauli turned to me. &quot;Hey, that&apos;s a great tan you have there. I didn&apos;t
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l60' n='N060'/>know Negroes got tans.&quot; Her broad smile was intended to announce the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l61' n='N061'/>remark as a joke.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l62' n='N062'/>My usual defense in such situations was to ignore the overtones, to let it
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l63' n='N063'/>go. But Dottie Daws, probably out of her own nervousness at Pauli&apos;s refer¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l64' n='N064'/>ence to the unmentionable, would not let the matter drop. Raved on and on
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l65' n='N065'/>about my great tan. Matched her arm to mine. Shook her pale blonde head,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l66' n='N066'/>telling whomever would listen that she wished she could tan like that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l67' n='N067'/>instead of burning, and did I know how lucky I was to be able to get such a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l68' n='N068'/>tan like that? I grew tired and then shakingly furious, having enough of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l69' n='N069'/>whatever it was.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l70' n='N070'/>How come you never make so much over my natural tan most days,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l71' n='N071'/>Dottie Daws; how come?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l72' n='N072'/>There was a moment of silence at the table, punctuated only by Muriel&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l73' n='N073'/>darkly appreciative chuckle, and then we moved on to something else,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l74' n='N074'/>15
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>mercifully. I was still shaking inside. I never forgot it.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>In the gay bars, I longed for other Black women without the need ever
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>taking shape on my lips. For four hundred years in this country, Black
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>women have been taught to view each other with deep suspicion. It was no
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>different in the gay world.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>Most Black lesbians were closeted, correctly recognizing the Black com¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>munity&apos;s lack of interest in our position, as well as the many more immedi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>ate threats to our survival as Black people in a racist society. It was hard
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>enough to be Black, to be Black and female, to be Black, female, and gay.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>To be Black, female, gay, and out of the closet, even to the extent of danc¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>ing in the Bagatelle, was considered by many Black lesbians to be simply
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l12' n='N012'/>suicidal. And if you were fool enough to do it, you&apos;d better come on so tough
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l13' n='N013'/>that nobody messed with you. I often felt put down by their sophistication,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l14' n='N014'/>their clothes, their manners, their cars, and their femmes,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l15' n='N015'/>The Black women I usually saw around the Bag were into heavy roles,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l16' n='N016'/>and it frightened me. This was partly the fear of my own Blackness mir
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l17' n='N017'/>rored, and partly the realities of the masquerade. These women felt to me
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l18' n='N018'/>like parts of my own sexual self I had not yet come to terms with. They
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l19' n='N019'/>seemed tough in a way I felt I could never be. Even if they were not, their
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l20' n='N020'/>self-protective instincts warned them to appear that way. By white ameri¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l21' n='N021'/>ca&apos;s racist distortions of beauty, Black women playing femme“ had very
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l22' n='N022'/>little chance in the Bag. There was constant competition among butches to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l23' n='N023'/>have the most &quot;gorgeous femme&quot; on their arm. And &quot;gorgeous&quot; was de¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l24' n='N024'/>fined by a white male world&apos;s standards.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l25' n='N025'/>For me, going into the Bag was like entering an anomalous no-woman&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l26' n='N026'/>land. I wasn&apos;t cute or passive enough to be femme,&quot; and I wasn&apos;t mean or
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l27' n='N027'/>tough enough to be &quot;butch.&quot; I was given a wide berth. Nonconventional
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l28' n='N028'/>people can be dangerous, even in the gay community
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l29' n='N029'/>With the exception of Felicia and myself, the other Black women in the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l30' n='N030'/>Bag came protected by a show of all the power symbols they could muster.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l31' n='N031'/>Whatever else they did during the week, on Friday nights when Lion or
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l32' n='N032'/>Trip appeared, sometimes with expensively dressed women on their arms,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l33' n='N033'/>sometimes alone, they commanded attention and admiration. They were
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l34' n='N034'/>well-heeled, superbly dressed, self-controlled high-steppers who drove
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l35' n='N035'/>convertibles, bought rounds of drinks for their friends, and generally took
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l36' n='N036'/>care of business.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l37' n='N037'/>But sometimes, even they couldn&apos;t get in unless they were recognized by
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l38' n='N038'/>the bouncer.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l39' n='N039'/>My friends and I were the hippies of the gay-girl circuit, before the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l40' n='N040'/>word was coined. Many of us wound up dead or demented, and many of us
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l41' n='N041'/>were distorted by the many fronts we had to fight upon. But when we sur¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l42' n='N042'/>vived, we grew up strong.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l43' n='N043'/>Every Black woman I ever met in the Village in those years had some
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l44' n='N044'/>part in my survival, large or small, if only as a figure in the head-count at
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l45' n='N045'/>the Bag on a Friday night.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l46' n='N046'/>Black lesbians in the Bagatelle faced a world only slightly less hostile
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l47' n='N047'/>than the outer world which we had to deal with every day on the outside—
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l48' n='N048'/>that world which defined us as doubly nothing because we were Black and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l49' n='N049'/>because we were Women—that world which raised our blood pressures
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l50' n='N050'/>and shaped our furies and our nightmares.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l51' n='N051'/>The temporary integration of war plants and the egalitarian myth of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l52' n='N052'/>Rosie the Riveter had ended abruptly with the end of World War II and the
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l1' n='N001'/>wholesale return of the american woman to the role of little wifey. So far as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l2' n='N002'/>I could see, gay-girls were the only Black and white women who were even
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l3' n='N003'/>talking to each other in this country in the 1950s, outside of the empty
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l4' n='N004'/>rhetoric of patriotism and political movements.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l5' n='N005'/>Black or white, Ky-Ky, butch, or femme, the only thing we shared, often,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l6' n='N006'/>and in varying proportions, was that we dared for connection in the name
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l7' n='N007'/>of woman, and saw that as our power, rather than our problem.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l8' n='N008'/>All of us who survived those common years had to be a little strange.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l9' n='N009'/>We spent so much of our young womanhood trying to define ourselves as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l10' n='N010'/>woman-identified women before we even knew the words existed, let alone
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l11' n='N011'/>that there were ears interested in trying to hear them beyond our im¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l12' n='N012'/>mediate borders. All of us who survived those common years have to be a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l13' n='N013'/>little proud. A lot proud. Keeping ourselves together and on our own tracks,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l14' n='N014'/>however wobbly, was like trying to play the Dinizulu War Chant or a Beet¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l15' n='N015'/>hoven sonata on a tin dog-whistle.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l16' n='N016'/>The important message seemed to be that you had to have a place.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l17' n='N017'/>Whether or not it did justice to whatever you felt you were about, there had
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l18' n='N018'/>to be some place to refuel and check your flaps.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l19' n='N019'/>In times of need and great instability, the place sometimes became more
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l20' n='N020'/>a definition than the substance of why you needed it to begin with. Some¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l21' n='N021'/>times the retreat became the reality. The writers who posed in cafes
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l22' n='N022'/>talking their work to death without writing two words; the lesbians, virile
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l23' n='N023'/>as men, hating women and their own womanhood with a vengeance. The
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l24' n='N024'/>bars and the coffee shops and the streets of the Village in the 1950s were
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l25' n='N025'/>full of nonconformists who were deathly afraid of going against their
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l26' n='N026'/>hard-won group, and so eventually they were broken between the group
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l27' n='N027'/>and their individual needs.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l28' n='N028'/>For some of us there was no one particular place, and we grabbed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l29' n='N029'/>whatever we could from wherever we found space, comfort, quiet, a smile,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l30' n='N030'/>nonjudgment.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l31' n='N031'/>Being women together was not enough. We were different. Being gay¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l32' n='N032'/>girls together was not enough. We were different. Being Black together was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l33' n='N033'/>not enough. We were different. Being Black women together was not
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l34' n='N034'/>enough. We were different. Being Black dykes together was not enough.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l35' n='N035'/>We were different.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l36' n='N036'/>Each of us had our own needs and pursuits, and many different alli¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l37' n='N037'/>ances. Self-preservation warned some of us that we could not afford to set¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l38' n='N038'/>tle for one easy definition, one narrow individuation of self. At the Bag, at
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l39' n='N039'/>Hunter College, uptown in Harlem at the library, there was a piece of the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l40' n='N040'/>real me bound in each place, and growing
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l41' n='N041'/>It was a while before we came to realize that our place was the very
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l42' n='N042'/>house of difference rather than the security of any one particular dif¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l43' n='N043'/>ference. (And often, we were cowards in our learning.) It was years before
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l44' n='N044'/>we learned to use the strength that daily surviving can bring, years before
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l45' n='N045'/>we learned that fear does not have to incapacitate, and that we could
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l46' n='N046'/>appreciate each other on terms not necessarily our own.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l47' n='N047'/>The Black gay-girls in the Village gay bars of the fifties knew each
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l48' n='N048'/>other&apos;s names, but we seldom looked into each other&apos;s Black eyes, lest we
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l49' n='N049'/>see our own aloneness and our own blunted power mirrored in the pursuit
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l50' n='N050'/>of darkness. Some of us died inside the gaps between the mirrors and those
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l51' n='N051'/>turned-away eyes.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
