<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Heresies Project</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>A Bucknell Production</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1"/>
         <p>Editorial
			</p>
         <p>There are a number of traditional ways
				of explaining violence in human culture.
				The perspective on violence is usually con-
				gruent with a set of beliefs about the
				sources of human motivation and behav-
				ior. The argument has often been
				drawn along the Nature/Nurture divide,
				with biology and culture placed in oppo-
				sition to each other. We need to question
				explanations based on erroneous assump-
				tions and explanations which cannot ac-
				count for the male use of violence against
				women in specific historical periods and
				social contexts. We need to be critical of
				simple answers whether they are presented
				by male scientists or feminist authors. The
				stance of a self-reflective movement re-
				quires a careful evaluation of answers that
				mask ideology or refuse to include
				counter-examples, including the ways in
				which women participate in violence and
				oppression. Locating the cause of violence
				within biology, socialization or a violent
				society posits the cure for that violence
				within its own terms. Biological explana-
				tions demand biological treatment. Im-
				plicit in all theories of causation are the
				appropriate remedies or "cures." There
				are three broad theories about the causes
				of violences.
				1) Biological Explanations—Socio-biolo-
				gy, a newer version of biological deter-
				minism, seeks to explain human behavior
				as the result of complex interaction be-
				tween genes, drives and instincts and
				social environment. In this view, based on
			</p>
         <p>hormonal differences, male aggression
				and violence is inevitable and natural:
				"boys will be boys." The only appropri-
				ate treatment is short-circuiting these
				drives by lobotomies, physical or chemical
				castration or a eugenics program that will
				breed gentler men. Some women would
				dispense with men altogether and institute
				a program of parthenogenisis. Similarly,
				those who attempt to explain women's
				subordination as a result of physiological
				differences in strength offer a biological
				determinist argument. This view rein-
				forces the status quo, as violence is seen to
				be inherent in the human race.
				2) Psychological Explanations — Here
				violence is not seen as a species problem
				but an individual problem. Usually vio-
				lence against women is termed an illness
				or pathology, an unfortunate deviation
				from "normal" male behavior. While
				some psychologists might believe it is na-
				tural for men to be aggressive and violent,
				some forms of violence are "sick," like
				rape and child molestation. The choice of
			</p>
         <p>treatment depends upon whether the vio-
				lence is seen to be deeply embedded in the
				unconscious during childhood or the re-
				sult of learning inappropriate behavior.
				If the key to male violence is to be
				found in the unconscious then only an ex-
				amination of intrapsychic structures can
				explain its occurence. This model claims
				that the Unconscious is basically un-
				bounded by history or culture, though
				influenced by socio-economic factors.
				Unconscious structures are seen to be uni-
				versal and as deeply embedded as
				language.
				Many psychologists who do therapy
				with sexual aggressives, a clinical name
				for rapists and wife abusers, endorse be-
				havior modification therapy. They believe
				that violence and aggressive sexuality are
				learned. The goal of treatment involves
				unlearning and relearning new modes of
				communication. Some programs teach
				volunteer rapists (those that are not in
				prison) how to have better heterosocial
				(continued on page 14)
			</p>
         <pb n="2"/>
         <p>Editorial
			</p>
         <p>skills; the contention being that these men
				are often not assertive with women and
				fear rejection. Family therapists teach
				husbands new ways of communicating
				their anger to their wives . . . slamming a
				book on the table instead of hitting her,
				and wives are instructed in "negotiating"
				procèdures. In this way their deviant be-
				havior will be brought into line with that
				of "normal'' men. Questions of power
				differences between husbands and wives
				in the family and men and women in soci-
				ety are ignored, as well as traditional sex
				role definitions.
				3) Sociological Explanations—Here be-
				havior is not simply a result of human
				nature but is primarily conditioned by the
				environment. Violence is not an irrational
				phenomenon, nor is it an individual prob-
				lem (though it is experienced individually).
				Violence has a social function; as a re-
				source to be implemented when other
				resources are lacking. It is often seen as a
				last resort, to be called into play when
				power and authority are threatened, as in
				the case of the State quelling revolts or re-
				bellions. Violence can also be used as an
				interpersonal resource by individuals
				when others means of exercising control
				are blocked or lacking. This view inter-
				prets violence against women in the home
				as a husband's reaction to his questioned
				authority in the household. Women are
				often beaten when they are pregnant and
				also during periods of economic insta-
				bility. It is assumed that violence can be
				used to buttress male status in the family
				and the community. If men rape women,
				if they terrorize us in our homes and har-
				ass us on the street it is because men are
				utilizing a behavior (privilege) that is
				available to them as men, social beings
				operating within the rules of a culture. Is
				violence the backlash of a threatened
				power-holder?
				Another social explanation is that vio-
				lence is the symptom of alienation. Men
				as workers are frustrated because condi-
				tions of labor are exploitative and social
				relations demeaning. The ultimate cause
				of violence then is an alienating social life
				under capitalism. This theory does not ac-
				count for the direction of the violence by
				class, race and gender, nor does it explain
				male violence in non-capitalist societies.
				Certainly the social conditions facing
				women under capitalism are as frustra-
				(continued on page 15)
			</p>
         <pb n="3"/>
         <p>Editorial
			</p>
         <p>ting. Women are socially and physically
				confined; our mobility, our life choices
				and life chances do not instill in us a sense
				of security or safety. We are paid less
				wages, have worse working conditions
				and do a double day. Yet we do not mo-
				lest or rape men. Whatever the cause of
				frustration, be it shaky male privilege or
				alienation, neither view relates frustra-
				tion/aggression theory to an analysis of
				gender relations. Violence is always re-
				lated to the structure of power.
				What most approaches to male violence
				share is the belief that sexual coercion and
				physical violation are somehow non-ra-
				tional or uncontrollable. Pent-up frustra-
				tion, whether it is sexual or political, must
				find its release. Women become the sacri-
				ficial victims as men work out 1. their ali-
				enation 2. their gender inadequacies 3.
				their inappropriate role modeling or 4.
				their instinctual drives.
				Women, like colonized people, must
				decide how to approach the complex rela-
				tionship between the system of male dom-
				ination and individual men. We have
				found that our discussions about the func-
				tion of violence in society often foun-
				dered on questions of assigning responsi-
				bility. Is the individual colonizer the
				enemy or the system that requires coloni-
				zation for its survival? Are individual men
				the enemy or the system that requires male
				domination? If colonialism serves the
				interests of all colonials, then does male
				supremacy serve the interests of all men?
				Theories abstract from the experience
				of women's daily lives to symbols and sys-
				tems of asymetical power relations. Wom-
				en who are daily fighting for survival, who
				are raped, sexually harassed on the job,
				tranquilized into passivity, and beaten
				cannot afford to make abstract theories.
				Merely blaming the system does not re-
				solve the issue of individual responsibility
				nor does it expand the analysis of social
				responsibility. One need not be substi-
				tuted for the other, but alone they are in-
				complete, disparate elements in the
				unfolding of patriarchal control.
			</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
