<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Issue15_Vitale20-21</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>GROWING UP NEGRO, SOON TO BE BLACK
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>BY SYLVIA WITTS VITALE
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>It happens all the time. For me as well as other Black people, some
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>racist instances are every day, every week, no big deal, the norm, what the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>hell did you expect, so what, who cares. So what occurs is that I get used to it.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>For the most part, I, as a Black person, have experienced so much overt
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>and covert racism that it is hard to focus in on one specific area. When my
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>white acquaintances tell me of instances in their lives that have made them
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>feel uncomfortable because they were in minority&quot; settings, I find it hard
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>to feel anything for them. Yet these instances stand out in their minds.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>I was raised during the Negro era and gradually graduated to the Black
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>era. My mother was raised during the colored-Negro era. My grandmother
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>was raised during the colored or, as they said, &quot;cullid&quot; era. These are very
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>distinct times in my development. I did not grow up in Philadelphia, Penn¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>sylvania, as a girl proud of her race. All I knew was what was on television,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>radio; what I learned from school, church, family and peers. I knew that my
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>race came from Africa, but that was nothing to be proud of in the 1950s.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>How could I be proud when Tarzan, the white man, was always Tarzan, the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>right man? I felt proud of Nat King Cole, Sammy Davis, Jr., Harry Belafonte,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>Marion Anderson, Diahann Carrol, Johnny Mathis, Pearl Bailey, the Harlem
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>Globetrotters, and a few others. But I only got to see these people when
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>they were on the Ed Sullivan Show or the Nat King Cole Show. My white
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>teachers led me to believe that this was all there was. As a people we did
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>not do anything other than sing, dance, entertain, do sports, get in trouble,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>go to jail, drink and be on relief, a.k.a. welfare.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>I can remember being the only Black girl in class when the teacher
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>showed us an anthropological film on—where else but—Africa. It made me
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>mad to be a Negro. Why did we have to look like that? Why were we always
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>depicted as savages in skimpy cloth? The class laughed and said things
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>like, There&apos;s Sylvia.&quot; One tribe had plates in their lips, another suffered
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>from elephantiasis. I felt so low, so bad that day. I was embarrassed and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>ashamed.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>I was about 12 years old when I moved to New York. I blossomed into a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>singer and actor. It was a great way for me to break out of my shell, meet
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>people, and be accepted for my talents. l&apos;ll never forget my first year in the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>All City High School Chorus try-outs. I had been called back for my second
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>week of auditions. The altos were sitting in &quot;posture&quot; position to sing. I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>started a conversation with a white girl about how nervous I was. She said
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>to me, What are you?&quot; I didn&apos;t know what she meant so I said, &quot;First
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>alto.&quot; &quot;No, I mean you, you know, your background.&quot; What a joke! I am
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>dark enough for it to be obvious so Ijust said, Negro.&quot; You talk real nice,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>you don&apos;t sound like a Negro.&quot; I busted out in this big beautiful smile. I was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>so happy that I did not sound like a Negro. She made my day.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>In 1967 I joined a group called Hector Rivera and the Latin Renaissance.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>We had just cut an album and I had time off from rehearsals. One of my best
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>friends, Author, asked me to go down South with her and her family for a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>visit. Ismiled at the invitation but behind the smile was fear. The South, oh
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>no, they&apos;ll kill me! I was so full of horror stories about what was done to my
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>people in the South by white folks that it took a whole lot of convincing to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>ease my fears. I was told that at least in the South you knew who did not
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>like you but in the North they&apos;Il pat you on the back with one hand and stab
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>you with the other. I was convinced that the South had changed and that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>people got along better. Anyway, the &quot;colored only/white only&quot; signs were
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>taken down.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l53' n='N053'/>My friend&apos;s family and I went to North Carolina to a dinky town called
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l54' n='N054'/>Chockowenity. We went out to eat one night at this restaurant that adver¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l55' n='N055'/>tised that the food was so good that it tasted like Mom made it. By the stares
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l56' n='N056'/>we got when 12 Black people walked into this small town restaurant, you&apos;d
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l57' n='N057'/>think that we had done something wrong. We ordered our food and waited.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l58' n='N058'/>And waited. And waited. I got scared and started thinking about what they
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l59' n='N059'/>must be doing to my food. I got images of them grinding glass and other junk
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l60' n='N060'/>to make me sick. When the food did come, I did not eat it. I did not trust
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l61' n='N061'/>these white folks. They unnerved me. My only frame of reference for whites
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l62' n='N062'/>with southern accents was the Ku Klux Klan. It was like by day they were
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l63' n='N063'/>normal, by night they wore sheets. My family is mostly from the South and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l64' n='N064'/>although most of them had lost their southern accents I could deal with a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l65' n='N065'/>Black southern accent. Not a white one. Sometimes I still have problems
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l66' n='N066'/>with it.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l67' n='N067'/>Since I spent a great deal of my time singing throughout New York for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l68' n='N068'/>various dignitaries and public officials, my racial horizons broadened. I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l69' n='N069'/>figured that since I learned to discard my fears and prejudices that white
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l70' n='N070'/>folks were doing the same thing. So in 1969 I enrolled in Kingsborough
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>Sylvia Witts Vitale, a sex therapist and sex educator, is a lecturer at various col¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>leges in the City University of New York.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l1' n='N001'/>Community College in Manhattan Beach. On my way to school one day I met
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l2' n='N002'/>a middle-aged white woman on the train platform. She asked me what was I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l3' n='N003'/>doing in the neighborhood. I told her I went to Kingsborough. She looked
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l4' n='N004'/>relieved. I found out later that most Black people in the area worked there
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l5' n='N005'/>either cleaning homes, in restaurants, or as other workers. I was too young¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l6' n='N006'/>looking for the above. She asked me what I was studying. I really had not
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l7' n='N007'/>made up my mind yet and I was torn between majoring in music or psychol¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l8' n='N008'/>ogy. So I said I was a music major. She smiled and said, &quot;Oh that&apos;s nice.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l9' n='N009'/>Your people sing and dance so well.&quot; I didn&apos;t smile. I went to school and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l10' n='N010'/>made a decision to major in psychology. I sang in the chorus and even won
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l11' n='N011'/>the music award but I refused to major in it. That&apos;s when I realized the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l12' n='N012'/>difference between the North and South. The South may have for colored
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l13' n='N013'/>only&quot; signs but the North has for colored only&quot; minds. In fact every time a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l14' n='N014'/>white person told me negative things, I excelled in spite of it.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l15' n='N015'/>My first Black history course was taught by a white woman. She&apos;s the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l16' n='N016'/>one who really changed the course of my life when she told me I was illit¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l17' n='N017'/>erate. After my first B in English, I aimed for and received A&apos;s throughout
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l18' n='N018'/>my college career. I could not wait to find this teacher one year later to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l19' n='N019'/>show her that I had now become an English tutor. In my quest to please her,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l20' n='N020'/>to have her accept me and take back those words, I worked my ass off. I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l21' n='N021'/>remember going to her office on several occasions to talk to her. She asked
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l22' n='N022'/>me how come I never gave her eye contact. I didn&apos;t know. I never gave
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l23' n='N023'/>anybody eye contact. During the course of her class I learned about how
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l24' n='N024'/>eye contact could mean death to slaves.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l25' n='N025'/>In slavery, Blacks taught their children how to act and how not to act
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l26' n='N026'/>around white folks. Black people were lynched, beaten, and severely pun¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l27' n='N027'/>ished for merely looking a white person in the eyes. Eye contact was too
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l28' n='N028'/>close to equality, sharing personal space and meaningful communication.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l29' n='N029'/>These lessons may have been painful sometimes in terms of discipline, but
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l30' n='N030'/>it kept many Black folks alive. I never learned this directly from my parents,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l31' n='N031'/>but they do not usually look people straight in the eyes either. So here I was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l32' n='N032'/>in my teacher&apos;s office, not giving eye contact to this white southern woman.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l33' n='N033'/>By 1973 I was well into my college life and digging it. This is also the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l34' n='N034'/>year I experienced the Women&apos;s Movement, which changed my life. I some¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l35' n='N035'/>how thought and was led to believe by various women that feminism em¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l36' n='N036'/>braced all women in a common struggle and that everything was better
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l37' n='N037'/>when women worked together. What a joke! I was never more patronized
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l38' n='N038'/>in my life. Queens College had a Women&apos;s Festival with a week-long series
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l39' n='N039'/>of talks, workshops, and films. I attended almost all of the activities. I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l40' n='N040'/>walked into each one and experienced being either the only Black woman
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l41' n='N041'/>or one of a few. By the second day I began to see the same faces and women
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l42' n='N042'/>began to open up to me. I was patted on the back by white feminist teachers
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l43' n='N043'/>and told such things as, &quot;You&apos;re great, you&apos;re so articulate,&quot; and other
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l44' n='N044'/>things that I at first thought were compliments. I started being invited to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l45' n='N045'/>faculty and student feminist parties. I joined a CR group. I was still basically
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l46' n='N046'/>O1982 Sylvia Witts Vitale
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_8_1l1' n='N001'/>20.
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>trying to figure out what feminism was and why so few Black women were
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>in it. The following week Queens College was back to normal. Classes as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>usual. All of a sudden I missed the high I was on. A white woman, whom I
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>met during the festival, saw me in the student lounge and came over to talk
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>to me. She told me about this meeting that was coming up at the old NOW
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>headquarters in Manhattan for Black women in the Women&apos;s Movement.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>She couldn&apos;t go because she was white and her Black lover did not want to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>go. So I thanked her for the information.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>I showed up at this meeting. I was in a room full of approximately 30
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>Black women. This was the first time I had seen so many sisters together
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>talking about feminism. Some faces I recognized from Queens College. I felt
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>so good. People like Reverend Magora Kennedy, Michele Wallace, Lore
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>Sharpe, and Faith Ringgold were there. Faith termed what we were experi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>encing  consciousness raging.&quot; I could dig it. I felt it. We knew we had to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>meet again. And we did. Again and again and again until we formed the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>National Black Feminist Organization. We held a press conference and our
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>story was carried in the New York Times. Florence Kennedy, Eleanor
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>Holmes Norton, and Shirley Chisolm were just a few who wished us well
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>and gave substantive support.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>In the meantime some of my white feminist friends began to have prob¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>lems with our organization. They somehow thought that we were dividing
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>and therefore weakening the movement. They could not see the need for
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>Black women to gather and focus in on issues that specifically spoke to our
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>needs. I said then and I still maintain that this autonomy is necessary. My
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>analogy is simple: During the ’60s Black folks had to go behind closed doors
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>to redefine ourselves. We yelled, we screamed, we disagreed, but when we
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>finished, we told the world, &quot;We are BLACK! not NEGRO, not COLORED.&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>We insisted on it and we succeeded. The tactics we used ended up being
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>the mode of operation for all liberation groups to follow. Similarly, women
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>had to go behind closed doors to scream, disagree, argue until we decided
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>who we were. We emerged as WOMEN, not GIRLS, not CHICKS, not
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>BITCHES, not LADIES. It was accepted. We defined ourselves with strength.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>Somehow both of these groups who fought so hard to define themselves
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>could not see the validity of Black women uniting to work on our issues.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>Black men and some Black women were led to believe, via Black Nationalist
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>philosophy, that when Black people were liberated, all benefited. Not true.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>Thanks to non-Blacks like Daniel P. Moynihan, who wrote  The Moynihan
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>Report,&quot; the focus was on finding jobs for Black men. The theory was that if
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>the Black man had a job he could therefore take his rightful place as head
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>of the household. He would marry Black and take care of his family. I even
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>heard discussions from Black women about how if they were in a situation
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>where the job opportunity came between them and the Black man, they
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>would yield to the Black man. Although Black women worked just as hard
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>as Black men in all of our liberation struggles, sexism was still a major
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>problem. So when some Black women embraced the Women&apos;s Movement,
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>somehow we felt that our common struggles were paramount. White femi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>nists wondered where all the Black women were. One white feminist even
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>told me that the Women&apos;s Movement needed Black women. That we were
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>strong and good leaders. But some Black women soon realized that our
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>issues went far beyond their issues. Black women could not afford to sepa¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>rate ourselves according to income, who lived in which neighborhoods, etc.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>Our movement consisted of the women who cleaned white women&apos;s homes.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>Our movement consisted of dealing with welfare mothers, household tech¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>nicians, students, single mothers, triply oppressed lesbians, high school
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>dropouts, teachers, lawyers, office workers—in other words, all Black
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>women. We needed to lend support to one another, to network. We needed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>to see each other&apos;s faces, hear our stories. Herstory has shown just how
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>strong Black women are.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>So why didn’t Black men and white women understand that? My dual
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>identification had a tendency to force me to make unreal choices. That is,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>until I became aware and strong enough to deal with the D &amp; C (divide and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>conquer) method. White women wanted me to identify as female and op¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>pressed as if I had no color. That was their way of not dealing with racism
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>yet being racist. Black men wanted me to identify as Black because being a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>female was not an issue. One day I was invited to speak at a women&apos;s con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>ference. A woman asked me: What do I identify most with, being Black or
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>female? That did it. I told the audience that I do not know what my mother
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>noticed first, that I was a girl or her brown baby. I do know, however, that I
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>was born head first and that is the way I will continue to operate—head
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>first
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>Ican remember being at women&apos;s conferences where the slogan &quot;Sister¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>hood is powerful&quot; was used a lot. White women would address the audi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>ence with the word &quot;sisters.&quot; Somehow I did not feel comfortable with the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>term because I knew that when I used it I meant women of African descent.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>Some white women challenged me one day and demanded to know why I
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>could not call them sisters. So I told them. When my ancestors were stolen
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>from Africa and brought to Amerika as slaves, families were divided. Some
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>because of health were dropped in the Caribbean. We were bred, traded,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>bought, and rarely knew where to find one another, so when we were so¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>called &quot;freed&quot; most of us did not know where our relatives were. I have
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>family&quot; throughout the Third World, in Brazil, Cuba, the West Indies, etc.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>So when I meet someone who says that I remind them of someone that they
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l38' n='N038'/>know, or I meet someone who reminds me of someone else that I know,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l39' n='N039'/>automatically think that somehow we are all &quot;slave-ancestor-relatives.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l40' n='N040'/>Therefore, the words sister&quot; and  brother&quot; have very significant roots. I
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l41' n='N041'/>understood very well why I could not call a white woman my sister. They
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l42' n='N042'/>can be &quot;cousins&quot; only.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l43' n='N043'/>It is not good enough for me just to sport my brown skin and call myself
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l44' n='N044'/>Black. To be Black in Amerika is to be politically aware of my past, present,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l45' n='N045'/>and future.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
