<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Issue1_Introduction</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>Feminism—Art—Politics. What is their connection? In
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>theory? In reality?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>Once there was a women&apos;s art center that was very
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>excited about an “Art as Work“ seminar 1 proposed. They
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>wanted a short personal resumé to follow the course de¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>scription in the catalogue —to let students know who 1 was,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>where I was coming from: Harmony Hammond is a lesbian
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>feminist artist who has exhibited at Callery X and Gallery Z
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>and taught at R. University and C. University. They wanted
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>my labels and then did not like them. No seminar. Really,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>was coming on too strong. Couldn’t 1 use a different word?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>Or just not say it at all? Would 1 be teaching art or politics?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>They were an “Art center. They were afraid, they said,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>afraid would jeopardize.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>Jeopardize what? Their art? Their teaching? Their stu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>dents? Their bodies? Their minds? Their sexuality? Their
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>politics? Their power? Their authority? Their thinking? They
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>did not know, they were just afraid.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>1did not fit their concept of a feminist and therefore !
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>was dangerous.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>Labels. The meaninglessness of labels. The power of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>labels. The confining. What does it mean to be a lesbian,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>radical feminist, activist, mother, artist? 1 am all of these
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>individually and combined. It means 1 am political. It
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>means I want to change existing power relationships. A list
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>of experiences. The power of labels is the power of ideas
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>and action combined.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>The political mother, the political artist, the political
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>feminist, and the political lesbian refuse to be second¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>class. They take action by “doing.“ They refuse to be
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>isolated into separatist stances, and they become a total
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>whole. They add up to what Charlotte Bunch has called a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>“non-aligned feminism&quot;—not automatically attached to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>one line ot feminism (socialist/left vs. reformist vs. cultural/
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>spiritual) but rather evaluating each individual issue and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>situation from an independent feminist perspective.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>Lesbian. Radical feminist. Activist. Mother. Artist.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>The common denominator is woman. Women are op¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>pressed as a class. This oppression underlies the patriarchal
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>institutions of capitalism, imperialism, racism, and hetero¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>sexism. To end all forms of oppression we must first end the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>oppression of all women regardless ot sexuality or eco¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>nomic class, racial or cultural background.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>Lesbian. Radical feminist. Activist. Mother. Artist.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>Together they form my teminism. Feminism is my poli¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>tics. My art both is formed by and is a statement of my
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>H.H.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>feminism.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>While l’d always worked in social programs, 1 never
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>considered myselt a political person. Political groups so
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>often revealed confused priorities that 1 inevitably ended
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>up by questioning my own. But feminism was different—so
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>much was personally at stake. If I questioned my commit¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>ment (how can 1 be amused by this or not outraged by
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>that), I soon found l was not amused and l was outraged by
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>things ! might once have considered innocuous or simply
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>unalterable. Feminism had become a persistent way of living
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>and thinking and the most important awareness of my life.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>Today ! trust the impulses calling out for radical change
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>because theyre rooted in a lifetime of self-analysis contin¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>uously and consistently validated by other women. Frustra¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>tion, it seems, is being resolved in conviction and action
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>and the awareness of this power has been startling to me.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>Needless to say, art which strengthens that awareness is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>exhilarating.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>l am a medievalist, I was attracted to the field by the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>escapist fantasies of folklore and romance. But ! now feel
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>that all art—whether ancient or modern—can be seen and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>A.L.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>judged within a feminist context.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>From the First-Issue Collective
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l1' n='N001'/>de
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_7_1l1' n='N001'/>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l1' n='N001'/>When pressed by the people who ask “What do you do?&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l2' n='N002'/>at times ! call myself an artist and then no one knows what
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l3' n='N003'/>to expect. The term is so vague and useless that it does not
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l4' n='N004'/>begin to identify a point of view. The fact that art work
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l5' n='N005'/>keeps the bourgeoisie in style, and the bourgeoisie keeps
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l6' n='N006'/>all the art, suggests that most artists don&apos;t bother with
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l7' n='N007'/>politics and ideology, instead they are united by a life¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l8' n='N008'/>style: generally you must privatize your work, hang your
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l9' n='N009'/>head to the left late at night in the bars, and think deeply
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l10' n='N010'/>about how your work will be understood in the melancholic
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l11' n='N011'/>future; be concerned about your isolation from the com¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l12' n='N012'/>munity.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l13' n='N013'/>It is difficult not to become a cynic. Opportunism
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l14' n='N014'/>knocks. Even the women&apos;s movement is another stepping
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l15' n='N015'/>stone towards critical recognition. Most people are more
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l16' n='N016'/>concerned with the objects we are producing than the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l17' n='N017'/>world into which we place our work. 1 make abstract paint-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l18' n='N018'/>ings and super-8 films—but not for a living. I work as an
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l19' n='N019'/>editor for a left news magazine called Seven Days. This is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l20' n='N020'/>where ! learned the business of developing an audience
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l21' n='N021'/>and disseminating information. Heresies is an attempt to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l22' n='N022'/>politicize the art world; a chance to attack the history ot
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l23' n='N023'/>our work as opposed to “documenting&quot; it.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l24' n='N024'/>have been a feminist it seems ever since Inoticed I was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l25' n='N025'/>living with great difficulty, it came out during the 1960s-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l26' n='N026'/>but that&apos;s a long story. In the 1970s, feminism has tenden¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l27' n='N027'/>cies which serve merely to push liberal institutions to their
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l28' n='N028'/>farthest extremes. This has left many women caught in a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l29' n='N029'/>dubious struggle; a recognition of strength and an inability
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l30' n='N030'/>to act. The feminist movement should not work towards
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l31' n='N031'/>gaining economic power, but towards developing a coher¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l32' n='N032'/>ent ideology if we are to participate in change and work
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l33' n='N033'/>towards socialism. (You knew l’d say that.) The point is that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l34' n='N034'/>an understanding of feminism without an analysis of class
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l35' n='N035'/>is like a long-tailed cat in a room full of rocking chairs.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l36' n='N036'/>Capitalism is so efficient that it can sustain its own alter¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l37' n='N037'/>natives, likewise the art world—one more radical magazine.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_9_1l38' n='N038'/>E.H.
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>am a feminist first and a socialist second, rather than a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>Socialist-Feminist. Not because I don&apos;t care about what
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>happens to the oppressed men in the world. Not because
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>lm against an ideally democratic socialism. But because
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>women&apos;s oppression crosses economic-class lines. Its a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>matter of focus. Clearly the needs of welfare-class women
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>are most urgent and those of upper-class women are least
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>urgent. Some socialists say that getting rid of patriarchy
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>won’t change the world. I wonder. Even in revolutionary
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>socialist movements women must maintain an autonomous
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>base. Revolution for Everyman isn’t the same as real social
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>change; it has taken place in the past without solving the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>&quot;woman question.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>In the meantime, living in a capitalist country without a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>strong Socialist Party provokes an irresistible urge to kill
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>time as a liberal feminist. Even though l’m aware of the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>dangers of opportunism, reformism, co-optation, and all
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>the slimy horde, 1 often find myself working for reform
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>rather than revolution because I can&apos;t bear to see nothing
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>done.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>Within the art world, this means l work to get women
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>artists into a system I oppose. Outside, in the real world,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>this means I want the ERA passed because its going to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>make a difference in women&apos;s lives. I want to see a politi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>cally aware feminist culture and I hope that Heresies will
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>help create it and help destroy some of the boundaries that
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>separate women from the power to make a better society
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>that will fit our needs as well as men&apos;s.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>(P.S. Because l’m a critic, l’ve been called a “class
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>enemy&quot; of artists, which is bullshit. l’m exploited by pub¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>lishers, and perhaps editors, just as artists are exploited by
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>galleries, and perhaps critics. lidentify with artists whether
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>or not they identify with me because long experience has
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>shown me that our lives are more or less the same.)
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>When we decided that each of us in the first issue
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>collective should write an individual statement to put
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>our political differences “out front,“ I thought it was a fine
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>idea. But trying to write one page about my notion of how
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>feminism relates to Marxism relates to making theory and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>making films was easier said than done: too much to argue
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>in too little space. So what 1 wanted to do was write,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>please see my article on page x” where l’ve tried to work
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>out some of these problems in more analytical depth. But
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>my sister-editors said, “write something personal.&quot; They
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>chided me for my rhetorical style and my obsessive?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>academic? commitment to making “complete” arguments.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>&quot;Who are you in all that,&quot; they asked. O.K. 1m a woman,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>l&apos;m white, l&apos;m 28. 1m a film teacher, l&apos;m a student, l&apos;m a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>writer, theorist, critic, filmmaker, I do political work—in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l16' n='N016'/>the feminist community and with a new Coalition (July 4th)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l17' n='N017'/>thats building toward a mass, progressive peoples&apos; move¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l18' n='N018'/>ment in this country. I guess l’m whats come to be called a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l19' n='N019'/>cultural worker.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l20' n='N020'/>Often it seems there’s just not enough time in each day
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l21' n='N021'/>to do all the things that have to be done. And to earn a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l22' n='N022'/>living, and write a dissertation, and see the art l care about,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l23' n='N023'/>and do the laundry, and talk with students, and be with the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l24' n='N024'/>friends I love, and see the ocean sometimes. Putting it all
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l25' n='N025'/>together, l&apos;doften like a few clones of myself to help out.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l26' n='N026'/>juggle whats possible with whats not.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l27' n='N027'/>Where does the fight for women fit with fighting im¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l28' n='N028'/>perialism? Does working in collectives really help change
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l29' n='N029'/>our deeply entrenched American individualism? How can
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l30' n='N030'/>“cultural workers” best advance these struggles? I often
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l31' n='N031'/>argue esthetics with my political comrades. Films, 1 say,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l32' n='N032'/>don’t have to be simplistic to communicate with mass
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l33' n='N033'/>audiences. We’re all subject to subtle propaganda from
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l34' n='N034'/>Hollywood and Madison Avenue. We’re all jugglers of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l35' n='N035'/>contradictions and need to see and hear and read about
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l36' n='N036'/>alternatives to what is. We have to make films that not only
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l37' n='N037'/>say something different but say it in a different way. They
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l38' n='N038'/>have to be made in a practical political context, in a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l39' n='N039'/>coherent theoretical context, and they have to be able to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l40' n='N040'/>recapture the imaginations of masses of people being lulled
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l41' n='N041'/>to sleep by the crap thats sold as “mass art.&quot; We have to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l42' n='N042'/>find strategies for making our alternate points of view
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l43' n='N043'/>visible, making peoples&apos; voices heard, our ideas and films
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l44' n='N044'/>seen; find ways of tighting the commercial monopolies that
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l45' n='N045'/>own the air waves, the movie screens, the mass media, that
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l46' n='N046'/>ownus
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l47' n='N047'/>argue politics with my feminist sisters. No more sep¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l48' n='N048'/>aratism, I say. I work on HERESIES to say that and also
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l49' n='N049'/>because—another contradiction—l need community in a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l50' n='N050'/>country that is in fragments. In short, and as labor people
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l51' n='N051'/>like my grandparents always said: women, artists, men,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l52' n='N052'/>people, we’ve got to get organized.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l53' n='N053'/>J.B.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>What kind of socialist-feminist-artist am 1?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>What kind of socialist artist loves Corot as well as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>Courbet and forgives oil painting its bourgeois origins and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>abstract expressionism its heraldry of U.S. imperialism?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>What kind of feminist artist sees pink as a private color to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>be sparingly used?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>To the women’s movement 1 would like to bring, as to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>art, the subtlest perceptions. To political action, I would
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>like to bring, as to art, a precise and delicate imagination.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>The personal is the political only if you make it so. The
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>connections have to be drawn. Feminism without socialism
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l12' n='N012'/>can create only utopian pockets. And the lifespan of a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l13' n='N013'/>collective is approximately two years.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l14' n='N014'/>Socialism without feminism is still patriarchy. But more
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l15' n='N015'/>smug. Try to imagine a classless society run by men.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l16' n='N016'/>Trying to be part of a collective is a little like being a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l17' n='N017'/>chameleon set on plaid. I may split apart before I get the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l18' n='N018'/>pattern right. But somehow it seems worth the pain be¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l19' n='N019'/>cause l believe community is the highest goal.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l20' n='N020'/>Ibelieve every woman&apos;s life is a little better because of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l21' n='N021'/>what we are doing.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l22' n='N022'/>M.S.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l1' n='N001'/>L.R.L
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
