<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Left Hand of History</title>
				<author>Teresa De Lauretis</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Heresies Issue 4</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="23"/>
			<head>The Left Hand of History</head>
			<byline><persName>Teresa De Lauretis</persName></byline>
			<div>
				<p> What is the place of textuality in feminist criticism? (I mean criticism both in
					the narrow sense of literary criticism and in the broad sense of sociocultural
					critique.) Since text ual analysis has a fundamental place in any theory of cul
					ture, how should the feminist critic approach her work with texts? What should
					her purpose be? 1 am not sure that a the ory of women’s writing is useful or
					even desirable at this point. Because women have been a colonized population for
					so long, 1 fear that any critical category we may find applic able today is
					likely to be derived from or imbued with male ideologies. As writers, critics,
					teachers, we know this from our daily experiences. I am not suggesting that we
					ought to clean the slate of history and start anew because 1 am enough of a
					historical materialist and semiotician that I cannot con ceive of a totally new
					world rising out of, and in no way con nected with, the past or the present. 1
					believe neither in utop- ias nor in the myth of Paradise Now, or ever. What I am
					suggesting is that theory is dialectically built on, checked against, modified
					by, transformed along with, practice—that is to say, with what women do, invent,
					perform, produce, concretely and not “for all time” but within specific histori
					cal and cultural conditions.</p>
				<p> In the summer of 1975, I was in the small town of Sant Arcangelo di Romagna
					(near Bologna, Italy) where an open- air theater festival sponsored performances
					by militant and experimental groups in the town square and courtyards of two
					medieval castles. One of these performances attracted my attention by its title,
					Nonostante Gramsci (Despite Gramsci). It was performed by a militant feminist
					collective, La Maddalena, based in Rome. Antonio Gramsci was foun der of the
					Italian Communist Party and one of the major European Marxist thinkers. He was
					the most important in fluence on the Italian left in general and on the politics
					of the Italian Communist Party (PCI) in particular. His historical analyses and
					theoretical foundations for Italian communism continue to be effective
					today.</p>
				<p> Gramsci was imprisoned in 1926 by the newly consolidat- ed Fascist dictatorship.
					He received a mock trial, was given a life sentence, and died in 1937 of illness
					and abuse suffered in one of Mussolini’s prisons. The circumstances of his death
					and his extraordinary intellectual and moral stature have made him perhaps the
					greatest hero and martyr of the Italian resistance. This is why the play’s
					title, Despite (or Notwith- standing) Gramsci, surprised and intrigued me, since
					I knew that Italian feminist groups consist almost exclusively of women with a
					record of militancy in the left. They couldn’t be against” Gramsci. Therefore,
					what did they mean by despite”?</p>
				<p> The background of the production reveals the group’s ideological stance. Both
					the text of the theatrical production and the underlying research on original
					documents were published together the following year under the editorship of
					Adele Cambria, a feminist writer and one of the editors of the major Italian
					feminist monthly EFFE.<note n="1">1. Adele Cambria, Amore come rivoluzione
						(Milano: Sugar Co., 1976): The volume includes the script and production
						notes for Nonostante Gramsci.</note> Cambria formu lated and conducted the
					research, but the theatrical work was performed, directed and written
					collectively. The pub lished volume, entitled Amore come rivoluzione (Love as
					Revolution) contains 1 believe not two texts—one creative/ artistic and one
					historical/biographical—but rather a single text. It self-consciously attempts
					to be at once historical and artistic, and deliberately presents itself as
					tendentious and critical. It is a text with its ideology clearly stated and with
					a basis of original research behind its fiction. This text is pos ited as a set
					of questions dealing with love and revolution—a complex problem that emerged in
					the late 1960s, was pushed to the foreground of political consciousness by
					radical femin ism, and is one of the major issues in revolutionary politics
					today.</p>
				<p> During the last eleven years of his life, the imprisoned Gramsci wrote the bulk
					of his theoretical work now pub- lished as Quaderni dal carcere (Prison
						Notebooks)<note n="2">2. The complete Italian edition, in four volumes, is
						Antonio Gramsci, Quaderni dal carcere, a cura di Valentino Gerratana
						(Torino: Einaudi, 1975). In English see Selections from the Prison Notebooks
						of Antonio Gramsci, edited and translated by Quintin Hoare and Geoffrey
						Nowell Smith (New York: International Publishers, 1971).</note> In 1922
					Gramsci spent several months in the Soviet Union as Italian envoy to the
					Executive Committee of the Communist Inter- national. While hospitalized in a
					sanatorium outside Mos cow, he met Eugenia Schucht, also a patient in the
					hospital, and her sister Giulia. Giulia and Antonio fell in love. After Gramsci
					had returned to Western Europe, recalled by his political duties, their son
					Delio was born in 1924. The couple were together only once again, the following
					year, when Giulia, the baby and Eugenia spent a few months in Rome with Gramsci
					who by then had been elected to the Italian parliament. When she returned to the
					Soviet Union, Giulia was pregnant with their second son, Giuliano, whom Gram sci
					never saw. History records that during his long years in prison, the only link
					between Gramsci and his family was Giulia s other sister, Tatiana Schucht, who
					lived in Italy and followed Gramsci as he was sent from one jail to another. She
					supported him materially and spiritually, assisting him through his long agony.
					It is Tatiana who rescued Gramsci’s Prison Notebooks after his death. But,
					history being the his tory of men, only Gramsci’s letters were deemed important
					historical documents.<note n="3">3. Antonio Gramsci, Lettere dal carcere, a cura
						di S. Caprioglio e E. Fubini (Torino: Einaudi, 1973). In English see Antonio
						Gramsci, Letters from Prison, selected and translated by Lynne Lawner (New
						York: Harper and Row, 1973). See also Guiseppe Fiori, Antonio Gramsci: Life
						of a Revolutionary (New York: Schocken Books, 1973).</note> The letters he
					received from Giulia and Tatiana were not published, although they existed,
					lying in a file at the Gramsci Institute in Rome. Official historiog raphy
					scorned them. They were women s letters, dealing only with children and
					marmalade, banal, insignificant. Little information could be found about these
					mute women, whose complex relationships to Gramsci and to one another
					constituted the most intense private aspect of Gramsci’s life as a
					revolutionary. Biographers record that Giulia grew more and more alienated from
					her husband as a result of mental illness. In his letters he lamented and
					grieved over her silence. Tatiana acted as a sister of mercy, visiting Gramsci
					in jail, sending him socks and medicines, relaying letters bet <pb n="24"/> ween
					him, Giulia and the children. Here ends their official history. Yet, if we read
					Gramsci’s letters many of the ques tions posed in them remain unanswered: What
					exactly was the nature of Giulia’s “illness”? Why did Tatiana and not she stay
					in Italy to assist him in jail? What moved Tatiana to literally devote her life
					to him? What was Eugenia’s role? There is no doubt that Gramsci’s thoughts were
					directed to these private concerns as much as to political problems and
					theory—his letters prove it despite the self-restraint imposed by personal
					ethics and prison censorship. Some of his most beautiful letters to Giulia deal
					with the education of their children and with the problems posed by his
					responsibilities to the revolution and to their love relationship—he even sug-
					gested a formal separation that would allow Giulia to re marry, if that would
					restore her well-being.</p>
				<p> Who were these women outside of the pale, pathetic hagi ography constructed by
					Gramsci’s biographers? This is what Adele Cambria set out to investigate. She
					carefully read all of the women’s letters in conjunction with Gramsci’s, inter
					viewed people who had been close friends of the sisters, stud- ied Eugenia’s
					letters to a friend in Rome and the notebooks in which Giulia had practiced
					compositions as an adolescent. Cambria s purpose throughout was to reconstruct
					an “affec tive biography” of the Schuchts and to discover the sources and modes
					of that “emotional energy” Shulamith Firestone identifies as the essential
					female contribution to male thought.<note n="4">4. The Dialectic of Sex: The
						Case for Feminist Revolution (New York: Bantam Books, 1970), pp.
						126-127.</note> Cambria’s project was a political one: to rewrite history,
					inscribing in it the missing voices of women, and therefore to examine the
					relationships between the private and the public, love and revolution,
					personal/sexual/emo tional needs and political militancy—relations which she
					sees as the moving forces of all revolutionary struggle. In restor ing to
					Gramsci’s epistolary monologue its real nature as dia logue, Cambria adds depth
					to the cultural image of a person whose complex humanity has been expediently
					stereotyped.</p>
				<p>In a letter to Giulia in 1924, before his imprisonment and at the height of
					revolutionary activities Gramsci himself posed the problem. He wrote:</p>
				<quote>How many times have I asked myself whether it was possible to tie oneself to
					a mass without ever having loved anyone .. whether one could love a collectivity
					if one hadn’t deeply loved some single human beings . . . Wouldn’t this have
					made barren my qualities as a revolutionary, wouldn’t it have reduced them to a
					pure intellectual fact, a pure mathe matical calculation? <note n="5">5. Quoted
						by Cambria, p. 9, from Duemila pagine di Gramsci (Milano: Il Saggiatore),
						Vol. II, p. 23, letter of June 9, 1924; my translation.</note></quote>
				<p> Gramsci’s question unwinds the ideological thread that runs through Cambria’s
					work and the collective theater produc tion, both of which focus on the “private
					aspect of Gram sci’s life. Thus an understanding of the Schucht family is es
					sential, in the context of the turn-of-the-century cultural val ues and of the
					changes brought by the October Revolution. Lenin, and later by Stalinism and
					Fascism.</p>
				<p> Apollo Schucht, father of the three sisters, was an exile from czarist Russia
					who had settled in Rome in 1908. Born into the upper bourgeoisie, he had
					belonged to the Russian populist social reform movement (narodvolcstvo) in the
					mid- nineteenth century. Deported with Lenin to Siberia where his third
					daughter, Eugenia, was born, he asked his friend Lenin to be her “godfather.”
					The family lived in Rome from 1908 to 1917. After the October Revolution, they
					all returned to the Soviet Union and worked in the CPSU except Tatiana who
					stayed at her teaching position in Rome. Significantly nothing much is known of
					Apollo’s wife, Lula, except that she was an excellent cook and housewife. It was
					Apollo’s strong influence that shaped the lives of his daughters. His world
					view, in matters of sex roles, was all but revolutionary. His daughters
					completed their higher education in Rome in the arts and natural sciences, areas
					that clearly trained wom en for the only careers suitable for them—marriage and
					teaching. The early writings of Giulia and Eugenia reveal how deeply they had
					absorbed their father’s late-romantic humanitarian values: a sense of duty
					toward the poor and dispossessed; contact with nature as a source of happiness,
					goodness and personal fulfillment; the love of children ideal ized as a pure
					unspoiled manifestation of Good Nature; a sentimental attachment to Family as
					nest and shelter from the disorder and potential danger of the outside world.
					None of this prepared them for the violent realities in which they were to live.
					In the turmoil after the revolution there came into their lives the man who,
					like their father before him, was to magnetize their existence. Gramsci became,
					for all three women, the center of their emotional world, the unwitting
					protagonist of romantic mystification, the pivot of a patriar chal model they
					had deeply internalized. They all were in love with Antonio.</p>
				<p> Eugenia met him first, but he fell in love with Giulia, the youngest, most
					beautiful and most “feminine” of them. Cambria documents, fairly convincingly,
					that Eugenia’s es pousal of the Communist cause—her “wedding” to the Party —came
					right after Antonio and Giulia met. The sisters’ close mother-daughter
					relationship had made Giulia emotionally and intellectually dependent on her
					older sister. Eugenia later exploited this by making herself indispensable,
					support- ing her financially, taking care of her children and living with her
					before and during Gramsci’s imprisonment, thus re- inforcing Giulia’s feelings
					of personal inadequacy in the roles of mother and wife. In Cambria’s
					interpretation, Eugenia was mainly responsible for keeping Giulia away from Gram
					sci. Her reasons were consistent with the prevailing values of the time: Giulia
					must stay in the Soviet Union to care for the children who would be in great
					danger in Fascist Italy; Giulia was “sickly and subject to depressions”; Giulia
					was a Soviet communist and the Party needed her. Eradicating from her life the
					possibility of a “private relationship with any man, Eugenia played the male
					role as political activist and head of the household. While praising and
					mythicizing Gramsci as a revolutionary leader (she translated his writings for
					the Soviet workers), Eugenia increased the human dis tance between him and
					Giulia.</p>
				<p> Tatiana met Antonio after his return to Rome, already married” to Giulia
					(officially recorded after the first child was born). Tatiana’s love for
					Gramsci, avowed as sisterly love, developed over the twelve years during which
					she per- formed for him the duties of the prisoner’s wife. A close read ing of
					their letters shows the ambivalence of their relation ship which, considering
					their strong ethical sense and mater- ial and social constraints, was perhaps
					the most fulfilling, if deformed, love relationship of any of the Schucht
					sisters. In defining herself as Giulia’s representative, she slowly made herself
					indispensable to the man she loved. She maintained contact with underground left
					leaders outside Italy in hope less attempts to free Gramsci through prisoner
					exchanges. As the only correspondent authorized by jail officials, she copied
					and relayed his letters to Giulia and the children and theirs to him. By this
					“charitable sacrifice” and sisterly devotion, and by never allowing her own
					needs to surface (but they are there, between the lines of the letters), Tatiana
					gradually ac quired a wife’s right to husbandly gratitude, a wifely
					possessiveness and the subtle power gained by female self- denial.</p>
				<p> Of the three stories, unrecorded by history, Giulia’s is the most lonely. She is
					still alive, as far as we know, in some psychiatric hospital where she has spent
					most of her life, im prisoned in her “mental illness” as Antonio was in his
					cell. <pb n="25"/> He burned in the hell of pain, captivity and death, but he
					won—he is a protagonist of history. Giulia is still burning, quietly, bothering
					no one, unnoticed, useless. One of Cam bria’s most significant contributions to
					feminist analysis is her effort to understand Giulia’s personal world with love
					and generosity, outside of myth and without mystification. She sees Giulia as a
					sensitive, intelligent, gifted woman in whom the traditional female
					socialization, with its emphasis on dependence, frailty and childlike trust,
					found a most re ceptive terrain. Giulia did not relate intellectually to others
					or to her own experience. Women of her time were not sup- posed to. She needed
					direct sensuous contact with reality, her children, her man. She gave up her
					violin for her children and the Party. The distance between her and Antonio was
					caused not only by circumstances but also by decisions made for her by Eugenią,
					to which Gramsci acquiesced. Her re sponse to the distance was expressed by a
					sense of personal inadequacy, increasing depression, surrendering her will to
					others and to the mechanical details of daily existence. The notion that absence
					makes the heart grow fonder did not work for her: she blamed herself for not
					being able to feel, for losing contact with Antonio who was becoming a mere ab
					straction—The Father of Her Children, The Revolutionary Hero—no longer her lover
					whom she could touch nor her friend whom she could see and hear and speak to.
					She felt guilty about this and when she finally dared to write to him about her
					illness he did not answer, could not accept the idea of mental illness, spoke
					harshly of psychoanalysis as a crutch, and like the rest of the family
					recommended iron, vit- amins and will power. No one ever seriously considered
					the possibility that Giulia move to Italy to assist Antonio, and she herself
					believed that she could never do for him what Tatiana did. In short, Eugenia and
					Tatiana usurped her roles as mother, housekeeper and wife and effectively de-
					prived her of meaningful emotional relationships and inten sified her sense of
					powerlessness. At last, Cambria main tains, Giulia’s inability to define herself
					conceptually or through any type of personal power, and the unreality of her
					existence that could not function within any socially accepted mode of female
					behavior, pushed Giulia to live her rebellion inwardly, in total passivity. This
					is precisely what is often diagnosed as madness in women.<note n="6">6. Cf.
						Phyllis Chesler, Women and Madness (Garden City, N.Y.: Double- day,
						1972).</note></p>
				<p> In a sense, the personalities and social roles assumed by the three Schucht
					sisters sketch almost to a T the only choices allowed women in most Western
					cultures: service functions within male structures, adherence to the feminine
					mystique of charity, sacrifice and self-denial, and madness. T’he textual
					strategies of Amore come rivoluzione are the result of ideological choices. The
					materials being mainly let- ters, there were three obvious genre possibilities:
					(1) publish- ing the letters, with some editing (as was done with Gramsci's
					letters); (2) putting together a sort of three-way epistolary novel of Giulia’s,
					Tatiana s' and Gramsci’s letters; or (3) giv- ing the materials a narrative
					form, i.e., writing a biography of the Schucht sisters. Cambria discarded all
					three alterna tives. Her decision to avoid a “novelistic” organization was a
					political as well as aesthetic choice: as recent critical theory in literature
					and film argues, narrative form is the primary aesthetic code developed to
					convey bourgeois and counter- revolutionary values.<note n="7">7. From Umberto
						Eco, Opera aperta (Milano: Bompiani, 1967) to Stephen Heath, “Narrative
						Space,” Screen (Autumn 1976), pp. 68-112.</note> Simply printing the letters
					without at- tempting to reproduce such “physical” qualities as hand writing, or
					the context in which they were written and dis covered, would have erased
					altogether the function of the subject (Cambria herself), as both writer and
					narrator of her book and at the same time reader of the Schucht letters.</p>
				<p> Cambria chose to print portions of the original documents in italics
					interspersed with passages from Gramsci’s letters, quotations, statements by
					friends or others involved in the events, while her own comments link, interpret
					and contex- tualize each passage. The rigorous separation, by different
					typefaces, between the women’s letters and her own com- mentary explicitly
					manifests the interpretive nature of the commentary, its tendentiousness, its
					having a viewpoint, its being “sectarian” rather than an innocent or “objective”
					ex planation. In this manner, a twofold process is set in motion in the text:
					the release of affective energies contained in the firsthand documents, which
					were personal writings aimed at a real person (Gramsci), not a literary
					readership; and the re lease of a corresponding emotional response in the modern
					woman reading the letters and mediating them for us through her personal and
					ideological, affective and concep tual codes. In many passages Cambria shares
					her emotion at discovering the letters, looking at the faded colors of the pa
					per, the elegant old-fashioned handwriting of Tatiana, the broken sentences and
					pencil scrawls of an already ill Giulia. Cambria also describes her feelings as
					she approached the Moscow house where Giulia lived and where Cambria inter
					viewed her son Giuliano.<note n="8">8. On the conditions of women in the Soviet
						Union since the revolution, see Sheila Rowbotham, “If You Like Tobogganing”
						in her Women, Resistance and Revolution (New York: Vintage Books, 1974), pp.
						134-169. Also very important to this topic is the work of Alexandra
						Kollontai, The Auto biography of a Sexually Emancipated Communist Woman (New
						York: Schocken Books, 1975). Women Workers Struggle for Their Rights
						(Bristol: Falling Wall Press, 1971), and Sexual Relations and the Class
						Struggle/Love and the New Morality (Bristol: Falling Wall Press,
						1972).</note></p>
				<p> Cambria conveys to readers how she absorbed Giulia, Tatiana and Eugenia as
					fragments of her own self, how their experiences can act as reactor to other
					women’s understand- ing of themselves; she also conveys her elation in
					discovering and unearthing a writing which is the testimony of unknown women.
					She reaches into an immense reservoir of women’s folklore, millions of letters
					in which women have spent their imagination and creativity writing to those they
					loved, all lost, but for the few who made literary history by loving a male
					protagonist.</p>
				<p> The performance I saw was in an open courtyard and used the Brechtian concept of
					epic theater. In the theatrical text, the double function of the subject as
					writer and as reader is dramatized in the character of The Girl, epic narrator
					and didactic commentator, who circulates among the four char acters (the three
					sisters and Gramsci), each of whom is con fined to an assigned scenic space. The
					Girl has a double function: as narrator and commentator, she provides the his
					torical background and the feminist interpretation of the per formed action. As
					character, she voices the lyrical conscious ness of the play, Woman-Orpheus. A
					contemporary woman, she is a barometer for the audience, reacting with pity and
					anger to the events enacted around her. The fact that she also acts visibly as a
					stage hand (she projects the slides, moves the structures, dresses the actors)
					is a brilliant theatri cal idea for she is perceived by the audience as a
					performer, i.e., as a real person participating in the entire fictional cre
					ation and not simply acting out a memorized part in some body else’s play.
					Furthermore, since she models audience response, it is very important that she
					does not remain emo tionally detached or objective in relation to the
					characters; at the same time her involvement must never become total. For, in
					the intentions of the epic theater, the audience and the performers must not
					identify totally with the characters, must not be drawn into the story
					forgetting that it is a fiction, must not experience catharsis at the conclusion
					of the play. Rather, they must remain conscious of the problems raised by the
					play and seek their solution outside, after the play, in the real world. One
					example: in “dressing” Giulia, revealing her to us, The Girl is a woman of today
					discovering her roots in a woman of the past and re-enacting herself in a
					fictional character. But when The Girl acts out the pain of pregnancy and
					childbirth, shouting her rejection of motherhood as a physical violence done to
					her body, as an emotionally trau matic infringement on her total person, at this
					moment The Girl is Giulia; she expresses the feeling that Giulia could <pb
						n="26"/> never express, the repression of which was one of the forms of her
					“insanity."</p>
				<p> Certain aspects of this production—the use of voices on tape, slides, lighting,
					the designed structures, objects of per sonal “ritual” created by the
					performers—are discussed in the direction notes and contributions by performers
					and designers printed in the appendix to the volume. These pro vide an integral,
					essential part of the text, outlining the dif ficult but rewarding practice of
					the performance, collective in every aspect from writing to staging to each
					performer’s self-direction.</p>
				<p> The historical text and the theatrical text were conceived interdependently.
					Although they are addressed to different, if overlapping, audiences and make
					different assumptions as textual mechanisms, they are not two distinct texts as
					would be, say, a biography and a play based on it. They are, rather, one set of
					raw materials examined with an identical ideologi cal perspective and presented
					differently to achieve a double impact by juxtaposition; when we experience them
					together, the historical text has a distancing effect from the highly emotional
					impact of the dramatic text. The first is rational, documented, footnoted; the
					second is lyrical and intensely charged with emotion. The verbal material in the
					play is almost entirely from the original letters, with the addition of some
					contemporary poems and other quotations which serve as intertextual links to
					expand the historical resonance of the themes.</p>
				<p> The characteristic features of Cambria’s entire work point to a new practice and
					vision of the relation between subject and modes of textual production.<note
						n="9">9. For the notion of modes of sign production see Umberto Eco, A
						Theory of Semiotics (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1976) and
						Gianfranco Bettetini, Produzione del senso e messa in scena (Milano:
						Bompiani, 1975)</note> As for the form of content: historical, not mythical
					materials are chosen from a concrete situation and real events. These are not
					necessarily contem porary but always refer to the current concerns of the audi
						ence.<note n="10">10. In the words of Dacia Maraini, who reviewed Amore come
						rivoluzione, “books like this should be written by the hundreds. There are
						hundreds of extraordinary women who have so much to teach us (even if often
						they only speak of failures and defeat), women still buried under the
						barren, impious ashes of patriarchal history.” (Tuttolibri, 17 aprile 1976,
						p. 4; my transla tion). The terms form of content and form of expression
						come from Louis Hjelmslev, Prolegomena to a Theory of Language (Madison:
						University of Wisconsin Press, 1961).</note> The historical events are
					examined in their socio cultural complexity from the ideological and emotional
					view points of contemporary feminism. The human sources of these views—writers,
					performers and the specific audience addressed (this is a play for women)—are
					clearly identified to avoid mystification and mythologizing. As for the form of
					ex pression: the rejection of the novelistic as the single organiz- ing
					principle of classical narrative forms like biography, romance or the “realist”
					novel must be seen in the light of current theories of the plurality of the
					text. This emphasizes the process of reading as a constitutive act of the
					subject. In this new textual form, where the rational historical inquiry is
					continually intersected by the lyrical and the personal, the subject is at once
					writer and reader, performer and audience. The resonance of the (documented)
					historical events in the subject is made possible by the “private” dimension and
					in turn makes possible the emergence of pathos as a creative critical process.
					The text is produced as and meant to be re ceived as the intersecting of the
					personal and the social, a process articulated dialectically on subjective codes
					and on objective realities.</p>
				<p> Working along these lines, we can perhaps develop a fem inist theory of textual
					production which is neither a theory of women’s writing nor just a theory of
					textuality. In other words, it is not a matter of finding common elements among
					the texts written or produced by women and defining them in terms of a presumed
					femaleness or femininity which, to my mind, is highly suspect of sexual
					metaphysics; rather, it is our task to envision a feminist theory of the process
					of textual production and consumption, which is of course inseparable from a
					theory of culture. In a recently translated article en titled “Is There a
					Feminine Aesthetic?”, Silvia Bovenschen argues that there is no such thing as an
					ever-present female counterculture as such, or a “female nature outside of his
					torical development; and that to insist on such notions as ir rational
					perception, cosmic powers or archetypal forms as categories for femaleness is at
					best playing men’s games, and at worst indulging in reactionary ideologies.<note
						n="11">11. Silvia Bovenschen, “Is There a Feminine Aesthetic?”, New German
						Critique, 10 (Winter 1977), pp. 111-137 and Heresies f4, pp. 10-12. Altman’s
						recent film, Three Women, seems to me to come close to the latter
						group.</note> Since it is the specifics of feminine experience and
					perception that deter- mine the form the work takes, we must not accept a priori
					categories and should look for evidence of feminine sensitiv- ity in concrete
					tests. It is good, Bovenschen claims, that no formal criteria for “feminine art”
					can be definitively laid down. This enables us to reject the notion of artistic
					norms and facile labeling, and prevents cooptation and further ex ploitation of
					women’s creativity. So it is not a question of what or how women write, but of
					how women produce (as makers) and reproduce (as receivers) the aesthetic object,
					the text; in other words, we need a theory of culture with women as subjects—not
					commodities but social beings producing and reproducing cultural products,
					transmitting and trans forming cultural values.<note n="12">12. For a good
						analysis of women’s position as objects of exchange in Lévi Strauss and
						Freud/Lacan, see Gayle Rubin, “The Traffic in Women: Notes on the Political
						Economy of Sex, in Rayna R. Reiter, ed., Toward an An thropology of Women
						(New York: Monthly Review Press, 1975), pp. 157-210.</note></p>
				<p> In this sense, and so that we can take possession of our cul tural
					(re)production, 1 think we should assert that women’s work is never done. </p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<p>*This paper was first presented at the Symposium WOMEN/ TEXTS at the University
					of Minnesota in Minneapolis, on April 20, 1977.</p>
				<p>I am grateful to the Center for 20th Century Studies of the University of
					Wisconsin-Milwaukee for the 1976-1977 Fellowship that has made possible the
					research and the writing of this paper. 1 must also thank my friends Renny
					Harrigan, Andreas Huyssen, Judith Mayne, Sheila Radford-Hill, Sylvie Romanowski
					and Marcella Tarozzi, who helped me greatly by lend- ing me books, arguing
					against me, and sharing their knowledge and in sights.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p>Teresa de Lauretis was born in Bologna, studied in Milan and now teaches Italian at
				the University of Wisconsin at Milwaukee. </p>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
