<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On Never Being Good Enough: Legal Institutional Racism, Sexism, and
					Elitism</title>
				<author>Yvone A. Flowers</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Issue 8: Third World Women: the Politics of Being Other</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="28"/>
			<div>
				<head><title>Some Reflections on Black Women in Film</title></head>


				<byline>Rosemari Mealy</byline>
				<dateline>© 1979</dateline>
			</div>
			<div>
				<p> would like to present a brief outline on some important aspects of a subject
					about which l’m most concerned—the deletion of a correct portrayal of Black
					women in film. l've been in many political discussions around this topic and as
					a Black woman l’ve gone to theaters only to be insulted by what l've watched on
					the screen. 1 have thus internalized the topic based on having an understanding
					of my own oppression as a Black woman. One film made me so angry 1 wanted to
					leave before the first half. The film was Which Way is Up. The comedy of Richard
					Pryor became the rage of Rosemari Mealy. 1 was so busy verbally analyzing the
					sexist attitude of Pryor towards Black women that 1 made a few folks move to
					other seats. ! applauded the Chicana sister when she drove off, with his child
					and another man leaving him to his petit bourgeois sexist antics. For me that
					film was a personification of the sexist decadence exemplified in "contemporary'
					Black film.</p>
				<p>Since the early 70’s contemporary Black films have done little or nothing to
					depict the correct image of Black people, much less that of Black women.</p>
				<p>Some years ago, 1 read Christopher Caudwell's IIlusion and Reality. Caudwell
					was a European scientist, writer, and poet. My respect for his writings
					increased when learned that he was also an anti-fascist who died fighting as
					such. Caudwell saw art as adapting the individual psyche to the environment,
					and fas] therefore one of the conditions of the development of society." 1 agree
					with that perspective. Therefore, 1 cannot talk about the characterization of
					Black women in film without first understanding the characterization of Black
					people historically in film. And we all know that racism and sexism permeated
					that characterization.</p>
				<p>The Black Scholar so amply summarized this characterization in its May 1976
					issue:</p>
				<quote>The Hollywood film industry has historically been a chief arbiter of American
					cultural values and images. Hollywood has fashioned and purveyed a celluloid
					American Dream—a dream that has been extremely profitable for the white
					film-makers, and which has molded and titillated the psyches of millions and
					milions of moviegoers.<lb/> Hollywood movies created and popularized American
					heroes and villains—prototypically, the white cowboy-adventurer-secret agent
					portrayed in righteous combat against treacherous Indians, Asians or Blacks.
					(And when the villain was not actually dark-skinned, it was customary for
					him to wear a black hat and/or coat.) Movies have thus been a major institu¬
					tional and ideological prop of American racism: distorting history, inculcating
					racist values and stereotypes, and largely excluding non-whites from
					participation in film-making.</quote>
				<p>The individual psyche of the Black theater audience has adapted to a dominant
					theme so prevalent in capitalist society. Violence then becomes the dominant
					theme in all social relationships. The perpetuation of racist and sexist
					stereotyping in film exacerbates the violence theme. Violence is an active
					phenomenon. Black women in film portray that violence; in reality, they are the
					victims of such in social and familial relationships—thousands of Black women
					were victims of domestic violence in the United States last year. The links
					between reality and the norms acceptable to institutions of society perpetuate
					the characterization within the film industry. Who are the heroes for our
					children? The pimp in The Mack, the super-niggers as portrayed by Fred
					Williamson and Jim Brown. What ingratiates these films to the bourgeoisie is the
					role most often portrayed by Black women—that of the victim as culprit. The
					extent of the Black woman's liberation on the screen is based on her willingness
					to take low, as well as how often she gives it up. From the historical
					perspective, the culprit has been the mammy, the tragic mulatto, the
					mammy-matriarch and the seductress.</p>
				<p>In the March/April 1973 issue of The Black Scholar, Edward Mapp adequately
					describes the historical role of Black women in film. He cites only one example
					of Hollywood's portrayal of the Black woman's experience as a possible take off
					point for extending a positive approach to Black women in film. He cites Lady
					Sings the Blues (1972) for its depiction of the Black female’s contribution to
					American culture and art. But even this is a totally inaccurate portrayal of
					the real life of Billie Holiday. 1 say we need films about Lucy Parsons, Black
					woman worker/labor organizer; the 1969 Charleston <pb n="29"/> Women Hospital
					workers, Ida b. Wells, Beulah Sanders, Fannie Lou Hammer, Ella Baker and
					Florence Wrice, ILGWU organizer; we need more films like Nothing But a Man,
					which creates a positive image in a negative context. In the 70’s, spurred on by
					the cultural nationalist movement, we were to produce a new mage, but the very
					first Black multi-million dollar film set the tone for what was later to be
					Hollywood's economic bail-out and a contemporary version of Green Pastures,
					where porkchops and watermelon were replaced by butts, bosoms and gun-toting
					niggers—black-faced versions of what was once the exclusive property of the
					white, male, racist and sexist dominated industry. Sweet Sweetback's Badass
					Song was the film—a nightmare from the mind of Melvin Van Peebles.</p>
				<p>The initial screen image presented by the film of the “New Black Image," even
					before the film title was introduced, is a Black woman prostitute committing
					statutory rape on a 10- year-old Black child. And it is significant that the
					first image was created by a Black male. But lest we fall into our bourgeois or
					feminist trap of the simplistic notion of Black men against Black women, we must
					define what kind of man Van Peebles is—what is his class attitude? It was always
					defined by him in terms of money!!! To be sure, the brother was talented and
					witty. He even got across the racist Hollywood unions to make this flick,
					claiming he was giving Black people jobs, providing them with technical skills
					and film exposure. But how many of these non-union Black men and women were to
					reap a significant portion of the more than 312 million in profits? And what
					organizations did Van Peebles leave behind to intervene and counter the racism
					of the union? How women were depicted within the supposedly “New Image'' was
					no more than a capitulation to sexist ideology. The screen no longer reflected
					the passive mammies, the tragic mulattos. They were now in the modern feminist
					idiom: the aggressive, gun-toting and in some cases emasculating "free fucking
					women,"' perpetuated by superstars Pam Greer, Vonetta McGee, and Pamela Dodson.
					They headed the money-making movies with their large breasts, long legs and
					pretty eyes rather than with their acting abilities. Or we saw the bit players
					whose primary acting talents lay in their ability to moan, groan and succumb
					to the ex-football machos like Jim Brown and Fred Williamson, or non-football
					heroes like Richard Roundtree. Again, these were men and women who were more
					committed to the mighty dollar—Hollywood—than to portraying a positive image
					to Black people. None of them had the social consciousness of our first Black
					film star Paul Robeson, whose portrayal of The Emperor Jones and a Black miner
					in the Welsh miners film called Proud Valley intimidated white film-makers. Paul
					Robéson was an ex-all-American football player who could also sing and act, even
					in the so-called "legitimate theater " But he refused to be housenigger In his
					book Hear / Stand he said, "The artist must elect to fight for freedom or
					slavery. 1 have made my choice. Between 1942 and 1946 his income dropped from
					$100,000 to $6,000.</p>
				<p>There are some contemporary women who have refused to prostitute their talent.
					Cicely Tyson starved for years before she got the half-decent roles of Jane
					Pittman and the mother in “Roots." However both dramas had their shortcomings
					due to the commercialism of the productions. Read the book to determine how
					Kizzy and the other women might have been portrayed. In the book, for example.
					Kunta didn’t get caught because he stopped off to get a quicky, and it was he,
					not Belle, who fought to keep the slave buyer from taking his precious Kizzy.
					Note in the TV version that Belle's strength in fighting for Kizzy while Kunta
					fell crying to his knees was an excellent example of how the Black woman's image
					is manipulated to relegate the Black man to a demeaning, subservient position.
					Similarly in the show "Good Times,"' at one time TV's only complete and positive
					Black family, a strong John Amos was killed off, leaving Esther Rolle in a
					neo-mammy role, catering to the character played by Jimmy Walker In this case,
					the demise of the strong male image manipulates the strong woman into a less
					than positive image.</p>
				<p>The petit bourgeois will always level criticism at the progressive film-maker for
					presenting "Documentaries"' as opposed to “Art'' forms. This fragmented
					distinction between "art"' and reality"' is a superficial offspring of a bour¬
					geois capitalist society, reinforced by the artists/ critics who see themselves
					separated and alienated from the masses.</p>
				<p>Film-makers like Haille Gerima, Ousmane Sembene, Nana Mahomo, Chris Choy, Robert
					Van Lierop, and Jose Garcia will continue to have limited exposure. It is
					unfortunate that their creations will not reach the mass media and will never be
					the dominant theme of American film under the present economic system.</p>
				<p>The internationally acclaimed Cuban cinema could never have existed in the old
					days. It <pb n="30"/> came only after the revolution. The award winning film
					Lucia demonstrates the ability of film to portray women in a revolutionary his¬
					torical perspective. Its mass distribution is attributed to the Cuban
					revolution. Only now, as in Bob Van Lierop's O Povo Organizado, do we see a
					revolutionary historical perspective of the African woman. Now Mozambique's
					artists are able to produce revolutionary images on a mass basis through the
					establishment of the National Cinema Institute.</p>

				<p> Black film-makers must now become proletarianized—organizers, building the
					unions that Van Peebles failed to build, going beyond the boundaries of
					bourgeois nationalism and making the necessary links with revolutionary film¬
					makers on an international basis. Most desirably, when Black women themselves
					become involved in the film-making process there will be an appreciable change
					in portraying the true image of Black women in film, a portrayal which reflects
					our social reality. </p>
				<caption>Mrs. Rosanelle Powell Whiskey Run Read. Camden, 1965.</caption>

				<quote> It ain't hot. It's hell out here. I was paying one hundred seventy-five
					dollars a year for that house, and it looked like it was about to fall. I was
					afeared the wind would blow it away. I had about twenty acres. I didn't make
					much, but I managed to get my children into college. Now I farm a little corn
					for the cows. I don't farm no cotton, cause there wasn't nothing to it.<lb/> I
					have ten children, but they're only three left. All the rest done gone to
					Connecticut. It's been sad times. Jack and Bob and King are dead. They killed
					them, because they didn't want the Negroes brought out from under their foots.
					That's how come they killed them. I don't see nothing else.</quote>
				<byline>—Mrs. Powell</byline>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
