<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Homophobia: Myths and Realities</title>
				<author>Naeemah Shabazz</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Issue 8: Third World Women</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="34"/>
			<div>
				<head><title>Homophobia: Myths and Realities</title></head>


				<byline>Naeemah Shabazz</byline>
				<dateline>© 1979</dateline>
			</div>
			<div>
				<p> This essay will speak to homophobia and identify some of the basic institutions
					that help formulate our sexual politics and reinforce societal myths about
					lesbians. Homophobia is a social illness characterized by the fear of being
					defined as, associated with, mistakenly identified for a homosexual. At the
					New York As- sociation of Black Psychologists Fourth Annual Spring Conference,
					Yvonne Flowers defined homophobia to the conference as “an exaggerated fear of
					homosexuals. This exaggerated fear is based on myths propagated by those in¬
					stitutions that help shape our lives. Homophobia is suffered by heterosexual
					and lesbian women, and is one of the major causes of division within the
					feminist movement. Lesbianism is often used as a "discipline"' on heterosexual
					women to keep them “in line"' and under control.</p>
				<p>Lesbianism will be defined here as an intimate relationship between women on
					the conscious level; elements of this intimate relationship being love,
					sensitivity, spiritual nurturing, validation of self, emotional and
					psychological growth.</p>
				<p>A bird's-eye view of the sexual socialization of women in this society shows the
					kind of input our basic institutions have in determining the norms that govern
					acceptable behavior which is not to be taken lightly by lesbian or heterosexual
					women. The family, the church and the school are the primary institutions that
					reinforce a "functional role theory"' for women and interpret women’s behavior
					as "female inferior negative"' and, for lesbians, "deviant inferior
					negative.</p>
				<p>The home is the primary foundation for socialization, and it is crucial in the
					development of sexual awareness and acceptance of one's own sex. Here children
					are exposed to the views of parents and very early internalize them as their
					own. In children's play one can hear the tapes played back by children (i.e.,
					Good little girls don’t do that"'). Play is one of the ways a child forms a
					repertoire of the dos and don’ts of the already-existing society. The child
					continues to internalize and imitate the parents' views and behavior until other
					surrogate socializers are introduced, such as baby-sitters, relatives, peer
					groups and other institutions. Elementary school educators define the goals
					that serve as a basic guideline for the school curriculum. One of the goals is
					to provide personal, social, moral, educational and vocational guidelines. The
					elementary school in this society has the responsibility of helping the six- to
					twelve-year-old learn the developmental task that goes with that age.</p>
				<p>From a sexual orientation perspective, the developmental task for age six to
					twelve is learning an appropriate sexual role. In the case of the female, sex
					roles are dictated in elementary school and many times go unchallenged as
					subtle sexist philosophies are interwoven into the curriculum. Even though most
					elementary schools are coeducational, some classroom and playground activities
					are sex-typed. A classic example: teacher to class, “1 need a strong boy to move
					a desk. Mary, would you water the plants?" Elementary school reading books con¬
					tinue to designate woman's primary role as mother-homemaker, teacher, nurse and
					volunteer service worker while defining man's role as breadwinner doctor
					lawyer shopowner and politician. While the defined roles of women mentioned are
					not any less important than those given to men, they are limited and do not lend
					themselves to women participating in the major decision-making arena of
					society.</p>
				<p>Secondary schools continue to propagate the "functional role theory" through sex
					education classes that deal only superficially with the needs of women to be
					sexually competent outside of the realm of motherhood. Undergraduate and
					graduate schools continue to operate under the "female negative inferior"'
					philosophy in the areas of faculty distribution and student admission. Ann
					Sutherland Harris, in her essay "The Second Sex in Academe," quoted President
					Nathan Pusey of Harvard, reacting to the possibility of the draft reducing male
					enrollment: "We shall be left with the blind, the lame, and the women."'
					Harris asserts that the excuse for limiting its female undergraduate
					enrollment to 25% of the total is that there is insufficient accommodation for
					women."</p>
				<p>The church has equal input into the sexual socialization of women. It asserts
					that woman, <pb n="35"/> created from the negative side of man, is responsible
					for the sins of the world and the pain of childbirth is a direct result of her
					cunning ability, intellectual inferiority and debasing nature. Consequently, she
					is constantly asking forgiveness for being a woman, being grateful for the
					inadequate space allotted her for religious administration and accepting her
					sexual inferiority as a divine act. The church through its philosophy reinforces
					the "female negative inferior"' image of women.</p>
				<p>The church, coupled with the home and the school, laid the foundation for the
					existing societal myths about women, namely lesbians, who have defined
					themselves sexually outside the norm. These myths are used as a "discipline"'
					on other women who even consider denouncing the "functional role theory" in
					ex<pb n="36"/> change for personal happiness and fulfillment. What are the
					myths about lesbians?</p>
				<list>
					<item>1. A woman is a lesbian because she possesses a natural defect. ("female
						negative inferior“')</item>
					<item>2. A lesbian is emotionally unstable, sexually frustrated, self-indulgent
						and morally degenerate. ("'deviant negative inferior')</item>
					<item>3. A lesbian is anti-revolutionary, hates men, suffers from penis envy and
						is a security risk. ("deviant negative inferior')</item>
					<item>4. A lesbian wears men's clothes, is sexually aggressive and physically
						unattractive. "deviant negative inferior''</item>
					<item>5. A lesbian is afraid of men based on her past experiences and has inner
						conflicts because she needs a man. (female negative inferior"')</item>
				</list>
				<p>These myths about lesbians make up the symptoms of homophobia, whose basic
					element is fear. This unfounded fear produces a chain of defensive reactions
					that serve to alienate women from each other thus weakening communication
					between women. Homophobia is suffered by lesbians and heterosexual women and is
					manifested in their oppressive behavior when addressing themselves to the
					lesbian lifestyle. It is not uncommon that the oppressed incorporate the
					values of the oppressor to maintain certain kinds of control. Women who
					subscribe to this behavior are said to be male-identified, in that they share
					the same views about women that men do. These women may fear a loss of sexual
					power or have unconsciously accepted the "female negative inferior"' concept
					of themselves and act it out in their relationships with other women. In the
					corporate world the male-identified woman serves as a tool for stifling economic
					growth and creativity among women. One of the concerns of the Third World
					Lesbian Feminist Movement ks the result of the socialization process that goes
					with upward mobility and its relationship to the oppressed becoming the op¬
					pressor which takes its toll on Third World esbian feminists.</p>
				<p>One of the greatest fears of the homophobic heterosexual woman is to be remotely
					connected to a lesbian in word, action or deed. To her it may mean a loss ot
					status among men, a destiny she cannot bear. It is the man who has defined her
					nature and given her a purpose in life. Homophobia serves as a defense mechan¬
					ism for she may be paranoid about admitting to her own sexual experiences as a
					child and the implications of lesbianism. Her inner conflict relating to her
					sexual self may result in a fanatical approach to heterosexuality, and she finds
					it easy to attach a moral judgment on lesbianism. The homophobic lesbian or
					heterosexual woman may doubt the political awareness and intellectual
					ability of lesbians in exchange for prevailing stereotypes. She may support
					competition as inherent in men, and limit her participation in a collective
					decision-making environment. She may also distrust the feminist movement, see
					it as counter-revolutionary, destructive, and may assist at some level in the
					attempt to sabotage the women's movement, based on fear and sexual contra¬
					dictions.</p>
				<p>Homophobia leaves a woman open to sexist manipulation, mind control, and can
					result in socioeconomic genocide for women.</p>
				<p>Some of the prevailing myths about lesbians need to be put into the proper
					perspective. The esbian suffers no more emotional stress, sexual frustration
					and inner conflict than her heterosexual sister. In fact much could be said
					about the maturity of the lesbian who relates to her sexual politics as having
					relevance outside of the "functional role theory." Third World lesbians, while
					not anti-race or counter-revolutionary, do question the role of the Third
					World woman in the revolution as it relates to the female negative inferior"'
					concept held by Third World men in the society.</p>
				<p>While some lesbians do see themselves as sexually aggressive, their behavior
					cannot be inked to the high incidence of sexual violence suffered by women and
					young girls. All lesbians are not separatist, or feminist, or unattractive,
					or suffering from penis envy, or secretly craving for a man. A lesbian may or
					may not have had a meaningful relationship with a man. She may or may not wear
					men's clothing, or drive a truck, or spit between her teeth, or live in the
					Village, or wear purple.</p>
				<p>The true lesbian sees herself no less than her male or female counterpart, but
					understands the implications of the distinct difference in the species as it
					relates to the spiritual development of the individual. One could say that the
					lesbian has turned "woman love"' inside; subsequently the content became the
					form. She receives her emotional, psychological and spiritual nurturing from
					woman, and credits her highly developed sensitivity to that energy. </p>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
