<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='93'/>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Joy Through Strength in the Bardo</l>
					<l>Sally George</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>This morning I saw a beautiful woman walking behind me. I was going to work</l>
					<l>through a neighborhood of factories and garages, tired, slumping cold and heavy</l>
					<l>inside my mouse-colored coat; my mouse-colored hair creeping greasily down my</l>
					<l>face. And a bulky man leaning drunk against a car spoke unintelligibly to the air</l>
					<l>behind me, prophesying a vision; and he spoke the truth, for I turned and there she</l>
					<l>was. She passed and we walked single-file, our paths amazingly the same through</l>
					<l>the grimy ruined streets. I watched her walk, watched the exact angle of street</l>
					<l>appear and disappear each time one leg swung past the other.</l>
					<l>The place I have worked for a month now is huge, brightly lit; a whole floor in a</l>
					<l>factory building. My boss lives there, in this one gigantic room. The kitchen is in</l>
					<l>one corner and the toilet is behind a low wall—like this morning on the street you</l>
					<l>hear events without seeing them. The place is sparsely furnished, each object care¬</l>
					<l>fully selected: stark German appliances, glass tables, a meat rack to hang coats on.</l>
					<l>he forks don’t look like forks and the knives are triangular, but they cut clean.</l>
					<l>Two others work here, and the boss leaves; I know most about the work; am I in</l>
					<l>charge? I make coffee several times; when I ask them, they join me. The slower</l>
					<l>typist reads the paper, makes mistakes, leaves early; the better one sits up straight,</l>
					<l>seldom speaks, needs nothing. No sandwiches, no jokes. She is a poet.</l>
					<l>Later, with my daughter, I go to the library and we look in the encyclopedia to</l>
					<l>learn that there are 500 species of frogs and the Pony Express began in 1860. There is</l>
					<l>a look-it-up club at school and she joined to wear their button; a man comes once a</l>
					<l>week to hear their answers. I am sure he will turn out to be an encyclopedia</l>
					<l>salesman. I am horrible to my daughter, grow impatient when she cannot find the</l>
					<l>right place in the encyclopedia; I have alphabetized too much today</l>
					<l>At home, the puppy will not eat his dinner. I have a box of cookies, my daughter</l>
					<l>has canned and frozen gook. We plan her Halloween costume. Someone calls, a</l>
					<l>woman 1 know slightly. Are you better? she says. You sounded so upset last time we</l>
					<l>talked. I’m not sure, but I think she said the same thing last time she called. Yes, l’m</l>
					<l>better, I said. l’m used to it now</l>
					<l>My work is making an index out of thousands of single cards, each with one name</l>
					<l>or fact written on it. It is like a jigsaw, like knitting, like having a baby. Every bit</l>
					<l>falls in place, and each place must be precisely right or it will be defective. We have</l>
					<l>been trying to bring it forth for two months now. It progresses, but it never gets fin¬</l>
					<l>ished. I think this all happened because I stopped reading The Castle in the middle;</l>
					<l>if I finished it we could finish the index, but I am under a spell and can do nothing.</l>
					<l>My life is promised to begin when this is over; I am to eat right and be kind to my</l>
					<l>daughter—perhaps l’Il find a lover, go to the country, or take up volleyball.</l>
					<l>After dinner I go back to work; my boss is hung over. Was it his turn to collapse</l>
					<l>though, or mine? We will miss our new deadline, he says; he means the one I</l>
					<l>thought was real. We can’t keep up this pace, he said. Him saying it means we can</l>
					<l>slow down. My saying it means l’m being difficult. He smiles when I disappoint</l>
					<l>him; perhaps he thinks l’m going to turn into an encyclopedia salesman.</l>
					<l>He walks me to the subway, we look out for rats. The drunks are gone now, it&apos;s</l>
					<l>too cold. Our index is about Hitler, these streets are not real. I live continuously in</l>
					<l>the bunker, see only the dog Blondi and the picture of Frederick the Great. There are</l>
					<l>speeches on Social Darwinism. Defeatism is severely punished in the army. When</l>
					<l>my new life starts, 1 am going to live it with great precision.</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lg>
					<l>Sally George is a writer who lives in Brooklyn. She has published short stories in Ms., Red¬</l>
					<l>book, North American Review and Christopher Street. She is presently interested in market</l>
					<l>research.</l>
					<l>Copyright O 1977 by Sally George</l>
				</lg>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
