<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='97'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_1' n='N001'/>Is lesbianism liberating for the artist? My own experi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_2' n='N002'/>ence suggests that it is. When at an early age I recognized
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_3' n='N003'/>the need to voice the poetry seething in me I observed
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_4' n='N004'/>my mother and all the women 1 knew of, living and
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_5' n='N005'/>dead, and saw that their lives were both destructive of
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_6' n='N006'/>women’s independence and dignity and inimical to the
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_7' n='N007'/>pursuit of an art. Along with this realization I was not
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_8' n='N008'/>attracted to men (though as yet not fully aware of their
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_9' n='N009'/>collective roles as oppressors). I knew nothing of a les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_10' n='N010'/>bian way of life but my own needs and observations
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_11' n='N011'/>were guiding me in that direction.
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_12' n='N012'/>When at the age of eighteen I learned of the Greek
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_13' n='N013'/>poet, Sappho, and her way of life I discovered what is
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_14' n='N014'/>now (inadequately) called &quot;a role model.&quot; Seeking out
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_15' n='N015'/>all I could of her way of life and her times I found inti¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_16' n='N016'/>mation of alternatives for women of talent and spirit not
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_17' n='N017'/>hinted at for those born where I was growing up. Not
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_18' n='N018'/>that my life could in any way resemble hers. She had
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_19' n='N019'/>every social and economic advantage. I had none.
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_20' n='N020'/>Penniless and with no formal education, no schooling
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_21' n='N021'/>after fourteen nor preparation for any sort of career, 1
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_22' n='N022'/>had to accept long hours of wage-slave menial office
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_23' n='N023'/>labor while trying to salvage space and time for creative
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_24' n='N024'/>work.
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_25' n='N025'/>Nevertheless, the sense of inner freedom, of broad-
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_26' n='N026'/>ened emotional horizons, was revelation. I could be
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_27' n='N027'/>was in my heart, though a wage-slave, an independent
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_28' n='N028'/>woman responsible to and for myself. 1 am aware that
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_29' n='N029'/>young women today, sixty years later, may not see it
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_30' n='N030'/>that way, some hoping for more freedom in marriage,
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_31' n='N031'/>others compromising with or feeling compelled to lean
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_32' n='N032'/>on welfare. But I think that any job is preferable to
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_33' n='N033'/>either spirit-cramping indignity. I wrote a poem bidding
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_34' n='N034'/>farewell to the socially prescribed roles and in it was the
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_35' n='N035'/>line, &quot;The wide world is to know.&quot; Security (how false is
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_36' n='N036'/>usually that promise) was scorned; the sense of adven¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_37' n='N037'/>ture predominant. However brash it may seem, 1 feel
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_38' n='N038'/>that this sense of adventure is necessary to the artist.
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_39' n='N039'/>Adventure always has been assumed to be the prerog-
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_40' n='N040'/>ative of men. On the other hand the life of housewife¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_41' n='N041'/>mother is totally mapped. You can see to the end of it in
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_42' n='N042'/>middle age, menopause, loneliness. The role of non¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_43' n='N043'/>heterosexual artist (in my case, poet) in the early twen¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_44' n='N044'/>ties was unexplored territory. You launched yourself
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_45' n='N045'/>into the unknown. Who can say that is not exhilarating?
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_46' n='N046'/>It did not occur to me that there could be any greater
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_47' n='N047'/>difficulties attached to my preference for women as
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_48' n='N048'/>lovers than I already faced. The economic and educa¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_49' n='N049'/>tional lack of advantages aside, I was already at a dis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_50' n='N050'/>advantage as a woman daring what was (still is) regarded
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_51' n='N051'/>as a male world. Being an aspiring poet compounded it:
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_1_1' n='N001'/>LESBIANISM AS A LIBERATING FORCE
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_2_1' n='N002'/>ELSA GIDLOW
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_1_2' n='N001'/>even male poets were expected to starve in garrets. Al¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_2_2' n='N002'/>ready critical of the whole course of bourgeois society
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_3_1' n='N003'/>and its inequities, I did not fit in on that level either¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_4_1' n='N004'/>nor do I wish to. Being lesbian could not make me more
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_5_1' n='N005'/>of an outsider. As the saying goes, &quot;You may as well be
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_6_1' n='N006'/>hung for a sheep as a lamb.&quot; Whatever the hazards, the
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_7_1' n='N007'/>attendant liberation from conformity was stimulating,
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_8_1' n='N008'/>compelling one to think for oneself
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_9_1' n='N009'/>If I was little inclined to consider the aloneness ahead,
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_10_1' n='N010'/>the heartache and hardship, that soon became plain.
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_11_1' n='N011'/>There was no supporting feminist movement. I hoped to
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_12_1' n='N012'/>find comrades on the way, what I called “my people”;
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_13_1' n='N013'/>but it was taking a long time. I have had other women
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_14_1' n='N014'/>today say, &quot;You had your gift, your art.&quot; Yes. That was
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_15_1' n='N015'/>what I lived for, in the face of every setback. But having
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_16_1' n='N016'/>talent is not unique. I believe that creativity is inherent
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_17_1' n='N017'/>in all humans as is the impulse in plants and trees to pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_18_1' n='N018'/>duce blossoms and fruit according to their kind and that
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_19_1' n='N019'/>it is a necessary concomitant of growth.
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_20_1' n='N020'/>Generally, the domestic way is not compatible with
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_21_1' n='N021'/>the way of the artist. Nor, as a rule, with other spiritual
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_22_1' n='N022'/>and intellectual dedications. Can it be coincidental that
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_23_1' n='N023'/>most priesthoods, East and West, have called for celiba¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_24_1' n='N024'/>cy? Sappho wrote: &quot;I am forever virgin.” And let us
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_25_1' n='N025'/>never forget that &quot;virgin&quot; in the original definition
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_26_1' n='N026'/>meant, not absence of erotic experience, but independ¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_27_1' n='N027'/>ence. For women, independence from men and marriage
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_28_1' n='N028'/>hence domesticity. (A virgin forest is an unexploited
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_29_1' n='N029'/>one.) Even the Virgin Mary in the Catholic church is not
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_30_1' n='N030'/>depicted as domestic. She has a priestly role. As does
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_31_1' n='N031'/>every artist.
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_32_1' n='N032'/>Does it become plain why lesbianism is liberating for
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_33_1' n='N033'/>the woman, for the artist in her? Or for those women
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_34_1' n='N034'/>born with or who cultivate what I call a lesbian person¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_35_1' n='N035'/>ality? As I see it, that personality manifests itself in inde¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_36_1' n='N036'/>pendence of spirit, in willingness to take responsibility
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_37_1' n='N037'/>for oneself, to think for oneself, not to take &quot;authorities
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_38_1' n='N038'/>and their dictum on trust. It usually includes erotic
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_39_1' n='N039'/>attraction to women, although we know there have
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_40_1' n='N040'/>been many women of lesbian personality who never had
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_41_1' n='N041'/>sexual relations with one another. Even where an erotic
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_42_1' n='N042'/>relationship exists the sensually sexual may be far from
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_43_1' n='N043'/>predominant. What is strongly a part of the lesbian per¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_44_1' n='N044'/>sonality is loyalty to and love of other women. And
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_45_1' n='N045'/>every lesbian personality I have knowledge of is in some
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_46_1' n='N046'/>way creative. To my mind this is because she is freed or
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_47_1' n='N047'/>has freed herself from the external and internal domin¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_48_1' n='N048'/>ance of the male and so ignored or rejected (usually
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_49_1' n='N049'/>male prescribed) social assumptions that the constella¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_50_1' n='N050'/>tion of domestic functions are peculiarly hers. The im¬
				<lb facs='#facs_97_region_1675015138849_1609_tl_51_1' n='N051'/>portant point is that the lesbian has sought wholeness
			</p>
			<pb n='98'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_1' n='N001'/>within herself, not requiring, in the old romantic sense,
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_2' n='N002'/>to be completed&quot; by an opposite.
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_3' n='N003'/>I do not wish to imply that a woman who is drawn to
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_4' n='N004'/>men, or who feels she loves a man, may not work to
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_5' n='N005'/>achieve these freedoms. But the men who will tolerate
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_6' n='N006'/>real autonomy in a woman partner, in whatever capac-
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_7' n='N007'/>ity, are so rare that I for one am skeptical of the possibil¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_8' n='N008'/>ity. It is a hard realization that a woman’s need to love
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_9' n='N009'/>and be loved, to cherish and be cherished, may become
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_10' n='N010'/>her most painful hurdle—a bar to self-realization.
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_11' n='N011'/>This pertains politically as well as personally. Despite
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_12' n='N012'/>the insights of some of our currently espoused ideologies
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_13' n='N013'/>and the (mainly expedient or token) gains for women as
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_14' n='N014'/>a result of their application, I know of no ideology that
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_15' n='N015'/>convinces me of the likelihood of women being rendered
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_16' n='N016'/>justice through a change of state master. The energies,
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_17' n='N017'/>skills and intelligence of women have been recognized
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_18' n='N018'/>and utilized within the several socialist countries more
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_19' n='N019'/>equitably on the whole than in the capitalist vocational
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_20' n='N020'/>arenas. But if unemployment looms, will women be
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_21' n='N021'/>rationalized back into &quot;the home”? And what of our les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_22' n='N022'/>bian personalities, even today, in the socialist states?
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_23' n='N023'/>I should like to be convinced to the contrary, but can
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_24' n='N024'/>anyone tell me of an existing male-birthed political sys¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_25' n='N025'/>tem that would grant to a woman of lesbian tempera¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_26' n='N026'/>ment the uncontested right to freely live and love as
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_27' n='N027'/>required by her needs and nature? To create her art,
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_28' n='N028'/>write her poetry or voice her views in accordance with
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_29' n='N029'/>her vision of a society compatible with women’s growth
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_30' n='N030'/>and flowering as women? I find it hard to give allegiance
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_31' n='N031'/>to the hope that this will happen in any society that
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_32' n='N032'/>requires acquiescence as a cog in a state machine, one
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_33' n='N033'/>whose practical daily politics is exerted to attain the pre¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_34' n='N034'/>dominance of that state over other states—the tradition¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_35' n='N035'/>al, seemingly ineradicable male competitive stance. The
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_36' n='N036'/>means always determine the ends. No state power ever
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_37' n='N037'/>has acquiesced in its own withering away nor does any
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_38' n='N038'/>today show signs of being likely to.
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_39' n='N039'/>Throughout my life I have defended the right to revolt
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_40' n='N040'/>against injustice. I have specifically defended the right
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_41' n='N041'/>of the Soviet peoples, the Cuban people, the people of
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_42' n='N042'/>China—all greatly to be admired despite reservations¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_43' n='N043'/>to have the kind of society suitable to their needs and
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_44' n='N044'/>development. In the fifties I was called before the Cali¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_45' n='N045'/>fornia Un-American Activities Committee, known as the
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_46' n='N046'/>Tenney Committee, and put on “trial&quot; in the town
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_47' n='N047'/>where I lived for my views and political activities. I was
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_48' n='N048'/>accused of being “communist, which I was not. But one
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_49' n='N049'/>cannot expect tunnel vision bigots to differentiate
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_50' n='N050'/>between, say, Marxism and something resembling
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_51' n='N051'/>philosophical anarchism. Since I earned my living as a
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_1_1' n='N001'/>free-lance writer and journalist I could not be deprived
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_2_1' n='N002'/>of a job by the publicity; but I did lose magazines that
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_3_1' n='N003'/>had been regularly accepting my work.
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_4_1' n='N004'/>I am not blind to the dilemma my sort of radicalism
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_5_1' n='N005'/>poses. I have thought about it lifelong and have no
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_6_1' n='N006'/>answers, only increasing numbers of questions. Perhaps
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_7_1' n='N007'/>the artist, the lesbian artist in particular, always will
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_8_1' n='N008'/>have to survive within the interstices of the chicaneries
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_9_1' n='N009'/>and despotism of any power structure. But being more
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_10_1' n='N010'/>hopeful than that, as 1 am, can we as women, as les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_11_1' n='N011'/>bians, as artists, clearly delineate in our own minds
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_12_1' n='N012'/>what sort of a society we would like to live in? Any
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_13_1' n='N013'/>number of questions and tentative formulations should
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_14_1' n='N014'/>be advanced before we become arbitrary in our politics
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_15_1' n='N015'/>or suggest a course for women and the women’s move¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_16_1' n='N016'/>ment. In the meantime, can we at least agree not to give
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_17_1' n='N017'/>our energies or allegiance, to any ideology, movement,
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_18_1' n='N018'/>or existing society that is not demonstrating unequivo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_19_1' n='N019'/>cally its rejection of residues of discrimination against
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_20_1' n='N020'/>women?
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_21_1' n='N021'/>I should like to end by proposing for meditation a
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_22_1' n='N022'/>brief comment by Mary Wollstonecraft made in an
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_23_1' n='N023'/>appendix to a collection of her letters written in the
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_24_1' n='N024'/>summer of 1796 during her travels in Sweden, Norway
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_25_1' n='N025'/>and Denmark. She had personally witnessed in Paris
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_26_1' n='N026'/>some of the excesses and horrors of the French Revolu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_27_1' n='N027'/>tion, which nevertheless she espoused. The time in
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_28_1' n='N028'/>which she lived and wrote was no less disruptive of
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_29_1' n='N029'/>settled ways and views than ours today; and she had
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_30_1' n='N030'/>fearlessly exposed herself to their full tide. Burning radi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_31_1' n='N031'/>cal where the eradication of human, especially women’s,
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_32_1' n='N032'/>miseries and oppression were concerned, she wrote
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_33_1' n='N033'/>these considered words two years before her death:
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_34_1' n='N034'/>&quot;An ardent affection for the human race makes enthusi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_35_1' n='N035'/>astic characters eager to produce alteration in laws and
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_36_1' n='N036'/>governments prematurely. To render them useful and
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_37_1' n='N037'/>permanent, they must be the growth of each particular
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_38_1' n='N038'/>soil, and the gradual fruit of the ripening understanding
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_39_1' n='N039'/>of the nation, matured by time, not forced by an un¬
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_40_1' n='N040'/>natural fermentation.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_1_2' n='N001'/>Elsa Gidlow is a poet who has made her living most of her life
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_2_2' n='N002'/>as a journalist. Her latest book SAPPHIC SONGS, Seventeen
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_3_2' n='N003'/>to Seventy, (Diana Press) includes recent work and lesbian
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_4_2' n='N004'/>love poems from her book On a Grey Thread, first published
				<lb facs='#facs_98_region_1675015161615_1621_tl_5_2' n='N005'/>in 1923.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
