<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Issue15_EditorialStatement</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>Issue 15 Editorial Collective: Vivian E. Browne, Cynthia Carr, Michele
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>Godwin, Hattie Gossett, Carole Gregory, Sue Heinemann, Lucy R. Lippard,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>May Stevens, Cecilia Vicuna, Sylvia Witts Vitale.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>ISSUE 15 EDITORIAL STATEMENT
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>(From Taped Conversation, October 21, 1982)
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>So what&apos;s the point of a collective statement? What do we want it to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>say? (S.H.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>Well, it&apos;s not an individual statement. What I could do with another
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>Black woman is totally different from what I can say in a collective state¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>ment. (S.W.V.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>The point of this is what we say to each other. Let&apos;s talk about what
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>were our expectations when we joined the group. (M.S.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>When I arrived from Boston the Heresies Collective was working on the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>Third World Women&apos;s issue. That was apparently a very difficult issue and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>the word that got back to me from Black feminists was the Heresies Collec¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>tive is a group of racist white women.... Then I read some of the issues and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>articles and I really liked the material. I had an article in the next issue,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>and decided to come to a meeting for this one. I was really happy to see so
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>many different women. I know a lot of people from different countries, but
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>this was a chance to focus on women. This was so different. We put in so
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>much hard work. We tried to be so fair and listened to each other&apos;s experi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>ences. Yet I am still shocked at the way white American women discuss
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>racism. So many of the manuscripts we got talked about white women and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>sex with Black men. Sexual contact was always the starting point, which is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>not how I see racism at all. If we&apos;re talking about feminism, we&apos;re talking
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>about women, so they&apos;re only interacting with me, a Black woman, through
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>their sexual image of Black men. Perhaps this is one major barrier. I don&apos;t
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>think about white men at all when I think about white women. Fortunately
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>nobody here in the collective did that; it was just in the manuscripts. (C.G.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>Part of the experience is the way the women in this collective looked at
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>that material and reacted to it. (S.H.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>Yeah, we were OK. (C.G.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>It wasn’t nearly as bad as I thought it would be, based on the stories I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>had heard from other women of color about working with &quot;those racist
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>white girls at Heresies.&quot; Not that both white girls and colored girls don&apos;t
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>have a lot of learning and growing to do. (H.G.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>Being on the racism issue—it was an experience. Hearing these people
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>argue about something that&apos;s so important when you usually don&apos;t hear
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>about it. You may read about it, but you usually don&apos;t hear other people
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>talking about it, unless you bring it up. (M.G.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>Carole, you say now you can talk to white women? (V.B.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>Not in general, only the women in this collective. (C.G.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l38' n='N038'/>So you felt some need to make some kind of contact? Was it satisfied?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l39' n='N039'/>(V.B.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l40' n='N040'/>I don&apos;t really like to make contact with white people. (C.G.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l41' n='N041'/>But you came here. (V.B.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l42' n='N042'/>I didn&apos;t see the racism issue as just white people, but many women com¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l43' n='N043'/>ing from many backgrounds to discuss the subject. Like at work you can not
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l44' n='N044'/>discuss racism with white people. (C.G.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l45' n='N045'/>Has this experience changed your approach to white people? Affected
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l46' n='N046'/>your attitudes in any way? (V.B.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l47' n='N047'/>That&apos;s hard to answer. I don&apos;t want to dismiss our work.... We needed
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l48' n='N048'/>to form a study group to define racism. Then, we would have had a common
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l49' n='N049'/>language. I felt that one of the stories we published is a racist piece. To
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l50' n='N050'/>refer to the West Indies as &quot;bush&quot; and to quote a Harlemite expressing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l51' n='N051'/>hatred of whites are negative symbols about Black people. The Nigerian
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l52' n='N052'/>author, Chinua Achebe, has asked white authors to refrain from creating
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l53' n='N053'/>more works like Conrad&apos;s &quot;Heart of Darkness&quot; in which Africans are de¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l54' n='N054'/>graded. However, no one agreed with my interpretation of the piece. Had I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l55' n='N055'/>not solicited manuscripts from Alice Walker and other women, I would
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l56' n='N056'/>have resigned from this collective on racism. Unconscious and conscious
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l57' n='N057'/>racist imagery hurts. (C.G.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l58' n='N058'/>This short-term process might not produce anything. I see that in the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l59' n='N059'/>classrooms when I talk about racism.... You might see a little bit of open¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l60' n='N060'/>ing up. (S.W. V.)
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>Heresies: A Feminist Publication on Art &amp; Politics is published Winter,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>Spring, Summer and Fall by Heresies Collective, Inc. 225 Lafayette Street,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>New York, NY 10012. Subscription rates: 515 for four issues; 324 for insti¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>tutions. Outside the U.S. and Canada, add §2 postage. Single copies: 85
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>each (current issue), 56 (back issues). Address all correspondence to:
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>Heresies, PO Box 766, Canal Street Station, New York, NY 10013.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>Heresies, ISSN 0145-3411. Vol. 4, No. 3, Issue 15.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>O1982, Heresies Collective, Inc. All rights reserved.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>Cover drawing by Michele Godwin.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>A little bit of opening up is a miracle. (M.S.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>Here you had the Civil Rights Movement, you are always aware of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>years of struggle between Black and white. But in Latin America, particu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>larly in Chile where I come from, racism is simply not discussed. So I had
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>never had the opportunity to think about racism in relation to my own ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>perience. It was a fantastic thing to think in those terms with Black and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>white women. My experience in this capital of the world is that whatever
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>art my Latin friends do, it&apos;s ignored by the mainstream. It does not exist, or
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>it&apos;s &quot;ethnic.&quot; Which is why I got out the issue of ethnocentrism. And I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>realized nobody in this collective shared this thing with me. I was disap¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>pointed that everybody said this issue is about racism and nobody was will¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l12' n='N012'/>ing to go to a more general, a more cultural and ideological issue. Nobody
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l13' n='N013'/>was willing to go from the emotional level of personal experiences about
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l14' n='N014'/>racism to the more philosophical level.... So I adapted! (C.V.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l15' n='N015'/>I remember those early meetings being very exciting, when there were
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l16' n='N016'/>Asian and other Latin women in the group too. A new experience for me
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l17' n='N017'/>too. Before that I had worked on racism in a group of all-white feminists. I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l18' n='N018'/>think I was afraid, at first, of working with women of color on this issue but
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l19' n='N019'/>I decided I wanted to do it anyway. Afraid, I guess, that l&apos;d unpeel new
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l20' n='N020'/>horrible layers of my own racism. Instead this was a really wonderful ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l21' n='N021'/>perience. I think I&apos;ve become much more aware of racism.... There are
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l22' n='N022'/>shortcomings in the issue, like the lack of input from Native American wom¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l23' n='N023'/>en, but in general l&apos;m proud of it. If racism is going to change, white people
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l24' n='N024'/>will have to do something to make it change. I think what we did here will
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l25' n='N025'/>be a tool for that change. What I discovered was just that simple step—that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l26' n='N026'/>you don&apos;t just say, &quot;Oh it&apos;s all so horrible,&quot; but that you can do something
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l27' n='N027'/>about it. (C.C.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l28' n='N028'/>Me too. Another thing I got out of the whole process was a deepened
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l29' n='N029'/>sense of the complexity of racism in the U.S., how it&apos;s affected by elements
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l30' n='N030'/>of class, education, degree of color, all that. And the intense ambivalence
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l31' n='N031'/>even the most positive women of color have toward the kind of work we&apos;ve
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l32' n='N032'/>been doing, and the psychological and historical roots of that ambivalence.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l33' n='N033'/>(L.R.L.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l34' n='N034'/>Working together you see how people feel and see. A lot of times white
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l35' n='N035'/>people aren’t aware that we’re being racist. We don’t really understand
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l36' n='N036'/>how it&apos;s understood. A lot of the racism that goes on is unintentional, un¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l37' n='N037'/>conscious. It&apos;s really important to work together to undo that... Misunder¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l38' n='N038'/>standing only gets corrected when there&apos;s a chance to understand. (S.H.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l39' n='N039'/>I&apos;ve had white women—friends—try to talk to me about racism and tell
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l40' n='N040'/>me they just don’t know what to say about racism because they&apos;re not in¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l41' n='N041'/>volved. Ijust couldn&apos;t believe that. The problem doesn&apos;t exist. (V.B.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l42' n='N042'/>That&apos;s what I meant about Latin America. People are very ready to dis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l43' n='N043'/>cuss class struggle because class struggle is a term that comes from Euro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l44' n='N044'/>pean culture that everybody shares, so this is OK. But to go beyond that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l45' n='N045'/>conception or even discuss the implications—like racism—it&apos;s awkward.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l46' n='N046'/>The subject of the Indians in Chile was usually treated as a problem of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l47' n='N047'/>class struggle, not a cultural or religious difference. We have to question to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l48' n='N048'/>what extent we&apos;ve been conditioned by all this miseducation we&apos;ve re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l49' n='N049'/>ceived. I worried about the narrowness of the experiences that were sub¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l50' n='N050'/>mitted. Most of the articles in this issue are individualized, separated ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l51' n='N051'/>periences—I felt this, you felt that.&quot; But we also have to put together our
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l52' n='N052'/>own experiences of racism with what&apos;s going on in the world, to reach a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l53' n='N053'/>more general concept of global racism. It&apos;s the American situation. If this
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l54' n='N054'/>collective were in Latin America, we would have arrived at a totally differ¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l55' n='N055'/>ent conclusion because we are marginal. We&apos;re always aware of the global
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l56' n='N056'/>situation because we have to be. (C.V.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l57' n='N057'/>This issue of Heresies is on the situation of racism in the U.S. today. It
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l58' n='N058'/>represents who we are and what we&apos;re concerned with, and how far we
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l59' n='N059'/>could go. (M.S.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l60' n='N060'/>We do need to put discussion on an intellectual plane at some point, but
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l61' n='N061'/>I do not necessarily agree that the word &apos;ethnocentrism&quot; for this country is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l62' n='N062'/>on an intellectual plane. Istill insist that for us here that&apos;s a cop-out. When
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l63' n='N063'/>you say how you are not chosen by the art world because it centers on
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l64' n='N064'/>here, that puts another meaning on ethnocentrism which has nothing&apos;to do
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l65' n='N065'/>with racism. It does have to do with peripheral vision. I insist on calling
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l66' n='N066'/>racism racism, a spade a spade (laughter). That&apos;s what it is and you cannot
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l67' n='N067'/>take it and water it down. I&apos;m not saying that your relation to the word is a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l68' n='N068'/>watering down for you, but this country has gone through so much shit, and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l69' n='N069'/>to come up with another name on top of the shit is to say it did not happen to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l70' n='N070'/>us. All these personal little things make up this country. (V.B.)
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l71' n='N071'/>(continued on inside back cover)
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>(continued from inside front cover)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>The legacy of U. S. slavery is racism. The Civil Rights Movement changed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>some of that racist history. I didn&apos;t feel powerless and I didn&apos;t give up. (C.G.)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>Iuse ethnocentrism to include racism and all bigotry. The basis as I see
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>it—and this is a very deep psychological thing—is I and my kind are su¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>perior.&quot; (M.S.)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>Ethnocentrism starts to sound like the umbrella and underneath it is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>racism and bigotry. When I hear it, feel it, experience it, it&apos;s racism. But
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>I&apos;m glad you were part of the collective so we could get your perspective on
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>the word. It&apos;s different. I was so anti the word ethnocentrism.&quot;...I&apos;m
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>sorry we could not get more into racism and anti-Semitism—the Black/
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>Jewish conflict—because it&apos;s about to explode again. I didn&apos;t have the cour¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>age to do it because I&apos;d get fired up, can’t take no more. Maybe sometimes
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>it&apos;s too close. You know, having a mother named Elizabeth Cohen and what¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>ever she went through with black skin.... (S.W.V.)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>Most of the material is by U.S. Black women or white women; there isn&apos;t
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>much from an identifiable Lesbian perspective. It&apos;s hard to say why. Flyers
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>were mailed to many groups and individuals around the world; various
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>racial and work-related and sexual-preference grapevines were utilized.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>This final working collective included Latina, Black and white. Two of us
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>are Lesbians and the others are hets. All seemed to know a wide range of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>women and were committed to involving them in working on the issue and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>bringing in material reflective of a wide range of women&apos;s experiences.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>Still, there are many voices that should be here that aren&apos;t. This is not an
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>apology or an excuse, just a statement of fact and concern. I guess it&apos;s also
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>reflective of where women are right now. The problem of broadening the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>participation in the women&apos;s movement is very real and will not be solved in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>any single or simple manner. (H.G.)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>Since racism comes up everywhere, every day, in all kinds of situations,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>Ican conceive of this body of literature being used and discussed by every¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>one, everywhere. Teachers can use it as a discussion-stimulator or as the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>basis for written assignments. My past experience has shown me how
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>white folks do not like to feel uncomfortable about racism so they change
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>the topic. I don’t want it changed. I want folks to deal with it. Discuss it.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>Understand it. I would hate to see racism pushed aside as a side issue. It is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>not. In government, schools, work, play, entertainment, racism is preva¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>lent. I also do not want white folks to run away from the issue screaming
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>about how they heard enough about this already so let&apos;s move on to more
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>relevant things.&quot; Now, what gets me about some of my Black folks is how
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>they can say things like: &quot;Look, I&apos;m tired of dealing with this racism stuff.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>That&apos;s the white girl&apos;s problem. Let her deal with it.&quot; Or the ones who say:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>&quot;Ican do anything I want to do. I don&apos;t let racism hang me up. That&apos;s what&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>wrong with Black people today, they always.... Both of these Black ap
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>proaches are as bad as their white counterparts.... On the whole, I would
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>say that working with this mixture of women&apos;s cultures proved to be very
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>positive for me. It restored my initial good feeling about the women&apos;s move¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>ment and the need to collaborate, network and dialogue. We were able to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>get through what could be labeled as very controversial topics without kill¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l49' n='N049'/>ing anyone, calling names or just being downright disrespectful. I was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l50' n='N050'/>pleased. I&apos;ve been in groups that have done the former. That we didn&apos;t says
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l51' n='N051'/>something real mature about us. ... Of course, I work with integrated
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l52' n='N052'/>groups all the time, but I usually get paid for it. (S.W.V.)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l53' n='N053'/>This time you get glory! (M.S.)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l54' n='N054'/>What are your reactions to this issue? Do you have additional ideas? We&apos;d like visu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l55' n='N055'/>al and verbal responses to publish in a new &quot;opinion&quot; section, starting with Issue 17.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l56' n='N056'/>This issue was typeset by Myrna Zimmerman, with display type by Talbot; printed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l57' n='N057'/>by Capital City Press, Montpelier, Vt.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l58' n='N058'/>Special thanks to the following women who participated in the Issue 15 Editorial Col¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l59' n='N059'/>lective through most of our deliberations: Yvonne Flowers, Ana Mendieta, Lorraine
				<lb facs='#facs_2_line_1666299708297_70' n='N060'/>O&apos;Grady, Angela Salgado. Thanks also to all the women who came to our early meet-
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_line_1666299717558_76' n='N001'/>ings and fed us with ideas. Finally, thanks to the women who helped in various 
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_line_1666299724619_82' n='N001'/>stages of production: Linda Cunningham, Sandra De Sando, Abigail Esman, Vana-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_line_1666299728567_85' n='N002'/>lyne Green, Patricia Jones, Kay Kenny, Adrienne Weiss.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>We deeply regret the death of Theresa Hak Kyung Cha, who was attacked and killed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>on a street near her apartment in lower Manhattan on Friday, November 5, 1982, in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>the early evening. Theresa&apos;s work appears in Heresies No. 14: The Women&apos;s Pages.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>Her recently published book Dictee is available from Tanam Press, 40 White Street,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>NY, NY 10013.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
