<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>King_issue13_12-26</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: hmb010@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>The problem with both analyses, however, is that gender
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>identity is neither fully natural nor fully cultural. And it is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>neither inherently oppressive nor inherently liberating. It
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>depends on other historical factors, and how we consciously
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>understand woman-identification and feminism.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>Socialist Feminism and Ecology: 4 Socialist feminists have for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>the most part yet to enter feminist debates on &quot;the ecology
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>question.&quot; They tend to be uneasy with ecological feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>fearing that it is based on an ahistorical, anti-rational woman/
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>nature identification; or they see the cultural emphasis in eco¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>logical feminism as &quot;idealist&quot; rather than &quot;materialist.&quot; The
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>Marxist side of their politics implies a primacy of material
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>transformation (economic/structural transformation precedes
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>changes in ideas/culture/consciousness). Cultural and material
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>changes are not completely separate. There is a dialectical
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>interaction between the two, but in the last instance the cul¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>tural is part of the superstructure and the material is the base.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>Historically socialism and feminism have had a curious
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>courtships and a rather unhappy marriage,° characterized by
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>a tug of war over which is the primary contradiction-sex or
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>class. In an uneasy truce, socialist feminists try to overcome
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>the contradictions, to show how the economic structure and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>the sex-gender system’ are mutually reinforced in historically
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>specific ways depending on material conditions, and to show
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>their interdependence. They suggest the need for an &quot;auto¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>nomous&quot; (as opposed to a &quot;separatist&quot;&apos;) women&apos;s movement,
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>to maintain vigilance over women’s concerns within the pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>duction and politics of a mixed society. They see patriarchy
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>as different under feudalism, capitalism and even under social¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>ism without feminism.s And they hold that nobody is free
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>until everybody is free.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>Socialist feminists see themselves as integrating the best of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>Marxism and radical feminism. They have been weak on radi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>cal cultural critique and strong on helping us to understand
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>how people’s material situations condition their conscious¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>nesses and their possibilities for social transformation. But
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>adherence to Marxism with its economic orientation means
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l12' n='N012'/>opting for the rationalist severance of the woman/nature
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l13' n='N013'/>connection and advocating the integration of women into
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l14' n='N014'/>production. It does not challenge the culture-versus-nature
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_5_1l15' n='N015'/>formulation itself. Even where the issue of woman&apos;s oppres¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>sion and its identification with that of nature has been taken
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>up, the socialist feminist solution has been to align women
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>with culture in culture’s ongoing struggle with nature.9
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>Here We Go Again, This Argument Is at Least 100 Years Old!
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>The radical feminist/socialist feminist debate does sometimes
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>seem to be the romantic feminist/rationalist feminist debate of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>the late 19th century revisited. 10 We can imagine 19th-cen¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>tury women watching the development of robber-baron capi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>talism, &quot;the demise of morality&quot; and the rise of the liberal
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>state which furthered capitalist interests while touting liberty
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>equality and fraternity. Small wonder that they saw in the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>domestic sphere vestiges of a more ethical way of life, and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>thought its values could be carried into the public sphere.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>This perspective romanticized women, although it is easy to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>sympathize with it and share the abhorrence of the pillage and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>plunder imposed by the masculinist mentality in modern
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>industrial society. But what 19th-century women proclaiming
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>the virtues of womanhood did not understand was that they
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>were a repository of organic social values in an increasingly
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>inorganic world. Women placed in male-identified power
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>positions can be as warlike as men. The assimilation or neutral¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>ization of enfranchised women into the American political
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>structure has a sad history.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>Rationalist feminists in the 19th century, on the other hand,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>were concerned with acquiring power and representing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>women’s interests. They opposed anything that reinforced the
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l1' n='N001'/>idea that women were “different&quot; and wanted male preroga¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l2' n='N002'/>tives extended to women. They were contemptuous of roman¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l3' n='N003'/>tic feminists and were themselves imbued with the modern
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l4' n='N004'/>ethic of Progress. They opposed political activity by women
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l5' n='N005'/>over issues not seen as exclusively feminist for the same rea¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l6' n='N006'/>sons rationalist radical feminists today oppose the feminism/
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l7' n='N007'/>ecology connection.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l8' n='N008'/>The Dialectic of Modern Feminism: According to the false
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l9' n='N009'/>dichotomy between subjective and objective-one legacy of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l10' n='N010'/>male Western philosophy to feminist thought-we must root
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l11' n='N011'/>our movement either in a rationalist-materialist humanism
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l12' n='N012'/>or in a metaphysical-feminist naturalism. This supposed choice
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l13' n='N013'/>is crucial as we approach the ecology issue. Either we take the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l14' n='N014'/>anthropocentric position that nature exists solely to serve the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_6_1l15' n='N015'/>13
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>needs of the male bourgeois who has crawled out of the slime
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>to be lord and master of everything, or we take the naturalist
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>position that nature has a purpose of its own apart from ser¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>ving &quot;man.&quot; We are either concerned with the &quot;environment
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>because we are dependent on it, or we understand ourselves
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>to be of it, with human oppression part and parcel of the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>domination of nature. For some radical feminists, only women
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>are capable of full consciousness.! Socialist feminists tend to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>consider the naturalist position as historically regressive, anti¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>rational and probably fascistic. This is the crux of the anthro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>pocentric/naturalist debate, which is emotionally loaded for
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>both sides, but especially for those who equate progress and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>rationality.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>However, we do not have to make such choices. Feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>is both the product and potentially the negation of the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>modern rationalist world view and capitalism. There was one
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>benefit for women in the &quot;disenchantment of the world,&quot;12
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>the process by which all magical and spiritual beliefs were
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>denigrated as superstitious nonsense and the death of nature
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>was accomplished in the minds of men.13 This process tore
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>asunder women’s traditional sphere of influence, but it also
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>undermined the ideology of &quot;natural&quot;&apos; social roles, opening a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>space for women to question what was &quot;natural&quot; for them to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>be and to do. In traditional Western societies, social and eco¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>nomic relationships were connected to a land-based way of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>life. One was assigned a special role based on one&apos;s sex, race,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>class and place of birth. In the domestic sphere children were
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>socialized, food prepared and men sheltered from their public
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>cares. But the 19th-century &quot;home&quot; also encompassed the pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>duction of what people ate, used and wore. It included much
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>more of human life and filled many more human needs than
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>its modern corollary-the nuclear family-which purchases
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>commodities to meet its needs. The importance of the domes¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>tic sphere, and hence women’s influence, declined with the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>advent of market society.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>Feminism also negates capitalist social relations by chal¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>lenging the lopsided male-biased values of our culture. When
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>coupled with an ecological perspective, it insists that we
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>remember our origins in nature, our connections to one
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>another as daughters, sisters and mothers. It refuses any longer
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>to be the unwitting powerless symbol of all the things men
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>wish to deny in themselves and project onto us-the refusal to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>be the “other.”14 It can heal the splits in a world divided
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>against itself and built on a fundamental lie: the defining of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>culture in opposition to nature.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>The dialectic moves on. Now it is possible that a conscious
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>visionary feminism could place our technology and productive
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>apparatus in the service of a society based on ecological princi¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>ples and values, with roots in traditional women&apos;s ways of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>being in the world. This in turn might make possible a total
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>cultural critique. Women can remember what men have denied
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>in themselves (nature), and women can know what men know
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>(culture). Now we must develop a transformative feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>that sparks our utopian imaginations and embodies our
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>deepest knowledge-a feminism that is an affirmation of our
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>vision at the same time it is a negation of patriarchy. The
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>skewed reasoning that opposes matter and spirit and refuses to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>concern itself with the objects and ends of life, which views
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>internal nature and external nature as one big hunting ground
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>to be quantified and conquered is, in the end, not only irra¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>tional but deadly. To fulfill its liberatory potential, feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>needs to pose a rational reenchantment that brings together
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>spiritual and material, being and knowing. This is the promise
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>of ecological feminism.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>Dialectical Feminism: Transcending the Radical Feminist/
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>Socialist Feminist Debate: The domination of external nature
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>has necessitated the domination of internal nature. Men have
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>denied their own embodied naturalness, repressed memories
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>of infantile pleasure and dependence on the mother and on
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>nature.1s Much of their denied self has been projected onto
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>women. Objectification is forgetting. The ways in which
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>women have been both included in and excluded from a cul¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>ture based on gender differences provide a critical ledge from
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>which to view the artificial chasm male culture has placed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>between itself and nature. Woman has stood with one foot on
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>each side. She has been a bridge for men, back to the parts of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>themselves they have denied, despite their need of women to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>attend to the visceral chores they consider beneath them.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>An ecological perspective offers the possibility of moving
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>beyond the radical (cultural) feminist/socialist feminist im¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>passe. But it necessitates a feminism that holds out for a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>separate cultural and political activity so that we can imagine,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>theorize or envision from the vantage point of critical other¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>ness. The ecology question weights the historic feminist debate
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>in the direction of traditional female values over the overly
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>rationalized, combative male way of being in the world.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>Rationalist feminism is the Trojan horse of the women&apos;s move¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>ment. Its piece-of-the-action mentality conceals a capitulation
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>to a culture bent on the betrayal of nature. In that sense it is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>unwittingly both misogynist and anti-ecological. Denying bio¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>logy, espousing androgyny and valuing what men have done
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l12' n='N012'/>over what we have done are all forms of self-hatred which
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l13' n='N013'/>threaten to derail the teleology of the feminist challenge to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l14' n='N014'/>this violent civilization.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_5_1l15' n='N015'/>The liberation of women is to be found neither in severing
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_6_1l1' n='N001'/>14
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l1' n='N001'/>This content downloaded from
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l2' n='N002'/>134.82.70.63 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:18:00 UTC
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_7_1l3' n='N003'/>All use subject to https: //about.jstor.org/terms
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>all connections that root us in nature nor in believing ourselves
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>to be more natural than men. Both of these positions are
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>unwittingly complicit with nature/culture dualism. Women&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>oppression is neither strictly historical nor strictly biological.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>It is both. Gender is a meaningful part of a person&apos;s identity.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>The facts of internal and external genitalia and women&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>ability to bear children will continue to have social meaning.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>But we needn’t think the choices are external sexual warfare
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>or a denatured (and boring) androgyny. It is possible to take
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>up questions of spirituality and meaning without abandoning
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>the important insights of materialism. We can use the insights
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>of socialist feminism, with its debt to Marxism, to understand
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>how the material conditions of our daily lives interact with
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>our bodies and our psychological heritages. Materialist insights
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>warn us not to assume an innate moral or biological super¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>iority and not to depend on alternative culture alone to trans¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>form society. Yet a separate radical feminist culture within a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>patriarchal society is necessary so we can learn to speak our
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>own bodies and our own experiences, so the male culture
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>representing itself as the &quot;universal&quot; does not continue to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>speak for us. 16
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>We have always thought our lives and works, our very
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>beings, were trivial next to male accomplishments. Women&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>silence is deafening only to those who know it&apos;s there. The ab¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>sence is only beginning to be a presence. Writers like Zora
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>Neale Hurston, Tillie Olsen, Grace Paley and Toni Morrison
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>depict the beauty and dignity of ordinary women&apos;s lives and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>give us back part of ourselves. Women artists begin to suggest
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>the meanings of female bodies and their relationships to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>nature.!7 Women musicians give us the sounds of loving our¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>selves. 18 The enormous and growing lesbian feminist com¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>munity is an especially fertile ground for women&apos;s culture.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>Lesbians are pioneering in every field and building communi¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>ties with ecological feminist consciousness. Third World
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>women are speaking the experience of multiple otherness¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>of race, sex and (often) class oppression. We are learning how
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>women’s lives are the same and different across these divisions,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>and we are beginning to engage the complexities of racism in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>our culture, our movement and our theory.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>There is much that is redemptive for humanity as a whole
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>in women’s silent experience, and there are voices that have
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>not yet been heard. Cultural feminism’s concern with ecology
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>takes the ideology of womanhood which has been a bludgeon
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>of oppression-the woman/nature connection-and transforms
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>it into a positive factor. If we proceed dialectically and recog¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>nize the contributions of both socialist feminism and radical
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>cultural feminism, operating at both the structural and cultural
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>levels, we will be neither materialists nor idealists. We will
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>understand our position historically and attempt to realize the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>human future emerging in the feminist present. Once we have
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>placed ourselves in history, we can move on to the interde¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>pendent issues of feminist social transformation and planetary
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>survival.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>Towards an Ecological Culture: Acting on our own conscious¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>ness of our own needs, we act in the interests of all. We stand
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>on the biological dividing line. We are the less rationalized side
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>of humanity in an overly rationalized world, yet we can think
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>as rationally as men and perhaps transform the idea of reason
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>itself. As women, we are naturalized culture in a culture
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>defined against nature. If nature/culture antagonism is the pri¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>mary contradiction of our time, it is also what weds feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>and ecology and makes woman the historic subject. Without
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>an ecological perspective which asserts the interdependence of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>living things, feminism is disembodied. Without a more sophis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>ticated dialectical method which can transcend historic
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>debates and offer a nondualistic theory of history, social trans¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>formation and nature/culture interaction, feminism will con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>tinue to be mired in the same old impasse. There is more at
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>stake in feminist debates over &quot;the ecology question&quot; than
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>whether feminists should organize against the draft, demon¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>strate at the Pentagon or join mixed anti-nuke organizations.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>At stake is the range and potential of the feminist social move¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>ment.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>Ecological feminism is about reconciliation and conscious
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>mediation, about recognition of the underside of history and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>all the invisible voiceless activities of women over millennia.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>It is about connectedness and wholeness of theory and prac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>tice. It is the return of the repressed-all that has been denigra¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>ted and denied to build this hierarchal civilization with its mul¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>tiple systems of dominance. It is the potential voice of the
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>Ellen Lanyon. Transformations II (Endangered). Detail.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>denied, the ugly and the speechless-all those things called
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>feminine.&quot; So it is no wonder that the feminist movement
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>rose again in the same decade as the ecological crisis. The im¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>plications of feminism extend to issues of the meaning, pur¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>pose and survival of life.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l7' n='N007'/>Never to despise in myself what 1 have been taught
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l8' n='N008'/>to despise. Not to despise the other.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l9' n='N009'/>Not to despise the it. To make this relation
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l10' n='N010'/>with it: to know that ! am it.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l11' n='N011'/>-Muriel Rukeyser, &quot;Despisals&quot; 19
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>1. Ellen Willis, The Village Voice (June 23, 1980). In the Voice (July
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>16-22, 1980), Willis began with the question: &quot;Is ecology a feminist
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>issue?&quot; and was more ambiguous than in her earlier column, although
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>her theoretical position was the same.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>2. Mary Daly, Gyn/Ecology: The Meta-Ethics of Radical Feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>(Boston: Beacon Press, 1978).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>3. Susan Griffin, Woman and Nature : The Roaring Inside Her (New
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>York; Harper &amp; Row, 1979).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>4. For an overview of socialist feminist theory, see Zillah Eisenstein,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>Ed., Capitalist Patriarchy and the Case for Socialist Feminism (New
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>York: Monthly Review Press, 1979).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>5. See Batya Weinbaum, The Curious Courtship of Women&apos;s Libera¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>tion and Socialism (Boston: South End Press, 1978).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>6. See Heidi Hartman, &quot;The Unhappy Marriage of Marxism and Fem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>inism: Towards a More Progressive Union,&quot; Capital and Class, no. 8
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>(Summer 1979).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>7. The notion of a &quot;sex-gender system&quot; was first developed by Gayle
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>Rubin in &quot;The Traffic in Women,&quot; Toward an Anthropology of Wo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>men, ed. R.R. Reiter (New York: Monthly Review Press, 1975).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>8. See Hilda Scott, Does Socialism Liberate Women? (Boston : Beacon
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>Press, 1976).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>9. See Sherry B. Ortner, “Is Woman to Nature as Man Is to Culture?,&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>Woman, Culture, and Society, ed. M.Z. Rosaldo &amp; L. Lamphere (Stan¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>ford: Stanford University Press, 1974).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>10. For a social history of the 19th-century romanticist/rationalist
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>debate see Barbara Ehrenreich and Dierdre English, For Her Own
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>Good (New York: Doubleday/Anchor, 1979)
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>11. Mary Daly comes very close to this position. Other naturalist fem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>inists have a less clear stance on essential differences between women
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>and men.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>12. The &quot;disenchantment of the world&quot; is another way of talking about
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>the process of rationalization discussed above. The term was coined by
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>Max Weber.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>13. See Carolyn Merchant, The Death of Nature: Women, Ecology and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>the Scientific Revolution (San Francisco: Harper &amp; Row, 1980).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>14. For a full development of the idea of &quot;woman as other,&quot; see
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>Simone de Beauvoir, The Second Sex (New York: Modern Library,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>1968).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>15. Dorothy Dinnerstein in The Mermaid and the Minotaur (New York:
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>Harper &amp; Row, 1977) makes an important contribution to feminist
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>understanding by showing that although woman is associated with
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>nature because of her mothering role, this does not in itself explain
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>misogyny and the hatred of nature.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>16. See de Beauvoir, The Second Sex.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>17. See Lucy Lippard, &quot;Quite Contrary: Body, Nature and Ritual
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>in Women&apos;s Art,&quot; Chrysalis, no. 2 (1977).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>18. Alive, Sweet Honey in the Rock, Meg Christian, Holly Near, Margie
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>Adam-the list is long and growing.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>19. Muriel Rukeyser, The Compiete Poems of Muriel Rukeyser (New
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>York: McGraw-Hill, 1978).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>Ynestra King, based in Northampton, Mass., is writing a book on fem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>inism, ecology and suwival entitled Feminism and the Reenchantment
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>of the Worfd. She works with Women and Life on Earth and the Wo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>men’s Pentagon Action and teaches in the Goddard College &quot;Feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>and Ecology&quot; summer program.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>Ellen Lanyon is a painter, printmaker and educator in Chicago and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>NYC. Her imagery involves science versus magic, transformations, and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>phenomena of the natural world.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
