<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>DeLauretis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_line_1670956376591_723' n='N001'/>The Left Hand of History
				<lb facs='#facs_1_line_1670956402728_735' n='N002'/>Teresa De Lauretis
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>What is the place of textuality in feminist criticism? (I
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>mean criticism both in the narrow sense of literary criticism
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>and in the broad sense of sociocultural critique.) Since text¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>ual analysis has a fundamental place in any theory of cul¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>ture, how should the feminist critic approach her work with
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>texts? What should her purpose be? 1 am not sure that a the¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>ory of women’s writing is useful or even desirable at this
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>point. Because women have been a colonized population for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>so long, 1 fear that any critical category we may find applic¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>able today is likely to be derived from or imbued with male
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>ideologies. As writers, critics, teachers, we know this from
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>our daily experiences. I am not suggesting that we ought to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>clean the slate of history and start anew because 1 am enough
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>of a historical materialist and semiotician that I cannot con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>ceive of a totally new world rising out of, and in no way con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>nected with, the past or the present. 1 believe neither in utop-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>ias nor in the myth of Paradise Now, or ever. What I am
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>suggesting is that theory is dialectically built on, checked
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>against, modified by, transformed along with, practice—that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>is to say, with what women do, invent, perform, produce,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>concretely and not “for all time” but within specific histori¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>cal and cultural conditions.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>In the summer of 1975, I was in the small town of Sant
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>Arcangelo di Romagna (near Bologna, Italy) where an open¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>air theater festival sponsored performances by militant and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>experimental groups in the town square and courtyards of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>two medieval castles. One of these performances attracted
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>my attention by its title, Nonostante Gramsci (Despite
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>Gramsci). It was performed by a militant feminist collective,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>La Maddalena, based in Rome. Antonio Gramsci was foun¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>der of the Italian Communist Party and one of the major
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>European Marxist thinkers. He was the most important in¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>fluence on the Italian left in general and on the politics of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>Italian Communist Party (PCI) in particular. His historical
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>analyses and theoretical foundations for Italian communism
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>continue to be effective today.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>Gramsci was imprisoned in 1926 by the newly consolidat-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>ed Fascist dictatorship. He received a mock trial, was given a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>life sentence, and died in 1937 of illness and abuse suffered in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>one of Mussolini’s prisons. The circumstances of his death
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>and his extraordinary intellectual and moral stature have
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>made him perhaps the greatest hero and martyr of the Italian
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>resistance. This is why the play’s title, Despite (or Notwith-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>standing) Gramsci, surprised and intrigued me, since I knew
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>that Italian feminist groups consist almost exclusively of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>women with a record of militancy in the left. They couldn’t
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>be against” Gramsci. Therefore, what did they mean by
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>despite”?
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>The background of the production reveals the group’s
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>ideological stance. Both the text of the theatrical production
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>and the underlying research on original documents were
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>published together the following year under the editorship of
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>Adele Cambria, a feminist writer and one of the editors of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>the major Italian feminist monthly EFFE.1 Cambria formu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>lated and conducted the research, but the theatrical work
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>was performed, directed and written collectively. The pub¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>lished volume, entitled Amore come rivoluzione (Love as
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>Revolution) contains 1 believe not two texts—one creative/
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>artistic and one historical/biographical—but rather a single
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>text. It self-consciously attempts to be at once historical and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>artistic, and deliberately presents itself as tendentious and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>critical. It is a text with its ideology clearly stated and with a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>basis of original research behind its fiction. This text is pos¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>ited as a set of questions dealing with love and revolution—a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>complex problem that emerged in the late 1960s, was pushed
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>to the foreground of political consciousness by radical femin¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>ism, and is one of the major issues in revolutionary politics
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>today.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>During the last eleven years of his life, the imprisoned
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>Gramsci wrote the bulk of his theoretical work now pub-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>lished as Quaderni dal carcere (Prison Notebooks)? In 1922
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>Gramsci spent several months in the Soviet Union as Italian
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>envoy to the Executive Committee of the Communist Inter-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>national. While hospitalized in a sanatorium outside Mos¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>cow, he met Eugenia Schucht, also a patient in the hospital,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>and her sister Giulia. Giulia and Antonio fell in love. After
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>Gramsci had returned to Western Europe, recalled by his
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>political duties, their son Delio was born in 1924. The couple
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>were together only once again, the following year, when
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>Giulia, the baby and Eugenia spent a few months in Rome
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>with Gramsci who by then had been elected to the Italian
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>parliament. When she returned to the Soviet Union, Giulia
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>was pregnant with their second son, Giuliano, whom Gram¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>sci never saw. History records that during his long years in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>prison, the only link between Gramsci and his family was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>Giulia s other sister, Tatiana Schucht, who lived in Italy and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>followed Gramsci as he was sent from one jail to another. She
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>supported him materially and spiritually, assisting him
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>through his long agony. It is Tatiana who rescued Gramsci’s
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l38' n='N038'/>Prison Notebooks after his death. But, history being the his¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l39' n='N039'/>tory of men, only Gramsci’s letters were deemed important
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l40' n='N040'/>historical documents.? The letters he received from Giulia
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l41' n='N041'/>and Tatiana were not published, although they existed, lying
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l42' n='N042'/>in a file at the Gramsci Institute in Rome. Official historiog¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l43' n='N043'/>raphy scorned them. They were women s letters, dealing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l44' n='N044'/>only with children and marmalade, banal, insignificant.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l45' n='N045'/>Little information could be found about these mute women,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l46' n='N046'/>whose complex relationships to Gramsci and to one another
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l47' n='N047'/>constituted the most intense private aspect of Gramsci’s life
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l48' n='N048'/>as a revolutionary. Biographers record that Giulia grew more
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l49' n='N049'/>and more alienated from her husband as a result of mental
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l50' n='N050'/>illness. In his letters he lamented and grieved over her
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l51' n='N051'/>silence. Tatiana acted as a sister of mercy, visiting Gramsci
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l52' n='N052'/>in jail, sending him socks and medicines, relaying letters bet¬
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>ween him, Giulia and the children. Here ends their official
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>history. Yet, if we read Gramsci’s letters many of the ques¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>tions posed in them remain unanswered: What exactly was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>the nature of Giulia’s “illness”? Why did Tatiana and not
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>she stay in Italy to assist him in jail? What moved Tatiana to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>literally devote her life to him? What was Eugenia’s role?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>There is no doubt that Gramsci’s thoughts were directed to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>these private concerns as much as to political problems and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>theory—his letters prove it despite the self-restraint imposed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>by personal ethics and prison censorship. Some of his most
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>beautiful letters to Giulia deal with the education of their
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>children and with the problems posed by his responsibilities
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>to the revolution and to their love relationship—he even sug-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>gested a formal separation that would allow Giulia to re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>marry, if that would restore her well-being.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>Who were these women outside of the pale, pathetic hagi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>ography constructed by Gramsci’s biographers? This is what
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>Adele Cambria set out to investigate. She carefully read all of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>the women’s letters in conjunction with Gramsci’s, inter¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>viewed people who had been close friends of the sisters, stud-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>ied Eugenia’s letters to a friend in Rome and the notebooks
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>in which Giulia had practiced compositions as an adolescent.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>Cambria s purpose throughout was to reconstruct an “affec¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>tive biography” of the Schuchts and to discover the sources
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>and modes of that “emotional energy” Shulamith Firestone
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>identifies as the essential female contribution to male
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>thought. Cambria’s project was a political one: to rewrite
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>history, inscribing in it the missing voices of women, and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>therefore to examine the relationships between the private
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>and the public, love and revolution, personal/sexual/emo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>tional needs and political militancy—relations which she sees
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>as the moving forces of all revolutionary struggle. In restor¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>ing to Gramsci’s epistolary monologue its real nature as dia¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>logue, Cambria adds depth to the cultural image of a person
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>whose complex humanity has been expediently stereotyped.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>In a letter to Giulia in 1924, before his imprisonment and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>at the height of revolutionary activities Gramsci himself
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>posed the problem. He wrote:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>How many times have I asked myself whether it was possible
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>to tie oneself to a mass without ever having loved anyone ..
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>whether one could love a collectivity if one hadn’t deeply
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>loved some single human beings . . . Wouldn’t this have
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>made barren my qualities as a revolutionary, wouldn’t it
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>have reduced them to a pure intellectual fact, a pure mathe¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>matical calculation? 5
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>Gramsci’s question unwinds the ideological thread that runs
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>through Cambria’s work and the collective theater produc¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>tion, both of which focus on the “private aspect of Gram¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l49' n='N049'/>sci’s life. Thus an understanding of the Schucht family is es¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l50' n='N050'/>sential, in the context of the turn-of-the-century cultural val¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l51' n='N051'/>ues and of the changes brought by the October Revolution.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l52' n='N052'/>Lenin, and later by Stalinism and Fascism.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l53' n='N053'/>Apollo Schucht, father of the three sisters, was an exile
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l54' n='N054'/>from czarist Russia who had settled in Rome in 1908. Born
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l55' n='N055'/>into the upper bourgeoisie, he had belonged to the Russian
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l56' n='N056'/>populist social reform movement (narodvolcstvo) in the mid¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l57' n='N057'/>nineteenth century. Deported with Lenin to Siberia where
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l58' n='N058'/>his third daughter, Eugenia, was born, he asked his friend
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l59' n='N059'/>Lenin to be her “godfather.” The family lived in Rome from
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l60' n='N060'/>1908 to 1917. After the October Revolution, they all returned
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l61' n='N061'/>to the Soviet Union and worked in the CPSU except Tatiana
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l62' n='N062'/>who stayed at her teaching position in Rome. Significantly
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l63' n='N063'/>nothing much is known of Apollo’s wife, Lula, except that
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l64' n='N064'/>she was an excellent cook and housewife. It was Apollo’s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l65' n='N065'/>strong influence that shaped the lives of his daughters. His
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l66' n='N066'/>world view, in matters of sex roles, was all but revolutionary.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l67' n='N067'/>His daughters completed their higher education in Rome in
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>the arts and natural sciences, areas that clearly trained wom¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>en for the only careers suitable for them—marriage and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>teaching. The early writings of Giulia and Eugenia reveal
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>how deeply they had absorbed their father’s late-romantic
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>humanitarian values: a sense of duty toward the poor and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>dispossessed; contact with nature as a source of happiness,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>goodness and personal fulfillment; the love of children ideal¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>ized as a pure unspoiled manifestation of Good Nature; a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>sentimental attachment to Family as nest and shelter from
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>the disorder and potential danger of the outside world. None
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>of this prepared them for the violent realities in which they
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>were to live. In the turmoil after the revolution there came
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>into their lives the man who, like their father before him, was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>to magnetize their existence. Gramsci became, for all three
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>women, the center of their emotional world, the unwitting
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>protagonist of romantic mystification, the pivot of a patriar¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>chal model they had deeply internalized. They all were in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>love with Antonio.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>Eugenia met him first, but he fell in love with Giulia, the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>youngest, most beautiful and most “feminine” of them.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>Cambria documents, fairly convincingly, that Eugenia’s es¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>pousal of the Communist cause—her “wedding” to the Party
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>—came right after Antonio and Giulia met. The sisters’ close
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>mother-daughter relationship had made Giulia emotionally
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>and intellectually dependent on her older sister. Eugenia
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>later exploited this by making herself indispensable, support-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>ing her financially, taking care of her children and living
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>with her before and during Gramsci’s imprisonment, thus re-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>inforcing Giulia’s feelings of personal inadequacy in the roles
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>of mother and wife. In Cambria’s interpretation, Eugenia
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>was mainly responsible for keeping Giulia away from Gram¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>sci. Her reasons were consistent with the prevailing values of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>the time: Giulia must stay in the Soviet Union to care for the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>children who would be in great danger in Fascist Italy;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>Giulia was “sickly and subject to depressions”; Giulia was a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>Soviet communist and the Party needed her. Eradicating
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>from her life the possibility of a “private relationship with
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>any man, Eugenia played the male role as political activist
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>and head of the household. While praising and mythicizing
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>Gramsci as a revolutionary leader (she translated his writings
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>for the Soviet workers), Eugenia increased the human dis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>tance between him and Giulia.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>Tatiana met Antonio after his return to Rome, already
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>married” to Giulia (officially recorded after the first child
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>was born). Tatiana’s love for Gramsci, avowed as sisterly
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>love, developed over the twelve years during which she per-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>formed for him the duties of the prisoner’s wife. A close read¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>ing of their letters shows the ambivalence of their relation¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>ship which, considering their strong ethical sense and mater-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>ial and social constraints, was perhaps the most fulfilling, if
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>deformed, love relationship of any of the Schucht sisters. In
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>defining herself as Giulia’s representative, she slowly made
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l53' n='N053'/>herself indispensable to the man she loved. She maintained
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l54' n='N054'/>contact with underground left leaders outside Italy in hope¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l55' n='N055'/>less attempts to free Gramsci through prisoner exchanges. As
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l56' n='N056'/>the only correspondent authorized by jail officials, she copied
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l57' n='N057'/>and relayed his letters to Giulia and the children and theirs to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l58' n='N058'/>him. By this “charitable sacrifice” and sisterly devotion, and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l59' n='N059'/>by never allowing her own needs to surface (but they are
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l60' n='N060'/>there, between the lines of the letters), Tatiana gradually ac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l61' n='N061'/>quired a wife’s right to husbandly gratitude, a wifely
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l62' n='N062'/>possessiveness and the subtle power gained by female self-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l63' n='N063'/>denial.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l64' n='N064'/>Of the three stories, unrecorded by history, Giulia’s is the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l65' n='N065'/>most lonely. She is still alive, as far as we know, in some
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l66' n='N066'/>psychiatric hospital where she has spent most of her life, im¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l67' n='N067'/>prisoned in her “mental illness” as Antonio was in his cell.
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>He burned in the hell of pain, captivity and death, but he
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>won—he is a protagonist of history. Giulia is still burning,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>quietly, bothering no one, unnoticed, useless. One of Cam¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>bria’s most significant contributions to feminist analysis is
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>her effort to understand Giulia’s personal world with love
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>and generosity, outside of myth and without mystification.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>She sees Giulia as a sensitive, intelligent, gifted woman in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>whom the traditional female socialization, with its emphasis
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>on dependence, frailty and childlike trust, found a most re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>ceptive terrain. Giulia did not relate intellectually to others
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>or to her own experience. Women of her time were not sup-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>posed to. She needed direct sensuous contact with reality,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>her children, her man. She gave up her violin for her children
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>and the Party. The distance between her and Antonio was
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>caused not only by circumstances but also by decisions made
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>for her by Eugenią, to which Gramsci acquiesced. Her re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>sponse to the distance was expressed by a sense of personal
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>inadequacy, increasing depression, surrendering her will to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>others and to the mechanical details of daily existence. The
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>notion that absence makes the heart grow fonder did not
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>work for her: she blamed herself for not being able to feel, for
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>losing contact with Antonio who was becoming a mere ab¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>straction—The Father of Her Children, The Revolutionary
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>Hero—no longer her lover whom she could touch nor her
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>friend whom she could see and hear and speak to. She felt
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>guilty about this and when she finally dared to write to him
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>about her illness he did not answer, could not accept the idea
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>of mental illness, spoke harshly of psychoanalysis as a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>crutch, and like the rest of the family recommended iron, vit-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>amins and will power. No one ever seriously considered the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>possibility that Giulia move to Italy to assist Antonio, and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>she herself believed that she could never do for him what
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>Tatiana did. In short, Eugenia and Tatiana usurped her
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>roles as mother, housekeeper and wife and effectively de-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>prived her of meaningful emotional relationships and inten¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>sified her sense of powerlessness. At last, Cambria main¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>tains, Giulia’s inability to define herself conceptually or
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>through any type of personal power, and the unreality of her
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>existence that could not function within any socially accepted
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>mode of female behavior, pushed Giulia to live her rebellion
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>inwardly, in total passivity. This is precisely what is often
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>diagnosed as madness in women.“
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>In a sense, the personalities and social roles assumed by
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>the three Schucht sisters sketch almost to a T the only
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>choices allowed women in most Western cultures: service
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>functions within male structures, adherence to the feminine
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>mystique of charity, sacrifice and self-denial, and madness.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>T’he textual strategies of Amore come rivoluzione are the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l49' n='N049'/>result of ideological choices. The materials being mainly let-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l50' n='N050'/>ters, there were three obvious genre possibilities: (1) publish-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l51' n='N051'/>ing the letters, with some editing (as was done with Gramsci&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l52' n='N052'/>letters); (2) putting together a sort of three-way epistolary
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l53' n='N053'/>novel of Giulia’s, Tatiana s&apos; and Gramsci’s letters; or (3) giv-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l54' n='N054'/>ing the materials a narrative form, i.e., writing a biography
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l55' n='N055'/>of the Schucht sisters. Cambria discarded all three alterna¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l56' n='N056'/>tives. Her decision to avoid a “novelistic” organization was a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l57' n='N057'/>political as well as aesthetic choice: as recent critical theory
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l58' n='N058'/>in literature and film argues, narrative form is the primary
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l59' n='N059'/>aesthetic code developed to convey bourgeois and counter-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l60' n='N060'/>revolutionary values.” Simply printing the letters without at-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l61' n='N061'/>tempting to reproduce such “physical” qualities as hand¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l62' n='N062'/>writing, or the context in which they were written and dis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l63' n='N063'/>covered, would have erased altogether the function of the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l64' n='N064'/>subject (Cambria herself), as both writer and narrator of her
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l65' n='N065'/>book and at the same time reader of the Schucht letters.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l66' n='N066'/>Cambria chose to print portions of the original documents
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l67' n='N067'/>in italics interspersed with passages from Gramsci’s letters,
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>quotations, statements by friends or others involved in the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>events, while her own comments link, interpret and contex-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>tualize each passage. The rigorous separation, by different
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>typefaces, between the women’s letters and her own com-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>mentary explicitly manifests the interpretive nature of the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>commentary, its tendentiousness, its having a viewpoint, its
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>being “sectarian” rather than an innocent or “objective” ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>planation. In this manner, a twofold process is set in motion
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>in the text: the release of affective energies contained in the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>firsthand documents, which were personal writings aimed at
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>a real person (Gramsci), not a literary readership; and the re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>lease of a corresponding emotional response in the modern
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>woman reading the letters and mediating them for us
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>through her personal and ideological, affective and concep¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>tual codes. In many passages Cambria shares her emotion at
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>discovering the letters, looking at the faded colors of the pa¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>per, the elegant old-fashioned handwriting of Tatiana, the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>broken sentences and pencil scrawls of an already ill Giulia.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>Cambria also describes her feelings as she approached the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>Moscow house where Giulia lived and where Cambria inter¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>viewed her son Giuliano.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>Cambria conveys to readers how she absorbed Giulia,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>Tatiana and Eugenia as fragments of her own self, how their
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>experiences can act as reactor to other women’s understand-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>ing of themselves; she also conveys her elation in discovering
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>and unearthing a writing which is the testimony of unknown
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>women. She reaches into an immense reservoir of women’s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>folklore, millions of letters in which women have spent their
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>imagination and creativity writing to those they loved, all
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>lost, but for the few who made literary history by loving a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>male protagonist.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>l’he performance I saw was in an open courtyard and used
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>the Brechtian concept of epic theater. In the theatrical text,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>the double function of the subject as writer and as reader is
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>dramatized in the character of The Girl, epic narrator and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>didactic commentator, who circulates among the four char¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>acters (the three sisters and Gramsci), each of whom is con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>fined to an assigned scenic space. The Girl has a double
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>function: as narrator and commentator, she provides the his¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>torical background and the feminist interpretation of the per¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>formed action. As character, she voices the lyrical conscious¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>ness of the play, Woman-Orpheus. A contemporary woman,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>she is a barometer for the audience, reacting with pity and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>anger to the events enacted around her. The fact that she
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>also acts visibly as a stage hand (she projects the slides,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>moves the structures, dresses the actors) is a brilliant theatri¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>cal idea for she is perceived by the audience as a performer,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>i.e., as a real person participating in the entire fictional cre¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>ation and not simply acting out a memorized part in some¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>body else’s play. Furthermore, since she models audience
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>response, it is very important that she does not remain emo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>tionally detached or objective in relation to the characters; at
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l53' n='N053'/>the same time her involvement must never become total.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l54' n='N054'/>For, in the intentions of the epic theater, the audience and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l55' n='N055'/>the performers must not identify totally with the characters,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l56' n='N056'/>must not be drawn into the story forgetting that it is a fiction,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l57' n='N057'/>must not experience catharsis at the conclusion of the play.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l58' n='N058'/>Rather, they must remain conscious of the problems raised
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l59' n='N059'/>by the play and seek their solution outside, after the play, in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l60' n='N060'/>the real world. One example: in “dressing” Giulia, revealing
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l61' n='N061'/>her to us, The Girl is a woman of today discovering her roots
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l62' n='N062'/>in a woman of the past and re-enacting herself in a fictional
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l63' n='N063'/>character. But when The Girl acts out the pain of pregnancy
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l64' n='N064'/>and childbirth, shouting her rejection of motherhood as a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l65' n='N065'/>physical violence done to her body, as an emotionally trau¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l66' n='N066'/>matic infringement on her total person, at this moment The
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l67' n='N067'/>Girl is Giulia; she expresses the feeling that Giulia could
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>never express, the repression of which was one of the forms
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>of her “insanity.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>Certain aspects of this production—the use of voices on
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>tape, slides, lighting, the designed structures, objects of per¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>sonal “ritual” created by the performers—are discussed in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>the direction notes and contributions by performers and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>designers printed in the appendix to the volume. These pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>vide an integral, essential part of the text, outlining the dif¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>ficult but rewarding practice of the performance, collective
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>in every aspect from writing to staging to each performer’s
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>self-direction.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>The historical text and the theatrical text were conceived
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>interdependently. Although they are addressed to different,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>if overlapping, audiences and make different assumptions as
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>textual mechanisms, they are not two distinct texts as would
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>be, say, a biography and a play based on it. They are, rather,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>one set of raw materials examined with an identical ideologi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>cal perspective and presented differently to achieve a double
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>impact by juxtaposition; when we experience them together,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>the historical text has a distancing effect from the highly
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>emotional impact of the dramatic text. The first is rational,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>documented, footnoted; the second is lyrical and intensely
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>charged with emotion. The verbal material in the play is
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>almost entirely from the original letters, with the addition of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>some contemporary poems and other quotations which serve
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>as intertextual links to expand the historical resonance of the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>themes.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>The characteristic features of Cambria’s entire work point
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>to a new practice and vision of the relation between subject
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>and modes of textual production.? As for the form of content:
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>historical, not mythical materials are chosen from a concrete
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>situation and real events. These are not necessarily contem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>porary but always refer to the current concerns of the audi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>ence.1° The historical events are examined in their socio¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>cultural complexity from the ideological and emotional view¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>points of contemporary feminism. The human sources of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>these views—writers, performers and the specific audience
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>addressed (this is a play for women)—are clearly identified to
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>avoid mystification and mythologizing. As for the form of ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>pression: the rejection of the novelistic as the single organiz-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>ing principle of classical narrative forms like biography,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>romance or the “realist” novel must be seen in the light of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>current theories of the plurality of the text. This emphasizes
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>the process of reading as a constitutive act of the subject. In
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>this new textual form, where the rational historical inquiry is
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>continually intersected by the lyrical and the personal, the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>subject is at once writer and reader, performer and audience.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>The resonance of the (documented) historical events in the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l49' n='N049'/>subject is made possible by the “private” dimension and in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l50' n='N050'/>turn makes possible the emergence of pathos as a creative
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l51' n='N051'/>critical process. The text is produced as and meant to be re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l52' n='N052'/>ceived as the intersecting of the personal and the social, a
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l53' n='N053'/>process articulated dialectically on subjective codes and on
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l54' n='N054'/>objective realities.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l55' n='N055'/>Working along these lines, we can perhaps develop a fem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l56' n='N056'/>inist theory of textual production which is neither a theory of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l57' n='N057'/>women’s writing nor just a theory of textuality. In other
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l58' n='N058'/>words, it is not a matter of finding common elements among
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l59' n='N059'/>the texts written or produced by women and defining them in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l60' n='N060'/>terms of a presumed femaleness or femininity which, to my
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l61' n='N061'/>mind, is highly suspect of sexual metaphysics; rather, it is
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l62' n='N062'/>our task to envision a feminist theory of the process of textual
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l63' n='N063'/>production and consumption, which is of course inseparable
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l64' n='N064'/>from a theory of culture. In a recently translated article en¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l65' n='N065'/>titled “Is There a Feminine Aesthetic?”, Silvia Bovenschen
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l66' n='N066'/>argues that there is no such thing as an ever-present female
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_1_1l67' n='N067'/>counterculture as such, or a “female nature outside of his¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>torical development; and that to insist on such notions as ir¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>rational perception, cosmic powers or archetypal forms as
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>categories for femaleness is at best playing men’s games, and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>at worst indulging in reactionary ideologies.11 Since it is the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>specifics of feminine experience and perception that deter-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>mine the form the work takes, we must not accept a priori
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>categories and should look for evidence of feminine sensitiv-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>ity in concrete tests. It is good, Bovenschen claims, that no
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>formal criteria for “feminine art” can be definitively laid
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>down. This enables us to reject the notion of artistic norms
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>and facile labeling, and prevents cooptation and further ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>ploitation of women’s creativity. So it is not a question of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>what or how women write, but of how women produce (as
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>makers) and reproduce (as receivers) the aesthetic object, the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>text; in other words, we need a theory of culture with women
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>as subjects—not commodities but social beings producing
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>and reproducing cultural products, transmitting and trans¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>forming cultural values.12
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>In this sense, and so that we can take possession of our cul¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>tural (re)production, 1 think we should assert that women’s
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>work is never done.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>*This paper was first presented at the Symposium WOMEN/ TEXTS at
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>the University of Minnesota in Minneapolis, on April 20, 1977.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>I am grateful to the Center for 20th Century Studies of the University of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>Wisconsin-Milwaukee for the 1976-1977 Fellowship that has made possible
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>the research and the writing of this paper. 1 must also thank my friends
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>Renny Harrigan, Andreas Huyssen, Judith Mayne, Sheila Radford-Hill,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>Sylvie Romanowski and Marcella Tarozzi, who helped me greatly by lend-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>ing me books, arguing against me, and sharing their knowledge and in¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>sights.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>. Adele Cambria, Amore come rivoluzione (Milano: Sugar Co., 1976):
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>The volume includes the script and production notes for Nonostante
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>Gramsci.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>2. The complete Italian edition, in four volumes, is Antonio Gramsci,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>Quaderni dal carcere, a cura di Valentino Gerratana (Torino: Einaudi,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>1975). In English see Selections from the Prison Notebooks of Antonio
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>Gramsci, edited and translated by Quintin Hoare and Geoffrey Nowell
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>Smith (New York: International Publishers, 1971).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>3. Antonio Gramsci, Lettere dal carcere, a cura di S. Caprioglio e E.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>Fubini (Torino: Einaudi, 1973). In English see Antonio Gramsci, Letters
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>from Prison, selected and translated by Lynne Lawner (New York: Harper
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>and Row, 1973). See also Guiseppe Fiori, Antonio Gramsci: Life of a
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>Revolutionary (New York: Schocken Books, 1973).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>4. The Dialectic of Sex: The Case for Feminist Revolution (New York:
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>Bantam Books, 1970), pp. 126-127.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>5. Quoted by Cambria, p. 9, from Duemila pagine di Gramsci (Milano: Il
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>Saggiatore), Vol. II, p. 23, letter of June 9, 1924; my translation.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>6. Cf. Phyllis Chesler, Women and Madness (Garden City, N.Y.: Double-
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>day, 1972).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>7. From Umberto Eco, Opera aperta (Milano: Bompiani, 1967) to Stephen
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>Heath, “Narrative Space,” Screen (Autumn 1976), pp. 68-112.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>8. On the conditions of women in the Soviet Union since the revolution, see
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l53' n='N053'/>Sheila Rowbotham, “If You Like Tobogganing” in her Women, Resistance
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l54' n='N054'/>and Revolution (New York: Vintage Books, 1974), pp. 134-169. Also very
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l55' n='N055'/>important to this topic is the work of Alexandra Kollontai, The Auto¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l56' n='N056'/>biography of a Sexually Emancipated Communist Woman (New York:
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l57' n='N057'/>Schocken Books, 1975). Women Workers Struggle for Their Rights
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l58' n='N058'/>(Bristol: Falling Wall Press, 1971), and Sexual Relations and the Class
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l59' n='N059'/>Struggle/Love and the New Morality (Bristol: Falling Wall Press, 1972).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l60' n='N060'/>9. For the notion of modes of sign production see Umberto Eco, A Theory
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l61' n='N061'/>of Semiotics (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1976) and Gianfranco
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l62' n='N062'/>Bettetini, Produzione del senso e messa in scena (Milano: Bompiani, 1975)
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l63' n='N063'/>10. In the words of Dacia Maraini, who reviewed Amore come rivoluzione,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l64' n='N064'/>“books like this should be written by the hundreds. There are hundreds of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l65' n='N065'/>extraordinary women who have so much to teach us (even if often they only
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l66' n='N066'/>speak of failures and defeat), women still buried under the barren, impious
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l67' n='N067'/>ashes of patriarchal history.” (Tuttolibri, 17 aprile 1976, p. 4; my transla¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l68' n='N068'/>tion). The terms form of content and form of expression come from Louis
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l69' n='N069'/>Hjelmslev, Prolegomena to a Theory of Language (Madison: University of
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l70' n='N070'/>Wisconsin Press, 1961).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l71' n='N071'/>11. Silvia Bovenschen, “Is There a Feminine Aesthetic?”, New German
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l72' n='N072'/>Critique, 10 (Winter 1977), pp. 111-137 and Heresies f4, pp. 10-12.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l73' n='N073'/>Altman’s recent film, Three Women, seems to me to come close to the latter
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l74' n='N074'/>group.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l75' n='N075'/>12. For a good analysis of women’s position as objects of exchange in Lévi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l76' n='N076'/>Strauss and Freud/Lacan, see Gayle Rubin, “The Traffic in Women: Notes
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l77' n='N077'/>on the Political Economy of Sex, in Rayna R. Reiter, ed., Toward an An¬
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l78' n='N078'/>thropology of Women (New York: Monthly Review Press, 1975), pp.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_2_1l79' n='N079'/>157-210.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>Teresa de Lauretis was born in Bologna, studied in Milan and now teaches Italian at
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>the University of Wisconsin at Milwaukee.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
