<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Sweeney_Issue1_104-106</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: rmh036@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>Wages For Housework: The Strategy for Women&apos;s Liberation
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>Pat Sweeney
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N001'/>Many &quot;feminist&quot; writers have contributed to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l3' n='N002'/>the ideology of housework. Radical-feminists,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l4' n='N003'/>while recognizing the identification of house¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l5' n='N004'/>work with our female nature, have proposed
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l6' n='N005'/>sharing this work with a man and leaving the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l7' n='N006'/>home for outside work. Socialist-feminists, de¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l8' n='N007'/>scribing housework as precapitalist, have pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l9' n='N008'/>claimed that our goal should be toward &quot;indus¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l10' n='N009'/>trialization,&quot; which would liberate our time for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l11' n='N010'/>more work—but in a factory, if not a collective
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l12' n='N011'/>kitchen. Liberal feminists have defined our
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l13' n='N012'/>problem as &quot;lack of consciousness,&quot; describing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l14' n='N013'/>women as dupes of Madison Avenue ad-men.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l15' n='N014'/>Finally, there are those feminists who, much to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l16' n='N015'/>capitalists&apos; rejoicing, have glorified our forced
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l17' n='N016'/>labor in the home as the embodiment of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l18' n='N017'/>best human potentials: our capacity to nurture
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l19' n='N018'/>and care, our very capacity to love. One thing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l20' n='N019'/>they all agree on is that women should not be
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l21' n='N020'/>paid for this work, because this presumably
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l22' n='N021'/>would institutionalize us in the home, and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l23' n='N022'/>extend the control of the state to &quot;the one area
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l24' n='N023'/>of freedom we have in our lives.&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l25' n='N024'/>Contrary to these criticisms, the Wages for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l26' n='N025'/>Housework Committee&apos;s perspective is based on
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l27' n='N026'/>the fact that housework is already controlled
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l28' n='N027'/>and institutionalized (Mother&apos;s Day is nothing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l29' n='N028'/>less than the celebration of this institutionaliza¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l30' n='N029'/>tion!) precisely because this work is unwaged.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l31' n='N030'/>Society is organized to force us into this job,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l32' n='N031'/>and the fact that we don’t receive a wage for the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l33' n='N032'/>work continuously undermines our power to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l34' n='N033'/>refuse it.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l35' n='N034'/>That housework is unwaged means first of all
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l36' n='N035'/>that it appears not as work, but as part of our
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l37' n='N036'/>female nature. Thus, when we refuse part of this
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l38' n='N037'/>work—as, for example, lesbian women do in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l39' n='N038'/>refusing to provide sexual services to men—we
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l40' n='N039'/>are branded as perverts, as if we were breaking
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l41' n='N040'/>some law of nature. We are divided into &quot;good“
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l42' n='N041'/>and &quot;bad&quot; women depending on whether or not
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l43' n='N042'/>we do the housework and whether or not we do
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l44' n='N043'/>it for free. In this society to be a good woman —
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l45' n='N044'/>or just to be a woman—is to be a good servant
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l46' n='N045'/>at everyone&apos;s disposal 24 hours a day; it means
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l47' n='N046'/>accepting that this work should not be paid
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l48' n='N047'/>because it supposedly fulfills our nature, and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l49' n='N048'/>thus contains its own reward.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l50' n='N049'/>Housework is not just washing dishes, scrub¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l51' n='N050'/>bing floors, or raising babies. What we do at
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>home is produce and reproduce workers: every
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>day we create and restore the capacity of others
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>(and ourselves) to work, and to be exploited. It
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>is ironic that as houseworkers we are not in¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>cluded in the nation’s labor force, for without
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>this work the workforce would not exist. The
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>lack of a wage obscures the indispensability of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>our work to the functioning of this society.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>Housework makes every other work possible.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>No car could be produced, no coal could be
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>dug, no office could be run, if there were not
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>women at home servicing and reproducing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>those who make the cars, those who dig the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>coal, those who run the offices. This is the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>sexual division of labor: workers make cars, and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l16' n='N016'/>women make the workers who make the cars.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l17' n='N017'/>And to make a worker is a much more time- and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l18' n='N018'/>energy-consuming job than to make a car! Not
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l19' n='N019'/>only do we &quot;reproduce“ them physically—
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l20' n='N020'/>cooking their dinners, doing the shopping
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l21' n='N021'/>(shopping is work, not consumption as some
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l22' n='N022'/>&quot;feminists&quot; would have us believe). We also
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l23' n='N023'/>service workers emotionally—taking the brunt
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l24' n='N024'/>of their tiredness and frustration day after day.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l25' n='N025'/>And we service workers sexually—the Saturday¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l26' n='N026'/>night screw keeps them going for yet another
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l27' n='N027'/>week at the assembly line or desk.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l28' n='N028'/>It appears that we freely donate all this work
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l29' n='N029'/>to our husbands and children out of our love for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l30' n='N030'/>them. In reality we are working for the same
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l31' n='N031'/>bosses, who are getting two workers for the price
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l32' n='N032'/>of one. Our lives are governed by the same work
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l33' n='N033'/>schedule as those we serve. When we cook
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l34' n='N034'/>dinner or when we &quot;make love&quot; is determined
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l35' n='N035'/>by the factory time-clock. Not only the quan¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l36' n='N036'/>tity, but also the quality of workers we repro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l37' n='N037'/>duce is controlled. If they don’t need many
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l38' n='N038'/>workers, we are sterilized; if they need more
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l39' n='N039'/>workers we are denied access to contraceptives
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l40' n='N040'/>and are forced to resort to backstreet butchers
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l41' n='N041'/>(the right to life is never claimed for women).
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l42' n='N042'/>Likewise, if we are on welfare or we tend to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l43' n='N043'/>produce &quot;troublemakers,&quot; we are again steril¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l44' n='N044'/>ized.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l45' n='N045'/>In every case, our sexuality is continuously
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l46' n='N046'/>under control to make sure that we use it pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l47' n='N047'/>ductively. Lesbianism and teenage sex are il¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l48' n='N048'/>legal, and rape in the family (or the battered
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l49' n='N049'/>wife) is not a crime since readily available
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l50' n='N050'/>sexual service is part of our job. It is the lack of
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>money of our own that creates the battered wife
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>or the closet lesbian and forces so many of us to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>remain in unwanted family situations. With
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>money in our hands, we would have the power
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>to walk out whenever we wanted. Men would
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>certainly think twice before raising their hands
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>to us if they knew that we could leave any
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>minute, without the prospect of starving.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>Our wageless condition in the home is the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>material basis of our dependence on men. This
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>weakness in the community, as wageless house¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>workers, is ultimately the weakness of the entire
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>class. Capitalism takes away from us in the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>community (through inflation—price hikes
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>rent increases, fare increases, etc.) what we
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>have gained through our power in the factory.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>Women pay a double price for this defeat.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>Higher prices mean an intensification of our
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>work, since we are expected to absorb the cost
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>of inflation with extra work.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>The struggle for wages for housework is a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>struggle for social power—for women first, but
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>ultimately for the entire working class. In fact,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>by demanding wages for the work we already
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>do, instead of demanding more work, we are
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>posing the question of the immediate reappro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>priation of the wealth we have produced. Ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>ploitation is the enforcement of unpaid labor
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>the only source of capitalist profits. Thus to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>attack our wagelessness is to attack capitalism
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>at its roots for capital is precisely the accumu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>lated labor that has been robbed from workers
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>generation after generation.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>In contrast, the strategy that has been offered
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>to us by &quot;feminists&quot; and the left—the strategy to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>obtain more work-would only mean further
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>enslavement to the present system. It is capital
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>that poses work as the only natural destiny in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>our lives, not the working class, whose struggles
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>are always directed toward gaining more money
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>and less work. To pose the &quot;right to work&quot; as our
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>road to liberation ignores that we are already
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>working, and that housework does not wither
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>away when we go out for a paid job. Our work
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>at home simply intensifies: we do it at night
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>when everybody is already asleep, or in the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>morning before everyone awakes or on week¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>ends. Our wages remain low—and they quickly
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l49' n='N049'/>disappear in paying for day-care centers
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l50' n='N050'/>lunches, carfare, etc. Furthermore, with two
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l51' n='N051'/>jobs we have even less time to organize with
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l52' n='N052'/>other women. Unions have long accused wom¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l53' n='N053'/>en of being backward. But when did unions
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l54' n='N054'/>consider that we are not free to attend meetings
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l55' n='N055'/>after our second job is over because we must
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l56' n='N056'/>hurry to report back to our first one—picking up
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l57' n='N057'/>the kids at the day-care center or babysitter&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l58' n='N058'/>getting to the supermarket before it closes, fix¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l59' n='N059'/>ing dinner for the men who expect it to be ready
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l60' n='N060'/>when they come home from work?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l61' n='N061'/>Another illusion is that to go &quot;out to work&quot; is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l62' n='N062'/>to break our isolation and gain the possibility of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l63' n='N063'/>a social life. Very often the isolation of a typing
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l64' n='N064'/>pool or a secretarial office matches our isola¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>tion in the home. We certainly aspire to a social
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>life better than the one provided by an assembly
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>line. But going out of the home is not much of a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>relief if we don’t have any money in our hands,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>or if we go out just for more work.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>We also reject the idea that sharing our ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>ploitation in the home with a man can be a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>strategy for liberation. &quot;Sharing the housework&apos;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>is not an invention of the Women&apos;s Movement.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>Women have continuously tried to get men to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>share this work. Despite some victories, we
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>have discovered that this battle also has many
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>limitations. First, the man is not home most of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>the time. If he brings in the money, and we are
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>economically dependent on him, we don’t have
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>the power to force him to do housework. In fact
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>it is often more work for us to get the man to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>share the work than do it ourselves. Most im¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>portantly, this strategy confines us to an in¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>dividual struggle which does not give us the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>power (or the protection) of a mass struggle.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>And it assumes that every woman has (or wants)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>a man with whom to share the work.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>As for a possible rationalization of house¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>work, we must immediately say that we are not
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>interested in making our work more efficient or
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>more productive for capital. We are interested
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>in reducing our work, and ultimately refusing it
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>altogether. But as long as we work in the home
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>for nothing, no one really cares how long or
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>how hard we work. For capital only introduces
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>advanced technology to cut its costs of produc-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>tion after wage gains by the working class. Only
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>if we make our work cost (i.e. only if we make
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>it uneconomical) will capital &quot;discover“ the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>technology to reduce it. At present, we often
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>have to go out for a second shift of work to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>afford the dishwasher that should cut down our
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>housework.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>Who will pay for this work?
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>We demand wages for housework from the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>government for two major reasons. First, every
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>sector of the economy benefits from our work¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>we don’t work for one boss, we work for all the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>bosses. Consequently we demand the money
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>from the state. Second, the government already
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>is our boss. In every country the government is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>responsible for guaranteeing an adequate labor
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>force to industry. This means that the govern¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>ment directly regulates and controls our work
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>through the family, world population control,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>immigration laws, and finally by entering the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l53' n='N053'/>community whenever we refuse to perform our
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l54' n='N054'/>work.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l55' n='N055'/>The question &quot;who will pay?&quot; is usually posed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l56' n='N056'/>so as to subvert the cause. It is assumed that the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l57' n='N057'/>government is broke, and that our demand will
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l58' n='N058'/>only divide the working class by forcing the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l59' n='N059'/>government to tax other workers to pay us a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l60' n='N060'/>wage. In reality, by getting more power for our¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l61' n='N061'/>selves, we will be giving more power not only to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l62' n='N062'/>men (power not over us but with respect to their
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l63' n='N063'/>bosses) but to every sector (the young, the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l64' n='N064'/>elderly, and the wageless in general). We will
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>begin to break the power relations which so far
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>have kept us divided. Through a united working
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>class we can force the government to tax the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>corporations, not other workers.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>A posture of defeat also ignores the struggles
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>women have made against housework and what
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>we have been able to win in rélation to this
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>work. It is no accident that after the massive
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>struggles welfare mothers waged in the 1960s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>for more money from the government—the first
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>money we have won for housework—the num¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>ber of female-headed families has dramatically
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>increased (doubling every decade) along with
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>the number of divorces, particularly among
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>women with children, and the number of young
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>women who have been able to set up indepen¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>dent households. This is not to glorify welfare.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>Welfare does not even begin to pay for all our
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>work—we need much more and we need it for
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>all of us. But it is to recognize how even a little
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>money has begun to break down some of the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>most powerful mechanisms of discipline which
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>traditionally have kept us in line.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>Pat Sweeney is an active member of the Wages For House¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>work Committee (288-8 8th Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11215)
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>and one of the founders of the Nassau County Womens
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>Liberation Center.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
