<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Grabenhorst-Randall</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>The Woman s Building
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>Terree Grabenhorst-Randall
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l2' n='N001'/>&quot;Even more important than the discovery of Columbus,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l3' n='N002'/>which we are gathered to celebrate, is the fact that the Government
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l4' n='N003'/>has just discovered women.”1 These words were voiced not by a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l5' n='N004'/>present-day feminist but by Bertha Honoré Palmer, a wealthy
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l6' n='N005'/>Chicago socialite, at the dedication ceremonies of the World’s Co¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l7' n='N006'/>lumbian Exposition in October 1892. While the Fair did indeed
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l8' n='N007'/>mark the 400th anniversary of Columbus’s discovery of the New
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l9' n='N008'/>World, more importantly it became the site of an international
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l10' n='N009'/>forum of women artists, writers, educators, scientists and craftsper¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l11' n='N010'/>sons. Government recognition, although not enthusiastic, aided the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l12' n='N011'/>construction of the Woman’s Building and the establishment of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l13' n='N012'/>Woman’s Branch of the Auxiliary Congress which served as a public
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l14' n='N013'/>podium for the discussion of women’s status and rights.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l15' n='N014'/>In fact, the very existence of the Woman’s Building can be credit-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l16' n='N015'/>ed largely to feminists active in the late 1800s. For instance, in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l17' n='N016'/>January 1890, when the United States Congress was considering
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l18' n='N017'/>establishing the Fair, Susan B. Anthony and other prominent fem¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l19' n='N018'/>inists urged the Senate to guarantee women an active role in its plan¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l20' n='N019'/>ning. As a token gesture a Board of Lady Managers was authorized,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l21' n='N020'/>and although it had as many members as the men’s Columbian
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l22' n='N021'/>Commission, the latter actually ran the Fair. Nonetheless, the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l23' n='N022'/>Woman’s Department of the Exposition, responsible for the Wo-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l24' n='N023'/>man’s Building, its contents and overall management, was legally
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l25' n='N024'/>recognized and funded by the United States Government.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l26' n='N025'/>Despite a certain second-class status, the women who par¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l27' n='N026'/>ticipated in and managed portions of the Fair wielded considerable
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l28' n='N027'/>authority. One of the major reasons for this was the presence of Ber¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l29' n='N028'/>tha Honore Palmer, President of the Board of Lady Managers, who
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l30' n='N029'/>was appointed to oversee the day-to-day operation of the Woman’s
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l31' n='N030'/>Building and the Auxiliary Congress. She was the wife of a powerful
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l32' n='N031'/>Chicago millionaire, Potter Palmer, the builder of Chicago’s famous
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l33' n='N032'/>Palmer House, who, not coincidentally, was a promoter of the Fair
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l34' n='N033'/>and one of its largest financial sponsors. Bertha Palmer, however,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l35' n='N034'/>was an extraordinary woman in her own right. Her participation in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l36' n='N035'/>the Exposition and that of other wealthy and socially prominent
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l37' n='N036'/>women, including textile designer and educator Candace Thurber
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l38' n='N037'/>Wheeler, in the Exposition’s work, helped elevate the view of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l39' n='N038'/>women’s art so that it was no longer viewed as an amateurish
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l40' n='N039'/>domestic hobby but as a serious endeavor.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l41' n='N040'/>But there was another reason for American women’s finally being
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l42' n='N041'/>included in so auspicious a gathering as a World’s Fair. With the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l43' n='N042'/>rapid rise of industrialization in America following the Civil War,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l44' n='N043'/>Washington found it politic to become officially involved with wom¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l45' n='N044'/>en’s employment in industry if not full female suffrage.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l46' n='N045'/>While critics of feminism maintained that woman’s status was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l47' n='N046'/>rooted in her economic dependence on man, one unalterable fact re-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l48' n='N047'/>mained: the rise of industrialization required a larger labor force to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l49' n='N048'/>operate mass-production machinery than could be supplied by
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l50' n='N049'/>males. Women filled that gap. Thus, the number of women working
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l51' n='N050'/>for pay outside the home doubled from four to eight million between
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l52' n='N051'/>1890 and 1910; a previously untapped economic resource was now
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l53' n='N052'/>being utilized. In addition, industrialization and invention of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l54' n='N053'/>telephone, typewriter and telegraph created the need for the office
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_3_1l55' n='N054'/>girl.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>The Industrial Revolution also had profound social implications.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>In search of jobs young women (most of them single), like young
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>men, flocked to large urban centers. Upon arriving in the city their
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>social status immediately and perceptibly changed. Young, alone
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>and economically independent, they were freed of their age-old
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>dependence on home and family. Thrown together for the first time,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>these women forged close ties of friendship, and before long discov-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>ered by acting in consort they could be a powerful political force.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>One of their very first actions was to agitate for the right to vote,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>which was then denied them.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>The Woman’s Department was, from the outset, plagued with
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>difficulties. As work progressed on the Fair, the government backed
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>away from its original commitment to the Woman’s Building and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>individual states had to assume the responsibility for funding its
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>various exhibits. As a result, the Woman’s Building, one of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l16' n='N016'/>smallest at the Exposition, was granted only 8200,000 for its
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l17' n='N017'/>construction out of an estimated total of $12,700,000 budgeted for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l18' n='N018'/>grounds and buildings. In addition, most of the women artists rep¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l19' n='N019'/>resented in the Woman’s Building not only contributed their time
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l20' n='N020'/>and work free, but also had to absorb shipping and installation costs
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l21' n='N021'/>for displays of their work; men whose works were commissioned
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l22' n='N022'/>were usually paid in advance.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l23' n='N023'/>Other forms of blatant discrimination continually hampered the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l24' n='N024'/>efforts of the Board of Lady Managers and eventually determined
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l25' n='N025'/>the use to which the Woman’s Building was put. The building was
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l26' n='N026'/>not originally intended to be used for exhibit space; it was planned
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l27' n='N027'/>as the headquarters for women connected with the Fair. But, as
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l28' n='N028'/>Bertha Palmer noted: the building . . . has been forced into that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l29' n='N029'/>relation with the rest of the Exposition because of the partial exclu¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l30' n='N030'/>sion of women elsewhere.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l31' n='N031'/>Bertha Palmer summarized the difficulties the women had en-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l32' n='N032'/>countered in an address she delivered at the opening of the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l33' n='N033'/>Woman’s Building: “We have been obliged to march with peace of-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l34' n='N034'/>ferings lest hostile motives be ascribed to us.”3 She went on to ad¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l35' n='N035'/>vocate the liberation of women and made it clear that the Woman’s
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l36' n='N036'/>Building and its contents represented opportunities to advance the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l37' n='N037'/>cause of women’s rights, especially those of working women. She
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l38' n='N038'/>said, perhaps with tongue in cheek:
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l39' n='N039'/>Without touching upon politics, suffrage, or other irrelevant is-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l40' n='N040'/>sues, this unique organization of women for women will devote itself
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l41' n='N041'/>to the formation of a public sentiment which will favor woman’s in-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l42' n='N042'/>dustrial equality, secure for her work the consideration and respect
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l43' n='N043'/>which it deserves, and establish her importance as an economic fac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l44' n='N044'/>tor. To this end it will endeavor to obtain and install in these
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l45' n='N045'/>buildings exhibits showing the value of her contributions to the in-
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l46' n='N046'/>dustries, sciences and arts, as well as statistics giving the proportion¬
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l47' n='N047'/>ate amount of her work in every country.&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l48' n='N048'/>In order to fulfill this commitment, the organizers included as
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l49' n='N049'/>part of the exhibition records of women’s professional and economic
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l50' n='N050'/>status, reports from social, industrial and cooperative associations
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l51' n='N051'/>and a compilation of statistics on women’s legal, social, political and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l52' n='N052'/>economic status in countries throughout the world. It was the aim of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l53' n='N053'/>the Board to see that this information was “. . . placed on record as
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>public documents among the archives of every country.”5 The
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>Woman’s Department further supplied information to women on
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>employment possibilities and training. It was the first time that such
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>a comprehensive survey of women’s activities and conditions in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>every part of the world had been made. The overall impact of this
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>contribution still has not been fully evaluated.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>Another far-reaching and innovative idea was the Children’s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>Building. It was conveniently located next to the Woman’s Building
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>and provided a place for women to leave their children safely in the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>hands of a trained staff for a small fee while they viewed the exhibits
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>at the Fair. The Children’s Building contained a large gymnasium,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>a library, a workshop, a nursery and several other departments. The
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>workshop contained every kind of machine and mechanical device,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>giving both boys and girls an opportunity to learn how to use tools
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>and develop their mechanical abilities. As such, it is probably the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>earliest example of a day-care center. Like other projects organized
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>by women at the Fair, the Children’s Building was given no money
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>by the Exposition authorities and was completely financed by the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>Board of Lady Managers.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>The architect for the Woman’s Building was Sophia G. Hayden.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>In 1890, she became the first woman to complete the four-year
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>course in architecture (with honors) from the Massachusetts In¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>stitute of Technology. Hayden’s design was selected from twelve
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>others and she began supervision of the building’s construction in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>July 1891. She designed her building in the neoclassic style which
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>was enjoying a revival at the time and was required by the Exposi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>tion committee.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>The elaborately ornamental Hall of Honor formed the spine of the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>structure and rose to the building’s full two-story height. Sixty-seven
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>and a half feet wide and 200 feet long, it was topped by a skylight.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>The Hall of Honor was reserved for the core of the fine arts exhibits
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>in the Woman’s Building. The major decoration of this important
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>room was left to six American artists: Mary Cassatt, Mary Mac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>Monnies, Lucia-Fairchild Fuller, Amanda Brewster Sewall, Rosina
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>Emmett Sherwood and Lydia Emmett.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>Sherwood and Emmett were sisters who had both studied with
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>William Merritt Chase at the Art Students’ League in New York
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l38' n='N038'/>and later in Paris at the Julian Academy. Sherwood’s mural was ti¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l39' n='N039'/>tled, “The Republic’s Welcome to Her Daughters.” Her sister’s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l40' n='N040'/>mural, “Music, Art and Literature, showed the three disciples
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l41' n='N041'/>personified by three female figures. Fairchild-Fuller, a Bostonian,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l42' n='N042'/>had also studied with Chase at the League and was a successful min¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l43' n='N043'/>iature painter. Her mural, “The Women of Plymouth, depicted
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l44' n='N044'/>Pilgrim women and children engaged in domestic chores. Sewall
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l45' n='N045'/>was born in upstate New York, studied at Cooper Union and with
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l46' n='N046'/>Chase and William Sartain at the League in Paris. For her mural,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l47' n='N047'/>Women in Arcadia, she was awarded a bronze medal by the Co-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l48' n='N048'/>lumbian Commission.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l49' n='N049'/>The two most famous women artists participating in the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l50' n='N050'/>building’s decoration were MacMonnies and Cassatt. MacMon-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l51' n='N051'/>nies’s 60-foot mural, “Primitive Woman,” located on the north tym¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l52' n='N052'/>panum of the Hall of Honor, was one of the largest ever painted by a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l53' n='N053'/>woman. It was divided into three sections that illustrated the roles of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_3_1l54' n='N054'/>ancient women as wives, mothers and workers. Cassatt’s commis¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>sion to decorate the south tympanum on the subject of modern
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>woman was her first commission in America and her first attempt at
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>mural decoration. Cassatt’s space was identical to MacMonnies’s,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>but Cassatt divided her mural into three separate panels with three
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>allegorical themes. The central and largest panel was “Young
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>Women Plucking the Fruits of Knowledge and Science.” In the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>right-hand panel were three women who personified the “Arts,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>Music and Dancing, and in the left-hand panel were “Young Girls
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>Pursuing Fame.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>Also decorating the Hall of Honor were murals and paintings,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>etchings and engravings contributed by American, German, Austri-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>an, English, French and Spanish women. In addition, sculpture
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>and numerous handicrafts were displayed. There was even a bas¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>relief entitled “Ophelia” made by the famous French actress, Sarah
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>Bernhardt. Finally, names of important women from around the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l16' n='N016'/>world in the arts, sciences, literature and other disciplines were
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l17' n='N017'/>recorded.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l18' n='N018'/>Running along the easterly side of the Hall of Honor were rooms
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l19' n='N019'/>largely devoted to the technological side of women’s contributions.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l20' n='N020'/>Among these rooms were two Scientific rooms, an Inventions room
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l21' n='N021'/>and an Educational room.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l22' n='N022'/>Passing through the corridors, the visitor could then enter the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l23' n='N023'/>Northern Pavilion (on the north side of the building) or the South-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l24' n='N024'/>ern Pavilion (on the south side). In the Northern Pavilion were ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l25' n='N025'/>hibits from countries such as Russia, Australia and England. The
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l26' n='N026'/>Russian section was especially notable. A remarkable reproduction
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l27' n='N027'/>of a Byzantine gate of the twelfth century marked the entrance. It
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l28' n='N028'/>was made of oak and joined together without a single nail. The
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l29' n='N029'/>wood surface was overlaid with gold leaf. The work was designed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l30' n='N030'/>and constructed solely by Russian women. Exhibits of cottage
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l31' n='N031'/>industries from Scotland and Ireland included hand-knitted stock¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l32' n='N032'/>ings and gloves, shawls and ecclesiastical vestments, as well as many
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l33' n='N033'/>fine examples of embroidery and needlework. Examples of uniquely
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l34' n='N034'/>Irish lacemaking techniques could be seen in displays of Irish point
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l35' n='N035'/>lace, Limerick lace and Carrickmacross lace. The Northern
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l36' n='N036'/>Pavilion also included exhibits of stained glass designs, wallpaper
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l37' n='N037'/>and silk designs, book-cover designs and book illustrations, con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l38' n='N038'/>tributed by American and foreign women.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l39' n='N039'/>The most notable exhibit in the Northern Pavilion was that of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l40' n='N040'/>American Applied Arts. The handicraft contributions (specifically,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l41' n='N041'/>needlework and embroidery) of the Associated Artists Society, one
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l42' n='N042'/>of the first American schools of embroidery and design, as well as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l43' n='N043'/>the woven textiles and tapestries, were among the best examples of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l44' n='N044'/>handwork in the Woman’s Building. This exhibit had been organ¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l45' n='N045'/>ized by Candace Thurber Wheeler, who lent her considerable ar-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l46' n='N046'/>tistic and managerial talents to the Woman’s Building and oversaw
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l47' n='N047'/>its interior decoration. It is fair to say that the American renaissance
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l48' n='N048'/>in embroidery and needlework was initiated and largely affected by
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l49' n='N049'/>Wheeler. Thanks to her perseverance and clout, needlework ex-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l50' n='N050'/>hibits at the Columbian Exposition were no longer predominantly
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l51' n='N051'/>English or European, as they had been in the Centennial Exposition
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l52' n='N052'/>seventeen years earlier.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l53' n='N053'/>Walking along the Loggia for a breath of fresh air and a fine
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_4_1l54' n='N054'/>overall view of the Exposition grounds, the visitor could then tour
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>the Southern Pavilion which was devoted to exhibits of lacemaking
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>embroidery, fan painting, jewelry, silverware, carved wood, leather
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>and fans. These exhibits came from France, Italy, Mexico, Japan,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>Spain, Belgium, Austria, Germany, Sweden and Norway, as well as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>far-off places such as Siberia, Siam, Ceylon, Brazil and the Cape of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>Good Hope. One of the most popular exhibits was that organized by
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>the Japanese Woman’s Commission. Two rooms of a typical
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>Japanese dwelling were carefully reproduced. The inclusion of such
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>details as fine inlaid boxes, polished steel mirrors and a woman’s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>boudoir gave the spectator a true sense of having actually visited a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>Japanese home. Another exhibit of special interest was the collec¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>tion of lace sent by Queen Margherita of Italy which traced the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>history of lacemaking in that country as well as in all other lace¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>making countries.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>The elevator, a welcome feature of the building at this point of the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>tour, would then whisk the visitor to the gallery floor of the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>building, which contained exhibits primarily from the United
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>States.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>Running along the east wall of the gallery floor were the Californ¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>ia, Cincinnati, Kentucky and Japanese rooms (the Japanese exhib¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>ited here as well as in the Southern Pavilion). The California room
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>was warmly inviting with its ceilings, doors and wainscoting all
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>made of rich, mellow redwood. The room was decorated with
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>stained glass designed and executed by American women.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>The Cincinnati room, the largest and most important room of this
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>section of the gallery, served as the Managers’ Drawing Room. Its
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>display of pottery executed by Cincinnati women underscored
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>women’s unique contributions to the craft. Of special interest was
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>Rookwood Pottery, an adaptation of the art nouveau style with flat,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>linear floral patterns and varied glazes—all of which had gained
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>Rookwood an international reputation for fine ceramics craftsman¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>ship. In addition to examples of Rookwood Pottery decorated by
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>the Rookwood Pottery founder, Mrs. Maria Longworth Nichols
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>Storer, there were pieces created by members of the Cincinnati Pot-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>tery Club. M. Louise McLaughlin, founder of the Pottery Club in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l3' n='N003'/>1879, had developed an unusual method of underglaze painting and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l4' n='N004'/>“Losanti Ware,” a hard porcelain with a feldspathic glaze fired at a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l5' n='N005'/>low temperature. Examples of her work were included in the Cin¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l6' n='N006'/>cinnati room exhibit.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l7' n='N007'/>Perhaps the most important room, next to the Hall of Honor, was
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l8' n='N008'/>the Library, located directly opposite the Cincinnati room on the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l9' n='N009'/>west side of the gallery. The interior decoration, including the dark,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l10' n='N010'/>carved oak bookcases, was the work of Candace Thurber Wheeler,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l11' n='N011'/>Dora Wheeler Keith, her daughter, decorated the Library’s ceiling.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l12' n='N012'/>She chose an allegorical theme appropriate to the room: a male
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l13' n='N013'/>figure represented Science; Literature was personified by a woman
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l14' n='N014'/>standing beside Science, and Imagination, also a female figure,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l15' n='N015'/>stood between the two, symbolizing the reconciliation and binding
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l16' n='N016'/>of one to the other. More importantly, the Library contained over
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l17' n='N017'/>7,000 volumes of American and foreign women’s writings (including
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l18' n='N018'/>such great authors as Jane Austen, the Bronte sisters, George Eliot,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l19' n='N019'/>the poetess Harriet Monroe, Louisa Alcott and Susan B. Anthony—
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l20' n='N020'/>making it the largest such collection at that time. Two Records
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l21' n='N021'/>rooms flanked the Library and contained statistics of woman’s work
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l22' n='N022'/>in several countries.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l23' n='N023'/>Also located on this side of the gallery was the English Training
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l24' n='N024'/>School for Nurses. It was a model of a room for the instruction of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l25' n='N025'/>nurses and contained all sorts of medical and surgical instruments
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l26' n='N026'/>along with portraits of women who were famous for their contri¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l27' n='N027'/>butions to nursing and medicine, such as Florence B. Nightingale.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l28' n='N028'/>After visiting the English Training School for Nurses, the fair¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l29' n='N029'/>goer could walk through the north corridor to the Assembly Room,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l30' n='N030'/>which was used for meetings, lectures and concerts, and then on to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l31' n='N031'/>the large Model Kitchen. The kitchen was equipped with the most
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l32' n='N032'/>modern appliances then available and staffed with teachers who in¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l33' n='N033'/>structed women in the science of preparing nutritional foods and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l34' n='N034'/>even in preparing Indian corn.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l35' n='N035'/>The visitor might pleasantly end the tour by resting and dining in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l36' n='N036'/>the garden cafe of the Woman’s Building—a quiet oasis in green in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l37' n='N037'/>which, reputedly, the best food at the Fair was to be found.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l38' n='N038'/>The significance of the exhibits of the Woman’s Building was
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l39' n='N039'/>multifaceted. By making the achievements of many fine women art-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l40' n='N040'/>ists and craftswomen more widely known, they corrected miscon¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l41' n='N041'/>ceptions about women’s artistic abilities and made it clear that
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l42' n='N042'/>women held an important place in the history of the arts. In addi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l43' n='N043'/>tion, the Woman’s Building provided a forum for presenting the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l44' n='N044'/>theme of the changing roles of women. Facts were available for
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l45' n='N045'/>public and personal consumption, and as they cut across social and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l46' n='N046'/>class barriers, must have had a considerable impact on both sexes.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l47' n='N047'/>For women, especially, the new sense of history, pride and ac¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l48' n='N048'/>complishment alone was worth the long and arduous struggle to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l49' n='N049'/>make their building and its contents public.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l1' n='N001'/>1. Mary Oldham Eagle Kavanaugh, ed., The Congress of Women, Chicago,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l2' n='N002'/>1894, p. 106.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l3' n='N003'/>2. Kavanaugh, p. 125.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l4' n='N004'/>3. Kavanaugh, p. 112.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l5' n='N005'/>4. Ibid.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_5_1l6' n='N006'/>5. Ibid.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_7_1l1' n='N001'/>Terree Grabenhorst-Randall is a Ph.D. candidate at the City University Graduate
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_7_1l2' n='N002'/>Center in New York. Her field is twentieth-century American art, and she works in the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_7_1l3' n='N003'/>slide library.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
