<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1"/>
         <p>
				On Never Quite Being Good Enough:
				Legal Institutional Racism, Sexism and Elitism
				Yvonne A. Flowers
				O 1979
			</p>
         <p>
				For those of us
				who were imprinted with fear
				like a faint line in the center of our foreheads
				learning to be afraid with our mother's milk
				for by this weapon
				this illusion of some safety to be found
				the heavy-footed hoped to silence us
				for all of us
				this instant and this triumph
				we were never meant to survive
				— Audre Lorde, “440 Litany for Survival"
			</p>
         <p>
				As the curtain of economic scarcity drops
				over our daily lives, Black and other Third
				World women are running smack into the brick
				wall of legal institutional racism and sexism.
				We are being told, "You do not qualify to do
				the jobs you want to do. You do not meet the
				criteria for what is good enough." After the
				sixties and the women's movement, tokenism
				and fair employment legislation, we are still
				being squeezed out of making money, making
				decisions and having control over our lives.
				White folks are still telling us that we don't
				measure up.
				In high school during the forties, 1 was told
				by my advisor that ! was a C student and would
				always be, so 1 shouldn’t even bother to go to
				college. Coming from the big white lady who is
				supposed to know about these things, on some
				level, 1 believed her. There were no role
				models, Black women or men or other Third
				World people teaching there to make me think
				otherwise. 1 was well into my thirties before
				began to get out from under the impact of
				those words from the authorities: "you're not
				good enough."
				Well, 1 went to college twice. Once to under¬
				graduate school for a B.A. and again to
				graduate school to become an occupational
				therapist. No role models there to assuage my
				doubts about any Black women being good
				enough. And now 1 teach in college and often
				think, "See, Mrs. Murphy didn’t know what
				she was talking about in 1947"'...until the
				issue of my tenure put me right back in touch
				with the question of "never quite being good
				enough."
			</p>
         <p>
				Today, legal institutional racism and sexism
				continue to operate. Sometimes it is blatant, at
				other times more subtle, but rarely do we hear
				it publicly challenged these days. And if so, the
				old cries "racist and sexist"' are usually dead
				news by the next day. Discrimination in insti¬
				tutions does not necessarily occur by conscious
				intent or personal prejudice against a group.
				But racism, ethnic and language group dis¬
				crimination, sexual prejudice and discrimination
				as to gender and sexual orientation, and elitism
				as to educational or economic class are a part
				of every institution in America. Ageism and all
				the other "isms"' are practiced there too. We
				are told to believe it has gone away.
				In most institutions, racism is fostered and
				nurtured by middle-aged white men who have
				the inclination and the power to hire and retain
				those persons who are exactly like themselves,
				i.e., "middle-aged white men," and exclude all
				others. This is especially true where critical de¬
				cisions are made, and future directions and
				strategies are planned. You may be included if
				you can prove that you can think and act exact¬
				ly like a middle-aged white man. (Among Black
				folks we call them “Oreo"' cookies—black on
				the outside and white on the inside.)
				Some women are a kind of “Oreo" too. That
				is, male-identified women. Women on the out¬
				side and men on the inside where their value
				system has incorporated all the sexist attitudes
				of men. These women may or may not look like
				men. They may or may not be lesbian women;
				more than likely they are not. The phenomenon
				of identification with the aggressor, or the op¬
				pressor as Paulo Frere defines it, does not end
			</p>
         <p>
				31
			</p>
         <p>
				This content downloaded from
				134.82.70.63 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:19:44 UTC
				to https: //about. jstor.org/terms
			</p>
         <pb n="2"/>
         <p>
				there. We find it among all the "isms,"
				closeted"' homosexuals who are really homo¬
				phobic, older persons who are on the top and
				will not hire their peers or their seniors, etc.
				Many of these people make it to middle man¬
				agement positions, assisting the boss, over¬
				seers, keeping the “niggers"' in line with even
				more ferociousness than the boss himself. We
				frequently see through their appearance be¬
				cause they feel like “the man.
				The message to us is always "'you're not
				good enough"' and "'you don’t measure up to
				the job." But you can't measure up, because
				who designed the very ruler by which you are
				being measured? Certainly it wasn’t no little
				Black girls. White men have set all the criteria
				for who and what is good enough. Women,
				African-Americans and other Third World peo¬
				ple, the young, the elderly and the handi¬
				capped have had no input into those criteria
				that measure them, and have had little, if any,
				chance to meet them. For have they had the
				very same opportunities that are offered by
				money, skin color privilege, education, self¬
				esteem, etc., that white men have had?
				And if one happens to meet the criteria, that
				is also no insurance for facts can be distorted,
				criteria ignored, behind the scene manipula¬
				tions can occur and technicalities are often
				raised; all done to ensure those with the power
				protection from the "others"' and to stamp the
				others"' as not quite good enough.
				So we don’t get to make the rulers. If so, we
				might make it an 11-inch "foot"' ruler or a 13-
				inch “foot"' ruler and middle-aged white men
				might not fit. They might not meet the new
				criteria. They might be short on or lacking in
				spirit or humility, be overconfident and/or poor
				managers. Look around our world. What a
				mess they have made. Look at the output of
				middle-aged white men in charge of govern¬
				ment, energy, health, inflation, etc., and one
				can see they are certainly very short on prob¬
				em-solving skills.
				When you step back and take a good look at
				who is making money off of whom, these mid¬
				dle-aged white men and their agents look like
				pimps. In ever-increasing numbers, at least in
				the urban areas, Third World people and
				women are consuming the services of the
				health and education industries. One might say
				these men are pimping off us. This seems
				especially true in the so-called alternative
				institutions and programs that were created
				from the aftermath of the “revolution," "riots,'
				demands and court actions of the sixties. These
				same institutions quietly slipped back into
				subtle racist and sexist politics in the guise of a
				need for financial and economic feasibility. And
				those who did make it into the inner sanctum
				go the way of “the last hired and the first
				fired.'
			</p>
         <p>
				Well, we must consider what to do about it.
				One thing, we must begin to get our focus
				clear. We don’t have to feel bad when they say
				we don’t fit. We are not incompetent and must
				get beyond feeling like a "fraud"' in their (our)
				work spaces or feeling guilty about our supposed
				failures. Remember their attitudes say more
				about them than they say about us. They are
				the ones with the problem.
				Well, what about the endless process of
				qualifying"' to meet their standards? Well, we
				can keep on qualifying until we get sick of it.
				Getting the necessary credentials is costly and
				time-consuming and never a guarantee. But
				while doing so, we ought to be careful that we
				do not become male-identified or "whitecized
				as Sylvia Vitale says. Take measures to
				counteract that phenomenon. Take strong doses
				of the antidote like Black and Third World
				Studies, women's studies, and humanistic
				studies so that you know who you are.
				We can set our own criteria and standards.
				When working alone and together we discover
				our own values and our own styles and know
				they are no less valid than those of the
				European patriarchy. We can be proud of our
				own when they feel “right." Yes we can get
				angry with the man and tell ’bout himself.
				Rage is an appropriate and necessary reaction
				to oppression which blocks our need for safety,
				mastery and self-actualization. It's about living
				not just surviving. And laugh at him too, with
				the silly business of covering up his inade¬
				quacies with face-saving arrogance. And above
				all don’t forget the revolution has just begun.
				Get ready to struggle, you do qualify for that.
			</p>
         <p>
				Zora Neale Hurston. 1901-1960. Novelist, folklorist and
				anthropologist who had more books published than any
				other Black American woman and epitomizes the African
				American woman's struggle “to be good enough." Photo
				credit: Carl Van Vetchen, 1935.
			</p>
         <p>
				32
			</p>
         <p>
				This content downloaded from
				134.82.70.63 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:19:44 UT(
				All use subject to https: //about.jstor.org/terms
			</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
