<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Heresies Project</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>A Bucknell Production</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1"/>
         <head><title>Feminist Abstract Art—A Political Viewpoint </title>
         	<lb/>
         	<persName>Harmony Hammond</persName> </head>
         	<p>There are many articles written on feminist
				art which try to pinpoint and define a feminist
				sensibility. Few of these articles go beyond the
				recognition that feminist art is based on the
				personal experiences of women by beginning to
				question its larger political implications and the
				roleitplaysin feminist revolution. Most articles
				originating from the art world tend to be formal
				descriptive attempts at documenting what
				women are doing, and do not attempt a femi-
				nist analysis of function and meaning.
				In a reactionary escape from formalist criti-
				cism, most movement writing on feminist art
				deals with political issues, but lacks any real
				understanding of the creative process, how it
				functions for the artist and how it affects form
				and content. Without such an understanding it
				is impossible to evaluate the work as art. While
				feminist poets and writers comment on each
				other's work and write of their own processes,
				we visual artists tend to remain silent and let
				others do the writing for us. Our silence contri-
				butes to a lack of dialogue between artist and
				audience, to the lack of criticism from a femi-
				nist perspective, and ultimately to the misinter-
				pretation of our work.
				In this article I wish to focus on abstract art
				and show that it can have a feminist basis and
				therefore be political. Feminists are not only
				people to attempt political or revolutionary art,
				but because certain ideas and issues occur over
				and over, they are of interest to us and worth
				exploring. I will focus on one area of abstract
				art by discussing concepts of marking and lan-
				guage in feminist drawing and painting-to
				show its origin, meaning, and political potential.
				In "Prime Time: Art and Politics" 1 Alexa Free-
				man and Jackie MacMillan look at how art is
				viewed in this capitalist, patriarchal society
				and criticize activists for reacting too quickly
				and overlooking the revolutionary potential of
				art. However, they in turn react to male estab-
				ishment myths about abstract (non-representa-
				tional) art and exclude it from feminist and
				political potential. They view abstract art as
				private expression which is not understandable
				or analyzable to the audience, and therefore
				irrelevant to feminist political goals. Thus they
				incorrectly see elitism as a pre-condition of
				abstract art, rather than realizing that this is
				how abstract art has been used by men as a
				defense mechanism against the alienation of
				their own capitalist system; that as well as fur-
			</p>
         <p>thering the myth of artist as alienated and
				isolated genius, abstract art has offered an illu-
				sion of objectivity. Such notions suggest that
				the content of one's work can be separated from
				one's political beliefs. By sponsoring interna-
				tional exhibitions showing apolitical abstract
				paintings by former Communist Party members,
				the C.I.A. (via the Museurn of Modern Art) has
				sought to impress other nations with the cultur-
				al freedom of the U.S.A. The way in which
				Abstract Expressionist art was defined and de-
				veloped by the artists and then used by others
				to further cold war politics in the fifties is only
				one example of the manipulation of abstract art
				to create the illusory separation of art and poli-
				tics. 2 Thus when women continue to respond to
				abstract art as "apolitical," they are reinforc-
				ing and maintaining myths established by men.
				The Freeman/MacMillan article is typical in
				its analysis of art and politics. Abstract art has
				become taboo for most artists who consider
				themselves political feminists. Because of the
				history outlined above, it is difficult to deter-
				mine abstract painting's relationship to feminist
				ideology. There are radical feminists who are
				making abstract art. Radical feminism operates
				from the belief that women as a class are op-
				pressed, and that a mass political women's
				movement is necessary to overthrow male su-
				premacy. 3 Therefore, we might ask, how are
				the visions of radical feminists analyzed and
				portrayed in this art?
				It is necessary to break down the myths and
				fears surrounding abstract art and make it
				understandable. Women — artists and non-
				artists-need to talk about art, and talking
				about abstract art need not be more difficult
				than discussing portraits, nudes, vaginas, or
				whatever. Every work of art is understandable
				on many different levels. It is by talking about
				our work and work processes that we will not
				only begin to develop a new language for inter-
				preting abstract art, but also to integrate this
				work with society. This language, which I see
				evolving from consciousness-raising techniques,
				will be able to be shared with any woman,
				regardless of class background. For artists, such
				a dialogue with the audience is essential, as it
				offers valuable feedback for the development
				of our art.
				I want to reclaim abstract art for women and
				transforrn it on our own terms. It is interesting
				to note that much of women's past creativity, as
			</p>
         <pb n="2"/>
         <p>well as the art by women of non-western cul-
				tures, has been abstract. I'm thinking of the
				incredible baskets, pottery, quilts, afghans, lace
				and needlework women have created. Many of
				the motifs used were based on "the stitch" it-
				self. The repetition and continuity of the stitch
				or weaver formed the individual shape and also
				the pattern resulting from its repetition. Usually
				these motifs and patterns were abstract and
				geometric. Patricia Mainardi points out that
				they had specific meaning for the women who
				made them, and in a sense formed a visual
				language in themselves:
				in designing their quilts, women not only made
				beautiful and functional objects, but expressed
				their own convictions on a wide variety of sub-
				jects in a language for the most part compre-
				hensible only to other women. In a sense, this
				was a secret language among women, for as
				the story goes, there was more than one man of
				Tory political persuasion who slept unknowing-
				ly under his wife's 'Whig Rose' quilt. Women
				named quilts for their religious beliefs...or
				their politics-at a time when women were not
				allowed to vote. The 'Radical Rose' design,
				which women made during the CIvil War, had
				a black center for each rose and was an expres-
				sion of sympathy with the slaves. 4
				As we examine some contemporary abstract
				art by women, it is important to develop a sense
				of identity and connection with our own past
				creativity rather than that of the oppressor who
				has claimed "fine art" and "abstract art" for
				himself. In fact, the patriarchal putdown of
				"decorative" traditional art and "craft" has out-
				right racist, classist, and sexist overtones. Eliza-
				beth Weatherford states:
				Art history assigns creative products to two
				categories -fine arts and crafts-and then cer-
				tifies as legitimate only the fine arts, thereby
				excluding those creative traditions of primitive
				people, peasants, women, and many other
				groups outside the mainstream of Western
				history. 5
				Until recently, decorative art, or craft tech-
				niques and materials, have been valid only as
				sources for contemporary male artists. While
				women working with these ideas, techniques,
				and materials have been ignored (Ann Wilson
				first painted on quilts in 1958) or put down for
				doing "womens work," men like Shields,
				Oldenburg, Stella, and Noland are hailed as
				innovative. But times have changed. Today
				many female artists are connecting to a long
				line of creativity by proudly referring to wom-
				en's traditional arts in their own work. They are
				recording the ritual of women's artmaking both
				in the past and the present, thereby reflecting a
				feminist concern not only with the end product
				but with the dally process and function of mak-
			</p>
         <p>ing art. Sewing techniques and materals as
				both process and content are used in a variety
				of ways in the abstract works of Sarah Draney,
				Pat Lasch, Nina Yankowitz, Paula Tavins, Patsy
				Norvell, Rosemary Mayer, and many other wom-
				en. Barbara Kruger says that she first learned to
				crochet and sew when she decided that these
				techniques could be used to make art. 6 For
				women, the meaning of sewing and knotting is
				"connecting" —connecting the parts of one's
				life, and connecting to other women-creating
				a sense of community and wholeness. Other
				women, drawing on women's traditional arts,
				make specific painterly reference to decoration
				and craft. Miriam Schapiro utilizes remnants of
				fabric, lace, and ribbon along with handker-
				chiefs and aprons in large collages, thus making
				the very material of women's lives the subject of
				her art. Joyce Kozloff and Mary Gregoriadis ex-
				plore decoration as fine art, basing their paint-
				ings on the abstract patterning of Islamic archi-
				tecture and tiles, Tantric art, Caucasian rugs,
				and Navaho weaving.
				The way many women talk about their work is
				revealing, in that it often denies formal art rhet-
				oric. Women tend to talk first about their per-
				sonal associations with the piece, and then
				about how these are implemented through vis-
				ual means; in other words, how successful the
				piece is in its own terms. This approach to art
				and to discussing art has developed from the
				consciousness-raising experience. It deals pri-
				marily with the work itself, what it says and how
				it says it-rather than with an imposed set of
				esthetic beliefs.
				In her excellent catalogue introduction to
				"Changes," an exhibition by Betsy Damon and
				Carole Fisher, Kathryn C. Johnson comments
				that "intent" is most important when defining
				feminist art. She states that it is "a powerful
				oneness of subject and content" that makes
				certain work feminist:
				...Their work both is and tells about the pain
				of their life experiences. It is about pain and is
				painful, but does not present woman as passive
				victim. The pain is presented with deep under-
				standing of its sources and effects, and the
				anger which follows confrontation with the
				hurt.7
				Fisher writes:
				Betsy looked at the work and recognized the
				fact that I worked to survive, to keep from
				growing crazy, and to keep the pain from be-
				coming too great. She recognized the pain in
				my work instantly! This was something I had
				only come to recently recognize and acknow-
				ledge in my work. Like many women in our
				culture, I had become adept at hiding and
				covering my pain. I had gotten all the messages
				that to be vulnerable in our culture is to be
				weak and despised. 8
			</p>
         <pb n="3"/>
         <p>It is this "oneness of subject and content"
				that carries their work through feminist con-
				sciousness beyond the personal to the political.
				It is also present in abstract paintings that seem
				superficially more related to the male modernist
				tradition than to women's creativity in that they
				involve the physically expressive manipulation
				of paint on a two-dimensional surface.
				In much of this work the reoccurring stitch of
				women's traditional artmaking becomes the re-
				petitive mark, taking on a new form as a "visual
				diary." Such works are dally records of thoughts
				and are used as such by the artists. Just as the
				weaver continues from day to day, from one
				physical and psychic location to another, mate-
				rials and dyes changing slighty, irregularities
				and tension showing, the painted marks also
				reveal daily emotional changes and tensions.
				They are a record of present feeling, a ritual
				giving in to the repetitive gesture, a language to
				reveal self-a woman's mantra.
				Jenny Snider's nervous lines recall ancient
				Chinese calligraphy, which has both a letter/
				character reference and a body/figure refer-
				ence. Her drawings are made with and are
				about her nervousness and vulnerability. She
				"is" the mark, the line. As the marks are repeat-
				ed and contained in different spaces (usually
				grids or rectangles suggesting fabric, rooms and
				houses), the quality and feeling of the line
				changes and she becomes more comfortable in
				some spaces than in others. She explores her
				self-image and feelings about her body in rela-
				tionship to other people and spaces. Snider de-
				scribes these works as "figurative." To me, it is
				the mark and its repetition that is most impor-
				tant. Her works are figurative in the sense that
				Chinese calligraphy is figurative-in having a
				direct body reference. Works are sometimes
				combined or used interchangeably with the
				markings, reinforcing Snider's commitment to
				the diaristic mode. As she says, "The words and
				lines come from the same psychological place
				and gesture and are not intended to describe or
				explain what the drawings are in terms of
				images-but rather express the fact that they
				come from a nervous hand and a yakking
				heart." Phrases such as "little sounds arose (and
				it showed)"; "Well, for one thing, never step on
				broken glass"; and "Remember when we saw
				the ocean? It was just like this, wasn't it?" tell
				where the drawing is coming from and what the
				drawing is about.
				Louise Fishman's paintings also function as a
				place for personal confrontation and as a state-
				ment directed towards other women. Earlier,
				Fishman ripped up her old paintings and recon-
				nected them by sewing and knotting them to-
				gether with fragile thread. Her past was used to
				make a statement about her present. The strips
				and connecting thread formed loose grids,
				transformed in later work to a series of strokes
				or marks repeated across the page of canvas or
			</p>
         <p>within the confines of a "particular felt shape"
				(a circle or a piece of irregularly cut masonite).
				The marks of paint, layered on top of each
				other, lead eventually to a rich sensuous sur-
				face. The top layer usually consists of strong
				marks holding the partially revealed under-
				marks to the painting surface-feelings re-
				vealed and hidden. Fishman has always talked
				about her work in terms of hiding, guilt, vul-
				nerability, anger, and personal individuation.
				In a seven-panel reversible painting on un-
				stretched canvas, Fishman deals with her feel-
				ings about her mother, also an artist. One side
				of each canvas is painted with calm strokes,
				while on the other side the marks explode into
				intensely scrawled letters reading "A letter to
				my mother about painting." Another canvas has
				the star of David and the words "I am a Jewish
				working-class dyke" scratched into the surface.
				Just as consciousness raising leads to political
				awareness; this work moves from the personal
				into the political. Titled Angry Jill, Angry Djuna,
				Angry Paula, Angry Sarah, and so on... they
				seem to be painted with the anger. When she
				made these "angry paintings" Fishman said that
				all she could feel was her rage. When she
				looked around at other women, she saw that
				they were crippled by their anger too. These
				paintings were made to force women to con-
				front it rather than letting it turn inward and
				become self-destructive. Grouped together as a
				wall of women's anger, the paintings show a
				tremendous amount of energy that can now be
				redirected towards feminist creativity and
				revolution.
				These women as well as others (Joan Snyder,
				Carla Tardi, and Pat Steir, to name a few) have
				used words and marks fairly interchangeably as
				abstract gestures with concrete feminist mean-
				ings. Words are marks and marks are words;
				their repetition becomes not only an interior
				monologue but also a dialogue with other wom-
				en. Like Damon and Fisher, these artists make
				individual feeling and experience the subject of
				their work, while the content deals with the
				difficulties and ambiguities of being a feminist
				artist in a patriarchal society.
				Their painting surfaces are often violated on
				mutilated; cut, gouged, ripped, scratched, or
				torn. The reversal of the usual additive process
				of painting refers to the violation of the tradi-
				tional painting surface and also to the physical
				and psychic violation of women. The thick paint
				applied with a palette knife in Fishman's work,
				for instance, acts both as poultice for wounds
				and cement for holding self together. In Joan
				Snyder's recent work the marks, cuts and burning
				combine with words and color to make a pas-
				sionate statement about sexuality.
				This work is certainly political. Yet Freeman
				and MacMillan, in their attempt to distinguish
				protest from political art, to show that specific
				forms are more conducive to one or another.
			</p>
         <pb n="4"/>
         <p>x
				Below: Louise Fishrnan. Angry Harrony. 1970. Acrylic and
				pastel on paper. 30" X 40". (Photo: Sarah Whitworth.)
				ssrcrnrseschit
				e    
				</p>
         <p>i
				</p>
         <p>Above: Jenny Snider. Split Scribble. 1972. Pencil on paper
				24" X 38". (Photo: Jenny Snider.)
			</p>
         <p>68
			</p>
         <pb n="5"/>
         <p>still ignore the political potential of abstraction. 9
				They accept male definitions of what art is, and
				do not deal with the evolution of a feminist
				creative process or feminist art forms. Theirs is a
				reformist approach to a revolutionary endeavor.
				I am reminded of Andrea Dworkin's "after-
				word"- "The Great Punctuation Typography
				Struggle" —in her book Woman Hating, where
				she explains how the text was altered against
				her will by the publisher's insistence on upper-
				case letters and standard punctuation. She had
				wanted the book to be as empty of convention
				as possible, to create a new form that would
				merge with the content.
				reading a text which violates standard form
				forces one to change mental sets in order to
				read. there is no distance. the new form, which
				is in some ways unfamiliar, forces one to read
				differentiy-not to read about different things,
				but to read in different ways.
				to permit writers to use forms which violate
				convention just might permit writers to devel-
				op forms which would teach people to think
				differently: not to think about different things,
				but to think in different ways. that work is not
				permitted.10
				The fact that innovative form is so feared by
				the male establishment shows that like content
				it has a power of its own. If our lives and our art
				are connected, and if "the personal is political"
				in the radical sense, then we cannot separate
				the content of our work from the form it takes.
			</p>
         <p>As abstract artists, we need to develop new
				abstract forms for revolutionary art.
				The women's work I've discussed here, and I
				include my own, is moving in this direction. We
				are not yet there. Hopefully, as we create art
				within the context of other women's art, and
				within the context of evolving feminist theory,
				we will develop a new visual language. Art in
				transition is political, for it both is our develop-
				ment and describes our development. In a sense
				we are coming out through our art, and the
				work itself is a record of the ongoing process of
				developing a feminist esthetic ideology.
			</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
