<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='67'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_4_tl_1' n='N001'/>From that moment on, she disowned the child.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_4_tl_2' n='N002'/>I was the child.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_4_tl_3' n='N003'/>Educated in suitcases, lonely without maps, 1 pressed an ear to my diary in the nights, listened
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_4_tl_4' n='N004'/>for the vague red stirrings of its heart.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_4_tl_5' n='N005'/>I could feel without looking how one town became the next, slight shift up or down on the scale
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_4_tl_6' n='N006'/>of chagrin. So this was civilization: running water and laws.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_3_tl_1' n='N001'/>I was a saleswoman. Landladies liked me, though I talked about vacuum cleaners, left
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_3_tl_2' n='N002'/>brochures in the cookie jars, gave supple demonstrations of equipment before dinner. I swept
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_3_tl_3' n='N003'/>and I sold in the wrinkles of the heartland. I called it a good life.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_3_tl_4' n='N004'/>There in the little towns darkness sighs away in the arms of each cricket. The mornings bring no
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_3_tl_5' n='N005'/>new disaster. Night comes again. The rooming house creaks with longing for its own flustered
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_3_tl_6' n='N006'/>century.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_2_tl_1' n='N001'/>l’d pile my coins along the nightstand for counting. l’d make fragile plans for the life to come.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_2_tl_2' n='N002'/>Really I thought nothing of the days that l’d passed through,
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_2_tl_3' n='N003'/>nothing of the nights that had passed over me.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_2_tl_4' n='N004'/>Ibound up my samples. The next house. The next house.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_2_tl_5' n='N005'/>&quot;Young ladies like you ’n them handy dandies, them sweepers, oughta head fer the tall times ’n
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_2_tl_6' n='N006'/>the bold times of the City.&quot; That’s what the farmers sometimes told me in the mornings when
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_2_tl_7' n='N007'/>they pushed back their cap brims, made decisions about the sun. Haw de haw haw them tall
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_2_tl_8' n='N008'/>times them bold times.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>But I could see it. The City. A line in each road there. A guitar in each doorway. I learned that
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>the blues is a bunch of fat people. I enrolled at a club for the timid. Yes that’s how I came to the
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>City. Iwas young.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>Irented a cardboard room in the quiet zone.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>Oh the tentative web of fashion spread its lace around my throat.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>Every night I pulled out from under the bed the hat box l’d painted in animals. My finery! Black
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>feathered hat. Stylish gloves small from washing. l’d hear the landlady shut the oven on her
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>frozen dinner, watch the light of the teevee dance over the walls.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>Outside the harsh things were fading along the Avenue. I called out “Carumbal Muchachos!&quot; in
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>the streets. Me without other words for uncertainty and joy.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_6_tl_1' n='N001'/>Cynthia Carr
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_5_tl_1' n='N001'/>Cynthia Carr wrote articles for the Chicago daily newspapers for four years and was a
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_5_tl_2' n='N002'/>member of the Lavender Woman collective. Her work appears in Amazon Quarterly&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_5_tl_3' n='N003'/>anthology, The Lesbian Reader.
				<lb facs='#facs_67_tr_5_tl_4' n='N004'/>﻿64
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
