<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="null"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>"From The Lesbian Issue Collective</title>
				<author>Collective</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Heresies Issue 3: Lesbian Art and Artists</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" xmlns:fabio="https://purl.org/spar/fabio#" xmlns:bf="http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#" xmlns:cito="https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#" xmlns:org="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#">
        <rdf:Description rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/">
          <![CDATA[{
	"@context": {
		"dcterms:created": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:created"
		},
		"dcterms:issued": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:issued"
		},
		"oa:motivatedBy": {
			"@type": "oa:Motivation"
		},
		"@language": "en",
		"rdf": "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#",
		"rdfs": "http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#",
		"as": "http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#",
		"cwrc": "http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#",
		"dc": "http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/",
		"dcterms": "http://purl.org/dc/terms/",
		"foaf": "http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/",
		"geo": "http://www.geonames.org/ontology#",
		"oa": "http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#",
		"schema": "http://schema.org/",
		"xsd": "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#",
		"fabio": "https://purl.org/spar/fabio#",
		"bf": "http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#",
		"cito": "https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#",
		"org": "http://www.w3.org/ns/org#"
	},
	"id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BrianaPerea/heresies/main/issue03/texts/collective.xml?organization_annotation_20230202201008032",
	"type": "oa:Annotation",
	"dcterms:created": "2023-02-03T01:10:08.032Z",
	"dcterms:modified": "2023-02-03T01:10:08.032Z",
	"dcterms:creator": {
		"@id": "https://github.com/BrianaPerea",
		"@type": [
			"cwrc:NaturalPerson",
			"schema:Person"
		],
		"cwrc:hasName": "Briana Perea"
	},
	"oa:motivatedBy": "oa:identifying",
	"oa:hasTarget": {
		"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BrianaPerea/heresies/main/issue03/texts/collective.xml?organization_annotation_20230202201008032#Target",
		"@type": "oa:SpecificResource",
		"oa:hasSource": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BrianaPerea/heresies/main/issue03/texts/collective.xml",
			"@type": "dctypes:Text",
			"dc:format": "text/xml"
		},
		"oa:renderedVia": {
			"@id": "https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org",
			"@type": "as:Application",
			"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
			"schema:softwareVersion": "2.3.1"
		},
		"oa:hasSelector": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BrianaPerea/heresies/main/issue03/texts/collective.xml?organization_annotation_20230202201008032#Selector",
			"@type": "oa:XPathSelector",
			"rdf:value": "TEI/text/body/div/p[2]/orgName"
		}
	},
	"oa:hasBody": {
		"@type": "org:Organization",
		"@id": "http://dbpedia.org/resource/Heresies:_A_Feminist_Publication_on_Art_and_Politics",
		"dc:format": "text/plain"
	},
	"as:generator": {
		"@id": "https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org",
		"@type": "as:Application",
		"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
		"schema:url": "https://leaf-writer.lincsproject.ca/",
		"schema:softwareVersion": "2.3.1"
	}
}]]>
        </rdf:Description>
      </rdf:RDF></xenoData></teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="2"/>

			<head>From The Lesbian Issue Collective:</head>
			<div type="statement">
				<p>l’m a writer who struggles constantly with the urge to remain silent.</p>
				<p>And I understood our collective process as a struggle with silence. Like an
					individual isolated lesbian, we worked first on self-validation. We talked about
					the famous respected closet cases—could we get them to come out or figure some
					way to claim them. (Claiming the "great ones" is a way for a despised group to
					feel good about itself.) And we spent many many meetings doing
					consciousness-raising on what it means to be lesbian artists—talking, some of
					us, about issues we had never discussed before. My excitement in working on this
					issue of <orgName key="Heresies: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics" ref="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Heresies:_A_Feminist_Publication_on_Art_and_Politics">Heresies</orgName> centered around the hope that many lesbian artists would write
					us, share their work, and contribute to this dialogue.</p>
				<p>The standard I used in judging work was based on my wish to be inclusive—to
					present as much diversity as possible, to present clearly articulated articles
					even if I disagreed with their content.</p>
				<p>Others in the collective felt differently. This we discovered as we worked and
					worked and no longer had time just to talk to each other. We had been too busy
					when we started—discussing our similarities, our struggles, our fears, and our
					opportunities as lesbian artists—to get very far in discussing our
					differences.</p>
				<byline>Cynthia Carr</byline>
			</div>
			<div type="statement">
				<p> The only talent I bring to the lesbian collective is my sexual preference, a
					scorn of self-important pretension, a nose for drivel, and a desire to see to it
					that we say it like it is. In the past we have done ourselves and our work a
					terrible damage by lying about our experience. Driven by a need for the com-
					fort of a common political position, we have all too often allowed rhetoric to
					pass for truth. Seeking an accommodation with the straight world, we have lied
					about our essential dif- ference. And in a spirit of loyalty we have compromised
					ourselves by supporting thinking and work which is simply bad. There is very
					little sense of humor in us. We have, by this excusable example, leaned heavily
					on many closet doors which might otherwise have sprung open. It was my hope that
					with this issue we might present truly good work by lesbians. Now, as I am about
					to be pasted up and mechanicaled, I can say that the effort has been exhausting
					and perilous. And certainly I am too close to the final product to say that we
					have succeeded.</p>
				<byline>Betsy Crowell</byline>
			</div>
			<div type="statement">
				<p> I usually think of myself as part scientist and part magician with certain
					skills that sometimes make art. Neither feminism nor lesbianism determine the
					form and content of my work yet it was only with the security of the former and
					the coming to terms with the latter (the muse) that my life and art began to be
					uniquely and overtly me.</p>
				<p>Initially I worked on the issue seeking a community to explore in depth the
					relationship of lesbianism to the artist and to discover what would happen if
					lesbian art and artists were brought together. Our editorial collective’s
					discussions were some of the most provoking and intimate that I have experi¬
					enced, yet after each I felt a sense of panic. I know that lesbians have made
					great art, I know that lesbians have been major contributors to culture, and I
					believe that lesbianism in the largest and most powerful sense of the word has
					been central not peripheral to the creative world of woman, yet I was worried
					that we wouldn’t receive sufficient "good” material. I also feared being viewed
					through society’s homophobic lenses yet I will not obscure the importance of
					lesbianism to my life and art. The muse and I are inextricably entwined and she
					is a woman. I struggle continually against any restrictions on my identity while
					questioning why this culture relentlessly omits and suppresses from discussion
					and history (even in the feminist community) the essentialness of lesbianism to
					the creative lives of women.</p>
				<p>However, there was a far deeper reason for my panic. After nine months of working
					on this issue 1 felt that our greatest unfaced demon was our own homophobia
					absorbed by all of us in different ways from a culture so homophobic that it
					ruthlessly suppresses and punished all exploration of female sexuality. This,
					coupled with the fact that lesbian artists desperately need visibility and
					credibility, gave us a common unexamined goal: visibility as matured and serious
					artists.</p>
				<p>This is only a beginning. Omitted from the issue is any dialogue that examines
					the role of lesbianism as central to women claiming full power over their
					sexuality and that such power is the root of strong and unique art. Do not for a
					minute imagine that art has to be explicitly about sex or anything so
					simplistic. I am speaking rather to the fact that a person must be able to put
					the full force of herself behind her work. Fear of being seen as sexual, fear of
					the audience, fear of offending heterosexual friends, fear of retribution for
					creating or being in the issue are only a few of the fears that are real and
					need to be faced before we can initiate a discussion that begins from a point
					that assumes that lesbianism is the key to the powerfulness of all women.</p>
				<byline>Betsy Damon</byline>
			</div>
			<div type="statement">
				<p> I wanted an issue on lesbian art and artists that would provoke me; an issue
					that would challenge all the assumptions I have about lesbians and art; an issue
					that would leave me filled with questions and with the energy with which to
					explore the questions further. I wanted lesbians to be excited and disturbed by
					what they read here, finding glimpses of themselves, as well as a sense of what
					is missing. What stories are still untold?</p>
				<p>What are lesbians? What are artists? In trying to reach a working definition of
					these two most basic questions, a sense of my own alienation from the task
					before us began to grow. This alienation came from being forced to examine
					sexuality from within a patriarchal context. A context which has created
					distinctions and categories in order to maintain its own power and privilege.
					The advantages gained by society's "power-brokers" through perpetuating and
					emphasizing the differences among racial, economic, sexual, and religious groups
					are clear. The most apparent difference between myself and a heterosexual woman;
					or myself (white, middle-class), and a Chicano working-class woman—is one of
					privilege. And for me, as a lesbian, as white, as middle-class, to maintain and
					perpetuate differences that ultimately exist only to deny privilege to some,
					seems wrong. One way I see myself as a lesbian perpetuating differences is in my
					focusing on what is and what is not a lesbian. "A woman who does not sleep with
					men." “Any woman who calls herself a lesbian.” “A woman that loves and sleeps
					with other women." “What if she sleeps with a man one time? Is she still a
					lesbian?” “What if she used to sleep with men, used to be married to one, and
					doesn’t now, but can’t predict the future?" “What is the difference between a
					woman-identified-woman and a lesbian?” It was in trying to answer questions like
					these that a sense of futility and absurdity developed. I am not a lesbian. I
					make love only with women. I am in every way what society calls a lesbian. I
					will call myself and insist upon being called a lesbian as long as something
					called a heterosexual or bisexual exists. In all probability, 1 am referring to
					a sexuality that will never exist inside me. A simple sexuality, without
					reference to another’s <pb n="3"/> gender. All of this is related to the
					question of circumstance (the time and space I live in) and therefore related to
					strategy (the means of change): an area l’m far less clear about than that of
					alienation.</p>
				<p>The dilemma for me is that regardless of how I view the role such distinctions
					serve in this society, 1 am brutally oppressed by them, as they have been
					accepted by most everyone. The fact that I am a lesbian has a profound affect on
					my life. (My job, my family, my friends always hang in the balance.) While
					believing that “heterosexual” and “lesbian" are concepts that directly serve to
					oppress us all, I know full well that as a les bian I am intentionally
					persecuted and isolated by this society. The nearest weapon to me with which to
					fight back is the taking of the concept and the word lesbian and claiming it as
					my own. My continuing to work on this issue is the result of that
					conclusion.</p>
				<p>The term “artist" serves a very similar function as the word "lesbian, though the
					specific effect upon society is quite different. The term "artist" distinguishes
					between those who are artists and those who are not. To me, an artist is a
					person who works without sham. One who works with integrity. The three most
					basic tools are a sense of self, honesty, and imagin ation. These are also three
					of the greatest enemies of this society. With good reason all three of these
					qualities are suppressed in most people at a very early age and replaced with
					subservience, confusion, and conformity. The expressing of oneself creatively
					demands not only a sense of self, honesty and imagination; but time...the time
					to listen, the time to concentrate. To have time, is one of the most important
					instances of privilege (and therefore oppression) in this society. If everyone
					had access to the same opportunities as everyone else—would there be such a
					creature as “artist?” Art would not have to speak for everyone if everyone could
					speak for themselves. Because of the privilege accorded to and/or fought for by
					artists in this society, the presumptuous assumption that some of us whether by
					genius, skill, or inspiration are better able to express "our” circumstance—I
					refuse to call myself or others “artists. Accepting money for work and
					associating with art institutions only contributes to the class system of art
					and artists. There are poets, performers, cooks and the like among us. These
					words refer to what we do. But "artist" refers to who we are in a context that
					inescapably implies a difference that furthers oppression rather than
					challenging it.</p>
				<p>The most important point to me, as it refers to this issue, is that just as the
					words “lesbian" and "artist" exist within a context and are affected by a
					circumstance, so does this issue.</p>
				<byline>Marty Pottenger </byline>
			</div>
			<div type="statement">
				<p> I want people to understand that to be a lesbian feminist is to be undefined,
					complex, groping, newly born, uncategorizable and uncategorized—i.e. not a
					“Lesbian as she has been culturally defined. I work and live for the day when
					the damnable categories of human behavior are gone. And towards this end, I am a
					part of Heresies and the lesbian issue. I don’t for a moment believe that we are
					presenting (or that we even looked for) any answers or final solutions in this
					issue. There were frightening moments when I felt that we had to say it all
					right now or never. As far as l’m concerned that's a reasonable and not too
					paranoid reaction to a culture which "gives us" NO place NO voice NO credibility
					NO trust. We just have to keep stretching, shoving, insisting, confronting, and
					pursuing whatever goals we each find most politically important and personally
					fulfilling. I find all the challenge I need in keeping my faith in the strength
					of the combined efforts of feminists and in taking seriously my individual acts
					of survival and growth in this death culture.</p>
				<p>I am committed to photography and the written word, to outrageous and humorous
					art, to women, to the chaos of reconstruction, and to publishing as a way to
					become visible, to be heard and felt by no matter how small or select an
					audience.</p>
				<byline>Su Friedrich</byline>
			</div>
			<div type="statement">
				<p> l’ve been painting for twelve years—as a feminist I feel l’ve been making “my
					own" art for six of those years—and have identified myself as a lesbian for four
					years. We continue, the work and 1, the commitment growing stronger, the
					relationship deeper. As 1 am less anxious that the work will leave me, or that
					others won’t approve, I step out of my protective world and find myself
					increasingly concerned with feminist political issues. I know how my work
					functions for me, but how does it fit into a larger social political view of
					feminism?</p>
				<p>I have to admit that, 1 came to this issue with a lot of expectations. From the
					beginning, I conceived of a whole issue devoted to lesbian art as political. I
					had hoped it would give lesbian artists visibility (especially lesbian visual
					artists who have virtually been ignored), create dialogue and community between
					lesbian visual artists and writers, remove the separation between lesbian art
					and politics, and bring an art consciousness to the lesbian community and a
					lesbian consciousness to the feminist art community. Since lesbian artists are
					so often isolated, I had hoped that in this special collective context we would
					take risks, ask questions, explore ideas, and theorize. Like a painter
					exhibiting for the first time, I wanted to show it all.</p>
				<p>Now that we have worked for almost a year on this issue, 1 have very mixed
					feelings. I think the work presented in this issue is excellent. The problem is
					not the art itself, for much strong work has been and is being made by lesbians.
					The problem is what’s missing, and what is missing is a context for the work. 1
					am disappointed that this issue has avoided controversial material and has
					continued the artistic fear of conscious political discussion. We have avoided a
					larger social political context for our work, as though it would somehow
					interfere with the work or take away from its power and meaning. To think
					politically doesn’t mean we can’t see creatively.</p>
				<p>If artmaking is an integral part of feminist revolution as l believe it is, we
					should be asking the following questions:</p>
				<list>
					<item>1. What is the role and function of lesbian feminist art in the lesbian
						movement?</item>
					<item>2. What is its role and function in the feminist movement?</item>
					<item>3. How does lesbian feminist art relate to larger social struggles for
						change in a society where lesbians and others will no longer be
						discriminated against?</item>
					<item>4. How does lesbian feminist art affect and transform culture?</item>
				</list>
				<p>The discussion of these questions is far more important than the answers. I
					believe that to be a lesbian artist is in itself political, but I also think in
					these days of homophobic backlash, that we need to push further and analyze all
					patriarchal institutions which control our lives. I feel that we have not
					allowed ourselves (because we’re artists?) to deal with important issues of
					lesbian separatism, socialist lesbians, lesbian sensibility, the relationship of
					lesbianism to feminism, and the issues of race and class. These subjects are not
					rhetorical, cliched, or irreleant to artmaking. To me they are very real and
					important in determining the quality of lesbian art.</p>
				<byline>Harmony Hammond</byline>
			</div>
			<div type="statement">
				<p> My impetus to work on this issue was rooted in the desperation and frustration I
					was experiencing working as a lesbian painter within a very circumscribed.peer
					group. 1 had begun to do what most lesbians have always done in creating a
					private world of reinforcement. I no longer believe these pockets of isolated
					support groups can bear the strain of what it means to be a lesbian in a culture
					predicated on misogyny and homophobia. This issue was an attempt to seek out
					lesbian artists and publicize the fact of their existence to myself, other les¬
					bians and other women. The dangers and ramifications of exposing myself and
					others in a solitary lesbian issue of a magazine whose audience and founders are
					predominately straight are inherent and menacing. But no matter what the extent
					of this issue’s token quality I believe that the content: pursue with integrity
					essential questions and possibilities facing all women.</p>
				<byline>K. Webster</byline>
			</div>
			<pb n="4"/>
			<div type="statement">
				<p> I believe we are lesbians largely because we realize on some level that the
					demands of heterosexual roles are rooted in a tradition of violence to women’s
					bodies and minds. This tradition is consciously and unconsciously ritualized; it
					is large and powerful, life determining in fact. Feminism can and must help
					alter the tradition but cannot ultimately transcend it. Some of us have tried to
					transcend it, could not, don’t believe anybody can at this time, and reject it.
					Equality is a myth that liberal feminism and theories of androgyny nourish. Self
					hatred, doubt, and homophobia on some level are operative in all our lives. In
					spite of this, and in defiance of this, I believe lesbianism is fundamentally
					about self-preservation and self-love in a culture that would have it otherwise.
					The choice to make art is directly aided and energized by such positive
					impulses.</p>
				<p>The connections between artist’s lives and their artistic creations have
					historically been acknowledged, probed and even embellished upon. However, the
					very existence of lesbiar lives has inveterately been denied. The connections
					between our lives and our work must be constructed and recognized, by ourselves,
					and eventually by others. It is essential that these connections and their
					powerful political ramifications be given credence, and a loud, loud voice.
					Despite my terror at signing my name to this magazine, my convictions are
					strengthened over and over: the presence of lesbians and lesbian artists must be
					affirmed. The third issue of Heresies is an attempt in this direction. My
					personal dedication is to all lesbian artists who understandably remain silent,
					in hopes that they won’t always have to.</p>
				<byline>Rose Fichtenholtz</byline>
			</div>
			<div type="statement">
				<p> This issue of Heresies has had a particularly difficult built-in problem.
					Heresies’ usual policy is not to print monographs of contemporary artists, but
					the invisibility of lesbian artists and the need for dialogue of every kind
					among lesbians moved us to consider altering the monograph policy in various
					ways. Essentially, because we decided to publish only lesbian-made material, the
					issue itself is monographical: Ourselves, our thought, our work.</p>
				<p>We used a discussion and voting process to determine what to publish. The
					question of inclusivity/exclusivity has been a source of trouble for us as a
					collective; it was a problem that we never resolved methodically. One direction
					that I felt the urge to follow was to print as much as we could, since this
					issue could be seen as a vehicle by which to strengthen a "women’s culture." As
					it has been defined by some women, a women’s culture is based in part on the
					principle of representation of as many of our voices as possible with the idea
					that the many voices make a beautiful choir.</p>
				<p>However, in the end I was committed to print only that material which I felt was
					most powerful. This outlook can be and has been seen as an alternative to the
					“many voices’ method of creating a women’s culture. I agree that what 1 deem
					“powerful" is colored by personal biases, some of which must be examined closely
					for their validity. But to try to reflect what was “out there” seemed foolish. I
					felt that it was more honest to print what I believe in; that is, not just what
					I agree with ideologically but what agrees with me esthetically Unfortunately
					the usual editorial message is that to deny space to something is to imply its
					worthlessness, and that, conversely, to print something is to assert its
					worth.</p>
				<p>As an editor I have reflected only my own biases and opinions. I have done so
					only with the hope that other lesbians will investigate our lives true to their
					own opinions and values—and that we will analyze our differences with an eye
					towards our diverse pasts and our collective future.</p>
				<byline>Amy Sillman</byline>
			</div>
			<div type="statement">
				<p> l’ve been a lesbian and l’ve been a painter for a long time. have little respect
					for rhetoric, politics that squeeze the life’s blood out of artists, or theories
					of lesbian sensibility or lesbian imagery formulated out of daydreams.</p>
				<p>I don’t like being isolated in this magazine because my lesbian artist sisters
					out there refuse to come out. Backlash is on its way, but we don’t even need
					backlash—we have the sanctity of the closet.</p>
				<p>l’d like to personally dedicate this issue to all the women who we know are
					lesbians and who have made it big in the last forty years—as artists, as
					dealers, and as intellectuals—for their steadfastness in the denial of their
					queerness. The starkness of their lives led me to cherish honest living and to
					search for an alternate route for making art.</p>
				<p>I want to share what 1 have learned in my twenty years of being a painter and a
					lesbian with lesbians who want a strong identity as artists. I am interested in
					work. I am first a painter. 1 am not interested in formulating politics or in
					promoting a lesbian universe. I am in this despite my doubts about the pro¬
					ductivity of collective enterprise and despite the distance it takes me from my
					work.</p>
				<byline>Louise Fishman</byline>
			</div>
			<div type="statement">
				<p> When I am making a work of art I am making it first and foremost therapeutically
					for myself, and I am alone in my studio and feeling usually very lonely. At this
					time there is only a vague sense that it is also for other women artists and
					women who like to look at art. And even when 1 have finished working on it and
					it is an expression of my own formulated and particular visual bias, it is still
					not yet complete. Women come to my studio and look at it and see things that I
					was too close to see and the painting’s meaning becomes larger. Anc still it is
					not yet finished. It seasons awhile in front of its small audiences and
					insistently sits before them and I bring people in front of it and say, “Yes,
					this is my art; this is my experience, until in some way it is recognized,
					analyzed and absorbed. Then it is finished. It is finished when it goes public,
					is recognized, given meaning.</p>
				<p>Women have managed somehow to survive in a woman- hating culture, but rarely have
					they found ways to complete expression in the culture. We know better than most
					that the personal is political because when we have insisted upon our personal
					viewpoint, when we have insisted upon our art, we have been burned, mutilated,
					raped and put away—at best ridiculed. Exposure, even sometimes to each other, is
					dangerous; fraught with memories of past violence, visions of future violence,
					the feeling that we will be considered crazy if we let others know who we are
					and what we think. We have no his torical or political context to decide which
					parts of us remain intact after suffering consistent negation and brutality.</p>
				<p>Who we choose as an audience is of vital consideration as long as exposure is
					dangerous. I sign my name to this issue with a great sense of purpose as well as
					real trepidation. Every day l am aware that people think I am crazy because I am
					a lesbian and that violence may be done to me because of it. This will continue
					long after male institutions grant us our civil rights. It will continue until
					we make the reality of our experience clear. Women have often had strength in
					the private domain, are safer there. When we have brought our experience, our
					work, our ideas to the world we have been repudiated and endangered. It is time
					to be particular and rigorous in our language and ideas, to articulate our needs
					and biases, and to insist, “Yes, this is our art; yes, this is our experience,”
					in a voice that can not be refuted.</p>
				<byline>Christine Wade</byline>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>