<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="null"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lesbian Art and Community</title>
            <author>Marguerite Tupper Elliot</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadsworth</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>Heresies Issue #3: Lesbian Art and Artists</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   <xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" xmlns:fabio="https://purl.org/spar/fabio#" xmlns:bf="http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#" xmlns:cito="https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#" xmlns:org="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#">
        <rdf:Description rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/">
          <![CDATA[{
	"@context": {
		"dcterms:created": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:created"
		},
		"dcterms:issued": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:issued"
		},
		"oa:motivatedBy": {
			"@type": "oa:Motivation"
		},
		"@language": "en",
		"rdf": "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#",
		"rdfs": "http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#",
		"as": "http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#",
		"cwrc": "http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#",
		"dc": "http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/",
		"dcterms": "http://purl.org/dc/terms/",
		"foaf": "http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/",
		"geo": "http://www.geonames.org/ontology#",
		"oa": "http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#",
		"schema": "http://schema.org/",
		"xsd": "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#",
		"fabio": "https://purl.org/spar/fabio#",
		"bf": "http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#",
		"cito": "https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#",
		"org": "http://www.w3.org/ns/org#"
	},
	"id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/elliot.xml?person_annotation_20230209211718232",
	"type": "oa:Annotation",
	"dcterms:created": "2023-02-10T02:17:18.232Z",
	"dcterms:modified": "2023-02-10T02:17:18.232Z",
	"dcterms:creator": {
		"@id": "https://github.com/Mayawadhwa",
		"@type": [
			"cwrc:NaturalPerson",
			"schema:Person"
		],
		"cwrc:hasName": "Maya Wadhwa"
	},
	"oa:motivatedBy": "oa:identifying",
	"oa:hasTarget": {
		"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/elliot.xml?person_annotation_20230209211718232#Target",
		"@type": "oa:SpecificResource",
		"oa:hasSource": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/elliot.xml",
			"@type": "dctypes:Text",
			"dc:format": "text/xml"
		},
		"oa:renderedVia": {
			"@id": "https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org",
			"@type": "as:Application",
			"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
			"schema:softwareVersion": "2.3.1"
		},
		"oa:hasSelector": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/elliot.xml?person_annotation_20230209211718232#Selector",
			"@type": "oa:XPathSelector",
			"rdf:value": "TEI/text/body/byline/persName"
		}
	},
	"oa:hasBody": {
		"@type": "cwrc:NaturalPerson",
		"@id": "https://www.margueriteelliot.com/about",
		"dc:format": "text/plain"
	},
	"as:generator": {
		"@id": "https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org",
		"@type": "as:Application",
		"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
		"schema:url": "https://leaf-writer.lincsproject.ca/",
		"schema:softwareVersion": "2.3.1"
	}
}]]>
        </rdf:Description>
      
        <rdf:Description rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/">
          <![CDATA[{
	"@context": {
		"dcterms:created": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:created"
		},
		"dcterms:issued": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:issued"
		},
		"oa:motivatedBy": {
			"@type": "oa:Motivation"
		},
		"@language": "en",
		"rdf": "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#",
		"rdfs": "http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#",
		"as": "http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#",
		"cwrc": "http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#",
		"dc": "http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/",
		"dcterms": "http://purl.org/dc/terms/",
		"foaf": "http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/",
		"geo": "http://www.geonames.org/ontology#",
		"oa": "http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#",
		"schema": "http://schema.org/",
		"xsd": "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#",
		"fabio": "https://purl.org/spar/fabio#",
		"bf": "http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#",
		"cito": "https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#",
		"org": "http://www.w3.org/ns/org#"
	},
	"id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/elliot.xml?person_annotation_20230209211848811",
	"type": "oa:Annotation",
	"dcterms:created": "2023-02-10T02:18:48.811Z",
	"dcterms:modified": "2023-02-10T02:18:48.811Z",
	"dcterms:creator": {
		"@id": "https://github.com/Mayawadhwa",
		"@type": [
			"cwrc:NaturalPerson",
			"schema:Person"
		],
		"cwrc:hasName": "Maya Wadhwa"
	},
	"oa:motivatedBy": "oa:identifying",
	"oa:hasTarget": {
		"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/elliot.xml?person_annotation_20230209211848811#Target",
		"@type": "oa:SpecificResource",
		"oa:hasSource": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/elliot.xml",
			"@type": "dctypes:Text",
			"dc:format": "text/xml"
		},
		"oa:renderedVia": {
			"@id": "https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org",
			"@type": "as:Application",
			"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
			"schema:softwareVersion": "2.3.1"
		},
		"oa:hasSelector": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/elliot.xml?person_annotation_20230209211848811#Selector",
			"@type": "oa:XPathSelector",
			"rdf:value": "TEI/text/body/epigraph/ab/persName"
		}
	},
	"oa:hasBody": {
		"@type": "cwrc:NaturalPerson",
		"@id": "https://ia904702.us.archive.org/14/items/heresies_03/heresies_03_text.pdf",
		"dc:format": "text/plain"
	},
	"as:generator": {
		"@id": "https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org",
		"@type": "as:Application",
		"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
		"schema:url": "https://leaf-writer.lincsproject.ca/",
		"schema:softwareVersion": "2.3.1"
	}
}]]>
        </rdf:Description>
      </rdf:RDF></xenoData></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="106"/>
         <head><title>Lesbian Art and Community</title></head>
         <byline><persName key="Marguerite Tupper Elliot" ref="https://www.margueriteelliot.com/about">Marguerite Tupper Elliot</persName></byline>

         <epigraph><ab>With much love and appreciation for my women's art group: <persName key="Marcie Baer" ref="https://ia904702.us.archive.org/14/items/heresies_03/heresies_03_text.pdf">Marcie Baer</persName>, Marianne
            Daransky, Vanalyne Green, Meg Harlam, Annette Hunt, Diana Johnson Connie Jost, Ellen
            Ledley, Melissa Mathis, Anne Phillips, Terry Platt, E.K. Waller, Denise
            Yarfitz</ab></epigraph>
         <p>I do not want to say that lesbian art looks like such and such. It is still too early
            and we would be excluding a lot of work made by lesbians if we were to put definitions
            on it. What I would like to do is to take the stigma off the label of lesbian art. I
            identify myself as a lesbian artist as an acknowledgment, an affirmation. In the act of
            naming, there is power. Since there has been so much oppression around being a lesbian,
            I would like to see lesbian artists, myself included, make the most outrageous lesbian
            art we can think of. I would like to see us free enough to be incredibly lesbian in our
            art-making process.</p>
         <p>Last year, as part of a cultural event produced by the Los Angeles League for the
            Advancement of Lesbianism in the Arts (LALALA) held at the Woman’s Building, Anne
            Phillips and myself curated a show by lesbian arists titled "Reflections of Lesbian
            Culture." My impetus in curating this show came from a desire to meet lesbian artists
            outside of the Woman’s Building, to show their work, and to create a context for the
            lesbian work my friends and I were making. Initially, I felt frustration at the lack of
            availability of lesbian feminist art. For example, some women did not want to be
            identified with a lesbian show. Because lesbian art has been so invisible, there were a
            lot of expectations and tensions about what a lesbian show should look like. There was
            pressure from some women to include all the work that was submitted; others wanted
            “high quality, professional work. Anne and I selected work that in some way re- flected
            a lesbian and/or feminist consciousness. As we did not have a set definition as to what
            we thought lesbian art should look like, the work we selected varied over a wide range
            of attitudes and media. This was my first experience of a specifically lesbian audience
            and the appreciative responses were incredible.</p>
         <p>We found the installation of the show to be somewhat controversial. It was strongly
            suggested that we take out two photographs from a group, as they did not present a
            "positive” lesbian image. Granted we would like to represent the lesbian community in
            the best way possible, and yet, what kind of censorship are we placing on it? Can we
            expect to have validating lesbian images overnight? It is my belief that we need to see
            where we have come from in order to have a solid base on which to grow.</p>
         <p> Our experience with the art establishment forces us to look at the lack of places in
            which to show lesbian art. Locally, there is the Woman’s Building. After that, it's back
            to the closet again. Presently, if women want their work available to the public, they
            are forced to use male-identified galleries. That will usually lead to some kind of
            conscious or unconscious censorship in order to make the work more acceptable. Also, by
            showing with the traditional galleries, women are supporting the elitist art
            establishment.</p>
         <p>Within the lesbian community in Los Angeles, I feel there still exists a mystification
            of the visual arts and its relevance in our lives, resulting in a separation between art
            and politics. This is important to recognize when looking for a lesbian audience.
            Lesbian writers are get- ting their work out through feminist presses and women’s
            bookstores. Lesbian musicians are getting their work out through feminist recording and
            production companies. Where is there a similar network for lesbian artists? During the
            past four years there have been hundreds of shows at the Woman’s Building, only one of
            which was exclusively lesbian, and few of which have been reviewed in the local feminist
            presses. It is evident that we have not considered visual art to be newsworthy or
            political. Part of this has to do with the fact that we as artists have not yet found a
            way to be directly accessible and responsible to the larger feminist community. Until
            recently women had to rely on male publications if they wanted their work to be
            written about, which in turn meant they had to exhibit in male galleries. In order for
            lesbian artists to be visible, they had to go through the male establishment; then they
            could be discovered and honored by the feminist communities. We are only beginning to
            trust our own values enough to stand behind women’s art that hasn’t received male
            approval.</p>
         <p>In my feminist artist group our growth has been an organic one. In coming together to
            share our work we give support and criticism to each other, and validation as artists in
            a world that barely recognizes or values the art-making process. It is of primary
            importance to me that our relationships with each other have developed through our work
            as opposed to developing in the bars or on the dance floor. For me, it has been a source
            of survival and growth. Most of us have participated in the Feminist Studio Workshop and
            have learned similar tools for critique. Our experiences and education prior to that in
            the straight art world, make it very easy to slip back into old patterns and value
            structures. Knowing that our viewpoint will be ignored by the art world, we turn to each
            other to answer questions that are meaning<pb n="107"/>ful to ourselves. I have
            experienced isolation and otherness when I am with artists who are dealing with formal
            issues. In our group, by acknowledging ourselves and other women to be our audience, we
            are creating the context in which to show our work. I feel that direct lesbian imagery
            would have taken much longer to develop or wouldn't have developed at all, if the work
            had not been understood or encouraged. We stop the process of accepting male art as
            universal, which makes our art merely a part of their system. We are not creating
            alternatives. Webster defines alternative as that which may be chosen in place of
            something else. We are already the something else. Would we want the kind of audience
            that perpetuates the oppressive values of the art galleries? One woman in our group,
            Terry Platt, is showing her work in various feminist households, treating it as a
            traveling show. Terry is almost directly accessible to the people who will be seeing her
            work, and in the process has redefined the relationship between the audience and the
            artist. The economics of our art is also being examined in relationship to our values.
            In order to make our art accessible perhaps we need to sell our work on a sliding scale
            or graphically mass produce it so as to be affordable. We are just beginning to see the
            issues involved with audience and economics.</p>
         <p>We are now faced with the same circumstances which, in the past, have kept lesbian
            artists invisible. We need to see that the same thing does not happen to us. Our art
            which is reflective of our experiences will chronicle our struggles, growth, and
            strength in formulating our lesbian feminist world.</p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <p>Marguerite Tupper Elliot, lesbian feminist artist aand curator, currently lives in Los
            Angeles. Former co-director of the Woman's Building Galleries, she is now employed at
            the Los Angeles Municipal Art Gallery. Media-wise, she works with ceramics, photography,
            and words. A large part of her work has been collaborative.</p>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>