<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="null"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Class Notes</title>
				<author>Harmony Hammond</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lucy Wadsworth</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Heresies Issue #3: Lesbian Art and Artists</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" xmlns:fabio="https://purl.org/spar/fabio#" xmlns:bf="http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#" xmlns:cito="https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#" xmlns:org="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#">
        <rdf:Description rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/">
          <![CDATA[{
	"@context": {
		"dcterms:created": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:created"
		},
		"dcterms:issued": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:issued"
		},
		"oa:motivatedBy": {
			"@type": "oa:Motivation"
		},
		"@language": "en",
		"rdf": "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#",
		"rdfs": "http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#",
		"as": "http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#",
		"cwrc": "http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#",
		"dc": "http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/",
		"dcterms": "http://purl.org/dc/terms/",
		"foaf": "http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/",
		"geo": "http://www.geonames.org/ontology#",
		"oa": "http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#",
		"schema": "http://schema.org/",
		"xsd": "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#",
		"fabio": "https://purl.org/spar/fabio#",
		"bf": "http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#",
		"cito": "https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#",
		"org": "http://www.w3.org/ns/org#"
	},
	"id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/zohanadeer/heresies/main/issue03/texts/hammond.xml?person_annotation_20230223182355092",
	"type": "oa:Annotation",
	"dcterms:created": "2023-02-23T23:23:55.092Z",
	"dcterms:modified": "2023-02-23T23:23:55.092Z",
	"dcterms:creator": {
		"@id": "https://github.com/zohanadeer",
		"@type": [
			"cwrc:NaturalPerson",
			"schema:Person"
		],
		"cwrc:hasName": "zoha nadeer"
	},
	"oa:motivatedBy": "oa:identifying",
	"oa:hasTarget": {
		"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/zohanadeer/heresies/main/issue03/texts/hammond.xml?person_annotation_20230223182355092#Target",
		"@type": "oa:SpecificResource",
		"oa:hasSource": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/zohanadeer/heresies/main/issue03/texts/hammond.xml",
			"@type": "dctypes:Text",
			"dc:format": "text/xml"
		},
		"oa:renderedVia": {
			"@id": "https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org",
			"@type": "as:Application",
			"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
			"schema:softwareVersion": "2.3.1"
		},
		"oa:hasSelector": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/zohanadeer/heresies/main/issue03/texts/hammond.xml?person_annotation_20230223182355092#Selector",
			"@type": "oa:XPathSelector",
			"rdf:value": "TEI/text/body/byline/persName"
		}
	},
	"oa:hasBody": {
		"@type": "cwrc:NaturalPerson",
		"@id": "http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5659529",
		"dc:format": "text/plain"
	},
	"as:generator": {
		"@id": "https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org",
		"@type": "as:Application",
		"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
		"schema:url": "https://leaf-writer.lincsproject.ca/",
		"schema:softwareVersion": "2.3.1"
	}
}]]>
        </rdf:Description>
      </rdf:RDF></xenoData></teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="34"/>
			<head>CLASS NOTES</head>
			<byline><persName key="Harmony Hammond" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5659529">HARMONY HAMMOND</persName></byline>
			<div>
				<p> Class hierarchies and heterosexuality are patriarchal institutions which divide
					women, give some women power over others, and destroy our strength. As a lesbian
					feminist artist, 1 am interested in examining the assumptions of class and
					heterosexuality in art, and the role of lesbian art as a potential catalyst for
					social change. This article will focus on the myth of art as classless, and how
					this myth functions to separate us from the reality of our lives and affects the
					way in which we see ourselves. Specifically, I want to discuss how we as lesbian
					artists need to defy this myth by developing class consciousness, and
					incorporating it in the development of lesbian art and culture.</p>
			</div>

			<div>
				<head>THE MYTH</head>
				<p>Fine art is a reflection of upper class interests, values, tastes, and patterns
					of thinking. The images found in art reflect and serve the needs of a small
					group of “corporate-government elite” (upper class white men) who define culture
					in America and elsewhere if they can profit from it. They found, fund, and run
					art museums, set standards of taste, and have a vested interest in creating,
					validating, and supporting art whose form and content justifies and furthers a
					patriarchal social order.<note>1. The Catalogue Committee of Artists Meeting for
						Cultural Change, an anti-catalogue, 1977. The catalogue was written as a
						protest to the Whitney exhibition, "American Art, 1976. I have included a
						condensed version of a more detailed discussion of “how art is mystified,
						how art exhibitions influence our views of history, and how collectors such
						as John D. Rockefeller III benefit from cultural philanthropy.</note> Jackie
					St. Joan has defined this social order as:</p>
				<quote>"...that system—intellectual, political, social, sexual, psychological—which
					requires in the name of human progress that one group (in the history of the
					world, rich, white men) controls and exploits the energies of another and in
					which women are particularly despised. It includes patriarchal institutions
					(heterosexuality, the nuclear family, private property, etc.) which are the
					tools of oppression as well as the patriarchal mind-constructs which, like the
					capitalist mind-constructs, limit even our ability to think beyond what
						is.<note>2. "A Lesbian Feminist: Jackie St. Joan, an interview, in Big Mama
						Rag, Jan-Feb, 1977, Vol. 5, no. 1.</note></quote>
				<p>Rarely does fine art include images of workers, the workplace, or daily survival.
					Rarely does it depict the experiences of Blacks, Native Americans, women, or
					lesbians. When these images do appear, they seem outside the experience of those
					portrayed because they are romanticized or stereotyped, rather than real. For
					instance, lesbian sexuality is rarely portrayed in visual art and when it is,
					say in film, lesbians are presented in butch/femme roles, as sick, masochistic,
					and sadistic, and as though sexuality was the only important thing in their
					lives. This limited male view hardly relates to my experience as a lesbian. Nor
					do I feel that my identity as an artist is realistically portrayed. The artist’s
					life is romanticized as a chosen struggle of economic hardship necessary to
					produce art rather than as a product of the alienation of artists from
					society.</p>
				<p>If art provides a way for us to perceive ourselves and the world around us, it
					seems necessary that we examine what is validated as art. An excellent example
					of an attempt to write social history through art was the exhibition “American
					Art,” a collection belonging to John D. Rockefeller III, which was shown last
					fall at the Whitney Museum as our Bicentennial survey exhibition of American
					art. This collection contains one work by a woman artist, one work by a Black
					artist, and no work by Hispanic or Native American artists. The absence of work
					by women and Third World artists in this and most other collections and
					exhibitions, denies the experiences of most Americans. Not to see their
					experiences reflected in culture is to say that they don’t exist. Because art
					both creates and reflects social realities, their absence becomes a political
					issue. As the artists writing in an anti-catalogue” state: “Omission is one of
					the mechanisms by which fine art reinforces the values and beliefs of the
					powerful and suppresses the experiences of others."<note>3. an
						anti-catalogue</note></p>
				<p>Another mechanism reinforcing upper class values is the myth of art as classless
					and universal. By creating the myth of universal art, those in power teach us to
					identify with images and the experiences these images represent, which have
					nothing to do with our own class position. We are told that art, and therefore
					the artist, is classless, and that our experiences are immaterial and should be
					ignored.</p>
				<p>All classes accept this myth, for to question it would be to reveal the
					oppressive political structures and social institutions underlying patriarchal
					capitalist society. Rita Mae Brown writes that “America is a country reluctant
					to recognize class differences. The American myth crystallized is: This is the
					land of equal opportunity; work hard, stay in line, you’ll get ahead. (Getting
					ahead always means money.)"<note>4. Brown, Rita Mae, “The Last Straw," Class and
						Feminism: A Collection of Essays From The Furies, edited by Charlotte Bunch
						and Nancy Myron, Diana Press, 1974.</note> Identification with this myth of
					classlessness redirects us from dealing with our own particular oppression as
					working class, as women, as lesbians, etc. The artists in an anti-catalogue”
					state:</p>
				<quote>“The mystification of art depends upon two things—upon our surrendering our
					capacity to judge and upon unquestioning acceptance of authority in place of the
					printed word and the authority of scholarly titles and distinctions. The
					mystification of art takes our passivity for granted. It encourages us to look
					upon art as if art had no bearing on experience.<note>5. an
						anti-catalogue.</note></quote>
				<pb n="35"/>
				<p> Accepting the myth is accepting our invisibility and powerlessness. To question
					cultural attitudes is to question social conditions. Passivity smooths the pain
					of powerlessness and helps us to survive these conditions. We need to see that
					behavioral patterns affect who becomes an artist, what artists create, what art
					is validated as quality, and how art in turn reinforces those patterns.</p>
			</div>

			<div>
				<head>HOW I BOUGHT THE MYTH</head>
				<p>Thinking back to junior high school in the fifties, I see that one reason 1 chose
					to be an artist was to escape the daily pain of lower middle class life in
					Hometown—of living in a duplex, taking a bus to school, and wearing
					hand-me-downs until I got a job at Lerner’s and could buy my own clothes. The
					guy I went with turned me on to Mulligan, Coleman, Getz, and all that jazz and
					the beat writers Kerouac, Ginsberg, and Prevert. They were "artists" and
					intellectuals, without money (like me), and romanticized. I thumbed my nose and
					fantasized riding naked down the highway. We fucked. I got a scholar- ship to
					the Saturday School of the Art Institute of Chicago. I wanted to be a dress
					designer or fashion illustrator because it sounded “classy” and "sophisticated."
					If all else failed, I could be an art teacher.</p>
				<p>In the museum I saw “real" painting and sculpture. I remember sitting in front of
					the Pollock, the Rothko, and the Still, thinking that I could do those
					paintings, but not realizing that I was a woman and that it didn’t matter what I
					did. In the studios I saw art being made by grubby students and I took note that
					the artist could wear anything, say anything, and didn’t have to socialize. The
					artist seemed special and not bound by class behavior. I would be an artist.
					Accepting fine art meant renouncing my class background and stepping out of the
					lower middle class life of Hometown into the universal world of the muses. Safe
					and protected at last. Who ever heard of a middle class muse?</p>
			</div>

			<div>
				<head>THE MYTH SHATTERED: CLASS IS HOW YOU SEE THE WORLD. ART IS HOW YOU SEE THE
					WORLD.</head>
				<p>It has taken me a long time to begin to understand and accept my lower middle
					class background, and to realize that the art world I entered wasn’t an
					alternative to middle class society but that women, Blacks, and the poor are
					also oppressed within the alternate “world of culture. As long as society
					allowed me to be a starving artist" I did not question my own experiences, or
					how they affected my work and work attitudes. Acting out a romanticized art life
					was my option to upward mobility. Heterosexual women get their privilege from
					the same patriarchal systems that give privilege to middle and upper class
					women. Coming out as a lesbian with a feminist consciousness forced me to
					realize what class privilege I did and did not have, and what I would now lose.
					Even the fact that I first came out to myself through my art and not in bed is
					in itself a reflection of my class position. As a feminist artist I had learned
					to use my work as a place to confront fears and other feelings privately in my
					studio. A woman working as a maid, a waitress, or a seamstress, does not have
					this option.</p>
				<p>As a lesbian, however, 1 was forced to confront and give up illusions I had about
					being accepted and rewarded by the male art world where they treated art
					seriously. To be public about being a lesbian means that your work may not be
					taken seriously, or may squeezed into a category of “camp” or erotic art.
					Because you do not hang out with the right men or the right women (those who
					hang out with the men) at the right bars, and since the lesbian feminist
					community doesn’t yet support its visual artists, you are less likely to make
					your work visible, to have professional dialogue, and to support yourself
					through your work either directly (sales) or indirectly (teaching). For women,
					the economic class system is largely determined by their relationship to men.
					The higher up the man she relates to, the more she benefits from the system. The
					lesbian, by not relating to men does not benefit economically and has no
					privilege unless she is independently wealthy. Most of us do not have that kind
					of support and opportunity, and without support, it is very difficult to
					continue making art. Historically, known lesbian visual artists (Rosa Bonheur,
					Romaine Brooks, etc.) were wealthy. Only they had the privilege to continue
					making art despite their public lesbian lifestyle.</p>
				<p>If we examine the relationship of lesbians to the class system, and to
					patriarchy, we can get an idea of the active role art can play in developing a
					culture that does not make women powerless and invisible. In “Lesbians and The
					Class Position of Women," Margaret Small writes:</p>
				<quote>...At this point in history, the primary role that lesbians have to play in
					the development of revolutionary consciousness is ideological. Because lesbians
					are objectively outside of heterosexual reality, they have potential for <pb n="36"/> developing an alternative ideology not limited by heterosexuality.
					Lesbians stand in a different relationship to (the) three conditions that
					determine the class position of women (production, reproduction, sexuality). The
					lesbian does not have a domestic base that is defined by the production of new
					labor power and maintenance of her husband’s labor power. Her relationship is in
					proletarian terms. The element of slave consciousness integral to
					heterosexuality is missing.<note>6. Small, Margaret, “Lesbians and the Class
						Position of Women," Lesbianism and the Women's Movement, edited by Nancy
						Myron and Charlotte Bunch, Diana Press, 1975.</note></quote>
				<p>I am interested in how we can do this through art. Developing a class
					consciousness does not mean that each work of art by a woman would have to
					directly relate to women of all classes, but rather that the form and content of
					the work, be it figurative or abstract, would somehow illuminate experience in
					such a way that it is shared with and includes rather than excludes women from
					different backgrounds. Instead of presenting one universal experience that is
					supposed to represent ALL of us yet represents few, art should reflect and give
					information—facts, emotional response, visual accounting, ways of seeing into
					and understanding different experiences and feelings. We must acknowledge our
					differences in order to learn about, support, and work with each other. Thus I
					feel that to make art as a lesbian with class consciousness has far-reaching
					creative and political potential for connecting women through work. This means
					actively rejecting cultural dictates, taking responsibility for our work, and
					questioning the concept of apolitical art. Art-making is where consciousness is
					formed.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>ANALYSIS—REINTEGRATION</head>
				<p>Ultimately it is a question of the function of art beyond the personal. It is not
					merely a matter of doing work that doesn’t oppress others, but also of doing
					work that pushes further towards a redefinition and transformation of culture.
					For me, coming out as a lesbian has a lot to do with developing a class
					consciousness, and that consciousness brought to my art raises questions of
					imagery, permanence, scale, ways of working, and concepts of art education. It
					raises questions of money and power, who sees my work, and what effect I want it
					to have on others.</p>
				<p>This does not mean that we as class conscious lesbian artists must make paintings
					with recognizable figurative imagery, that we must be downwardly mobile, give up
					making art for “real political struggle, or involve ourselves in the rhetorical
					circles of the artistic left. What it does mean is not making or accepting class
					assumptions about art such as what is allowable as art, who makes it, who sees
					it, and what its function is to be. By removing esthetic hierarchies and the
					need to pretend that we all share the same experiences, meaning can become
					accessible and available.</p>
				<p>Talk about "bringing art to the people” only reinforces class distinctions. Class
					consciousness can be reflected through our art by demystifying and deprivatizing
					the creative process. Presently it is difficult for a working class woman who
					likes to write, paint, or dance even to consider being a professional artist.
					When making art as well as owning art ceases to be a privilege, and the
					art-making process itself is available to women of different classes, races, and
					geographic backgrounds, we can begin to understand the political potential of
					creative expression.</p>
				<p>As lesbians, we need our experience validated culturally. To refuse art that
					denies our existence and to deny that art is apolitical and universal, is to
					actively challenge the wealthy few and their supporters who have been defining
					and controlling social order through the manipulation of fine art. Demanding
					group and self identity in art is one means of resisting oppression. The
					art-making process is a tool for making these demands and changes.</p>
				<p>Art is essentially work. Simone Weil writes that art is a surplus commodity in
					this culture because it does not have immediate consumption and is not shared
					and used by the people. That artists are not part of the paid work force further
					separates the productive from the consumptive classes. The work process (and the
					purpose of work) have always been external to the worker. Just as she writes
					that our main task is to discover how it is possible for the work to be free and
					to integrate it, we must free the art-making process so it is accessible and
					understandable to everyone. The process should be as available as the
						product.<note>7. Weil, Simone, First and Last Notebooks, translated by
						Richard Rees, Oxford University Press, London, 1970, p. 58-61.</note></p>
				<p>Acknowledging the existence of class structures, and how through art they can
					affect cultural attitudes is just a beginning—a necessary step one. In the long
					run, we should not focus merely on the relationship of one class to another, or
					on the relationship of art and class, but on defining a future classless
					society. The integration of art into the lives of all people and not just the
					upper class contributes to that vision. "Revolution presupposes not simply an
					economic and political transformation but also a technical and cultural
						one."<note>8. First and Last Notebooks.</note></p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p> Harmony Hammond is a painter and sometimes writer who is a member of the Heresies
				collective. She teaches at any university and feminist art program that will have
				her, and gives workshops and lectures on lesbian artists and feminist artists. </p>
		</back>

	</text>
</TEI>