<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="null"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>What we mean to say: Notes Toward Defining the Nature of Lesbian
					Literature</title>
				<author>Bertha Harris</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Heresies Issue #3: Lesbian Art and Artists</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" xmlns:fabio="https://purl.org/spar/fabio#" xmlns:bf="http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#" xmlns:cito="https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#" xmlns:org="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#">
        <rdf:Description rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/">
          <![CDATA[{
	"@context": {
		"dcterms:created": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:created"
		},
		"dcterms:issued": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:issued"
		},
		"oa:motivatedBy": {
			"@type": "oa:Motivation"
		},
		"@language": "en",
		"rdf": "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#",
		"rdfs": "http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#",
		"as": "http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#",
		"cwrc": "http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#",
		"dc": "http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/",
		"dcterms": "http://purl.org/dc/terms/",
		"foaf": "http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/",
		"geo": "http://www.geonames.org/ontology#",
		"oa": "http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#",
		"schema": "http://schema.org/",
		"xsd": "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#",
		"fabio": "https://purl.org/spar/fabio#",
		"bf": "http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#",
		"cito": "https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#",
		"org": "http://www.w3.org/ns/org#"
	},
	"id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/harris.xml?person_annotation_20230209202307696",
	"type": "oa:Annotation",
	"dcterms:created": "2023-02-10T01:23:07.696Z",
	"dcterms:modified": "2023-02-10T01:23:07.696Z",
	"dcterms:creator": {
		"@id": "https://github.com/Mayawadhwa",
		"@type": [
			"cwrc:NaturalPerson",
			"schema:Person"
		],
		"cwrc:hasName": "Maya Wadhwa"
	},
	"oa:motivatedBy": "oa:identifying",
	"oa:hasTarget": {
		"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/harris.xml?person_annotation_20230209202307696#Target",
		"@type": "oa:SpecificResource",
		"oa:hasSource": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/harris.xml",
			"@type": "dctypes:Text",
			"dc:format": "text/xml"
		},
		"oa:renderedVia": {
			"@id": "https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org",
			"@type": "as:Application",
			"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
			"schema:softwareVersion": "2.3.1"
		},
		"oa:hasSelector": {
			"@id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Mayawadhwa/heresies/main/issue03/texts/harris.xml?person_annotation_20230209202307696#Selector",
			"@type": "oa:XPathSelector",
			"rdf:value": "TEI/text/body/byline/persName"
		}
	},
	"oa:hasBody": {
		"@type": "cwrc:NaturalPerson",
		"@id": "http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q48813116",
		"dc:format": "text/plain"
	},
	"as:generator": {
		"@id": "https://leaf-writer.leaf-vre.org",
		"@type": "as:Application",
		"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
		"schema:url": "https://leaf-writer.lincsproject.ca/",
		"schema:softwareVersion": "2.3.1"
	}
}]]>
        </rdf:Description>
      </rdf:RDF></xenoData></teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="5"/>

			<head><title><title>What we mean to say: Notes Toward Defining The Nature of Lesbian Literature</title></title></head>
			<byline><persName key="Bertha Harris's Lover: lesbian and postmodern." ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q48813116">BERTHA HARRIS</persName></byline>

			<note>The original version of this paper was intended for, and presented to, academics
				at a Forum on Homosexual Literature at the 1974 Modern Language Association
				Convention. The paper was entitled, “The Purification of Monstrosity: The Lesbian As
				Literature." Since then, have written other versions on this subject of the lesbian
				as monster in literature; and have begun to realize that can only finally complete
				what I have to say in book- length form. So l’ve started writing the book. The version below contains the theory and a partial analysis. For examples here, however, l
				have chosen mostly instances of popular literature—such as Dracula, Jaws, Burnt
				Offerings, etc. Expanded, this essay on the idea of lesbian monstrosity in popular
				fiction will form one chapter of the book lam preparing.</note>

			<p>To misappropriate Oscar Wilde’s remark about the English and fox-hunting: lesbian
				literature is the pursuit of the inedible by the unspeakable. It is also the pursuit
				of the unspeakable by the inedible; and it is this particularly. As lesbians are
				"unspeakable” so is "lesbianism" a taste for the "inedible." Literature (in any
				form) is like the fox, a luxury; a peripheral pastime, because it is inedible; and
				so is lesbianism. Lesbians and lesbian literature are unspeakable and inedible.
				Most contemporary attempts to make both palatable and "speakable” (to put a fox in
				every home’s Sunday pot)—universally accept able and welcome—are tantamount to
				grinding up chateaubriand into winkieburgers.</p>

			<p>To those acquainted with reading (but most people, and most lesbians, do not read)
				what is being called lesbian literature these days is sheer winkieburger; and
				around and about that "literature” is afoot a movement to make the world safe for
				winkieburger—although tree-worshippers on our west coast will not touch it; and
				ritualists who periodically burn their menstrual <pb n="6"/> blood prefer to do that
				instead. Most lesbians (like everyone else) would rather feel than read; they thus
				achieve their most longed-for goal: to be like everyone else. And that is too bad.
				Lesbians, instead, might have been great, as some literature is: unassimilable, awesome, dangerous, outrageous, different: distinguished. Lesbians, as some literature
				is, might have been monstrous—and thus have everything. Monsters are, and have
				always been, invented to express what ordinary people cannot: feeling. Monsters
				(among other things) are emblems of feeling in patriarchy. The enemy of the monster
				is phallic materialism, which demands that chaos be shaped and ordered, made
				sexually economical, around the emblem of a cock. The literature of phallic
				materialism is about reducing “chaos” (wilderness, woman, imagination, the erotic)
				into an erect (predictable) order (by means of rifles and missiles, fire and
				concrete, the ritual of marriage and the double bed; genital spasm). The story is
				about what it means to be a cock; and what it means to be the other end of the cock.
				The most inventive of these stories is regularly awarded the Nobel Prize.
				"Invention” in these stories regularly takes the form of what constitutes the other
				end of the cock: what form the monster will take.</p>
			<p>Most writers of imaginative literature (by which I mean fiction and poetry)—and their
				attentive readers - do not understand that a lesbian form significantly differing
				from the patriarchal form I have described is not achieved through sexual
				substitution. For example, two women (instead of a woman and a man) overcoming
				parental opposition, surviving the wilderness, enjoying domestic bliss together,
				achieving orgasm with a finger instead of a penis is only Romeo and Juliet again
				with two differences: happy endings—of both kinds. A woman suffering in Tolstoyan
				detail over another woman (instead of a man) overwhelms with catalogues of sexual
				candor; genital explicitness substituting for Napoleon’s entry into Moscow. It is
				not that these, and all the others, are not good" books. They are—and so are the
				excruciatingly refined recollections of a dear old lady who mistakes the chirrups of
				a female sociologist for the call of the Wild. Anything is, after all, better than
				nothing. My complaint lies in the fact that these individual turnabouts of
				heterosexual reality seem, to many, to constitute a literary expression of lesbian
				sensibility; and as such distract us from the apprehension of lesbian reality.</p>
			<p>The great service of literature is to show us who we are. Put more simply, we tend to
				behave, and think, as books show us how to behave and think (and I am being
				deliberately naive here—I do know that movies and television have almost
				completely taken over the role of books as behavior show-ers and shapers). Lesbians,
				historically bereft of cultural, political and moral context, have especially
				relied on imaginative literature to dream themselves into situations of cultural,
				political and moral power. Twenty years ago, without Molly Bolt, we were Rhett
				Butler and Stephen Gordon and the Count of Monte Cristo. It is, of course, much more
				to the point to be Molly Bolt—or Patience or Sarah or Mrs. Stevens. The trouble with
				this process (vulgarly referred to as "identifying with") is that while the new
				lesbian hero is certainly safer for our mental health than Rhett or the Count of
				Stephen—we do not have to associate power and adventure with the penis any longer;
				we do not have to call on God to cure us of "inversion and wear male underwear any
				longer—and while we see her operating in what some might very loosely call a
				"cultural" context of tree-hugging, feminist folk/rock, vegetarianism and
				goddess-worship, her aggressive, strong, even magnificent image is by and large
				taken or by her beholder still inside the heterosexual/patriarchal definition of
				moral and political reality. Lesbian literature is not a matter of a woman plus a
				woman in bed. As the devout seek to "prove” a matriarchal pre-history by pointing to
				circular forms in cave painting; as stil. others cherish bizarre snippets of human
				detritus as the foreskin of Jesus—lesbians overwhelmingly believe that acts of
				lesbianism are positive proof—both in and out of literature—of the existence of
				lesbians. As though we were spending all our lives in the courts of law, we rely
				almost entirely on materiality as evidence of truth. It is sexual materiality, of
				course, that is these days the supreme evidence, not only of truth and love but,
				indeed, that one is alive. And perhaps it has always been so; and perhaps it is best
				that it is so. But lesbians have been unable to enact a completely lesbian
				reality—and therefore, a literature—because of such reliance on the sensational as
				proof of existence: because we have been the apotheosis of the sensational, defined
				utterly by sexual behavior and no other kind. As such, we have served an emotionally
				crippled society well: imagined as entirely sexual, we are also imagined as
				complete: i.e., a human form (therefore natural) engaging in unnatural (therefore
				supernatural) activity. Law, basing its decision on material evidence, thus shows
				what is out of law; and makes the divine, which is worshipped; and makes the
				criminal, which is brutalized—and adored, <pb n="7"/> and for the same reasons the
				“divine” is worshipped: because of its difference. Human beings tend to adore that
				which they are not, but long to be; or, given the "chance," can be; and this is a
				wish for salvation—and salvaging. Such a wish, expressed in an entirely whole social
				context, makes a literature in which heroes appear performing great tasks of
				strength, love, endurance, intellectuality, suffering. Each task accomplished for
				the hero means transcendence, not only for the hero but for the culture whose need
				he has accomplished. The task itself changes from time to time; from place to place;
				but its purpose—transcendence—does not. The lesbian equivalent of such a hero in
				literature is the monster. Monsters, heroes, criminals and lesbians (and sometimes
				saints and gods) have the following traits in common: an ability to make a life
				outside the social norm that seems both enviable and frightening to those inside; an
				actual or imagined power to concentrate which may be either emotionally or
				intellectually expressed—but whose object is to solve a problem; marks of difference
				that are physically manifested and both horrify and thrill; a desire to avenge its
				own (and sometimes others) outcast misery: through destruction or through forcing a
				change in the world that will admit it and its kind; an ability to seduce and tempt
				others into its “evil" ways; super-human power.</p>
			<p>From boy to man to old man, the male body changes hardly at all. The changes it does
				incur are hardly dramatic. From girl to woman to old woman, the female body is in
				constant flux; and to the primitive imagination (which we all have) female
				physical change is the matter of all magic; the genesis of all fear; the stuff of
				all mythic and fictive exaggeration. The female bleeds. She bleeds, but does not die
				from bleeding. She grows breasts: breasts springing from the nothing that is chest.
				Her hips spread; her waist indents; her belly grows huge. In great physical
				turbulence, she produces life, her self’s replica, and seemingly at her will and
				unaided. Her body can feed this new life. Such a creature with such power—not only
				over life itself but power over the continuing life of the community—must be dealt
				with: her power over life must be met with an equivalent power. 1ne most obvious
				form that this new invented power (invented through motives of fear and envy) will
				take is the power to choose whether the woman will live or die. Her power over life
				must be matched with a power over her death. This invented power over woman is
				enacted in various overlapping stages: she is made sacred and worshipped (because
				she is outside the male “norm ”). Through worship, it is hoped, she will be
				propitiated - she will not turn her magic inside out and cause death instead of
				on-going life. She is made profane, stripped of her magical properties, reduced to
				“mere” flesh. In this form she embodies horror and thrill and, especially, evil. For
				fear that she herself will turn her magic inside-out, the community appropriates
				that decision and does it instead. In both divine and obscure forms, the woman’s
				magic is under the control of others and she is rendered powerless. To experience
				powerlessness is to experience death. Further, both forms of control have the added
				effects of "taming" that which was perceived as wild, and therefore dangerous. For
				the male to appear wild, he must create a contrast to tameness; in effect, steal
				woman’s wildness and use it as drag: become magic himself. And he will become
				divine, by contrast, if she can be made profane. And he will become pure if she can
				be shown (as her bleeding testifies) to be impure. Such a cooptive process is
				accompanied by huge eruptions of guilt and fear which, in literary creation (as
				well as myth), takes the form of the monster: the quintessence of all that is
				female; and female enraged.</p>
			<p>The amount of collective guilt by those who hold power over women can be effectively
				measured at any one time by the amount of “monster” literature that is published
				during that time. Especially if such literature is popular with the public (as it
				was in nineteenth century Europe and as it is now in twentieth century America)
				we can be certain that two emotions have seized the general imagination: extreme
				fear that those who have been tricked of power are conspiring to regain it—and
				will—and that artificial restraints on the wild (such as marriage) are collapsing;
				and a great longing (accompanied by remorse and nostalgia for “real” wildness) for
				the conspiracy to succeed. While Mary Shelley was composing Frankenstein, William
				Blake was observing the havoc the Industrial Revolution was wreaking on England’s
				green nature. Mary Shelley’s monster rises out of “dark Satanic Mills" as pure evil
				and as a result of evil inflicted on the natural: “Oh Horror!—let me fly this
				dreadful monster of my own creation!" Frankenstein’s monster longs to be loved; many
				monsters feel that love will cure their alienation. Significantly (perhaps unique - 
				ly among monsters) Mary Shelley also wishes it could read and write. Blake’s “dark
				Satanic Mills" have advanced into the last half of the twentieth century transformed
				into sophisticated technological death; and almost daily a new monster is
				mass-distributed in paperback. Vampires, poltergeists, witches are being refur
				<pb n="8"/> bished in modern guise: Ann Rice deliberately recreates old Dracula
				as a dream of eroticism; but old Dracula, from the nineteenth century, still
				threatens his worthy pursuers (intent on making the world safe from “vampires")
				that he will take their women away from them and turn them (the men) into his
				jackals. An adolescent girl, abominated because she is “different" elects to let
				difference serve her instead of defeat her, and turns the "shame" of menstruation
				into a bloom of napalm. The natural conspires with the supernatural—as it always has
				through monster literature; and, through the union, produces both a configuration of
				love that is non-phallic; and of power that is counter-phallic. A maiden plus a
				beast produces a monster: that is, “unspoiled” nature (unfucked, unsocialized) whose
				image is the maiden who will find herself (sometimes through happenstance, sometimes
				even deliberately) in league with the supernatural. Together, they terrify, and
				must be separated (by the phallus)—one, commonly, transformed to wife; the other
				exchanged for husband. While patriarchal guilt has invented the monster to manifest
				its guilt, patriarchal need to reenact triumph over the monster is so far a greater
				urge. But Burnt Offerings, another mass-market paperback, is an interesting switch;
				as is Carrie. Carrie, though she herself is killed in the holocaust her rage
				creates, seems as alive after death as she was before. "Can female anger be quenched
				by the grave?” seems to be the question. Certainly, the vampire’s cannot—except by
				the stake through the heart: a long, stiff, pointed object snuffing out eternal life
				through love’s symbol. While Burnt Offerings is thematically similar to Shirley
				Jackson's The Haunting of Hill House (but thematically only; literary merit is not
				an issue here); and while there is material lesbian content in Jackson's novel and
				not in the other, Burnt Offerings is one of the few monster tales with a happy
				monster ending. The young housewife, with the help of the vicious house, gleefully
				turns into a witch (or witch variant), uses her new power to destroy her husband and
				son; and at last can enjoy not only a room of her own but an entire, and rather
				lovely, house of her own. Blood, as in the case of the vampire, is the transforming
				agent. Frequently patriarchal guilt will, besides the monster, produce types of
				men to suffer and eventually defeat her. Bram Stoker’s Dracula and Peter Benchley’s
				Jaws are exactly the same in this respect: a man of the past, a man of the present
				and a man of the (technological) future unite emotionally and as workers to kill
				the being whose erotic rage most threatens their sexual control; and the crucial
				lesson of male/skill bonding against female/creature union is again reinforced. Of
				this genre, Jaws—whose direct ancestor is the old tale of "Beauty and the Beast"—is
				the most clearly lesbian. Maiden, beast and nature are fused in one giant, ravenous
				killer form whose freedom depends upon the wipeout of the nuclear-familied,
				heterosexual beach and all its supporting structures. And this time it takes more
				than mere phallic flesh to subjugate the monster: the penis (the pointed stake
				through the heart) has become great tubes of lethal explosive. As vagina dentata
				grows even longer, stronger incisors, so must the weaponry to blow it up—and teach
				it a lesson—increase in diameter, length and ability to shoot straight. When Djuna
				Barnes wrote Night- wood she was creating, in the silent, devouring magic of her
				lesbian, Robin Vote, a sleepless swimmer in the depths of all our imaginations; and
				her new name is Jaws—and her ancient name, Beauty.</p>
			<p>But lesbian literature, which, in patriarchy is necessarily monster literature, has
				begun to take new shapes utterly independent and free of the male tradition: as it
				must, to produce any kind of happy ending. With only a few exceptions, the old
				monster is experiencing its most telling re-rendering in the imaginative literature
				from the independent women’s presses, where it is being returned to its original
				female shape. The old fearsome disguises, the gruesome costumes of terror are being
				stripped away, revealing what was there all along: a free woman declaring through
				art, for the first time, what a lesbian is. Much of what a lesbian is, this new work
				is telling us, is that which has been unspeakable about women. In June Arnold's The
				Cook and The Car- penter, we learn that political passion is a direct result of
				physical passion among women. In Linda Marie’s I Must Not Rock and Nancy Lee Hall's
				The True Story of a Drunken Mother the “common” language of the com- mon woman that
				Judy Grahn prophesied in The Common Woman poems is at least an esthetic reality.
				In June Arnold’s Sister Gin to be old and fat is also to be a lover. Pat Parker’s
				poetry shows that it is even possible to be Black and stay Black when one is a
				lesbian. In M.F. Beal’s Angel Dance and in my own novel, Lover, men are dangerous to
				the lives of women: and so they are killed. Such works, from such places, constitute
				the beginnings of the future of lesbian literature and serve to show what the
				lesbian is becoming: a creature of tooth and claw, of passion and purpose:
				unassimilable, awesome, dangerous, outrageous, different: distinguished. </p>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p> Copyright © by Bertha Harris.</p>
			<p>Bertha Harris is a novelist, a feminist, a mother, an essayist an editor, a teacher,
				a misanthropist and a lesbian. Her most recent novel is Lover, published by
				Daughters, Inc. </p>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>