<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Ladden</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>If.. . you are asked to do a lot of giving without . . . reward,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>says Fascinating Womanhood, which ranks self-effacement
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>with God and the flag, “remember, when you cast your bread
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>upon the waters, it comes back buttered.” The phrase sums up
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>the martyred woman today: passive and awed by powerful
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>tides, she willingly surrenders everything to fate while standing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>in a sea of grease. There-isolated, unabated-she practices .
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>THE MARTYR
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>ARTS
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>Arlene Ladden
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>This content downloaded from
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>134.82.70.63 on Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:00:45 UTC
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>A look at early Christian history shows that woman’s lot was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>anything but a lot. Man’s marriage to woman was grudg-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>ingly conceded as a necessary evil.1 She was a “foe to friend¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>ship, an inevitable penance . . . a domestic peril.”2 It was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>officially questioned whether woman had a soul (in 585, the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>Council of Macon decided that she did, but only by a single
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>vote).? Repeatedly admonished to “be in subjection to (her)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>own husband,”4 she was, at best, “a natural temptation, a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>coveted calamity.”5 A weak vessel for man s seed, she was a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>plaque on which he could mount his sexual organ.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>For the religious woman, who naturally believed her life
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>worthless, there were few alternatives. She could dumbly
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>worship the saints or, if ambitious enough, she could emulate
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>them: St. Simon Stylites ate very little; St. John of the Cross
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>licked the sores of lepers.“ And while some women performed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>no less austerely (St. Rose ate nothing but sheep’s gall, ashes
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>and bitter herbs, and she drank the blood of a sick patient),
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>many—martyred through constant devotion and sacrifice—
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>displayed a peculiar brand of sensuality.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>Veronica Guliani—who went to bed with, and kissed, and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>suckled a lamb, the lamb being a symbol of Christ—is per¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>haps atypical. But not Mechthilde of Madgeburg, who pre-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>ferred to see Jesus as “charming,” affectionate and 18 years
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>old. Nor Margaretha of Ypern, who thought herself “en-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>gaged” to Jesus. Nor Christine Ebner, who imagined she
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>carried Jesus’ child. The church deliberately inspired such
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>sensuous imaginings. “Ever let the Bridegroom sport with
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>you within (your chamber),” St. Jerome wrote to a virgin.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>When sleep falls on you, He will come beside the wall and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>will put his hand through the hole in the door and will touch
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>your belly . . .”7 With nuns “marrying” Christ in a formal
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>ceremony—their “I love Christ into whose bed I have en-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>tered” being roughly equivalent to the modern “I do”—it is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>not surprising that, while most martyrs sought to transcend
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>the body, female martyrdom at times unveiled a complexion
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>entirely its own. Pocked with the scars of lacerations and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>burnings, flushed with desire for a polygamous, heterosexual
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>Jesus, it encouraged a centuries-long tradition of woman&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>self-sacrifice and suffering for man. For only by cleaving to a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>seeming savior or holy man could a woman hope to rise even
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>a fraction as much as she had fallen.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>Take the example of Margaret-Mary Alacoque, a particu-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>larly fervent practitioner. She shafted a novice for rivaling
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>her holiness, lest she rival her also in the Savior’s affections.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>And while her frequent convulsions were probably due to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>austerity—she drank mostly dirty wash-water, and drank
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>nothing at all from Thursday to Sunday (though she occas¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>ionally licked up vomit with her tongue)—she was hotly fe-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l49' n='N049'/>verish with love of Jesus, even tattooing his name on her
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l50' n='N050'/>chest with a small knife. (When the scars healed, she burned
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l51' n='N051'/>in the insignia with a candle.) Such actions were proof of a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l52' n='N052'/>beautiful soul.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l53' n='N053'/>Suffering has long been a value in the west. An attribute of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l54' n='N054'/>saints and a must for martyrs, it has also lately been required
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l55' n='N055'/>of the artist, who, as Susan Sontag aptly notes, now replaces
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l56' n='N056'/>the saint as exemplary sufferer.? And Sontag’s tenet, I think,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l57' n='N057'/>can be reversed: the saint, or martyr, was a kind of artist in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l58' n='N058'/>earlier times. Aestheticians like Jacques Maritain would
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l59' n='N059'/>seem to agree, seeing art as “makling) a form shine on the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l60' n='N060'/>matter,” form being “the profound splendor of the soul shin-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l61' n='N061'/>ing through .. . the principle . . . of pain and passion.” Liv¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l62' n='N062'/>ing in true perfection, he says, “may be metaphorically de-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l63' n='N063'/>scribed as an art . . . an art which only the saints master
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l64' n='N064'/>fully.&quot;
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l65' n='N065'/>Now, that Margaret-Mary wasn’t perfect is not impor¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l66' n='N066'/>tant; it’s enough that the church assures us she was. What is
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l67' n='N067'/>important is that she was an exemplary sufferer if there ever
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l68' n='N068'/>was one. She suffered; she suffered wholly and completely—
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l69' n='N069'/>and this gave her a decided advantage. For, notes Sontag,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l70' n='N070'/>quoting from the diary of a suffering artist, only through
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_1_1l71' n='N071'/>such total surrender can we “disarm the power of suffering,
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>make it our own creation, our own choice,”1° By giving in to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>suffering, we mold it, reshape it. We sublimate suffering into
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>art.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>That life and art can be one and the same is an old idea.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>John Dewey” upheld it, defining art as any activity reshap-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>ing experience more meaningfully, coherently and vividly
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>than ordinary life allows. “Emotion,” he says, “is . . . the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>cementing force.” By selecting and coloring, it unifies the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>disparate events of experience, transforming them into an
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>experience. “The enemies of the aesthetic,” says Dewey,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>are neither the practical or the intellectual. They are the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>hum-drum.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>However repugnant Margaret-Mary’s actions may seem,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>by male aesthetic criteria Margaret-Mary was an artist and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>her martyrdom was art. It dictated her every action, and her
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>every action was contrived to reflect a beautiful soul.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l17' n='N017'/>Martyrdom provided her with a form for her life, and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l18' n='N018'/>through it she assumed control over the fragmented matter of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l19' n='N019'/>her existence. She indulged in suffering; it engrossed her,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l20' n='N020'/>diverted her, and thoroughly absorbed her. Pain became
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l21' n='N021'/>objectified. Life became a passionate performance (indeed,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l22' n='N022'/>her breast resembled a theater marquee), soulful, dramatic,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l23' n='N023'/>cohesive, consistent and meaningful. By classical definitions
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l24' n='N024'/>of art, her life, in assuming a magnitude and order, fulfilled
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l25' n='N025'/>the conditions of the beautiful. In fact, martyrdom for Jesus,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l26' n='N026'/>and later secularized martyrdom for man, has been one of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l27' n='N027'/>woman’s most pervasive and enduring traditional art forms.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l28' n='N028'/>For Margaret-Mary was not alone in indulging in suf-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l29' n='N029'/>fering; other women matched her passion. Christine Ebner
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l30' n='N030'/>etched out a cross on the skin of her chest and tore it off.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l31' n='N031'/>Mary Magdalene dei Pazzi had herself cut, trampled,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l32' n='N032'/>whipped and burned. Christine of St. Trond had herself
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l33' n='N033'/>bound, hung, racked, buried and baked. Surely, Christian-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l34' n='N034'/>ity’s chapter on the martyrs and mystics is one of the most
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l35' n='N035'/>astounding chapters in history. Less astounding, perhaps,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l36' n='N036'/>are the women who, like Felicula or Saints Agnes and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l37' n='N037'/>Agatha, opted for tortures over marriage. These women were
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l38' n='N038'/>saving themselves for Christ and wouldn’t succumb. But
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l39' n='N039'/>there were also martyrs among those who did, like Therese, a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l40' n='N040'/>nineteenth century madwoman and would-be mystic whose
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l41' n='N041'/>longing for Christ drove her insane until finally, distracted,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l42' n='N042'/>demoralized and institutionalized, she wrote: “Now I only
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l43' n='N043'/>believe in God and suffering. I feel it is necessary to get mar-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l44' n='N044'/>ried.”12 Therese was deranged, but her resignation reflected
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l45' n='N045'/>a sordid truth: for many who lived in later centuries, mar¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l46' n='N046'/>riage itself had become yet another form of martyrdom,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l47' n='N047'/>supplying an aesthetic where none existed.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l48' n='N048'/>The altruistic female sacrificing for a husband was an old
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l49' n='N049'/>ideal. The twelfth-century Marie de France featured her in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l50' n='N050'/>Eliduc where a wife graciously surrenders her husband to a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l51' n='N051'/>woman he loves. Years later, she welcomes the new wife into
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l52' n='N052'/>her convent where, sisters in Christ, the two women are
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l53' n='N053'/>bound again by love for a single man, the husband and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l54' n='N054'/>Christ being, metaphorically, one and the same.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l55' n='N055'/>By the fourteenth century, with Chaucer’s and Boccac-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l56' n='N056'/>cio’s patient Griselda, the emphasis had changed.13 A female
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l57' n='N057'/>Job, Griselda stands obediently by while her husband humil-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l58' n='N058'/>iates her, repudiates her—even when she believes he mur-
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l59' n='N059'/>dered her children; her only concern is to meet his wants,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l60' n='N060'/>however cruel they seem to her. Now the love of one woman
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l61' n='N061'/>for another is strongly de-emphasized—relief can only come
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l62' n='N062'/>from man—and man’s worth is wholly unquestioned, wom¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l63' n='N063'/>an’s soul seeming all the greater for his cruelty.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l64' n='N064'/>It was this ideal which began to flourish in the eighteenth
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l65' n='N065'/>century. Because Protestantism had changed woman’s role,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l66' n='N066'/>transposing mystical values to the domestic sphere, later
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l67' n='N067'/>centuries saw the revival of the martyrdom aesthetic in a new
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l68' n='N068'/>light. Aestheticians since Fichte had taught that beauty was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l69' n='N069'/>subjective—a manifestation of the beautiful soul—many be¬
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l70' n='N070'/>lieving, with Muller, that the highest art was the art of life.&quot;“
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r_2_1l71' n='N071'/>Now, soulful woman could approach the sublime without ev¬
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l1' n='N001'/>er leaving her immediate neighborhood, not to mention fore-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l2' n='N002'/>going a trip to heaven. Just as, classically, art was a lofty
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l3' n='N003'/>reflection of nature, the good wife was a lofty reflection of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l4' n='N004'/>man, so lofty in fact, that she ceased to have substance alto¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l5' n='N005'/>gether (a Dorsetshire wedding ceremony likened her to “a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l6' n='N006'/>Mirrour which hath no image of its own”).15 A young girl
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l7' n='N007'/>(pupilla) was said to exist in the pupil of every man’s eye,16
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l8' n='N008'/>and while this classically meant man’s perceptions were soul-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l9' n='N009'/>ful, now it stood for another tenet: that woman should only
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l10' n='N010'/>exist in the glazed eyes of man. She was wife only—merely a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l11' n='N011'/>part of her husband’s family, famulus meaning servant or
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l12' n='N012'/>slave. As Fichte had also taught: “(Woman’s) own dignity
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l13' n='N013'/>requires that she should give herself up entirely as she is . . .
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l14' n='N014'/>17
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l15' n='N015'/>and should utterly lose herself in (her husband).
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l16' n='N016'/>Now Christ was absent. As with Jane Eyre in the Bronte
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l17' n='N017'/>novel, woman was to persist dutifully in soulful devotion to a
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l18' n='N018'/>cynical master and, eventually, his contemplation of her—
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l19' n='N019'/>distanced and mystical in her suffering goodness—might
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l20' n='N020'/>touch his soul and effect his overt transformation. Just as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l21' n='N021'/>Jane restored the blinded Rochester’s vision, so could wom-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l22' n='N022'/>an, like the highest art, elevate a husband’s vision, turning
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l23' n='N023'/>cynic into believer, teaching and delighting. A classical rep-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l24' n='N024'/>resentation of beauty, she incited compassion and pity, if not
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l25' n='N025'/>fear.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l26' n='N026'/>But such idealizations were fiction, pure fairy tale.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l27' n='N027'/>Bronte’s Jane was, in real life, de Sade’s Justine. A perpetual
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l28' n='N028'/>victim, she often suffered for men who were unrelenting,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l29' n='N029'/>unrepenting.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l30' n='N030'/>With religious executions a thing of the past and passion¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l31' n='N031'/>ate martyrdom for Christ wholly repugnant to the Protestant
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l32' n='N032'/>ethic, the clergy, who now found marriage desirable, trans¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l33' n='N033'/>ferred the imagery of Jesus onto the husband with new, if
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l34' n='N034'/>pedestrian, significance. The female martyr was now
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l35' n='N035'/>plunked down in the family cottage where, virtuous and sex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l36' n='N036'/>less, she suffered for her family. There, mystical and beauti¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l37' n='N037'/>ful, she persevered. Determined and powerless, she perse-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l38' n='N038'/>vered. John Ruskin’s directive was typical: “(Woman must
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l39' n='N039'/>be) instinctively, infallibly wise—wise, not for self-develop¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l40' n='N040'/>ment, but for self-renunciation.”1s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l41' n='N041'/>In fact, she hadn’t much choice. The rise of capitalism
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l42' n='N042'/>had, by the eighteenth century, aggravated woman s econ¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l43' n='N043'/>omic dependence while it banished traditional duties from
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l44' n='N044'/>the home. Domestic spinning, weaving, brewing and baking
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l45' n='N045'/>had once been essential and, however tedious, had used up
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l46' n='N046'/>time. Now, with moral prohibitions still further diminishing
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l47' n='N047'/>woman’s activities, idleness exposed the void. By roman¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l48' n='N048'/>tically and utterly surrendering to suffering, woman might
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l49' n='N049'/>become absorbed; life’s form might assume a grandiose
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l50' n='N050'/>beauty, masking the pettiness of its content. As before, if
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l51' n='N051'/>woman could exalt her suffering, she could shape it, perfect
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l52' n='N052'/>it; she could languish in contemplation of her own sorrow.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l53' n='N053'/>Formalized and ritualized, it aesthetically formed and in¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l54' n='N054'/>formed her life. And the aesthetic became an anaesthetic.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l55' n='N055'/>For no matter how sentient martyrdom’s manifestations, it
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l56' n='N056'/>numbed woman to her own insignificance, protecting her
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l57' n='N057'/>from the more genuine pain of small emotions. The niggling
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l58' n='N058'/>void became flushed with feeling, feeling believed to soften
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l59' n='N059'/>and deepen the soul. Or so believed Madame de Stael, whose
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l60' n='N060'/>exposition on suffering also credited the virtues of habitual
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l61' n='N061'/>submisiveness. Her tract was written to justify suicide. No
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l62' n='N062'/>wonder.19
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l63' n='N063'/>Martyrdom was still an art: no longer for Jesus, no longer
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l64' n='N064'/>even for a powerful man whose cruelty masked a beautiful
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l65' n='N065'/>soul. It was now martyrdom for any man, be he a stern patri¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l66' n='N066'/>arch or a sodden drunk, or a stem patriarch and a sodden
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l67' n='N067'/>drunk. As Tolstoy saw it: Wives should be loving, unobtru¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l68' n='N068'/>sive and unassuming—“comforters of the drunken, the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l69' n='N069'/>weak, and the dissolute.”2° Or in Fichte’s words: The wife of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_1_1l70' n='N070'/>a degenerate husband “is held all the more in esteem the gen-
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l1' n='N001'/>she bears it,” though still, she must appear to be
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l2' n='N002'/>“lost in the man of her choice.”21 Wet nurses to alcoholics,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l3' n='N003'/>wives soaked their men with spirit, and disappeared.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l4' n='N004'/>In 1920, in a perverse tribute to pained sensibility, Mar¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l5' n='N005'/>garet-Mary Alacoque was canonized. Her emblem was the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l6' n='N006'/>Sacred Heart. It was increasingly presented more and more
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l7' n='N007'/>bloodily—grotesque, fiery, disembodied, now an isolate
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l8' n='N008'/>lump of throbbing muscle—the pulsing symbol of a female
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l9' n='N009'/>aesthetic and the badge of hundreds of Catholic schools.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l10' n='N010'/>The good woman, it thumps, is all heart.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l11' n='N011'/>But its beat is getting ever weaker. Like the allure of habit-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l12' n='N012'/>ual sacrifice itself. Like the utter devotion (submission) for
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l13' n='N013'/>which it stands—one passion, indivisible, with guilt and op¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l14' n='N014'/>pression for all. Woman’s fluid acquiescence has leaked its
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l15' n='N015'/>glamour, and women are letting women know it.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_2_1l16' n='N016'/>Sacrifice is self-abuse. Death to martyrdom.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l1' n='N001'/>1. Since-woman was considered a temptress irresistible to the weak, St.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l2' n='N002'/>Paul preferred marriage when adultery seemed inevitable, conceding: “It is
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l3' n='N003'/>better to marry than to burn.” (I Corinthians 7:9).
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l4' n='N004'/>2. Salimbene, in From St. Francis to Dante: Translations from the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l5' n='N005'/>Chronicle of the Franciscan Salimbene (1221-1288), 2nd ed., ed. and trans.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l6' n='N006'/>G. G. Coulton (London: David Nutt, 1907), p. 97. Salimbene falsely attri¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l7' n='N007'/>butes these epithets to St. Chrysostom, whose own expression was equally
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l8' n='N008'/>appalling, if less succinct.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l9' n='N009'/>3. Bernard Murstein, Love, Sex and Marriage Through the Ages (New
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l10' n='N010'/>York: Springer Publishing Co., 1974), p. 94.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l11' n='N011'/>4. 1 Peter 3:1. These sentiments, with virtually identical wording, are ex¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l12' n='N012'/>pressed also in Ephesians 5:22, Collosians 3:18 and, later, in the first en¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l13' n='N013'/>during systematization of church law, Gratian’s Decretum (c. 1140), quoted
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l14' n='N014'/>in Not in God’s Image, ed. Julia O’Faolain and Lauro Martines (New York:
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l15' n='N015'/>Harper and Row, 1973), p. 130.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l16' n='N016'/>5. Salimbene, p. 97.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l17' n='N017'/>6. For factual information relating to the saints, martyrs and mystics, I
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l18' n='N018'/>have primarily referred to Henry Osborn Taylor, “Mystic Visions of Ascetic
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l19' n='N019'/>Women,” in The Medieval Mind (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l20' n='N020'/>Press, 1959), vol. I, pp. 458-486; Rev. S. Baring-Gould, The Lives of the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l21' n='N021'/>Saints, rev. ed., 16 vols. (Edinburgh: John Grant, 1914); Donald Attwater’s
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l22' n='N022'/>The Penguin Dictionary of Saints (New York: Penguin Books, 1965); and,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l23' n='N023'/>for the more gruesome cases, Gordon Rattray Taylor, Sex in History (New
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l24' n='N024'/>York: Harper and Row, 1970), pp. 31-50 and passim as well as Havelock
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l25' n='N025'/>Ellis, “The Auto-Erotic Factor in Religion,” in Studies in the Psychology of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l26' n='N026'/>Sex (New York: Random House, 1936), vol. I, pp. 310-325.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l27' n='N027'/>7. Epistle 22 in Select Letters of St. Jerome, trans. F. A. Wright (Cam-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l28' n='N028'/>bridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1963), p. 109. The translator has
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l29' n='N029'/>rendered “belly” (ventrem) as “flesh”; perhaps he has censored the saint in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l30' n='N030'/>the interest of delicacy.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l31' n='N031'/>8.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l32' n='N032'/>The Artist as Exemplary Sufferer,” in Against Interpretation and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l33' n='N033'/>Other Essays (New York: Dell, 1961), p. 42.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l34' n='N034'/>9. Art et Scholastique (Paris: Louis Rouart et Fils, 1927), pp. 20-21, 44,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l35' n='N035'/>46. My translations.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l36' n='N036'/>10. Sontag, quoting Caesar Pavese, p. 43.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l37' n='N037'/>11. “Having an Experience,” in Art as Experience (New York: Capri¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l38' n='N038'/>corn Books, 1934), pp. 35-37.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l39' n='N039'/>12. Therese’s case is treated by Ellis, pp. 316-319.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l40' n='N040'/>13. See Chaucer’s “Clerk’s Tale” and the tenth tale of the tenth day in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l41' n='N041'/>Boccaccio’s Decameron.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l42' n='N042'/>14. For a summary discussion of aesthetic theory from Baumgarten to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l43' n='N043'/>Knight, see Leo Tolstoy’s What is Art? and Essays on Art, trans. Alymer
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l44' n='N044'/>Maude (London: Oxford University Press. 1930), pp. 92-110.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l45' n='N045'/>15. Quoted by Gwendolyn Bridges and Robert Utter in Pamela’s Daugh-
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l46' n='N046'/>ters (1963; rpt. New York: Russell and Russell, 1972), p. 25.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l47' n='N047'/>16. For a description of this etymology—so cloyingly written as to belie
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l48' n='N048'/>its true meaning—see Iwan Bloch, The Sexual Life of Our Time, 6th ed.,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l49' n='N049'/>trans. M. Eden Paul (London: Rebman Ltd., 1908), p. 78.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l50' n='N050'/>17. “Fundamental Principles of the Rights of Family,” in The Science of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l51' n='N051'/>Rights, trans. A.E. Kroger (Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott, 1869), p. 402.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l52' n='N052'/>18. “Of Queens’ Gardens,” in Sesame and Lilies: Three Lectures, rev.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l53' n='N053'/>and enl. (New York: Metropolitan, 1871), p. 152.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l54' n='N054'/>19. “Reflexions sur le suicide,” in Ouvres de Madame la Baronne de
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l55' n='N055'/>Stael-Holstein (Paris: Chez Lefevre, 1858), vol. III, pp. 711-752.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l56' n='N056'/>20. Tolstoy, p. 326.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l57' n='N057'/>21. Fichte, pp. 424 and 441. Fichte remarks (p. 441): “She has the power
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l58' n='N058'/>to withdraw her freedom, if she could have the will to do so; but that is the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l59' n='N059'/>very point: she cannot rationally will to be free.” In other words, any wom¬
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l60' n='N060'/>an who chooses freedom is necessarily irrational; thus, she cannot sensibly
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_3_1l61' n='N061'/>assess her motives or use her freedom. It is curiously circular reasoning.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l1' n='N001'/>Arlene Ladden is a free-lance writer teaching at La Guardia Community College in
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r_4_1l2' n='N002'/>New York and a member of the HERESIES Collective.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
