<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='37'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_1' n='N001'/>Class hierarchies and heterosexuality are patriarchal
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_2' n='N002'/>institutions which divide women, give some women
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_3' n='N003'/>power over others, and destroy our strength. As a les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_4' n='N004'/>bian feminist artist, 1 am interested in examining the
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_5' n='N005'/>assumptions of class and heterosexuality in art, and the
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_6' n='N006'/>role of lesbian art as a potential catalyst for social
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_7' n='N007'/>change. This article will focus on the myth of art as
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_8' n='N008'/>classless, and how this myth functions to separate us
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_9' n='N009'/>from the reality of our lives and affects the way in which
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_10' n='N010'/>we see ourselves. Specifically, I want to discuss how we
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_11' n='N011'/>as lesbian artists need to defy this myth by developing
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_12' n='N012'/>class consciousness, and incorporating it in the develop¬
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_13' n='N013'/>ment of lesbian art and culture.
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_14' n='N014'/>THE MYTH
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_15' n='N015'/>Fine art is a reflection of upper class interests, values,
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_16' n='N016'/>tastes, and patterns of thinking. The images found in art
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_17' n='N017'/>reflect and serve the needs of a small group of “corpor¬
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_18' n='N018'/>ate-government elite” (upper class white men) who
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_19' n='N019'/>define culture in America and elsewhere if they can
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_20' n='N020'/>profit from it. They found, fund, and run art museums,
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_21' n='N021'/>set standards of taste, and have a vested interest in
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_22' n='N022'/>creating, validating, and supporting art whose form and
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_23' n='N023'/>content justifies and furthers a patriarchal social order.
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_24' n='N024'/>Jackie St. Joan has defined this social order as:
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_25' n='N025'/>..that system—intellectual, political, social, sexual,
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_26' n='N026'/>psychological—which requires in the name of human
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_27' n='N027'/>progress that one group (in the history of the world, rich,
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_28' n='N028'/>white men) controls and exploits the energies of another
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_29' n='N029'/>and in which women are particularly despised. It includes
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_30' n='N030'/>patriarchal institutions (heterosexuality, the nuclear fam¬
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_31' n='N031'/>ily, private property, etc.) which are the tools of oppres¬
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_32' n='N032'/>sion as well as the patriarchal mind-constructs which, like
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_33' n='N033'/>the capitalist mind-constructs, limit even our ability to
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_34' n='N034'/>think beyond what is.
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_35' n='N035'/>Rarely does fine art include images of workers, the
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_36' n='N036'/>workplace, or daily survival. Rarely does it depict the
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_37' n='N037'/>experiences of Blacks, Native Americans, women, or
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_38' n='N038'/>lesbians. When these images do appear, they seem out¬
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_39' n='N039'/>side the experience of those portrayed because they are
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_40' n='N040'/>romanticized or stereotyped, rather than real. For
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_41' n='N041'/>instance, lesbian sexuality is rarely portrayed in visual
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_42' n='N042'/>art and when it is, say in film, lesbians are presented in
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_43' n='N043'/>butch/femme roles, as sick, masochistic, and sadistic,
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_44' n='N044'/>and as though sexuality was the only important thing in
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_45' n='N045'/>their lives. This limited male view hardly relates to my
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_46' n='N046'/>experience as a lesbian. Nor do I feel that my identity as
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_47' n='N047'/>an artist is realistically portrayed. The artist’s life is
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_1_1' n='N001'/>CLASSNOTES
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_2_1' n='N002'/>HARMONY HAMMOND
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_1_2' n='N001'/>romanticized as a chosen struggle of economic hardship
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_2_2' n='N002'/>necessary to produce art rather than as a product of the
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_3_1' n='N003'/>alienation of artists from society.
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_4_1' n='N004'/>If art provides a way for us to perceive ourselves and
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_5_1' n='N005'/>the world around us, it seems necessary that we examine
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_6_1' n='N006'/>what is validated as art. An excellent example of an
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_7_1' n='N007'/>attempt to write social history through art was the
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_8_1' n='N008'/>exhibition “American Art,” a collection belonging to
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_9_1' n='N009'/>John D. Rockefeller III, which was shown last fall at the
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_10_1' n='N010'/>Whitney Museum as our Bicentennial survey exhibition
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_11_1' n='N011'/>of American art. This collection contains one work by a
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_12_1' n='N012'/>woman artist, one work by a Black artist, and no work
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_13_1' n='N013'/>by Hispanic or Native American artists. The absence of
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_14_1' n='N014'/>work by women and Third World artists in this and
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_15_1' n='N015'/>most other collections and exhibitions, denies the experi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_16_1' n='N016'/>ences of most Americans. Not to see their experiences
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_17_1' n='N017'/>reflected in culture is to say that they don’t exist.
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_18_1' n='N018'/>Because art both creates and reflects social realities,
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_19_1' n='N019'/>their absence becomes a political issue. As the artists
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_20_1' n='N020'/>writing in an anti-catalogue” state: “Omission is one of
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_21_1' n='N021'/>the mechanisms by which fine art reinforces the values
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_22_1' n='N022'/>and beliefs of the powerful and suppresses the experi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_23_1' n='N023'/>ences of others.&quot;3
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_24_1' n='N024'/>Another mechanism reinforcing upper class values is
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_25_1' n='N025'/>the myth of art as classless and universal. By creating
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_26_1' n='N026'/>the myth of universal art, those in power teach us to
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_27_1' n='N027'/>identify with images and the experiences these images
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_28_1' n='N028'/>represent, which have nothing to do with our own class
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_29_1' n='N029'/>position. We are told that art, and therefore the artist, is
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_30_1' n='N030'/>classless, and that our experiences are immaterial and
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_31_1' n='N031'/>should be ignored.
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_32_1' n='N032'/>All classes accept this myth, for to question it would
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_33_1' n='N033'/>be to reveal the oppressive political structures and social
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_34_1' n='N034'/>institutions underlying patriarchal capitalist society.
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_35_1' n='N035'/>Rita Mae Brown writes that “America is a country reluc¬
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_36_1' n='N036'/>tant to recognize class differences. The American myth
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_37_1' n='N037'/>crystallized is: This is the land of equal opportunity;
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_38_1' n='N038'/>work hard, stay in line, you’ll get ahead. (Getting ahead
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_39_1' n='N039'/>always means money.)&quot;“ Identification with this myth
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_40_1' n='N040'/>of classlessness redirects us from dealing with our own
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_41_1' n='N041'/>particular oppression as working class, as women, as
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_42_1' n='N042'/>lesbians, etc. The artists in an anti-catalogue” state:
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_43_1' n='N043'/>“The mystification of art depends upon two things—upon
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_44_1' n='N044'/>our surrendering our capacity to judge and upon unques¬
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_45_1' n='N045'/>tioning acceptance of authority in place of the printed
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_46_1' n='N046'/>word and the authority of scholarly titles and distinctions.
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_47_1' n='N047'/>The mystification of art takes our passivity for granted. It
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_48' n='N048'/>encourages us to look upon art as if art had no bearing on
				<lb facs='#facs_37_region_1674939466496_765_tl_49' n='N049'/>experience.
			</p>
			<pb n='38'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_1' n='N001'/>Accepting the myth is accepting our invisibility and
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_2' n='N002'/>powerlessness. To question cultural attitudes is to
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_3' n='N003'/>question social conditions. Passivity smooths the pain
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_4' n='N004'/>of powerlessness and helps us to survive these condi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_5' n='N005'/>tions. We need to see that behavioral patterns affect
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_6' n='N006'/>who becomes an artist, what artists create, what art is
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_7' n='N007'/>validated as quality, and how art in turn reinforces
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_8' n='N008'/>those patterns.
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_9' n='N009'/>UTT
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_10' n='N010'/>HOWIBOUGHI IHEMYTH
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_11' n='N011'/>Thinking back to junior high school in the fifties, I see
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_12' n='N012'/>that one reason 1 chose to be an artist was to escape the
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_13' n='N013'/>daily pain of lower middle class life in Hometown—of
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_14' n='N014'/>living in a duplex, taking a bus to school, and wearing
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_15' n='N015'/>hand-me-downs until I got a job at Lerner’s and could
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_16' n='N016'/>buy my own clothes. The guy I went with turned me on
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_17' n='N017'/>to Mulligan, Coleman, Getz, and all that jazz and the
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_18' n='N018'/>beat writers Kerouac, Ginsberg, and Prevert. They were
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_19' n='N019'/>&quot;artists&quot; and intellectuals, without money (like me), and
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_20' n='N020'/>romanticized. I thumbed my nose and fantasized riding
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_21' n='N021'/>naked down the highway. We fucked. I got a scholar-
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_22' n='N022'/>ship to the Saturday School of the Art Institute of
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_23' n='N023'/>Chicago. I wanted to be a dress designer or fashion
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_24' n='N024'/>illustrator because it sounded “classy” and &quot;sophisti¬
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_25' n='N025'/>cated.&quot; If all else failed, I could be an art teacher.
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_26' n='N026'/>In the museum I saw “real&quot; painting and sculpture. I
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_27' n='N027'/>remember sitting in front of the Pollock, the Rothko,
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_28' n='N028'/>and the Still, thinking that I could do those paintings,
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_29' n='N029'/>but not realizing that I was a woman and that it didn’t
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_30' n='N030'/>matter what I did. In the studios I saw art being made by
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_31' n='N031'/>grubby students and I took note that the artist could
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_32' n='N032'/>wear anything, say anything, and didn’t have to social¬
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_33' n='N033'/>ize. The artist seemed special and not bound by class
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_34' n='N034'/>behavior. I would be an artist. Accepting fine art meant
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_35' n='N035'/>renouncing my class background and stepping out of
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_36' n='N036'/>the lower middle class life of Hometown into the univer¬
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_37' n='N037'/>sal world of the muses. Safe and protected at last. Who
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_38' n='N038'/>ever heard of a middle class muse?
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_40' n='N040'/>THEMYTHSHATTEI
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_41' n='N041'/>ED:
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_42' n='N042'/>CLASSIS HOW YOU SEE THE WORLD.
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_43' n='N043'/>ART IS HOWYOUSEE THEWORLD.
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_44' n='N044'/>It has taken me a long time to begin to understand
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_45' n='N045'/>and accept my lower middle class background, and to
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_46' n='N046'/>realize that the art world I entered wasn’t an alternative
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_47' n='N047'/>to middle class society but that women, Blacks, and the
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_48' n='N048'/>poor are also oppressed within the alternate “world of
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_49' n='N049'/>culture. As long as society allowed me to be a starving
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_50' n='N050'/>artist&quot; I did not question my own experiences, or how
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_1_1' n='N001'/>they affected my work and work attitudes. Acting out a
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_2_1' n='N002'/>romanticized art life was my option to upward mobility.
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_3_1' n='N003'/>Heterosexual women get their privilege from the same
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_4_1' n='N004'/>patriarchal systems that give privilege to middle and
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_5_1' n='N005'/>upper class women. Coming out as a lesbian with a
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_6_1' n='N006'/>feminist consciousness forced me to realize what class
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_7_1' n='N007'/>privilege I did and did not have, and what I would now
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_8_1' n='N008'/>lose. Even the fact that I first came out to myself
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_9_1' n='N009'/>through my art and not in bed is in itself a reflection of
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_10_1' n='N010'/>my class position. As a feminist artist I had learned to
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_11_1' n='N011'/>use my work as a place to confront fears and other
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_12_1' n='N012'/>feelings privately in my studio. A woman working as a
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_13_1' n='N013'/>maid, a waitress, or a seamstress, does not have this
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_14_1' n='N014'/>option.
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_15_1' n='N015'/>As a lesbian, however, 1 was forced to confront and
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_16_1' n='N016'/>give up illusions I had about being accepted and
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_17_1' n='N017'/>rewarded by the male art world where they treated art
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_18_1' n='N018'/>seriously. To be public about being a lesbian means
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_19_1' n='N019'/>that your work may not be taken seriously, or may
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_20_1' n='N020'/>squeezed into a category of “camp” or erotic art.
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_21_1' n='N021'/>Because you do not hang out with the right men or the
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_22_1' n='N022'/>right women (those who hang out with the men) at the
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_23_1' n='N023'/>right bars, and since the lesbian feminist community
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_24_1' n='N024'/>doesn’t yet support its visual artists, you are less likely
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_25_1' n='N025'/>to make your work visible, to have professional
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_26_1' n='N026'/>dialogue, and to support yourself through your work
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_27_1' n='N027'/>either directly (sales) or indirectly (teaching). For
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_28_1' n='N028'/>women, the economic class system is largely determined
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_29_1' n='N029'/>by their relationship to men. The higher up the man she
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_30_1' n='N030'/>relates to, the more she benefits from the system. The
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_31_1' n='N031'/>lesbian, by not relating to men does not benefit eco¬
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_32_1' n='N032'/>nomically and has no privilege unless she is independ¬
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_33_1' n='N033'/>ently wealthy. Most of us do not have that kind of
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_34_1' n='N034'/>support and opportunity, and without support, it is
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_35_1' n='N035'/>very difficult to continue making art. Historically,
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_36_1' n='N036'/>known lesbian visual artists (Rosa Bonheur, Romaine
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_37_1' n='N037'/>Brooks, etc.) were wealthy. Only they had the privilege
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_38_1' n='N038'/>to continue making art despite their public lesbian
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_39_1' n='N039'/>lifestyle.
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_40_1' n='N040'/>If we examine the relationship of lesbians to the class
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_41_1' n='N041'/>system, and to patriarchy, we can get an idea of the
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_42_1' n='N042'/>active role art can play in developing a culture that does
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_43_1' n='N043'/>not make women powerless and invisible. In “Lesbians
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_44_1' n='N044'/>and The Class Position of Women,&quot; Margaret Small
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_45_1' n='N045'/>writes:
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_46_1' n='N046'/>...At this point in history, the primary role that lesbians
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_47_1' n='N047'/>have to play in the development of revolutionary con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_48_1' n='N048'/>sciousness is ideological. Because lesbians are objectively
				<lb facs='#facs_38_region_1674939487198_774_tl_49_1' n='N049'/>outside of heterosexual reality, they have potential for
			</p>
			<pb n='39'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_1' n='N001'/>developing an alternative ideology not limited by hetero¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_2' n='N002'/>sexuality. Lesbians stand in a different relationship to
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_3' n='N003'/>(the) three conditions that determine the class position of
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_4' n='N004'/>women (production, reproduction, sexuality). The les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_5' n='N005'/>bian does not have a domestic base that is defined by the
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_6' n='N006'/>production of new labor power and maintenance of her
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_7' n='N007'/>husband’s labor power. Her relationship is in proletarian
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_8' n='N008'/>terms. The element of slave consciousness integral to
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_9' n='N009'/>heterosexuality is missing.?
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_10' n='N010'/>I am interested in how we can do this through art.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_11' n='N011'/>Developing a class consciousness does not mean that
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_12' n='N012'/>each work of art by a woman would have to directly
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_13' n='N013'/>relate to women of all classes, but rather that the form
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_14' n='N014'/>and content of the work, be it figurative or abstract,
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_15' n='N015'/>would somehow illuminate experience in such a way
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_16' n='N016'/>that it is shared with and includes rather than excludes
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_17' n='N017'/>women from different backgrounds. Instead of present¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_18' n='N018'/>ing one universal experience that is supposed to repre¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_19' n='N019'/>sent ALL of us yet represents few, art should reflect and
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_20' n='N020'/>give information—facts, emotional response, visual
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_21' n='N021'/>accounting, ways of seeing into and understanding dif¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_22' n='N022'/>ferent experiences and feelings. We must acknowledge
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_23' n='N023'/>our differences in order to learn about, support, and
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_24' n='N024'/>work with each other. Thus I feel that to make art as a
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_25' n='N025'/>lesbian with class consciousness has far-reaching cre¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_26' n='N026'/>ative and political potential for connecting women
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_27' n='N027'/>through work. This means actively rejecting cultural
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_28' n='N028'/>dictates, taking responsibility for our work, and ques¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_29' n='N029'/>tioning the concept of apolitical art. Art-making is
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_30' n='N030'/>where consciousness is formed.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_31' n='N031'/>ANALYSIS—REINTEGRATION
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_32' n='N032'/>Ultimately it is a question of the function of art
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_33' n='N033'/>beyond the personal. It is not merely a matter of doing
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_34' n='N034'/>work that doesn’t oppress others, but also of doing
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_35' n='N035'/>work that pushes further towards a redefinition and
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_36' n='N036'/>transformation of culture. For me, coming out as a les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_37' n='N037'/>bian has a lot to do with developing a class conscious¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_38' n='N038'/>ness, and that consciousness brought to my art raises
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_39' n='N039'/>questions of imagery, permanence, scale, ways of
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_40' n='N040'/>working, and concepts of art education. It raises ques¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_41' n='N041'/>tions of money and power, who sees my work, and
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_42' n='N042'/>what effect I want it to have on others.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_43' n='N043'/>This does not mean that we as class conscious lesbian
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_44' n='N044'/>artists must make paintings with recognizable figurative
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_45' n='N045'/>imagery, that we must be downwardly mobile, give up
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_46' n='N046'/>making art for “real political struggle, or involve our¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_47' n='N047'/>selves in the rhetorical circles of the artistic left. What it
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_48' n='N048'/>does mean is not making or accepting class assumptions
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_49' n='N049'/>about art such as what is allowable as art, who makes it,
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_50' n='N050'/>who sees it, and what its function is to be. By removing
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_51' n='N051'/>esthetic hierarchies and the need to pretend that we all
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_52' n='N052'/>share the same experiences, meaning can become acces¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_53' n='N053'/>sible and available.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_54' n='N054'/>Talk about &quot;bringing art to the people” only reinforces
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_55' n='N055'/>class distinctions. Class consciousness can be reflected
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_56' n='N056'/>through our art by demystifying and deprivatizing the
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_57' n='N057'/>creative process. Presently it is difficult for a working
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_58' n='N058'/>class woman who likes to write, paint, or dance even to
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_59' n='N059'/>consider being a professional artist. When making art as
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_60' n='N060'/>well as owning art ceases to be a privilege, and the
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_61' n='N061'/>art-making process itself is available to women of dif¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_62' n='N062'/>ferent classes, races, and geographic backgrounds, we
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_63' n='N063'/>can begin to understand the political potential of
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_64' n='N064'/>creative expression.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_65' n='N065'/>As lesbians, we need our experience validated cul¬
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_1_1' n='N001'/>turally. To refuse art that denies our existence and to
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_2_1' n='N002'/>deny that art is apolitical and universal, is to actively
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_3_1' n='N003'/>challenge the wealthy few and their supporters who
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_4_1' n='N004'/>have been defining and controlling social order through
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_5_1' n='N005'/>the manipulation of fine art. Demanding group and self
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_6_1' n='N006'/>identity in art is one means of resisting oppression. The
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_7_1' n='N007'/>art-making process is a tool for making these demands
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_8_1' n='N008'/>and changes.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_9_1' n='N009'/>Art is essentially work. Simone Weil writes that art is
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_10_1' n='N010'/>a surplus commodity in this culture because it does not
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_11_1' n='N011'/>have immediate consumption and is not shared and
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_12_1' n='N012'/>used by the people. That artists are not part of the paid
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_13_1' n='N013'/>work force further separates the productive from the
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_14_1' n='N014'/>consumptive classes. The work process (and the purpose
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_15_1' n='N015'/>of work) have always been external to the worker. Just
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_16_1' n='N016'/>as she writes that our main task is to discover how it is
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_17_1' n='N017'/>possible for the work to be free and to integrate it, we
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_18_1' n='N018'/>must free the art-making process so it is accessible and
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_19_1' n='N019'/>understandable to everyone. The process should be as
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_20_1' n='N020'/>available as the product.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_21_1' n='N021'/>Acknowledging the existence of class structures, and
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_22_1' n='N022'/>how through art they can affect cultural attitudes is just
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_23_1' n='N023'/>a beginning—a necessary step one. In the long run, we
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_24_1' n='N024'/>should not focus merely on the relationship of one class
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_25_1' n='N025'/>to another, or on the relationship of art and class, but
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_26_1' n='N026'/>on defining a future classless society. The integration of
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_27_1' n='N027'/>art into the lives of all people and not just the upper
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_28_1' n='N028'/>class contributes to that vision. &quot;Revolution presup¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_29_1' n='N029'/>poses not simply an economic and political transforma¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_30_1' n='N030'/>tion but also a technical and cultural one.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_1_2' n='N001'/>FOOTNOTES
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_2_2' n='N002'/>1. The Catalogue Committee of Artists Meeting for Cul¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_3_2' n='N003'/>tural Change, an anti-catalogue, 1977. The catalogue
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_4_2' n='N004'/>was written as a protest to the Whitney exhibition,
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_5_2' n='N005'/>&quot;American Art, 1976. I have included a condensed
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_6_2' n='N006'/>version of a more detailed discussion of “how art is
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_7_2' n='N007'/>mystified, how art exhibitions influence our views of
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_8_2' n='N008'/>history, and how collectors such as John D. Rockefeller
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_9_2' n='N009'/>III benefit from cultural philanthropy.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_10_2' n='N010'/>&quot;A Lesbian Feminist: Jackie St. Joan, an interview, in
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_11_2' n='N011'/>Big Mama Rag, Jan-Feb, 1977, Vol. 5, no. 1.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_12_2' n='N012'/>3. an anti-catalogue
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_13_2' n='N013'/>4. Brown, Rita Mae, “The Last Straw,&quot; Class and Femin¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_14_2' n='N014'/>ism: A Collection of Essays From The Furies, edited by
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_15_2' n='N015'/>Charlotte Bunch and Nancy Myron, Diana Press,
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_16_2' n='N016'/>1974.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_17_2' n='N017'/>5. an anti-catalogue.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_18_2' n='N018'/>6. Small, Margaret, “Lesbians and the Class Position of
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_19_2' n='N019'/>Women,&quot; Lesbianism and the Women&apos;s Movement,
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_20_2' n='N020'/>edited by Nancy Myron and Charlotte Bunch, Diana
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_21_2' n='N021'/>Press, 1975.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_22_2' n='N022'/>Weil, Simone, First and Last Notebooks, translated by
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_23_2' n='N023'/>Richard Rees, Oxford University Press, London, 1970,
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_24_2' n='N024'/>p. 58-61.
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_25_2' n='N025'/>8. First and Last Notebooks.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_1_3' n='N001'/>Harmony Hammond is a painter and sometimes writer who is
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_2_3' n='N002'/>a member of the Heresies collective. She teaches at any univer¬
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_3_3' n='N003'/>sity and feminist art program that will have her, and gives
				<lb facs='#facs_39_region_1674939514116_789_tl_4_3' n='N004'/>workshops and lectures on lesbian artists and feminist artists.
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
