<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
         	<title>Who Are We? What Do We Want? What Do We Do?</title>
         	<author>Accion para la Liberacion de la Mujer Peruana</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>Heresies</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="99"/>
         <head>
         	<title>Who Are We? What Do We Wont? What Do We Do? <note>*Excerpts (slightly rearranged) from the booklet of this
         		name distributed by "Accion para la Liberacion de la Mujer
         		Peruana," April 15, 1975, Lima, Peru. This text was taken
         		from the first half of the booklet; the second half deals with
         		a specific program for practical revolutionary work. The
         		following are listed as the group's coordinators and "hon¬
         		orary members“: Cristina Portocarrero Rey, Ana Maria
         		Portugal, Amor Arguedas, Dorelly Castafieda, Beatriz
         		Ramos, Lucia Parra, Margot Loayza, Edith Alva, Carmela
         		Bravo, Dora Ponce, Flor Herrera, Leo Arteaga, Diana
         		Arteaga, Dora Guerrero, Bertha Vargas, Inés Pratt, Adela
         		Montesinos, Estela Luna Lôpez.</note>
         	
				Accion para la Liberacion de la Mujer Peruana</title>
         </head>
         <p >We are a group of women who have orga¬
				nized to study, work and fight for our liberation,
				and especially to work with and for our sisters
				who suffer a double oppression: in being wom¬
				en and in belonging to a social sector which has
				been historically dominated and exploited.
			</p>
         <lg><l>The struggle of women is integrally bound to</l>
				<l>the struggle of working-class women.</l>
				<l>No! to Mother's Day.</l>
				<l>Yes! to Peruvian Woman's Day.</l>
				<l>Less homage, more rights.</l>
			</lg>
         <p >Why are we named Action for the Liberation
				of Peruvian Women?</p>
				<p>Because we want to carry out our work with¬
				out euphemisms or timidity—in short, without
				masks or half-measures. It is correct to call
				actions which are destined to radically change
				our condition by their rightful name: liberation.</p>
				<p>Ours is simultaneously a study-group and an
				action-group. We are by no means a political
				party. We do not aspire to be an institution with
				traditional hierarchic structure. We reject ver¬
				ticalism, dogmatism and leadership positions.
				Ideologically, we align ourselves within free
				Humanist Socialism and adopt the best of its
				tenets conducive to female emancipation.</p>
         <p ><lg><l>Without national liberation, there can be no</l>
				<l>women's liberation. Fight!</l>
				<l>Only reactionary men are our enemies!</l>
				<l>Sisters, Unite with us!</l>
				<l>Liberation is action!</l></lg>
			</p>
         <p >Because we cannot separate our specific
				problems from our socio-economic context, all
				our work strategies are adapted to the actual
				conditions of our country. We do not copy
				foreign movements because we are aware of
				living in a Third-World Society where imperjal¬
				ism is our most powerful enemy. Therefore we
				express solidarity with other liberation struggles
				on this continent, as well as with other women
				and men fighting for national liberation in their
				respective countries.
			</p>
         <p ><lg><l>To analyze the historic and social origins of our</l>
				<l>condition is to revolutionize our understanding</l>
		<l>		of the world!</l></lg>
			</p>
         <p >We believe our liberation is inseparable from
				that of other oppressed groups—workers and
				peasants. The liberation of our brothers will
				never be realized while their women—workers
				and peasants too—are second-class citizens,
				and while prostitution is seen as a "necessary
				and insuperable evil."</p>
				<p>Consequently we do not believe in individual
				liberation. The fact that some of our sisters are
				being promoted to important public positions
				or are gaining access to professional and tech¬
				nical careers in increasingly greater numbers
				has nothing to do with liberation. We believe
				that only structural change will produce real
				"women's liberation."</p>
				<p>So our position, our actions, are aimed at
				contributing to the process of transformation
				taking place in our country, at helping it
				strengthen and advance without obstacles. We
				support this Revolution because it is anti¬
				imperialist and anti-oligarchic, and because it
				makes possible our own liberation.</p>
				<p>What do we call Cultural Revolution?</p>
				<p>The process by which the old system is entire¬
				ly questioned and revised: its values, behavior,
				habits, customs, institutions and forms of com¬
				munication. A Cultural Revolution must reject
				all individualism, engendering a collective way
				of life harmonious with group ideals, while re¬
				sistant to group egoism. A Cultural Revolution
				must combat stereotypical attitudes like "male¬
				ism" (machismo) and "femaleism" (hembrismo)
				—brute maleness and coy femaleness. A Cul¬
				tural Revolution must change patriarchal insti¬
				tutions like bourgeois marriage and the nuclear
				family—two characteristic expressions of capi¬
				talism and the division of labor. Finally, a
				Cultural Revolution's ultimate goal must be to
				change life, to culminate in a free and humane
				socialism.</p>

         <p ><lg><l>Wanting to shape your own destiny is wanting</l>
				<l>to transform injustice.</l>
				<l>Wanting to transform injustice is being political.</l></lg>
			</p>
         <p >What do we want to be liberated from?</p>
				<p>From the social, economic, political, cultural
				and moral conditions imposed by a patriarchal
				capitalist society which assigns us secondary
				roles, condemning us to live as marginal beings
				passively supporting and "servicing" men.</p>
				<p>From reformist paternalism which perpetually
				treats us as legal minors, because it reduces
         <pb n="100"/>
        everything to the creation or amplification of
				protectionary laws that are pretexts to mask our
				real situation of dependence on men and
				second-class citizenship.</p>
				<p>From all kinds of ideological pressure, ex¬
				pressed in the terror most of us feel about join¬
				ing feminist organizations, under the assump¬
				tion that if we do so, we must be "against men.“
				From the fear of being ridiculed or insulted as
				tomboys," "whores," or "dykes."</p>
      	
         <p ><lg><l>Statistics affirm that few women are workers.</l>
				<l>Out of the home and onto the production lines!</l>
				<l>Working women also carry the burden of the home!</l>
				<l>Communal eating-places, day-care centers and</l>
				<l>laundries—to create new jobs and lessen the</l>
				<l>load of unpaid workers in the home.</l>
				<l>Being a mother and being fulfilled shouldn’t be</l>
				<l>a contradiction.</l>
				<l>We want family planning in hospitals, accessible to everyone.</l></lg>
			</p>
         <p >Against whom must we struggle?</p>
				<p>Against the Patriarchal-Capitalist System
				which determines an unjust society, fostering
				exploitation, abuse, discrimination, hunger,
        		wars and massacres; a system which transforms
				woman into a beast of burden (if she is prole¬
				tarian), or into a luxury sex-object (if she is bour¬
				geois). Capitalism has also reviled love, reduc¬
				ing male-female relationships to economic
				factors or to mere social appearances. It is a
				system in which children are the responsibility
				of individual couples and, in actual practice, of
				the women alone.</p>
				<p>Against all sexist ideology which gains by re¬
				inforcing our situation as "different“ and which
				is expressed in the cult of "femininity“—sweet¬
				ness, weakness, virginity and motherhood as
				woman's only aim and destiny.</p>
				<p>And finally, against all threats to the libera¬
				tion front whose ultimate goal is the Monolithic
				Unity of Revolutionary Women, and of those
				men who integrally support the cause of our
				liberation.</p>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
