<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Sister Outsiders</title>
				<author>Audre Lorde</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Issue 15: Racism is the Issue</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="15"/>

			<head><title>SISTER OUTSIDERS</title></head>
			<byline>BY AUDRE LORDE</byline>

			<p> I walked down those three little steps into the Bagatelle on a weekend night in
				1956. There was an inner door, guarded by a male bouncer, ostensibly to keep out
				the straight male intruders come to gawk at the "lezzies, but in reality to keep out
				those women deemed "undesirable." All too frequently, undesirable meant Black.</p>
			<p>Women stood three-deep around the bar and between the tables, and in the doorway to
				the postage-stamp-sized dance floor. By 9:00 p.m. the floor was packed solid with
				women's bodies moving slowly to the jukebox beat of Ruth Brown's When your friends
				have left you all alone / and you have no one to call your own... or Frank Sinatra's
				"Set 'em up, Joe / I got a little story.</p>
			<p>When I moved through the bunches of women cruising each other in the front room, or
				doing a slow fish on the dance floor in the back, with the smells of cigarette smoke
				and the music and the hair pomade whirling together like incense through charged
				air, it was hard for me to believe that my being an outsider had anything to do with
				being a lesbian. But when I, a Black woman, saw no reflection in any of the faces
				there week after week, I knew perfectly well that being an outsider in the Baga¬
				telle had everything to do with being Black.</p>
			<p>The society within the confines of the Bagatelle reflected the ripples and eddies of
				the larger society that had spawned it, and which allowed the Bagatelle to survive
				as long as it did, selling watered-down drinks at inflated prices to lonely dykes
				who had no other social outlet or community gathering place.</p>
			<p>Rather than the idyllic picture created by false nostalgia, the fifties were really
				straight white america's cooling-off period of "let's pretend we're happy and that
				this is the best of all possible worlds and we'll blow those nasty commies to hell
				if they dare to say otherwise.' The Rosenbergs had been executed, the transistor
				radio had been invented, and frontal lobotomy was the standard solution for
				persistent deviation. For some, Elvis Presley and his stolen Black rhythms became
				arch-symbols of the antichrist.</p>
			<p>Young america's growing pains, within the Bagatelle, were represented by the fashion
				conflicts between the blue-jeans set and the Bermuda-shorts set. Then, of course,
				there were those who fell in between, both by virtue of our art or our craziness or
				our color.</p>
			<p>The breakdown into the mommies and daddies was an important part of lesbian
				relationships in the Bagatelle. If you asked the wrong woman to dance, you could get
				your nose broken in the alley down the street by her butch, who had followed you out
				of the Bag for exactly that purpose. It was safer to keep to yourself. And you were
				never supposed to ask who was who, which is why there was such heavy emphasis on
				corréct garb. The well-dressed gay-girl was supposed to give you enough clues for
				you to know.</p>
			<p>For some of us, however, the role-playing reflected all the depreciating attitudes
				toward women which we loathed in straight society. It was a rejection of these roles
				that had drawn us to the life" in the first place. Instinctively, without particular
				theory or political position or dialectic, we recognized oppression as oppression,
				no matter where it came from. But those lesbians who had carved some niche in the
				pretend world of dominance/subordination rejected what they called our "confused"
				life style, and they were in the majority.</p>
			<p>Felicia was so late one Sunday afternoon for our photography lesson that Muriel and I
				went off to Laurel's without her, because you had to be early on Sundays to get
				something to eat. The Swing Rendezvous had closed its table, but at Laurel's on
				Sunday afternoon there was free brunch with any drink, and that meant all you could
				eat. Many of the gay bars used this to get Sunday afternoon business at a
				traditionally slow time, but Laurel's had the best food. There was a Chinese cook
				there of no mean talent. He cooked back and kept it coming. After the word got
				around, every Sunday afternoon at four o'clock there would be a line of gay-girls in
				front of Laurel's, smoking and talking and trying to pretend we had all arrived
				there at that time by accident.</p>
			<p>When the doors opened, there was a discreet but determined stampede, first to the bar
				and then to the food table, set up in the rear of the lounge. We tried to keep our
				cool, pretending that we couldn’t care less for barbecued spare ribs with peach
				and apricot sweet sauce, or succulent pink shrimp swimming in thick golden lobster
				sauce, dotted with bits of green scallion and bright yellow egg drops, tiny pieces
				of pork and onion afloat on top. There were stacked piles of crispy brown egg rolls
				filled with shredded ham and chicken and celery, rolled together and fried with a
				touch of sesame paste. There were fried chicken bits, and every once in a great
				while, a special delicacy such as lobster or fresh crab. Only the first lucky few
				got to taste those special dishes, so it was worthwhile being first on line and
				pushing your cool image a little bit askew.</p>
			<p>We were healthy young female animals mercifully more alive than most of our peers,
				robust and active women, and our blood was always high and our pockets empty and a
				free meal in convivial surroundings—meaning around other lesbians—was a big treat
				for most of us, even if purchased at the price of a bottle of beer, which was fifty
				cents, with many complaints. Dancing wasn't allowed at Laurel's so it never got to
				be as popular as the Bag, except on Sunday afternoons. Muriel preferred it because
				it was always quieter. Trix ran the place, and always had a hand for 'her girls.'
				Tiny and tough, with a permanent Florida tan and a Bronx accent, she took a shine to
				Muriel and me, and sometimes she would buy us a beer, and sit down and talk with us
				if the place wasn't too crowded.</p>
			<p>We all knew the situation with gay bars, how they came in and out of existence with
				such regularity and who really profited from them. But Trix was pretty and bright
				and hard and kind all at the same time, and her permanent tan particularly
				endeared her to me. She looked like one of the nicer of the hickory-skinned devils
				who used to people my dreams of that period.</p>
			<p>Actually, the lifespan of most gay bars was under a year, with the notable exception
				of a few like the Bag. Laurel's went the way of all the other gay bars—like the
				Swing and Snooky's and the Grapevine, the Sea Colony and the Pony Stable Inn. Each
				closed after a year or so, while another opened and caught on somewhere else. But
				for that year, Laurel's served as an important place for those of us who met and
				made some brief space for ourselves there. It had a feeling of family.</p>
			<p>On summer Sunday afternoons, Muriel and I would split from the gay beach at Coney
				Island or Riis Park early, take the subway back home in time to wash up and dress
				and saunter over to Laurel's in time for the food at 4:00. I had my first open color
				confrontation with a gay-girl one Sunday afternoon in Laurel's.</p>
			<p>Muriel and I had come back that day from Riis Park, full of sun and sand. We loved
				with the salt still on our skins, then bathed, washed our hair, and got ready to go
				out. I put on my faded cord riding britches with the suede crotch, and a pale blue
				short-sleeved sweatshirt bought earlier that week at John's on Avenue C for
				sixty-nine cents. My skin was tanned from the sun and burnished ruddy with the heat
				and much loving. My hair was newly trimmed and freshly washed, with the particular
				crispiness that it always develops in sustained summer heat. I felt raunchy and
				restless. We walked out of the hot August afternoon sun into the suddenly dark
				coolness of Laurel's downstairs. There was Muriel, in her black Bermuda shorts and
				shirt, ghost pale, her eternal cigarette in hand. And I was beside her, full of
				myself, knowing I was fat and Black and very fine. We were without peer or category,
				and on that day I was conscious of being very proud of it, no matter who looked down
				her nose at us.</p>
			<p>After Muriel and I had gotten our food and beer and copped one of the tables, Dottie
				and Pauli came over. We saw them a lot at the Bag and in the supermarket over on
				Avenue D, but we'd never been to their house nor they to ours, except for New Year's
				food, when everyone came.</p>
			<p>Where you guys been?" Pauli had an ingenuous smile, her blonde hair and blue eyes
				incandescent against the turquoise mandarin shirt she wore. Riis. Gay Beach."
				Muriel's finger crooked over the bottle as she took a slug. All of us eschewed
				glasses as faggy, although I sometimes longed for one because the cold beer hurt my
				teeth.</p>
			<p>Pauli turned to me. "Hey, that's a great tan you have there. I didn't know Negroes
				got tans." Her broad smile was intended to announce the remark as a joke.</p>
			<p>My usual defense in such situations was to ignore the overtones, to let it go. But
				Dottie Daws, probably out of her own nervousness at Pauli's reference to the
				unmentionable, would not let the matter drop. Raved on and on about my great tan.
				Matched her arm to mine. Shook her pale blonde head, telling whomever would listen
				that she wished she could tan like that instead of burning, and did I know how lucky
				I was to be able to get such a tan like that? I grew tired and then shakingly
				furious, having enough of whatever it was.</p>
			<p>How come you never make so much over my natural tan most days, Dottie Daws; how
				come?</p>
			<p>There was a moment of silence at the table, punctuated only by Muriel's darkly
				appreciative chuckle, and then we moved on to something else, <pb n="16"/>
				mercifully. I was still shaking inside. I never forgot it. In the gay bars, I longed
				for other Black women without the need ever taking shape on my lips. For four
				hundred years in this country, Black women have been taught to view each other with
				deep suspicion. It was no different in the gay world.</p>
			<p>Most Black lesbians were closeted, correctly recognizing the Black community's lack
				of interest in our position, as well as the many more immediate threats to our
				survival as Black people in a racist society. It was hard enough to be Black, to be
				Black and female, to be Black, female, and gay. To be Black, female, gay, and out of
				the closet, even to the extent of dancing in the Bagatelle, was considered by many
				Black lesbians to be simply suicidal. And if you were fool enough to do it, you'd
				better come on so tough that nobody messed with you. I often felt put down by their
				sophistication, their clothes, their manners, their cars, and their femmes,</p>
			<p>The Black women I usually saw around the Bag were into heavy roles, and it frightened
				me. This was partly the fear of my own Blackness mir rored, and partly the realities
				of the masquerade. These women felt to me like parts of my own sexual self I had not
				yet come to terms with. They seemed tough in a way I felt I could never be. Even if
				they were not, their self-protective instincts warned them to appear that way. By
				white america's racist distortions of beauty, Black women playing femme“ had very
				little chance in the Bag. There was constant competition among butches to have the
				most "gorgeous femme" on their arm. And "gorgeous" was defined by a white male
				world's standards.</p>
			<p>For me, going into the Bag was like entering an anomalous no-woman's land. I wasn't
				cute or passive enough to be femme," and I wasn't mean or tough enough to be
				"butch." I was given a wide berth. Nonconventional people can be dangerous, even in
				the gay community.</p>
			<p>With the exception of Felicia and myself, the other Black women in the Bag came
				protected by a show of all the power symbols they could muster. Whatever else they
				did during the week, on Friday nights when Lion or Trip appeared, sometimes with
				expensively dressed women on their arms, sometimes alone, they commanded attention
				and admiration. They were well-heeled, superbly dressed, self-controlled
				high-steppers who drove convertibles, bought rounds of drinks for their friends, and
				generally took care of business.</p>
			<p>But sometimes, even they couldn't get in unless they were recognized by the
				bouncer.</p>
			<p>My friends and I were the hippies of the gay-girl circuit, before the word was
				coined. Many of us wound up dead or demented, and many of us were distorted by the
				many fronts we had to fight upon. But when we survived, we grew up strong.</p>
			<p>Every Black woman I ever met in the Village in those years had some part in my
				survival, large or small, if only as a figure in the head-count at the Bag on a
				Friday night.</p>
			<p>Black lesbians in the Bagatelle faced a world only slightly less hostile than the
				outer world which we had to deal with every day on the outside— that world which
				defined us as doubly nothing because we were Black and because we were Women—that
				world which raised our blood pressures and shaped our furies and our nightmares.</p>
			<p>The temporary integration of war plants and the egalitarian myth of Rosie the Riveter
				had ended abruptly with the end of World War II and the wholesale return of the
				american woman to the role of little wifey. So far as I could see, gay-girls were
				the only Black and white women who were even talking to each other in this country
				in the 1950s, outside of the empty rhetoric of patriotism and political
				movements.</p>
			<p>Black or white, Ky-Ky, butch, or femme, the only thing we shared, often, and in
				varying proportions, was that we dared for connection in the name of woman, and saw
				that as our power, rather than our problem. All of us who survived those common
				years had to be a little strange. We spent so much of our young womanhood trying to
				define ourselves as woman-identified women before we even knew the words existed,
				let alone that there were ears interested in trying to hear them beyond our im¬
				mediate borders. All of us who survived those common years have to be a little
				proud. A lot proud. Keeping ourselves together and on our own tracks, however
				wobbly, was like trying to play the Dinizulu War Chant or a Beethoven sonata on a
				tin dog-whistle.</p>
			<p>The important message seemed to be that you had to have a place. Whether or not it
				did justice to whatever you felt you were about, there had to be some place to
				refuel and check your flaps.</p>
			<p>In times of need and great instability, the place sometimes became more a definition
				than the substance of why you needed it to begin with. Sometimes the retreat
				became the reality. The writers who posed in cafes talking their work to death
				without writing two words; the lesbians, virile as men, hating women and their own
				womanhood with a vengeance. The bars and the coffee shops and the streets of the
				Village in the 1950s were full of nonconformists who were deathly afraid of going
				against their hard-won group, and so eventually they were broken between the group
				and their individual needs.</p>
			<p>For some of us there was no one particular place, and we grabbed whatever we could
				from wherever we found space, comfort, quiet, a smile, nonjudgment.</p>
			<quote>Being women together was not enough. We were different. Being gay-girls together
				was not enough. We were different. Being Black together was not enough. We were
				different. Being Black women together was not enough. We were different. Being Black
				dykes together was not enough. We were different.</quote>
			<p>Each of us had our own needs and pursuits, and many different alliances.
				Self-preservation warned some of us that we could not afford to settle for one
				easy definition, one narrow individuation of self. At the Bag, at Hunter College,
				uptown in Harlem at the library, there was a piece of the real me bound in each
				place, and growing.</p>
			<p>It was a while before we came to realize that our place was the very house of
				difference rather than the security of any one particular difference. (And often,
				we were cowards in our learning.) It was years before we learned to use the strength
				that daily surviving can bring, years before we learned that fear does not have to
				incapacitate, and that we could appreciate each other on terms not necessarily our
				own.</p>
			<p>The Black gay-girls in the Village gay bars of the fifties knew each other's names,
				but we seldom looked into each other's Black eyes, lest we see our own aloneness and
				our own blunted power mirrored in the pursuit of darkness. Some of us died inside
				the gaps between the mirrors and those turned-away eyes.</p>

		</body>
		<back>
			<p>Ihis plece is excerpted from Audre Lorde's new work of fiction, <title>Zam: A New
					Speling of My Name</title> (Persephone Press). Audre Lorde teaches poetry at
				Hunter College. Her other recent book is <title>Chosen Poems —Old and New</title>
				(Norton).</p>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
