<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Heresies no 03</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1' n='N001'/>From The Lesbian Issue Collective:
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1_1' n='N001'/>l’m a writer who struggles constantly with the urge to re¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_2' n='N002'/>main silent.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_3' n='N003'/>And I understood our collective process as a struggle with
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_4' n='N004'/>silence. Like an individual isolated lesbian, we worked first on
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_5' n='N005'/>self-validation. We talked about the famous respected closet
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_6' n='N006'/>cases—could we get them to come out or figure some way to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_7' n='N007'/>claim them. (Claiming the &quot;great ones&quot; is a way for a despised
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_8' n='N008'/>group to feel good about itself.) And we spent many many
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_9' n='N009'/>meetings doing consciousness-raising on what it means to be
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_10' n='N010'/>lesbian artists—talking, some of us, about issues we had never
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_11' n='N011'/>discussed before. My excitement in working on this issue of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_12' n='N012'/>Heresies centered around the hope that many lesbian artists
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_13' n='N013'/>would write us, share their work, and contribute to this
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_14' n='N014'/>dialogue.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_15' n='N015'/>The standard I used in judging work was based on my wish
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_16' n='N016'/>to be inclusive—to present as much diversity as possible, to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_17' n='N017'/>present clearly articulated articles even if I disagreed with their
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_18' n='N018'/>content.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_19' n='N019'/>Others in the collective felt differently. This we discovered
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_20' n='N020'/>as we worked and worked and no longer had time just to talk
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_21' n='N021'/>to each other. We had been too busy when we started—dis¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_22' n='N022'/>cussing our similarities, our struggles, our fears, and our op¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_23' n='N023'/>portunities as lesbian artists—to get very far in discussing our
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_24' n='N024'/>differences.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_25' n='N025'/>Cynthia Carr
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1_2' n='N001'/>The only talent I bring to the lesbian collective is my sexual
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_2_1' n='N002'/>preference, a scorn of self-important pretension, a nose for
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_3_1' n='N003'/>drivel, and a desire to see to it that we say it like it is. In the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_4_1' n='N004'/>past we have done ourselves and our work a terrible damage
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_5_1' n='N005'/>by lying about our experience. Driven by a need for the com-
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_6_1' n='N006'/>fort of a common political position, we have all too often
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_7_1' n='N007'/>allowed rhetoric to pass for truth. Seeking an accommodation
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_8_1' n='N008'/>with the straight world, we have lied about our essential dif-
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_9_1' n='N009'/>ference. And in a spirit of loyalty we have compromised our¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_10_1' n='N010'/>selves by supporting thinking and work which is simply bad.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_11_1' n='N011'/>There is very little sense of humor in us. We have, by this
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_12_1' n='N012'/>excusable example, leaned heavily on many closet doors
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_13_1' n='N013'/>which might otherwise have sprung open. It was my hope that
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_14_1' n='N014'/>with this issue we might present truly good work by lesbians.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_15_1' n='N015'/>Now, as I am about to be pasted up and mechanicaled, I can
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_16_1' n='N016'/>say that the effort has been exhausting and perilous. And cer¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_17_1' n='N017'/>tainly I am too close to the final product to say that we have
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_18_1' n='N018'/>succeeded.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_19_1' n='N019'/>Betsy Crowell
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1_3' n='N001'/>I usually think of myself as part scientist and part magician
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_2_2' n='N002'/>with certain skills that sometimes make art. Neither feminism
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_3_2' n='N003'/>nor lesbianism determine the form and content of my work yet
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_4_2' n='N004'/>it was only with the security of the former and the coming to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_5_2' n='N005'/>terms with the latter (the muse) that my life and art began to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_6_2' n='N006'/>be uniquely and overtly me.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_7_2' n='N007'/>Initially I worked on the issue seeking a community to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_8_2' n='N008'/>explore in depth the relationship of lesbianism to the artist and
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_9_2' n='N009'/>to discover what would happen if lesbian art and artists were
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_10_2' n='N010'/>brought together. Our editorial collective’s discussions were
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_11_2' n='N011'/>some of the most provoking and intimate that I have experi¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_12_2' n='N012'/>enced, yet after each I felt a sense of panic. I know that les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_13_2' n='N013'/>bians have made great art, I know that lesbians have been
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_14_2' n='N014'/>major contributors to culture, and I believe that lesbianism in
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_15_2' n='N015'/>the largest and most powerful sense of the word has been cen¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_16_2' n='N016'/>tral not peripheral to the creative world of woman, yet I was
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_17_2' n='N017'/>worried that we wouldn’t receive sufficient &quot;good” material. I
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_18_2' n='N018'/>also feared being viewed through society’s homophobic lenses
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1_4' n='N001'/>yet I will not obscure the importance of lesbianism to my life
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_2_3' n='N002'/>and art. The muse and I are inextricably entwined and she is a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_3_3' n='N003'/>woman. I struggle continually against any restrictions on my
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_4_3' n='N004'/>identity while questioning why this culture relentlessly omits
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_5_3' n='N005'/>and suppresses from discussion and history (even in the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_6_3' n='N006'/>feminist community) the essentialness of lesbianism to the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_7_3' n='N007'/>creative lives of women
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_8_3' n='N008'/>However, there was a far deeper reason for my panic. After
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_9_3' n='N009'/>nine months of working on this issue 1 felt that our greatest
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_10_3' n='N010'/>unfaced demon was our own homophobia absorbed by all of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_11_3' n='N011'/>us in different ways from a culture so homophobic that it ruth¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_12_3' n='N012'/>lessly suppresses and punished all exploration of female
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_13_3' n='N013'/>sexuality. This, coupled with the fact that lesbian artists des¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_14_3' n='N014'/>perately need visibility and credibility, gave us a common
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_15_3' n='N015'/>unexamined goal: visibility as matured and serious artists.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_16_3' n='N016'/>This is only a beginning. Omitted from the issue is any
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_17_3' n='N017'/>dialogue that examines the role of lesbianism as central to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_18_3' n='N018'/>women claiming full power over their sexuality and that such
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_19_2' n='N019'/>power is the root of strong and unique art. Do not for a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_20_1' n='N020'/>minute imagine that art has to be explicitly about sex or any¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_21_1' n='N021'/>thing so simplistic. I am speaking rather to the fact that a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_22_1' n='N022'/>person must be able to put the full force of herself behind her
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_23_1' n='N023'/>work. Fear of being seen as sexual, fear of the audience, fear of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_24_1' n='N024'/>offending heterosexual friends, fear of retribution for creating
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_25_1' n='N025'/>or being in the issue are only a few of the fears that are real
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_26' n='N026'/>and need to be faced before we can initiate a discussion that
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_27' n='N027'/>begins from a point that assumes that lesbianism is the key to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_28' n='N028'/>the powerfulness of all women.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_29' n='N029'/>Betsy Damon
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_1_5' n='N001'/>I wanted an issue on lesbian art and artists that would pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_2_4' n='N002'/>voke me; an issue that would challenge all the assumptions I
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_3_4' n='N003'/>have about lesbians and art; an issue that would leave me
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_4_4' n='N004'/>filled with questions and with the energy with which to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_5_4' n='N005'/>explore the questions further. I wanted lesbians to be excited
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_6_4' n='N006'/>and disturbed by what they read here, finding glimpses of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_7_4' n='N007'/>themselves, as well as a sense of what is missing. What stories
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_8_4' n='N008'/>are still untold?
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_9_4' n='N009'/>What are lesbians? What are artists? In trying to reach a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_10_4' n='N010'/>working definition of these two most basic questions, a sense
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_11_4' n='N011'/>of my own alienation from the task before us began to grow.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_12_4' n='N012'/>This alienation came from being forced to examine sexuality
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_13_4' n='N013'/>from within a patriarchal context. A context which has
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_14_4' n='N014'/>created distinctions and categories in order to maintain its
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_15_4' n='N015'/>own power and privilege. The advantages gained by society&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_16_4' n='N016'/>&quot;power-brokers&quot; through perpetuating and emphasizing the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_17_4' n='N017'/>differences among racial, economic, sexual, and religious
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_18_4' n='N018'/>groups are clear. The most apparent difference between myself
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_19_3' n='N019'/>and a heterosexual woman; or myself (white, middle-class),
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_20_2' n='N020'/>and a Chicano working-class woman—is one of privilege.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_21_2' n='N021'/>And for me, as a lesbian, as white, as middle-class, to main¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_22_2' n='N022'/>tain and perpetuate differences that ultimately exist only to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_23_2' n='N023'/>deny privilege to some, seems wrong. One way I see myself as
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_24_2' n='N024'/>a lesbian perpetuating differences is in my focusing on what is
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_25_2' n='N025'/>and what is not a lesbian. &quot;A woman who does not sleep with
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_26_1' n='N026'/>men.&quot; “Any woman who calls herself a lesbian.” “A woman
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_27_1' n='N027'/>that loves and sleeps with other women.&quot; “What if she sleeps
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_28_1' n='N028'/>with a man one time? Is she still a lesbian?” “What if she used
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_29_1' n='N029'/>to sleep with men, used to be married to one, and doesn’t now,
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_30' n='N030'/>but can’t predict the future?&quot; “What is the difference between a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_31' n='N031'/>woman-identified-woman and a lesbian?” It was in trying to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_32' n='N032'/>answer questions like these that a sense of futility and absurd¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_33' n='N033'/>ity developed. I am not a lesbian. I make love only with
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_34' n='N034'/>women. I am in every way what society calls a lesbian. I will
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_35' n='N035'/>call myself and insist upon being called a lesbian as long as
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_36' n='N036'/>something called a heterosexual or bisexual exists. In all pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_37' n='N037'/>bability, 1 am referring to a sexuality that will never exist
				<lb facs='#facs_5_region_1674858535215_302_tl_38' n='N038'/>inside me. A simple sexuality, without reference to another’s
			</p>
			<pb n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_1' n='N001'/>gender. All of this is related to the question of circumstance
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_2' n='N002'/>(the time and space I live in) and therefore related to strategy
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_3' n='N003'/>(the means of change): an area l’m far less clear about than
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_4' n='N004'/>that of alienation.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_5' n='N005'/>The dilemma for me is that regardless of how I view the role
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_6' n='N006'/>such distinctions serve in this society, 1 am brutally oppressed
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_7' n='N007'/>by them, as they have been accepted by most everyone. The
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_8' n='N008'/>fact that I am a lesbian has a profound affect on my life. (My
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_9' n='N009'/>job, my family, my friends always hang in the balance.) While
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_10' n='N010'/>believing that “heterosexual” and “lesbian&quot; are concepts that
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_11' n='N011'/>directly serve to oppress us all, I know full well that as a les
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_12' n='N012'/>bian I am intentionally persecuted and isolated by this society.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_13' n='N013'/>The nearest weapon to me with which to fight back is the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_14' n='N014'/>taking of the concept and the word lesbian and claiming it as
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_15' n='N015'/>my own. My continuing to work on this issue is the result of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_16' n='N016'/>that conclusion.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_17' n='N017'/>The term “artist&quot; serves a very similar function as the word
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_18' n='N018'/>&quot;lesbian, though the specific effect upon society is quite dif¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_19' n='N019'/>ferent. The term &quot;artist&quot; distinguishes between those who are
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_20' n='N020'/>artists and those who are not. To me, an artist is a person who
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_21' n='N021'/>works without sham. One who works with integrity. The
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_22' n='N022'/>three most basic tools are a sense of self, honesty, and imagin
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_23' n='N023'/>ation. These are also three of the greatest enemies of this
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_24' n='N024'/>society. With good reason all three of these qualities are
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_25' n='N025'/>suppressed in most people at a very early age and replaced
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_26' n='N026'/>with subservience, confusion, and conformity. The expressing
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_27' n='N027'/>of oneself creatively demands not only a sense of self, honesty
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_28' n='N028'/>and imagination; but time...the time to listen, the time to
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_29' n='N029'/>concentrate. To have time, is one of the most important
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_30' n='N030'/>instances of privilege (and therefore oppression) in this
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_31' n='N031'/>society. If everyone had access to the same opportunities as
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_32' n='N032'/>everyone else—would there be such a creature as “artist?” Art
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_33' n='N033'/>would not have to speak for everyone if everyone could speak
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_34' n='N034'/>for themselves. Because of the privilege accorded to and/or
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_35' n='N035'/>fought for by artists in this society, the presumptuous assump¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_36' n='N036'/>tion that some of us whether by genius, skill, or inspiration are
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_37' n='N037'/>better able to express &quot;our” circumstance—I refuse to call
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_38' n='N038'/>myself or others “artists. Accepting money for work and
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_39' n='N039'/>associating with art institutions only contributes to the class
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_40' n='N040'/>system of art and artists. There are poets, performers, cooks
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_41' n='N041'/>and the like among us. These words refer to what we do. But
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_42' n='N042'/>&quot;artist&quot; refers to who we are in a context that inescapably
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_43' n='N043'/>implies a difference that furthers oppression rather than
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_44' n='N044'/>challenging it.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_45' n='N045'/>The most important point to me, as it refers to this issue, is
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_46' n='N046'/>that just as the words “lesbian&quot; and &quot;artist&quot; exist within a
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_47' n='N047'/>context and are affected by a circumstance, so does this issue.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_48' n='N048'/>Marty Pottenger
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_1_1' n='N001'/>I want people to understand that to be a lesbian feminist is
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_2_1' n='N002'/>to be undefined, complex, groping, newly born, uncategoriz¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_3_1' n='N003'/>able and uncategorized—i.e. not a “Lesbian as she has been
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_4_1' n='N004'/>culturally defined. I work and live for the day when the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_5_1' n='N005'/>damnable categories of human behavior are gone. And
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_6_1' n='N006'/>towards this end, I am a part of Heresies and the lesbian issue.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_7_1' n='N007'/>I don’t for a moment believe that we are presenting (or that
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_8_1' n='N008'/>we even looked for) any answers or final solutions in this
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_9_1' n='N009'/>issue. There were frightening moments when I felt that we had
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_10_1' n='N010'/>to say it all right now or never. As far as l’m concerned that&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_11_1' n='N011'/>a reasonable and not too paranoid reaction to a culture which
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_12_1' n='N012'/>&quot;gives us&quot; NO place NO voice NO credibility NO trust. We
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_13_1' n='N013'/>just have to keep stretching, shoving, insisting, confronting,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_14_1' n='N014'/>and pursuing whatever goals we each find most politically
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_15_1' n='N015'/>important and personally fulfilling. I find all the challenge I
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_16_1' n='N016'/>need in keeping my faith in the strength of the combined
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_17_1' n='N017'/>efforts of feminists and in taking seriously my individual acts
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_18_1' n='N018'/>of survival and growth in this death culture.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_19_1' n='N019'/>I am committed to photography and the written word, to
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_20_1' n='N020'/>outrageous and humorous art, to women, to the chaos of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_21_1' n='N021'/>reconstruction, and to publishing as a way to become visible,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_22_1' n='N022'/>to be heard and felt by no matter how small or select an
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_23_1' n='N023'/>audience.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_24_1' n='N024'/>Su Friedrich
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_1_2' n='N001'/>l’ve been painting for twelve years—as a feminist I feel l’ve
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_2_2' n='N002'/>been making “my own&quot; art for six of those years—and have
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_3_2' n='N003'/>identified myself as a lesbian for four years. We continue, the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_4_2' n='N004'/>work and 1, the commitment growing stronger, the relation¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_5_2' n='N005'/>ship deeper. As 1 am less anxious that the work will leave me,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_6_2' n='N006'/>or that others won’t approve, I step out of my protective
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_7_2' n='N007'/>world and find myself increasingly concerned with feminist
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_8_2' n='N008'/>political issues. I know how my work functions for me, but
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_9_2' n='N009'/>how does it fit into a larger social political view of feminism?
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_10_2' n='N010'/>I have to admit that,1 came to this issue with a lot of expec
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_11_2' n='N011'/>tations. From the beginning, I conceived of a whole issue
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_12_2' n='N012'/>devoted to lesbian art as political. I had hoped it would give
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_13_2' n='N013'/>lesbian artists visibility (especially lesbian visual artists who
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_14_2' n='N014'/>have virtually been ignored), create dialogue and community
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_15_2' n='N015'/>between lesbian visual artists and writers, remove the separa¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_16_2' n='N016'/>tion between lesbian art and politics, and bring an art con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_17_2' n='N017'/>sciousness to the lesbian community and a lesbian conscious¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_18_2' n='N018'/>ness to the feminist art community. Since lesbian artists are so
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_19_2' n='N019'/>often isolated, I had hoped that in this special collective con¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_20_2' n='N020'/>text we would take risks, ask questions, explore ideas, and
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_21_2' n='N021'/>theorize. Like a painter exhibiting for the first time, I wanted
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_22_2' n='N022'/>to show it all.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_23_2' n='N023'/>Now that we have worked for almost a year on this issue, 1
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_24_2' n='N024'/>have very mixed feelings. I think the work presented in this
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_25_1' n='N025'/>issue is excellent. The problem is not the art itself, for much
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_26_1' n='N026'/>strong work has been and is being made by lesbians. The pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_27_1' n='N027'/>blem is what’s missing, and what is missing is a context for the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_28_1' n='N028'/>work. 1 am disappointed that this issue has avoided controver¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_29_1' n='N029'/>sial material and has continued the artistic fear of conscious
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_30_1' n='N030'/>political discussion. We have avoided a larger social political
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_31_1' n='N031'/>context for our work, as though it would somehow interfere
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_32_1' n='N032'/>with the work or take away from its power and meaning. To
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_33_1' n='N033'/>think politically doesn’t mean we can’t see creatively.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_34_1' n='N034'/>If artmaking is an integral part of feminist revolution as l
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_35_1' n='N035'/>believe it is, we should be asking the following questions:
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_36_1' n='N036'/>1. What is the role and function of lesbian feminist art in the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_37_1' n='N037'/>lesbian movement?
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_38_1' n='N038'/>2. What is its role and function in the feminist movement?
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_39_1' n='N039'/>3. How does lesbian feminist art relate to larger social strug¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_40_1' n='N040'/>gles for change in a society where lesbians and others will
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_41_1' n='N041'/>no longer be discriminated against?
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_42_1' n='N042'/>4. How does lesbian feminist art affect and transform cul¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_43_1' n='N043'/>ture?
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_44_1' n='N044'/>The discussion of these questions is far more important than
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_45_1' n='N045'/>the answers. I believe that to be a lesbian artist is in itself poli¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_46_1' n='N046'/>tical, but I also think in these days of homophobic backlash,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_47_1' n='N047'/>that we need to push further and analyze all patriarchal insti¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_48_1' n='N048'/>tutions which control our lives. I feel that we have not allowed
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_49' n='N049'/>ourselves (because we’re artists?) to deal with important issues
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_50' n='N050'/>of lesbian separatism, socialist lesbians, lesbian sensibility, the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_51' n='N051'/>relationship of lesbianism to feminism, and the issues of race
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_52' n='N052'/>and class. These subjects are not rhetorical, cliched, or irrele¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_53' n='N053'/>vant to artmaking. To me they are very real and important in
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_54' n='N054'/>determining the quality of lesbian art.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_55' n='N055'/>Harmony Hammond
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_1_3' n='N001'/>My impetus to work on this issue was rooted in the despera¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_2_3' n='N002'/>tion and frustration I was experiencing working as a lesbian
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_3_3' n='N003'/>painter within a very circumscribed.peer group. 1 had begun to
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_4_3' n='N004'/>do what most lesbians have always done in creating a private
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_5_3' n='N005'/>world of reinforcement. I no longer believe these pockets of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_6_3' n='N006'/>isolated support groups can bear the strain of what it means to
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_7_3' n='N007'/>be a lesbian in a culture predicated on misogyny and homo¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_8_3' n='N008'/>phobia. This issue was an attempt to seek out lesbian artists
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_9_3' n='N009'/>and publicize the fact of their existence to myself, other les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_10_3' n='N010'/>bians and other women. The dangers and ramifications of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_11_3' n='N011'/>exposing myself and others in a solitary lesbian issue of a
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_12_3' n='N012'/>magazine whose audience and founders are predominately
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_13_3' n='N013'/>straight are inherent and menacing. But no matter what the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_14_3' n='N014'/>extent of this issue’s token quality I believe that the content:
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_15_3' n='N015'/>pursue with integrity essential questions and possibilities
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_16_3' n='N016'/>facing all women.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_region_1674858726850_355_tl_17_3' n='N017'/>K. Webster
			</p>
			<pb n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_1' n='N001'/>I believe we are lesbians largely because we realize on some
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_2' n='N002'/>level that the demands of heterosexual roles are rooted in a
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_3' n='N003'/>tradition of violence to women’s bodies and minds. This tra¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_4' n='N004'/>dition is consciously and unconsciously ritualized; it is large
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_5' n='N005'/>and powerful, life determining in fact. Feminism can and must
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_6' n='N006'/>help alter the tradition but cannot ultimately transcend it.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_7' n='N007'/>Some of us have tried to transcend it, could not, don’t believe
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_8' n='N008'/>anybody can at this time, and reject it. Equality is a myth that
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_9' n='N009'/>liberal feminism and theories of androgyny nourish. Self
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_10' n='N010'/>hatred, doubt, and homophobia on some level are operative in
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_11' n='N011'/>all our lives. In spite of this, and in defiance of this, I believe
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_12' n='N012'/>lesbianism is fundamentally about self-preservation and self¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_13' n='N013'/>love in a culture that would have it otherwise. The choice to
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_14' n='N014'/>make art is directly aided and energized by such positive
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_15' n='N015'/>impulses.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_16' n='N016'/>The connections between artist’s lives and their artistic
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_17' n='N017'/>creations have historically been acknowledged, probed and
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_18' n='N018'/>even embellished upon. However, the very existence of lesbiar
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_19' n='N019'/>lives has inveterately been denied. The connections between
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_20' n='N020'/>our lives and our work must be constructed and recognized,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_21' n='N021'/>by ourselves, and eventually by others. It is essential that
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_22' n='N022'/>these connections and their powerful political ramifications be
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_23' n='N023'/>given credence, and a loud, loud voice. Despite my terror at
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_24' n='N024'/>signing my name to this magazine, my convictions are
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_25' n='N025'/>strengthened over and over: the presence of lesbians and les-
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_26' n='N026'/>bian artists must be affirmed. The third issue of Heresies is an
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_27' n='N027'/>attempt in this direction. My personal dedication is to all les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_28' n='N028'/>bian artists who understandably remain silent, in hopes that
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_29' n='N029'/>they won’t always have to.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_30' n='N030'/>Rose Fichtenholtz
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_1_1' n='N001'/>This issue of Heresies has had a particularly difficult built-in
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_2_1' n='N002'/>problem. Heresies’ usual policy is not to print monographs of
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_3_1' n='N003'/>contemporary artists, but the invisibility of lesbian artists and
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_4_1' n='N004'/>the need for dialogue of every kind among lesbians moved us
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_5_1' n='N005'/>to consider altering the monograph policy in various ways.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_6_1' n='N006'/>Essentially, because we decided to publish only lesbian-made
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_7_1' n='N007'/>material, the issue itself is monographical: Ourselves, our
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_8_1' n='N008'/>thought, our work.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_9_1' n='N009'/>We used a discussion and voting process to determine what
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_10_1' n='N010'/>to publish. The question of inclusivity/exclusivity has been a
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_11_1' n='N011'/>source of trouble for us as a collective; it was a problem that
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_12_1' n='N012'/>we never resolved methodically. One direction that I felt the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_13_1' n='N013'/>urge to follow was to print as much as we could, since this
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_14_1' n='N014'/>issue could be seen as a vehicle by which to strengthen a
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_15_1' n='N015'/>&quot;women’s culture.&quot; As it has been defined by some women, a
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_16_1' n='N016'/>women’s culture is based in part on the principle of representa¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_17_1' n='N017'/>tion of as many of our voices as possible with the idea that the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_18_1' n='N018'/>many voices make a beautiful choir.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_19_1' n='N019'/>However, in the end I was committed to print only that
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_20_1' n='N020'/>material which I felt was most powerful. This outlook can be
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_21_1' n='N021'/>and has been seen as an alternative to the “many voices’
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_22_1' n='N022'/>method of creating a women’s culture. I agree that what 1
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_23_1' n='N023'/>deem “powerful&quot; is colored by personal biases, some of which
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_24_1' n='N024'/>must be examined closely for their validity. But to try to
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_25_1' n='N025'/>reflect what was “out there” seemed foolish. I felt that it was
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_26_1' n='N026'/>more honest to print what I believe in; that is, not just what I
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_27_1' n='N027'/>agree with ideologically but what agrees with me esthetically
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_28_1' n='N028'/>Unfortunately the usual editorial message is that to deny space
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_29_1' n='N029'/>to something is to imply its worthlessness, and that, converse¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_30_1' n='N030'/>ly, to print something is to assert its worth.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_31' n='N031'/>As an editor I have reflected only my own biases and
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_32' n='N032'/>opinions. I have done so only with the hope that other lesbians
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_33' n='N033'/>will investigate our lives true to their own opinions and
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_34' n='N034'/>values—and that we will analyze our differences with an eye
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_35' n='N035'/>towards our diverse pasts and our collective future.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_36' n='N036'/>Amy Sillman
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_1_2' n='N001'/>l’ve been a lesbian and l’ve been a painter for a long time.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_2_2' n='N002'/>have little respect for rhetoric, politics that squeeze the life’s
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_3_2' n='N003'/>blood out of artists, or theories of lesbian sensibility or les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_4_2' n='N004'/>bian imagery formulated out of daydreams.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_5_2' n='N005'/>I don’t like being isolated in this magazine because my les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_6_2' n='N006'/>bian artist sisters out there refuse to come out. Backlash is on
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_7_2' n='N007'/>its way, but we don’t even need backlash—we have the sanct-
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_8_2' n='N008'/>ity of the closet.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_9_2' n='N009'/>l’d like to personally dedicate this issue to all the women
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_10_2' n='N010'/>who we know are lesbians and who have made it big in the last
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_11_2' n='N011'/>forty years—as artists, as dealers, and as intellectuals—for
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_12_2' n='N012'/>their steadfastness in the denial of their queerness. The
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_13_2' n='N013'/>starkness of their lives led me to cherish honest living and to
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_14_2' n='N014'/>search for an alternate route for making art.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_15_2' n='N015'/>I want to share what 1 have learned in my twenty years of
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_16_2' n='N016'/>being a painter and a lesbian with lesbians who want a strong
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_17_2' n='N017'/>identity as artists. I am interested in work. I am first a painter.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_18_2' n='N018'/>1 am not interested in formulating politics or in promoting a
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_19_2' n='N019'/>lesbian universe. I am in this despite my doubts about the pro¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_20_2' n='N020'/>ductivity of collective enterprise and despite the distance it
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_21_2' n='N021'/>takes me from my work.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_22_2' n='N022'/>Louise Fishman
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_1_3' n='N001'/>When I am making a work of art I am making it first and
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_2_3' n='N002'/>foremost therapeutically for myself, and I am alone in my
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_3_3' n='N003'/>studio and feeling usually very lonely. At this time there is
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_4_3' n='N004'/>only a vague sense that it is also for other women artists and
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_5_3' n='N005'/>women who like to look at art. And even when 1 have finished
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_6_3' n='N006'/>working on it and it is an expression of my own formulated
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_7_3' n='N007'/>and particular visual bias, it is still not yet complete. Women
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_8_3' n='N008'/>come to my studio and look at it and see things that I was too
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_9_3' n='N009'/>close to see and the painting’s meaning becomes larger. Anc
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_10_3' n='N010'/>still it is not yet finished. It seasons awhile in front of its small
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_11_3' n='N011'/>audiences and insistently sits before them and I bring people in
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_12_3' n='N012'/>front of it and say, “Yes, this is my art; this is my experience,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_13_3' n='N013'/>until in some way it is recognized, analyzed and absorbed.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_14_3' n='N014'/>Then it is finished. It is finished when it goes public, is recog¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_15_3' n='N015'/>nized, given meaning.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_16_3' n='N016'/>Women have managed somehow to survive in a woman-
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_17_3' n='N017'/>hating culture, but rarely have they found ways to complete
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_18_3' n='N018'/>expression in the culture. We know better than most that the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_19_3' n='N019'/>personal is political because when we have insisted upon our
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_20_3' n='N020'/>personal viewpoint, when we have insisted upon our art, we
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_21_3' n='N021'/>have been burned, mutilated, raped and put away—at best
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_22_3' n='N022'/>ridiculed. Exposure, even sometimes to each other, is danger¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_23_2' n='N023'/>ous; fraught with memories of past violence, visions of future
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_24_2' n='N024'/>violence, the feeling that we will be considered crazy if we let
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_25_2' n='N025'/>others know who we are and what we think. We have no his
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_26_2' n='N026'/>torical or political context to decide which parts of us remain
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_27_2' n='N027'/>intact after suffering consistent negation and brutality.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_28_2' n='N028'/>Who we choose as an audience is of vital consideration as
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_29_2' n='N029'/>long as exposure is dangerous. I sign my name to this issue
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_30_2' n='N030'/>with a great sense of purpose as well as real trepidation. Every
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_31_1' n='N031'/>day l am aware that people think I am crazy because I am a les¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_32_1' n='N032'/>bian and that violence may be done to me because of it. This
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_33_1' n='N033'/>will continue long after male institutions grant us our civil
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_34_1' n='N034'/>rights. It will continue until we make the reality of our exper¬
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_35_1' n='N035'/>ience clear. Women have often had strength in the private
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_36_1' n='N036'/>domain, are safer there. When we have brought our experience,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_37' n='N037'/>our work, our ideas to the world we have been repudiated
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_38' n='N038'/>and endangered. It is time to be particular and rigorous in
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_39' n='N039'/>our language and ideas, to articulate our needs and biases, and
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_40' n='N040'/>to insist, “Yes, this is our art; yes, this is our experience,” in a
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_41' n='N041'/>voice that can not be refuted.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_region_1674858873860_396_tl_42' n='N042'/>Christine Wade
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
