<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
        href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>________________</p>
         <p>Architecture and Social Change</p>
         <p>Nunzia Rondanini</p>
         <p>As a movement uniting all women in a struggle against exploitation and
                discrimination, feminism includes the goals of attaining our own identity and of
                achieving a share of power. Yet, among ourselves, we may disagree on the meaning of
                both identity and power. I, for instance, do not see feminism as independent of
                class struggle, but rather as a stream that eventually flows into the larger
                movement toward a new social organization. This explains why, in dealing with the
                relationships between architecture and social change, I cannot identify an
                exclusively feminist dimension of the problem.</p>
         <p>Architecture, like feminism, is also a much debated term. The role of the architect
                today is particularly uncertain and ambiguous. A coherent and solid foundation to
                contemporary practice necessitates a theoretical framework if questions raised by
                this practice are to be answered coherently. This rational foundation must be sought
                in history, in the works that were built or only planned, as they appear in their
                ultimate expression: form. History--whether man's or woman's-has never experienced
                interruptions. Historical events--and architecture-may change or develop, but they
                always originate in their precedents. Architecture is as old as people themselves.
                Can we now "invent" it, starting from fanciful images of tomorrow's world or from
                what we think a liberated feminine sensibility should be? We will not do anything
                different unless we do something better. And this implies a knowledge of what we
                will improve upon. It is only through history that we can learn about architecture.
                The fact that history has been written and built mostly by men is a reality we
                cannot wipe out in a single sweep.</p>
         <p>The industrial and bourgeois revolutions in the 19th century brought to an end the
                dialogue between the prince and the architect that had traditionally been the
                generator of architecture. The unity of architectural theory and practice was thus
                dissolved, opening the way to diverse, conflicting interpretations.</p>
         <p>Three such interpretations in particular are currently trying to assert their
                theoretical supremacy in competition with one another: functionalism, according to
                which the form of any architectural work</p>
         <p>is the direct offspring of its function, i.e., the material requirements that it is
                meant to fulfill; the heteronomous theories, which derive form from the analyses and
                conclusions of social and behavioral sciences; and formalism, which maintains that
                architectural form comes into being through a unique and independent process.
                Functionalism</p>
         <p>In every city there are certain buildings, streets, and squares that last beyond
                their time and stand out among other urban elements. We call them monuments. If form
                really derives unequivocally from function, as functionalists claim, and given that
                function relates to the needs of a specific age and society, monuments should have
                disappeared along with the generation that created them. Instead, they have
                survived, sometimes by serving a purpose different from that originally intended.
                Indeed, one of their most interesting characteristics is precisely that they have
                outlived the immediate needs for which they were constructed. Yet monuments continue
                to impose their presence on the city and influence its development. The city
                acquires its unique form through a continuous interaction between monuments, the
                plan, and the smaller urban fabric. Such form is of great importance because it
                conveys the architectural message of the city.</p>
         <p>Surrounded by a wild tropical landscape, the Mayan ruins are an example of what form
                by itself can mean. Although little is known about Mayan civilization and the
                practical use of these spaces, they nevertheless provoke an overwhelming aesthetic
                experience. Their function has been forgotten, but their form is still alive and one
                can learn from it.</p>
         <p>Together with the other arts, architecture is a cultural manifestation of society.
                Functionalism ignores this reality. While function may play a role in defining
                architectural form, the relationship between function and form is not
                deterministic.</p>
         <p>Heteronomous Theories</p>
         <p>The heteronomous theories derive architectural form from the analyses and conclusions
                of sciences such as anthropology, sociology, and economics. While these disciplines
                unquestionably contribute to an understanding of architecture, especially of the
                city, they should not interfere with its actual making. It is not possible to travel
                backwards and deduce a more "human" or "just" architecture from the findings of
                social sciences. There is no need for such sciences to mediate between architecture
                and reality because architecture is already a direct expression of society. The
                central and the longitudinal church plans, for example, show two different ways in
                which society envisioned the relationships between people, priest, and God; these
                views are expressed in the very configuration of the plans</p>
         <p>Social sciences are not involved with the process of creating form; they only concern
                themselves with it a posteriori. Those who wish to influence social behavior
                directly through architecture imply that one can establish a static relationship
                between some hypothetically desirable way of life and a corresponding architectural
                form. As in functionalism, form is subordinated to specific external requirements
                which supposedly generate it. Since these change continuously, it is bound to an
                early obsolescence. Experience has shown that an architectural form, such as a
                square, which at a given time fostered social interaction, may easily fail to do so
                when revived for this purpose. Similarly, the architectural proposals of utopian
                socialism or of German rationalism between the wars were products of careful social
                studies. However, once executed, they often proved ineffectual as instruments of
                social advancement and even became tools of oppression-an example being the concept
                of existenz minimum as it was applied to workers' housing. Formalism</p>
         <p>Formalism maintains that the real field of expression of architecture is form, which
                finds its origin and definition through its own particular process, as the
                fulfillment of independent cultural choices. In discussing this question, György
                Lukacs refers to the town wall, among the very first examples of architecture. While
                the primary function of the town wall was to keep the enemy out, the feeling of
                security it gave to town dwellers soon ceased to be an accidental consequence and
                became a necessary component of the structure. At a certain stage,</p>
         <p>© 1981 Nunzia Rondanini</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
